<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An admonition to Con∣templation for the Rea∣der, and especially for my countriemen of Wales.</title>
           <author>Vaughan, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119031_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14282</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24599</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119031</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An admonition to Con∣templation for the Rea∣der, and especially for my countriemen of Wales.</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ten introductions : how to read, and in reading, how to vnderstand; and in vnderstanding, how to beare in mind all the bookes, chapters, and verses, contained in the holie Bible. With an answer for lawyers. Physitions. Ministers</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>222 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>An admonition to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and especially for my countriemen of Wales.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S among all other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie accidences that are incident to the prosperitie or aduersitie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, there is nothing in earth that more fully proportioneth the ioys in heauen, than Musicke, and Mariage: to heare the one, we leaue our meat and drinke; and to be ioyned in the other, w
<pb facs="8"/> leaue father and mother; euen so among all ordinarie instructions incident to the earthly prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and aeternall felicitie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, there is nothing that more fully proportioneth our condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be iust, than the law; nor any thing that more fully propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth our saluation to be in Christ Iesus, than the Gospell. In the one we heare thūdring, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, lamentations, mournings and woe: in the other nothing else but sweet voices, pleasaunt songs, and instruments of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, all proportioning and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually pointing our marriage with Christ Iesus, in whom we are freed from the curse &amp; threats of the law, &amp; all other inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences whatsoeuer; who saith vnto vs as vnto his bride, My Doue shew me thy selfe, let me heare
<pb facs="8"/> thy voice, thy voice is sweet,<note place="margin">Cant. 2, 14.4, 1. to 8.</note> and thy sight comly. Behold thou art faire, behold thou art faire, thou art all faire my loue, &amp; there is no spot within thee. Now then (good christian Reader) tell me, tell me, I pray you, tel me, who wil not leaue marrying with a noble Lady in Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael or in England, to be marryed with Christ Iesus in heuen? &amp; who wil not leaue all the musicke &amp; all the pleasurs of this life, to obtaine the companie of Angels, the ioys of heauen, and the presence of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ himselfe? The studie and the diligent apprehending of these exceeding great blessednesse, doe consist in the apprehending of the true vse and intent of the law and the Gospell.</p>
   <p>Cease not, cease not, O my good contriemen and friends, whilst you liue cease not to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate
<pb facs="9"/> the wonderfull wonders of <hi>Iehoua,</hi> of <hi>Iehoua,</hi> our aeternall God and sauior <hi>Iehoua,</hi> O behold and contemplate who is so great a God as our God; is not the God of Israel the God of England? and is not the vniformitie of his truth among vs as it was among them who liued in tents and taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles? O English Israel, O people of England, the high Sacrificer, the perpetuall <hi>Aaron</hi> hath powred out vpon thee as out of a ful horn, the dew of Hermon,<note place="margin">Psal. 133.1.2.</note> the ioy of the whole earth. O my loue, my spouse (saith Christ) thou wast in the rocks solitarie,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> like a Doue that had lost hir mate, thou wast vpon the hils all brused and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, like a bird scarred from hir young ones,<note place="margin">Psal. 11.1.2.</note> and thou wast in the wildernesse all weake and blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, like a woman no rather deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="9"/> of hir child, forced to flee,<note place="margin">Reu. 12, 1.2.3.</note> for the safegard of hir owne life. Arise now my loue, my faire one, and come away,<note place="margin">Cant. 2, 11.12.13.</note> for behold win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is past, the rain is changed and gone away, the flowers appeare in the earth, the time of the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of birds is come, and the voice of the Turtle is heard in our land. As though Christ had said; True it is O my beloued bride, my wife, my dear one, yee were perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted too and fro, yee were hid here and there, yee were in places of small comfort, as in a rocke, yee were in places of scarsitie, as in a hill or mountaine, and yee were in danger of your liues as among wild beasts in the wildernesse: but take a good heart, feare not, cast away euerie thing that presseth downe, and the sinne that hangs on so fast betraying the succors
<pb facs="10"/> which reason offreth. Winter, which is by relation, The time of desolation, is past. Sūmer which signifieth Peace and Plentie, is come, all arguments in the earth and in the elements inforceth the proofe thereof, for euerie thing in their order and kind doe bring forth a ioy innarrable, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of frute. Well then (my good friends and countriemen) remember your selues, consider wel what you are, where you liue, and the time you liue in, take time in time to repent, vse the season, obserue the opportunity in which you may bequeath and dedicate your selues to God. Now is that acceptable time: You haue had many ioyfull iubilees, you haue now the presence of the Ark, nay, ye haue the presēce of Iesus Christ himselfe. <hi>Moses</hi> rod hath eaten vp
<pb facs="10"/> the rods of the Aegyptian force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers;<note place="margin">Exod. 7.12. 1. Sam. 5, 4.</note> the Lords Arke hath thrown downe the Philistins Dagon, and the sound of Gods siluer Trumpets haue broken the neck of poperie, for the voice of the Turtle is heard in our land. The church, the Sanctified Syon, is this Turtle; the preaching of the word is hir voice, which we haue heard this six and thirty summers, by the godly gouernment of a Turtle, in the same nature and kinde, who liues solely and solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, not meet to be matched with any but with Iesus Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</p>
   <p>The son of <hi>Sirach</hi> saith; There be two manner of people that I abhorre, and the third are no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: the first that sit vpon the mountains of Samaria, the second the Philistins that dwell in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimis.
<pb facs="11"/> They that sit vpon the mountaines of Samatia, repose themselues vpon the authoritie of Rome, the Philistins represent the Turke, Sarazens, and other miscreants; These are the sons of men (said <hi>Dauid;</hi>) These are the generation of vipers, (said <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptist; These are the children of darkenesse (said S. <hi>Paule;</hi>) and these are they (say all men) that labor to ouer-run our countries, to ouerthrow our churches, to burne our houses, to bereaue vs of our liues, and to depriue vs of our queene, and both hir and vs of the Gospell. They conspire against God like Hipocrites, against our quiet queen like traitors, &amp; against our common weale like spoilers. My good countriemen and kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, if you will adhibite any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite to my councell, if you haue
<pb facs="11"/> any comfort in the mercifulnesse of God, and if you haue any bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Christian affection to your posteritie, then now at the last get you Bibles; leaue off your beads, place learned preachers; displace Ieroboams Priests, walke in the light of the gospell; extinguish the light of Tapers and Torches, the one brings you the high way to heauen, the other the ready way to hell.</p>
   <p>As <hi>Ioab</hi> tooke hold on the horns of the Alter for the safegard of his life: so now take you hold on Iesus Christ for the safegard of your liues. All kind of creatures are in an vnitie praising God, they call you to ioyne and to vnite your selues with vs in one religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Strange sights haue bin seen in the element and in the earth, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you to repentance, fire hath
<pb facs="12"/> come downe from heauen, fishes haue throwne thēselues to land, and beasts haue brought foorth vntimely monsters, calling you to repentance, the earth hath quaked vnder our feete, and our houses haue shaken ouer our heads, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you to repentance. O ioyne then with vs, &amp; we wil now ioyne with you, let vs goe togither into the house of God hād in hand, &amp; heart in heart, let vs sing one song as with one voice, to the praise of our one only God. Thus I haue boldly &amp; briefly admonished you in the Lord; and that you may the better cōtemplate to your cōfort, I haue here, as you see, comprised and composed my two former labors into one, with some sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction and with some such ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as may best further you to the speech of his diuine maiesty, in your owne person, when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb facs="12"/> shalbe offered for your selues &amp; for your houshold. One quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a years pains, as I haue poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, will bring you 40 years pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in earth, and at the expiration thereof, aeternall pleasure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And when you haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my promise, I desire but your praiers and your meditations to God for me, &amp; for the posteritie of the religious and magnanimious gentleman, Sir <hi>William Herberd</hi> knight, who for his owne part hath runne his race in the faith of Iesus Christ, and finished his course according to conscience towards you, as may appeare; whose body is a sleepe in the Lord, and whose soule is in ioy with Iesus Christ. There are three sorts of professors that doe suffer great indignitie at the hands, and from the hearts of many picke-thanke
<pb facs="13"/> Parasites, stily Sicophants; too too hard, yea heathenish or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hellish censures are giuen in and granted out against them. I know their obiections vpon long experience, and I know that vpon small skill and little reading their turnesicke spirite of giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse may easily be quailed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though through ignorance and wilfull stubbernnesse they will neuer be answered. Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian countriemen and courteous Readers, I am loath to offend you with tediousnesse about these matters, hauing a great shew of indeuour and purpose to draw you to other matters of greater importance. I haue therfore thought good and more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to speake of them in the latter end of this booke. The first doth partlie concerne this worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="13"/> gentleman, to whom I write for protection. The second doth concerne partly mine owne bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly health, and the third doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the earthly prosperity, and the heauenly faelicity of all the elect, and therefore I may not passe it, neither may you in any case omit the learning of it, that with him and me and with the rest of Gods inheritance you may be readie to defend it. And thus for this time I humbly take my leaue, and with such conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie as I may, do now betake my selfe in the feare of God to the matter. From <hi>Leonard</hi> Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dich, and county of Middlesex, nere London.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours if you be the Lords.</hi> Edw: Vaughan.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>