<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right woorship∣full and my singuler good La∣die, the Ladie Anne Herbert of Wil∣ton.</title>
           <author>Thomas, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119757_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13731</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24023</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119757</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right woorship∣full and my singuler good La∣die, the Ladie Anne Herbert of Wil∣ton.</title>
                 <author>Thomas, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vanitee of this world. Anno. M.D.XLIX</title>
                 <author>Thomas, William, Clerk of the Council to Edward VI</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right woorship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and my singuler good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the Ladie Anne Herbert of Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eyng persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the lyght of the trouthe dooeth more flourishe here amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest vs in Englande, than elswhere thoroughout the whole world, and seyng the fruite of our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes rather to empayre than amende, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>schiefe to grow and vertue to decaie, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetousenesse to reigne where godlinesse is professed, and of euerie other thyng the contrary to haue place, of that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che shoulde be auoyded: me seemed I could no lesse doe, than reason with my selfe, what all these thing{is} shuld meane. And findyng in conclusion, that they,
<pb facs="3"/>
whiche knowe reason, can not yet rule theim selfes by reason: me thought it necessarie to publisshe vnto the worlde this little woorke, that I haue scraped out of the dust: Not thynkyng therby to obteine redresse of al men, but in hope that some vertuous myndes beholdyng here as in a glasse, the spottes of theyr owne vices, shall yet the rather bende theyr hertes towardes charitee and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of these worldely vanitees. And because I haue founde so muche negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in man, that almost he deserueth not to be warned any more of his folie: therfore did I determine to dedicate my boke vnto a woman, to proue whether it maie take any roote in theim: to the entent that men ashamed, thorough the vertuouse examples of women, maie be prouoked therby to refourme theim sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, whiche no kinde of admonicion can persuade theim to dooe. And findyng amongest women your Ladiship in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and bountee to excelle as the dya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant
<pb facs="3"/>
amongest the iewelles, I thought it my duity to commende it specially vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Assuryng my selfe, that the wonderfull qualitees and modestee of your Ladiship shall be a no lesse terrour to theim, that viciousely would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne this little worke, than the thyng it selfe shall be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion to others, that beyng well dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, maie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to amende theyr lyfes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶Your Ladiships most humble seruaunt Wylliam Thomas.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>