<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119177_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09561</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19839</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119177</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The coppy of a letter and commission, of the King of Spaine, Phillip the third, sent vnto the vice-roy of Portugall, dated the 20. day of Iune, in the yeare of our Lord God. 1602 : Wherein the dealings and trade of ships &amp; marchandize is forbidden, with the subiectes of Holland, Zealand and England, &amp;c. with the said lands and countries of Spaine and Portugall. Whereby appeareth the inueterate, and continuall malice of the said Spaniards, against the dominions of England, Holland and Zealand, &amp;c. Truely translated out of the Spanish originall, into the Dutch tongue; and now translated againe out of the Dutch copye, into English</title>
                 <author>Spain, Sovereign (1598-1621 : Philip Iii)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, after that Phillip the second of that name
King of Spaine, had vexed these Countries of Holland and Zealand, with
tedious and continual wars, and with many Imbargos or arrestes, made vpon
their Ships and Merchandize, to the mighty hindrance of their Nauigation and
Mariners, &amp; to the great damage and ouerthrow of many honest Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants:
And not therewith contented, vsed more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer his great Tiranye against the
Masters and Mariners, putting them into his Gallyes, and like vnto poore
miserable slaues, with chaines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable trauailes and labours
tormenting them, vntill such time as the Almighty God (by the wise dealings
of the Honorable Lords the States) at last did send release and freedome
vnto a great nūber, which then remained aliue. And after this, his sonne,
Phillip the third, comming to the Crowne after the death of his Father,
seeketh &amp; practiseth to Imitate herein, the waies &amp; foote-steps
of his <pb facs="3"/>Father, as it appeareth most
plainly by this Letter, dated the 20. day of Iune 1602. sent vnto the
Vice-roy of Portugall: Wherein hee declareth those of Holland and Zealand,
for enemyes and rebels to God and his Maiesty: Notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were
neuer bound by oath of dutye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, nor euer were his subiects: meaning
in this sort to rule and gouerne ouer them as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath done before
him: which is nothing at al to be wondred at, seeing he hath bin nourished
and brought vp vnder the wings of the holie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Spanish
Inquisition: wee haue in such sort fostred him, that they name him to
be <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani generis desiderium,</hi> that by him they may fullie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
their rage and tyranie according to their owne wished desire, to the
surpression of these lands and their priueledges, and also to the
rooting out of Gods holye word, from which our mercifull God defend and keepe
vs. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>