<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the christian Reader Iohn Whatton wisheth all good giftes of vertue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119808_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22805</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the christian Reader Iohn Whatton wisheth all good giftes of vertue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A misticall deuise of the spirituall and godly loue betwene Christ the spouse, and the church or congregation : Firste made by the wise Prince Salomon, and now newly set forth in verse by Iud Smith. Wherunto is annexed certeine other briefe stories. And also a treatise of prodigalitie, most fit and necessarie to be read [and] marked of all estates. 1575</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Kirkham, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38+ pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>¶ To the christian Reader Iohn Whatton</hi> wisheth all good giftes of vertue.</head>
   <p>(∴)</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N perusing this little vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume intituled, A misticall deuise, being requested of my frend therunto, I did fynde such a pleasantnes therin, that my hart reioyced and gaue du signes what pleasure and delight my minde of it conceiued. For surely (gentle Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) if thou couit to heare anye olde bables, as I may terme them, or stale tales of Chauser, or to learne howe Acteon came by his horned head? If thy mynde be fixed to any such meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphocall toyes, this booke is not apt nor fit for thy purpose. But if thou art contrary wise bent, to heare, or to reade holsome documentes, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh all Christians, then take this same: For thou shalt fynde it sweeter (as the Prophet sayeth) then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye
<pb facs="3"/>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/> or the honye combe. For Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon had great delite in the makinge of these, to recreat and renyue his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and called them by this name, <hi>Canticum Canticorum,</hi> whyche is to saye: the song of songes.</p>
   <p>Would to God that all our rebald songes were abrogated and cast quit away, and that we would once call to mynde this sweete saying of our Lord God. (O that my people would haue harkened vnto mee.) Therefore let vs followe the good counsail of the Apostle, that is: To cast awaye the workes of darknesse, and put on the Armour of lyght, which lyght is the true worde of the most hiest: as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in his Psalmes writteth. Thy worde is a Lanterne vnto my feete, &amp; a lyght vnto my path. God graunt that we may frame our lyues accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that lyght.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Vale.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>