<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST GRACIOVS and Sacred Princesse ANNA QVEENE of Eng∣land, Scotland, France, and Ireland.</title>
           <author>Dowland, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119394_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20694</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7097</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST GRACIOVS and Sacred Princesse ANNA QVEENE of Eng∣land, Scotland, France, and Ireland.</title>
                 <author>Dowland, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lachrimæ, or Seauen teares figured in seauen passionate pauans : vvith diuers other pauans, galiards, and almands, set forth for the lute, viols, or violons, in fiue parts: By Iohn Dowland Bacheler of Musicke, and lutenist to the most royall and magnificent, Christian the fourth, King of Denmarke, Norway, Vandales, and Gothes, Duke of Sleswicke, Holsten, Stormaria, and Ditmarsh: Earle of Oldenburge and Delmenhorst</title>
                 <author>Dowland, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dowland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>50 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST GRACIOVS and Sacred Princesse ANNA QVEENE of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France, and Ireland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I had accesse to your Highnesse at VVinchester, (most gracious Queene) I haue beene twice vnder sayle for Denmarke, hastning my returne to my most royall King and Master, your deare and worthiest Brother; but by contrary windes and frost, I was forst backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and of necessitie compeld to winter here in your most happie Kingdome. In which time I haue endeuoured by my poore labour and study to manifest my humblenesse and dutie to your highnesse, being my selfe one of your most affectionate Subiects, and also seruant to your most Princely Brother, the onely Patron and Sun-shine of my else vnhappie Fortunes. For which respects I haue presumed to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate this worke of Musicke to your sacred hands, that was begun where you were borne, and ended where you raigne. And though the title doth promise teares, vnfit guests in these ioyfull times, yet no doubt pleasant are the teares which Musicke weepes, neither are teares shed alwayes in sorrowe, but sometime in ioy and gladnesse. Vouchsafe then (worthy Goddesse) your Gracious protection to these showers of Harmonie, least if you frowne on them, they bee Metamorphosed into true teares.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties in all humilitie deuoted, <hi>IOHN DOVVLAND.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>