<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epilogue or Postscript to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119361_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08944</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19222</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119361</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epilogue or Postscript to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe dissection of Germaines affliction : with warre, pestilence, and famine; and other deducable miseries, lachrimable to speak of; more lamentable to partake of. Sent as a (friendly) monitor to England, warning her to beware of, (generally) ingratitude, and security as also (particularly) other greevous sinnes, the weight whereof Germany hath a long time felt, and at this present doth (and England may feare to) feele. Written from approv'd intelligence, by M. Parker</title>
                 <author>M. P. (Martin Parker)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Grove, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>The Epilogue or Postscript to the Reader.</head>
   <l>THus (tender hearted Reader have I set</l>
   <l>Before thine eyes (what thou shouldst nere forget)</l>
   <l>The misery which neighbour Nations feele,</l>
   <l>Through war, famine, and pestilence, the wheele</l>
   <l>Of Fortune's still in motion, though we sit</l>
   <l>In peace, and plenty, yet ith midst of it,</l>
   <l>Tis fit we should on <hi>Iosephs</hi> troubles thinke,</l>
   <l>Least of the cup of wrath, we also drinke,</l>
   <l>Let's all consider tis th' Almighties hand,</l>
   <l>That striketh others, and doth spare our land,</l>
   <l>And that his love, (not our desarts) are cause,</l>
   <l>Why from our Nation he the stroke withdrawes,</l>
   <l>We are as wicked (if not more) then they</l>
   <l>On whom he doth his rod of anger lay,</l>
   <l>And therefore though as yet we live in mirth,</l>
   <l>(Injoying all the blessings upon earth,</l>
   <l>A Gracious King, under whose Governement</l>
   <l>We live, in peace, and for our more content</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="13"/>Are fortifi'd with Royall Off-spring which</l>
   <l>Our land with future blessings may inrich,)</l>
   <l>Yet if this peace and plenty which we have,</l>
   <l>Doe make us proud, forgetting him who gave</l>
   <l>Vs all these comforts, which our neighbours want,</l>
   <l>We well may feare, least he his love transplant,</l>
   <l>Into another people, that will yeild</l>
   <l>A larger crop of thankes; O let the field</l>
   <l>Of each ones heart, receive the seede of grace,</l>
   <l>And with true gratitude prevent his face,</l>
   <l>Lets hate our loved sins, our vaine excesse</l>
   <l>Of (Luciferian) pride, sloth, drunkennesse,</l>
   <l>Extortion, avarice, and luxury,</l>
   <l>Let's feede and cloath Christ in necessity,</l>
   <l>I meane in's little ones, what's done to them,</l>
   <l>His owne words ratifie, as done to him,</l>
   <l>This is his will, to do't lets all endever,</l>
   <l>And he (no doubt) will give us peace for ever.</l>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="13"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>