<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>White, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119890_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15081</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25380</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119890</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>White, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The orthodox faith and vvay to the Chvrch explaned and ivstified : in answer to a popish treatise, entituled, White died blacke; wherein T.W. p. in his triple accusation of D. White for impostures, vntruths, and absurd illations, is proued a trifler: and the present controuersies betweene vs and the Romanists are more fully deliuered and cleared. By Francis White Bachelour in Diuinitie, and elder brother of Doctor Iohn White</title>
                 <author>White, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Barrett, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 405, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the deceasse of my Brother D. White, there is published against him a libelling and despitefull Treatise, <hi>entituled, White dyed blacke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Author thereof (being a Romish Priest) vndertaketh to demonstrate, that <hi>the Doctor in his booke called the way to the Church, hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many foule and wilfull abuses; and in particular: cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth Authors, deliuereth manifest and confessed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths: and in his disputing vseth many loose and absurd illations.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And to the perswading hereof, he proceedeth as follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> In the Epistles prefixed to his booke, and in sundry passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges besides, he largely and loudly accuseth the Doctor, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and thundreth against him, with a whole volue of loose words: and boasteth and florisheth before he come to the fight, of an absolute conquest and victory ouer him and his worke. The facing and verball ostentation of this Romist, is so impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it putteth downe the Giant of Gath. <hi>1.</hi> Sam. <hi>17.</hi> (Onely his force and stature is meaner, his ioynts and limbes are feebler, and his armour is lighter.)</p>
   <p>When a certaine mercenary souldier did with many bold and impure reproches exclaime against Great Alexander:<note place="margin">Plutarch. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm.</note>
      <hi>Memnon the Generall of Darius his armie,</hi> lent him a blow with his lance: saying, that he had hired him to fight against Alexander, and not to raile at him. And howsoeuer
<pb facs="10"/> the verbal clamors of this Romist are much applauded by his fautors, yet indeed they rather deserue stripes, Pro. <hi>19.29.</hi> then praises: and are nought else but windie and worthlesse stuffe, of no more force to make a conquest of the Doctor and his cause: then the prating of the souldier was to disparkle the inuincible armie of Alexander the Great.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> In his progresse about the matter it selfe: This Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie doth not confute, either the whole or any one continuate part of the Doctors worke, as it lyeth in order, but maketh a rapsodie, and selecteth here and there instances and mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, which seeme aduantageous to his purpose. And as the Amalekites, not daring to affront the maine hoast of the Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, preyed vpon straglers, and such as were feeble and hindmost in the companie. Deut. <hi>25.18.</hi> So this Champion dissembleth, and passeth ouer the maine bodie and firme testimonies and arguments of euery question, and fasteneth his nailes vpon the more feeble<note n="*" place="margin">Iustin. collo. cū Tryph. Soletis seu muscae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolare ad exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerata, si qua in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plurima re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè dicta exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit vel vnum quippiam quod vobis displicet, aut non satis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>is.</note> &amp; lesse principall branches.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> This Aduersarie hauing without all modestie, taxed my Brother of corruption, vntruth, &amp;c. doth himselfe perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally commit the same offences.</p>
   <p>In the front of his booke he affixeth a select sentence out of Augustine<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. lib. 2. cont. Petil. Don. c. 51. Cathedra tibi quid fecit Ecclesiae Rom. in qua Petrus sedit, &amp; in qua Anastasius ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die sedet.</note>, to make the Reader beleeue, that this Father is a witnesse for the Monarchie of the Pope: But he pareth off one clause thereof<note n="b" place="margin">Vel Ecclesiae Hierosolomita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae in qua Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus sedit, &amp; in qua hodie Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes sedet, quibus nos in Catholica vnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate connecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</note>, which being added, sheweth that this great Doctor gaue equall authoritie to the Church of Hierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem and the Romane: and made the Patriarches of these two Seas, colleagues and compeeres.</p>
   <p>And throughout his worke, he scarce frameth one suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient or tollerable illation and consequent<note n="c" place="margin">Reade part. 3. of this booke in the beginning.</note>: and he peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the meaning of all Authors<note n="d" place="margin">Obserue in the first part of this book, in sundry paragraphs his abusiue dealing with authors, &amp;c</note> which he produceth. And, which is a certaine argument of his cowardise and bad cause: In the most points he dissembleth the proposition and assertion
<pb facs="10"/> which the Doctor deliuereth, and whereunto he coupleth his testimonies and illations: And in place thereof, substitutes another proposition or sentence, that so he may haue color to say what he listeth. When Diogenes<note n="f" place="margin">Diog. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tius lib. 6. vita. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los.</note> beheld a wilde and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull archer, he ran to the marke, thinking to stand there in greatest safetie: and if the Reader repaire to the true point and state of euery question, he shall perceiue that this obiecter in most of his exceptions, roueth at a contrary marke, and fighteth against a scarre crow or Chimera of his owne deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> This Romist pretendeth that the allectiue or impulsiue cause, which awakened his sleepie pen, and impelled him to writing, was the euill deportment of the Doctor in his booke: But his manner of proceeding, to wit, his insinuations (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which this is notorious, that he dedicateth his booke to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge) his derision, declaiming, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniation, &amp;c. and then his slender and emptie disputing, being onely popular and not theologicall or scholasticke (and in no sort fitting these acute and iudicious persons whom he presumed in his preface to make his Peeres and Censors,) do solemnly proclaime, that the essentiall reason of diuulging his Treatise, was to salue the credit of his Popish cause, with his owne partie: and hauing obserued the euill successe of his compartner A. D. (who opposed the matter,) he laboureth by popular and plausible pretexts to eleuate the esteeme of the Doctors writings: which had wrought impression vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and were likely to preuaile further.<note place="margin">Hier. Prooem. l. 12. in Esa. Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus tam imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus scriptor est, qui non inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at lectorem si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milem sui. Laert. in vita Diog. l. 6.</note>
   </p>
   <p>This Cretensian is not ignorant, that vaine and instable minds (whereof there are great plentie) do greedily attend and affect that which is like vnto themselues: and perhaps he hath read, how when the Philosopher spake soberly to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they gaue him no audience, but playing the minstrell,
<pb facs="11"/> multitudes flocked about him: all so superstitious Romists, are prone to credit the worst, concerning all them which are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse to them: and the most of them are inuenomed with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred against vs. And our answer for our selues is not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be heard or read by them<note n="g" place="margin">Septim. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretal. lib. 5. tit. 4. c. 6.</note>: And thereupon to be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by any of their owne partie, is to their proselytes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction of vs. And it fareth with them as Tertullian<note n="h" place="margin">Tertul. de spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctac. c. 2.</note> said of the Gentiles: <hi>Linguam ad maleloquium, &amp; aures ad receptaculum maleloquij:</hi> Their tongues are bent to euill speaking, and their eares are open to entertaine euill saying. And I may charge this aduersarie, as S. August.<note n="i" place="margin">Aduers. leg. &amp; proph. l. 2. c. 4.</note> did a Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chee, that he is one of that number, who stoned the messengers that were sent vnto them, Math. <hi>21.35. Non ictibus saxeis, sed maledictionibus duris:</hi> not with knocks of stones (which present times, and protection of gracious Princes permit not) but with hard and grieuous words. He is according to the manner of the Seminary, extremely slanderous<note n="k" place="margin">Plutarch. de discr. adul. &amp; amic. Medius princeps parasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dri magni, suis praecepit, vt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacter calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijs incesserent: Quia etsi vulnus sanauerit qui sauciatus est, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catrix tamen manet.</note>: and without any knowledge, witnesse, or probabilitie of the things obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, cryeth Beelzebub, Samaritan, glutton, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer, we may not desist from reproouing error, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the reproch of men,</hi> Esay <hi>51.7.</hi> And the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>passed before vs through good report and euill. 2.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.8.</hi> And Cyprian<note n="l" place="margin">Cypr. Ep. 55. Si id enitimur &amp; elaboramus, vt possimus Deo placere, conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia &amp; maledicta humana debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus contemne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> complained in his dayes of such as trauelled to Rome against him, <hi>cum mendaciorum merce,</hi> with a packet of lies: and Cyril<note n="m" place="margin">Cyr. in concil. Ephesin.</note> saith, <hi>It is not possible to escape the venime of euill speakers, if a man be neuer so vnblameable:</hi> But yet as Cyprian<note n="n" place="margin">Ep. 55.</note> saith: <hi>Non qui audit, sed qui facit conuicium miser est:</hi> He onely is miserable that vttereth slander, and not they which are reproched. And (with Chrysostome<note n="o" place="margin">Chrys. 1. Cor. hom. 43.</note>) <hi>We maruell not if a serpent spit venime at vs when he is pricked: and we more honour our valiant Captaines, when they returne with dyed
<pb facs="11"/> garments from the conquest of their enemies. That cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dishonest and malicious things</hi> (saith Cyprian<note n="p" place="margin">Ep. 52.</note>) <hi>are bruited of him, I would not haue thee maruell; seeing thou knowest that this is perpetually, the diuels worke to teare in peeces Gods seruants with lies: &amp; to conspurcate and vilifie their glorious name, with false opinions, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> This Popish Priest hath turned himselfe into many shapes, to make sowre appeare sweete, darknesse light, and euill good: and he applieth the best complements of fraud and art which are in him, to extenuate the worth of his aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and his cause; and to exalt and blandish his owne: <hi>Yet as a pot-sheard couered with siluer.</hi> Pro. <hi>26. and as dung mixed with perfume</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Creg. Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> so is the burden and substance of his worke. And I shall not wrong him in applying that sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Augustine<note n="r" place="margin">Cont. faust. Manich. l. 13. c. 6.</note>, to his tripartite worke: <hi>Puerile ludibrium, muliebre iocamentum, aniculare delira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, continens initium truncum, medium putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp; finem ruinosum:</hi> It is a childish toy, a womanish trifle, and an old wiues dotage: containing a blockish first part, a rotten middle, and a ruinous conclusion.</p>
   <p>If God had ordained my Brother longer life, himselfe had bene best able (if this Treatise had come forth) to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended his owne worke, and to haue put this Alyen to flight: But the diuine prouidence (which all things obey) dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing otherwise: and he being now translated out of the Church Militant into the Church Triumphant; his owne trauels are ended, and his warfare is accomplished: And resisting and reprouing his Aduersaries in this world, must either ceasse, or be supplied by others.</p>
   <p>Now had the Aduersarie proceeded in this matter with any moderation, I would not haue interposed my selfe, nor presumed in this ripe and lettered age to haue come in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<pb facs="12"/> neither had it needed. The defence of the faith and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of England, dependeth not vpon such priuate mens labors, but is supported by firmer pillars and more solid bases. But the insolencie of this Romist, was so abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue and intollerable: (presuming no doubt the Doctor being deceassed, he should neuer be called to a reckoning) that many deemed it vnworthy for me, to suffer a dog to pisse vpon the dead ashes of my well deseruing Brother: and an impure sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophant (hauing all his force in his tongue as an adder hath in his taile) to distaine and deride his iust deserts.</p>
   <p>And being now engaged in this businesse, I intreate the Reader to consider these few things following.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> That the veritie of doctrine, and the cause beeweene our Aduersaries and vs, dependeth not vpon gaudie and auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious speeches of either side, but vpon substance and weight of things; and therefore he must not measure the truth of the cause by painted and glorious words: but penetrate into the matter it selfe. For as they which behold enterludes, do not esteeme those Actors to be Kings and great Worthies which play the parts and vtter the speeches of such: knowing that these things do onely serue the scene: so it happeneth in our Aduersaries proceedings, when they stile themselues Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and their Aduersaries heretikes, nouellists, &amp;c. And enrobe themselues with the habit of Antiquitie, succession, vniuersalitie and the rest: here is a very stage play. Thersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes acteth Achilles his part, and a Cobler beareth Hercules club.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> Take notice that I haue purposely and with premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abstained from replying to sundry opprobrious and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue passages of this Aduersarie: not for want of matter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; but partly for that it irketh me to vse such demainor, as the indignitie of his abuses require: partly taking counsell
<pb facs="12"/> from Saint Hierom, who saith: <hi>It auaileth not the cause,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ad Pammach &amp; Ocean. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine error.</note>
      <hi>to remaligne them which haue wronged vs, or to requite our Aduersaries with the law of like.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> I haue added to sundry passages of this Treatise, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations concerning the matters in question betweene the Aduersaries and vs: partly to make my labor more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Reader, which otherwise would for the more part haue bene taken vp in altercation &amp; word-bate; and partly to notifie to the Reader the state of the question &amp; true Tenet of each side: (which our Aduersaries continually obscure and dissemble, placing a Chimera and counterfeit in stead thereof.)</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> I haue placed in the margent of my booke the words of many Authors, whose testimonies I produce: partly to abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiate the worke in the text, partly to take away iust occasion of quarrell from the Aduersary, about translation or other falsification; and also to benefit such persons as want the bookes of the said Authors, and to offer others a present view of that which I affirme.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> In sundry questions I omit very weightie arguments and documents belonging to our cause, by reason the same are obuious in our worthie writers, and are better and more fully handled and proposed by them, then they could haue bene by me.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> If it seeme good to this Popish Priest to reply, it shall be iust for him to proceed according to the state of the question deliuered by me, and not to reply (as he hath done in this booke) vpon an imaginarie Tenet. And I further presume that in regard of his owne reputation, (which is already im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired by this demainor) he will not trifle out the time in banding words, or collecting pretended contradictions, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting assertions besides their meaning: Or snatch here
<pb facs="13"/> and there, (as a dog lappeth Nilus) or diuorce &amp; disioyne one parcell of my sentences from another: But seeing that I haue proposed in each question perspicuous and distinct matter for him to reply vpon, which he cannot mistake, (vnlesse he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to raise a smoke, and thereby to shelter himselfe:) that he will accordingly descend to the examination and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of that which is disliked by him, and maintained by me.</p>
   <p>And now referring these my labors to the iudgement and conscience of each discreet and impartiall Reader: and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my doctrine and writing to the Church of England, whose obedient sonne I professe my selfe to be: I will descend to the particular examination of the Aduersaries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all the offices of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and truth, FRANCIS WHITE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>