<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Walker, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119338_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14661</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24963</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119338</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Walker, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and profitable treatise of Gods prouidence : Written for the instruction and comfort of the godly: for the winning and conuersion of sinners: and for a terror to the obstinate and prophane: diuided into sixe parts. By Ralph Walker preacher of the Word</title>
                 <author>Walker, Ralph, preacher of the word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 354 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering (Christian Reader) the precept of our Sauiour Christ, Matth. <hi>6.33.</hi> the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of all Gods children,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.31.</note>
      <note place="margin">Jn Cant.</note>
      <hi>Ea prius ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usque curare quae sunt viciniora saluti: First and chiefely</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> saith) <hi>to respect those things which are most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable to saluation:</hi> I cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the common course of the world, that whereas the knowledge of the Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, is most requisite to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, being both an introduction to the rest, and also simplie necessarie in it selfe; and that the whole world being a schoole of the same, euery creature a Tutor,<note place="margin">Quocunque te vertis, veritas vestigijs qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>husdam quae o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peribus suis impressit, tibi loquitur. Aug. de lib. Arbit.</note> euery acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a proofe, and euery motion a plaine Demonstration; that yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (as lamentable experience doth teach) most men, if not in all, yet in some points are whollie ignorant of the same. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this doth proceede from shame to enquire, sloth to learne, neglect to know, scorne to bee taught, or from a perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb facs="6"/>that wee see well alreadie,<note place="margin">Multa nesciun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut sciendi incuria, aut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendi desidia, aut verecundia inquirendi; &amp; quidem huius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non habet excusationem. Bern. in Epist. Ad Valent. Jn Moral.</note> like the foole in <hi>Seneca,</hi> who though her eyes were quite out, yet would sooner beleeue the house was darke at noone day, then that shee had lost her seeing; this ignorance thus farre growing, or thus arising, can pleade no excuse. <hi>Aliud est nescire, aliud nolle scire: It is one thing</hi> (saith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>) <hi>not to know, and another thing to refuse to know: Gregorie</hi> notes the difference, <hi>Nescire ignorantia est, sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re noluisse, superbia est: Not to know is ignorance, but to refuse to know, is arrogancie.</hi> And who doe refuse? <hi>Chrysostome</hi> telles thee; <hi>Quibus fuit inueniendi facultas, si fuisset quaerendi voluntas: Those which had meanes to know, if they had had willes to seeke. Augustine</hi> telles mee there are two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons commendable in Religion:<note place="margin">De vtilit. cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi.</note> the one, hee which hath found the truth, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee which would finde it. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the consideration of the precept of Christ, of the practise of the Church, of the necessitie of this doctrine, of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous estate of those that are ignorant of it, shall mooue to a desire to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed therein, this person I would help a
<pb facs="6"/>little; of that former I would bee hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped my selfe: and therefore dare not offer this my simple Treatise, (like an vnskilfull Empirick,) to enforme a Doctor: but see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the contagion of sinne verie extreme, and euerie good Physition to haue more then enough to doe to cure the same, I haue presumed to minister those approued receites, which of great and good Physiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I haue long agoe learned. God sends the more excellent, sometimes to the lesse excellent, as man to the ante, the swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the storke, the crane, the oxe, the asse, to learne vnderstanding: my hope is then,<note place="margin">Modus dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di apertus, est omnibus acces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilis, licèt paucissimis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrabilis. Aug. ad Volusia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> that the best may get some good from hence; if it bee but from a sight of the small gifts in mee, to consider of the great in themselues, and so to bee stirred vp to more thankefulnesse to God, and greater care to vse them, they shall not lose their labour. All true members though not in the same place, nor of the same dignitie, yet doe labour the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the whole. Euerie man cannot bring gold and siluer to the Temple: eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one hath not the skill of caruing, and working curiously: if I may bring baser mettals, so they bee necessarie, or by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="7"/>plainely, may helpe in the building, it shall bee my comfort, and I shall harte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie praise God for it: neither distrust I, but that by diligent reading, and faithfull prayers to God for a blessing, it shall bee effected.<note place="margin">Quod credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, debemus authoritati: quod intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, rationi. quod ceramus, opinioni. Aug. de vtil. cred.</note> And so leauing the errors of the wilful to their opinions which begate them, but wishing that thy vnderstanding (gentle Reader) may leane to reason, and thy beliefe to the surest au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: I commit thee to Gods protection.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, RALPH WALKER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>