<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ARTHVR BOVRCHIER TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119929_Fr1_6_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15140</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25438</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119929</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ARTHVR BOVRCHIER TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A choice of emblemes, and other deuises, for the moste parte gathered out of sundrie writers, Englished and moralized. And diuers newly deuised, by Geffrey Whitney. A worke adorned with varietie of matter, both pleasant and profitable: wherein those that please, maye finde to fit their fancies: bicause herein, by the office of the eie, and the eare, the minde maye reape dooble delighte throughe holsome preceptes, shadowed with pleasant deuises: both fit for the vertuous, to their incoraging: and for the wicked, for their admonishing and amendment</title>
                 <author>Whitney, Geffrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Leiden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Plantin, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raphelengius, Franciscus</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 230, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>ARTHVR BOVRCHIER TO THE READER.</head>
   <l>
      <hi>PERFECTION</hi> needes no other foyles, suche helpes comme out of place:</l>
   <l>For where it selfe, can grace it selfe, there needes no other grace.</l>
   <l>Why should I then my fruiteles praise on <hi>WHITNEYS</hi> worke bestowe,</l>
   <l>Where wisdome, learninge, and deuise, so perfectly doe flowe.</l>
   <l>Yet gentle Reader by thy leaue, thus muche I mente to wrighte,</l>
   <l>As one that honours these his giftes, but seekes them not t'indighte.</l>
   <l>No longe discourse, no tedious tale, I purpos'de am to tell:</l>
   <l>Lest thou shouldst saye, where is the nutte, you feede me with the shell.</l>
   <l>Goe forwarde then in happie time, and thou shalt surely finde,</l>
   <l>With coste, and labour well set out, a banquet for thy minde.</l>
   <l>A storehouse for thy wise conceiptes, a whetstone for thy witte:</l>
   <l>Where, eache man maye with daintie choice his fancies finely fitte.</l>
   <l>Giue <hi>WHITNEY</hi> then thy good report, since hee deserues the same:</l>
   <l>Lest that the wise that see thee coye, thy follie iustly blame.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>