<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>BRIEFE NOTES RE∣LATING TO THE DVBI∣OVS AND OFFENSIVE places in the following CONSIDERATIONS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119070_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14258</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24571</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119070</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>BRIEFE NOTES RE∣LATING TO THE DVBI∣OVS AND OFFENSIVE places in the following CONSIDERATIONS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hundred and ten considerations of Signior Iohn Valdesso : treating of those things which are most profitable, most necessary, and most perfect in our Christian profession. Written in Spanish, brought out of Italy by Vergerius, and first set forth in Italian at Basil b Coelius Secundus Curio, anno 1550. Afterward translated into French, and printed at Lions 1563. and again at Paris 1565. And now translated out of the Italian copy into English, with notes. Whereunto is added an epistle of the authors, or a preface to his divine commentary upon the Romans</title>
                 <author>Valdés, Juan de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 311, 13 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_notes">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>BRIEFE NOTES RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATING TO THE DVBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS <hi>AND OFFENSIVE</hi> places in the following CONSIDERATIONS.</head>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 3 CONSID. upon these words, <hi>Not for thy speech! Other Law and other Doctrine have we.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese words about the H. Scripture suite with what he writes elsewhere, especially Consid. 32. But I like none of it, for it slights the Scripture too much: holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have not only an Elementary use, but a use of perfection, and are able to make the man of God perfect 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. And <hi>David</hi> (though <hi>David)</hi> studied all the day long in it: And <hi>Ioshua</hi> was to meditate therein Day and Night. <hi>Iosh.</hi> the 1.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 3 CONSID. upon those words, <hi>As they also mak use of the Scriptures to conserve the health of their minds.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>All the Saints of God may be said in some sence to have put con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in Scripture, but not as a naked Word severed from God, but as the Word of God: And in so doing they doe not sever there trust from God. But by trusting in the word of God they trust in God. Hee that trusts in the Kings word for any thing trusts in the King.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>To the 5 CONSID. <hi>Vpon these words. God regards not how pious, or impious we be.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>This place together with many other, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> namely Consid. 71. upon <hi>Our Father;</hi> and Consid. 94. upon these words▪ God doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> hold them for good, or for evill for that they observe, or not observe &amp;c. though it were the Authors opinion, yet the truth of it would be examined. See the note upon Consid. 36</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 6 CONSID.</head>
      <p>The Doctrine of the last passage must be warily understood. First that it is not to be understood of actuall sinnes, but habituall, for I can no more free my selfe from actuall sinnes after Baptisme, then I could of Originall before, and without Baptisme. The exemption from both, is by the Grace of God. Secondly, among Habits some oppose Theologicall vertues, as Vncharitablene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e oppos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Charity, Infidelity, Faith; Distrust Hope: Of these none can free themselves of themselves, but only by the Grace of God: Other Habits oppose morall vertues, as Prodigality opposes Moderation; and Pusillanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Magnanimity: Of these the heathen freed themselves, only by the generall Providence of God, as <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Aristides, &amp;c.</hi> Where he sayes the <hi>Inflammation of the naturall▪</hi> he sayes aptly, so it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood with the former distinction, for <hi>Fomes</hi> is not taken away, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t <hi>Accensio Fomitis;</hi> the naturall concupiscence is not quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished, but the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e of it af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>waged.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 11 CONSID.</head>
      <p>He often useth this manner of speech <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>leeving by Revelation, not by relation,</hi> whereby I understand he meaneth, Only the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all operation or illumination of the holy spirit, testifying, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the revealed truth of the Gospell; and not any private Enthusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmes, or Revelations: As if he should say; a generall apprehension, or assent to the promises of the Gospell by heare-say, or relation from others, is not that which filleth the heart with joy and peace in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; but the spirits bearing witnesse which our spirit revealing and applying the generall promises to every one in particular with such syncerity, and efficacy, that it makes him godly, righteous, and sober all his life long; this I call <hi>beleeving by Revelation, and not by Relation.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>To the 32 CONSID.</head>
      <p>I much mislike the Comparison of the Images, and H. Scripture, as if they were both but Alphabets and after a time to be left. The H. Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> (as I wrote before) have not only an Elementary use, but a use of perfection, neither can they ever be exhausted, (as Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures may be by a plenarie circumspection) but still even to the most learned and perfect in them, there is somewhat to be learned more: Therefore <hi>David</hi> desireth God in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>19 <hi>Psalme,</hi> to open his eyes that he might see the wondrous things of his Lawes, and that he would make them his study. Although by other words of the same <hi>Psalme</hi> it is evident, that he was not meanly conversant in them. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he that shall so attend to the bark of the letter, as to neglect the Consideration of Gods Worke in his heart through the Word, doth amisse; both are to be done the Scriptures still used, and Gods worke within us still observed, who workes by his Word, and ever in the reading of it. As for the Text, <hi>They shall be all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ught of God,</hi> it being Scripture cannot be spoken to the disparagement of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but the meaning is this, That God in the dayes of the Gospell will not give an outward Law of Ceremonies as of old, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> such a one as shall still have the assistance of the holy spirit applying it to our hearts, and ever outrunning the Teacher, as it did when <hi>Peter</hi> taught <hi>Cornelius:</hi> there the case i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> plaine, <hi>Cornelius</hi> had revelation, yet <hi>Peter</hi> was to be sent for, and those that have inspirations must still use <hi>Peter,</hi> Gods Word: if we make another sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e of that Text; wee shall overthrow all means, save catechizing, and set up Enthusiasmes.</p>
      <p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell rows="2">In the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are</cell>
               <cell>Doctrines, these ever teach more and more.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Promises, these ever comfort more and more <hi>Ro.</hi> 15. 4.</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 33 CONSID.</head>
      <p>The Doctrine of this Consideration cleareth that of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. For as the servant leaves not the letter when he hath read it, but keepes it by him, and reads it againe and againe, and the more the promise is delayed, the more he reads it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ortifies himselfe with it; so are wee to doe with the Scriptures and this is the use of the promises of the Scriptures. But the use of the Doctrinall part i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> more, in regard it presents us not with the same thing only when it
<pb facs="5"/>
is read as the promises doe, but enlightens us with new Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the more we read i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</p>
      <p>Much more might be said, but this sufficeth, he himselfe allowes it for a holy conversation and refreshment.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 36 CONSID. <hi>On these words, Neither fearing chastisement for transgressiion; nor hoping for reward, for observation, &amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>All the discourse from this line till the end of this Chapter may seeme strange, but it is sutable to what the Author holds elsewhere, for he maintaines that it is Faiith and Infidelity that shall judge us now since the Gospell, and that no other sin or vertue hath any thing to doe with us; if we believe, no sinne shall hurt us; if we believe not, no vertue shall helpe us. Therefore he saith here we shall not be punished (which word I like here better then chastizement, because even the godly are chastized but not punished) for evill doing nor rewarded for weldoing or living, for all the point lies in believing or not believing. And with this exposition the Chapter is cleare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but the truth of the Doctrine would be examined, however it may passe for his opinion, in the Church of God there is one fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall, but else variety.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the XXXVII. CONSID. <hi>On these words; That God is so delicate and sensitive &amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>The Apostle saith that the wages of Sinne is death, and therefore <note place="margin">This note is the French Translators.</note> there is no sinne so small, that merits not death, and that doth not provoke God, who is a jealous God.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 46 CONSID. <hi>On these words, Exercise not thy selfe in anything pretending Iustification.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>He meaneth (I suppose) that a man presume not to merit, that is, to oblige God, or justify himselfe before God, by any acts or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises of Religion; but that he ought to pray God affection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tely, and fervently to send him the light of his spirit, which may be unto him as the sunne to a Travellour in his journey, hee in the meane while
<pb facs="5"/>
applying himselfe to the duties of true Piety, and syncere Religion, such as are Prayer, Fasting, Alme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>-deedes, &amp;c. after the example of devout <hi>Cornelius</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 49 CONSID. <hi>On these words, Remaining quiet when they perceive no motion, &amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>In indifferent things there is roome for motions and expecting of them; but in things good, as to relieve my Neighbour, God hath already revealed, his Will about it. Therefore wee ought to proceed, except there be a restraining motion (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> had) when hee would have preached in Asia, and I conceive the restraining motions are much more frequent to the godly, then inviting motions; because the Scripture invites enough, for it invites us to all good, according to that singular place, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 8. A man is to embrace all good, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he cannot doe all, God often chuseth which he shall doe, and that by restraining him from what he would not have him doe.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the same CONSID. <hi>Vpon these words, A man's free-will doth consist, &amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>He meanes a mans fre-will is only in outward, not in spirituall things.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the same CONSID. <hi>On these words, Neithor</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>nor</hi> Iudas <hi>&amp;c. could cease to be such.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>This doctrine however true in substance, yet needeth discre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t, and wary explaining</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the LVIII. CONSID. <hi>Vpon the seventh difference.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>By <hi>occasions</hi> (I suppose) hee meaneth the ordinary, or necessary duties, and occasions of our calling and condition of life; and not those which are in themselves occasions of sinne; such as are all vain
<pb facs="6"/>
conversations: For as for these, pious persons ought alwaies to avoid them: but in those other occasions, Gods Spirit will mortify and try them as gold in the fire.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the LIX. CONSID. <hi>Upon these words, And with doubtfulnesse I see he prayed in the Garden.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>To say our Saviour prayed with doubtfulnesse, is more then I can or dare say; But with condition, or conditionally he prayed as man, though as God he knew the event. Feare is given to Christ, but not doubt, and upon good ground.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the LXII. CONSID.</head>
      <p>This Chapter is considerable, the intent of it, that the world <hi>pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth</hi> not godly mens actions no more then Gods, is in some sort true because they are spiritually discerned. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. So likewise are the godly in some sort exempt from Lawes, for <hi>Lex iusto non est pofita:</hi> But when he enlargeth them hegoes too farre. For first concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi> I ever tooke that for a weaknesse in the great Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>k: And that the best of Gods Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>vants should have weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses is no way repugnant to the way. of Gods Spirit in them, or to the Scriptures, or to themselves being still men, though godly men. Nay they are purposely accorded in holy Writ. Wherefore as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid's</hi> Adultery cannot be excused, so need not <hi>Abraham's</hi> Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor <hi>Paul's</hi> neither, when he professed himselfe a Pharisee, which strictly he was not, though in the point of Resurrection he agreed with them, and they with him. The reviling also of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>anias</hi> seemes by his owne recalling, an oversight; yet I remember the Fathers forbid us to judge of the doubtfull actions of Saints in the Scriptures; which is a modest admonition. But it is one thing not to judge, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to defend them. Secondly, when he useth the Word Iurisdiction allowing no Iurisdiction over the godly, this cannot stand, and it is ill Doctrine in a common-wealth. The godly are punishable as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when they doe amisse, and they are to be judged according to the outward fact, unlesse it be evident to others, as well as to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves that God moved them. For otherwise any Malefactor may pretend motions, which is unsufferable in a Common-wealth. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I doubt but if <hi>Abraham</hi> had lived in our Kingdome under government, and had killed his sonne <hi>Isaac,</hi> but he might have been justly put to death for it by the Magistrate, unleffe he could have
<pb facs="6"/>
made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> appeare, that it was done by Gods immediate precept. He had done justly, and yet he had been punished justly, that is <hi>in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> foro &amp; secundum praesumptionem legalem.</hi> So may a warre be just on both sides, and was just in the Canaanites and Israelites both. How the godly are exempt from Laws is a known point a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Divines, but when he sayes they are equally exempt with God, that is dangerous and too farre.</p>
      <p>The best salve for the whole Chapter, is to distinguish Iudgments There is a judgment of authority (upon a fact) and there is a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Learned; for as a Magistrate judgeth in his tribunall, so a Scholar judgeth in his study, and censureth this or that; whence come so many Books of severall mens opinions: perhaps he meant all of this later not of the former. Worldly learned men cannot judg spirituall me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> actions, but the Magistrate may.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the LXIII. CONSID.</head>
      <p>The Authour doth still discover too slight a regard of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as if it were but childrens meat, whereas there is not onely milke there, <hi>but strong meat also.</hi> HEB. 5. 14. <hi>Things hard to bee understood.</hi> 2. PFT. 3. 16. <hi>Things needing great Consideration.</hi> MAT. 24. 15. Besides he opposeth the teaching of the spirit to the teaching of the scripture, which the holy spirit wrot. Although the holy spirit apply the scripture, yet what the scripture teacheth, the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit teacheth, the holy spirit indeed sometime doubly teaching both in penning and in applying. I wonder how this opinion could befall so good a man as it seems <hi>Valdesso</hi> was, since the Saints of God in all ages have ever held in so pretious esteem the word of God, as their Ioy, and Crowne, and their Treasure on earth. Yet his owne practice seemes to confute his opinion, for the most of his Considerations being grounded upon some text of scripture, shewes that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually conversant in it, and not used it for a time onely, and then cast it away, as he sayes strangely.</p>
      <p>There is no more to be said of this Chapter but that his opinion of the scripture is unsufferable. As for the text of S. PFT. 2. Ep. 1. 19. which he makes the ground of his Consideration, building it all upon the word <hi>uutill the day starre arise,</hi> it is nothing. How many places doe the Fathers bring about Vntil against the Heretiques who dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted against the Virginity of the blessed Virgin out of that text MAT. 1. 25. where it is said, <hi>Joseph knew her not, untill shee had brought forth her first borne Sonne,</hi> as if afterwards he had knowne her: and indeed in common sence, if I bid a man stay in a place untill I come, I doe not then bid him goe away but rather stay longer, that I may
<pb facs="7"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>peak with him or doe some thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e when I doe come; so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Peter bidding the dispersed Hebrews at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>end to the word till the day da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, doth not bid them then cast away the word, or leave it off: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he would have them attend to it till that time, and then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they will attend it of themselves without his exhortation. Nay it is observeable that in that very place he preferres the Word before the sight of the Transfiguration of Christ. So that the Word hath the precedence even of Revelations and Visions. And so his whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course and sevenfold observation falls to the ground.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 65. CONSID. <hi>on these words,</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <hi>Acknowledging the benefit received by Iesus Christ our Lord; like as it betides unto a thirsty Travellour, to whom &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>This comparison is infinitely too base, there is none of the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, which we have had with our Lord Iesus Christ, dissolved but <note place="margin">This note is the French Translators.</note> infinitely perfected, and he shall ever continue our glorious head, and all the influences of our happinesse shall ever descend from him, and the chief our glory shall (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> I conceive) consist in that which he saith amongst the last words that he spake in the 17. Iohn. v. 24. <hi>Father I will that they also whom thou hast given me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ee with me, where I am, that they also may behold the glory which thou hast gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me before the foundation of the world.</hi> To which agreeth that which S. Paul writes, 2. THES. 1. <hi>chap. v.</hi> 9.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>
         <hi>To the</hi> 69. <hi>CONSID. upon these words,</hi> So much faith, as thereby to remove Mountaines.</head>
      <p>Divines hold, that justifying faith, and the faith of miracles are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers guifts, and of a different nature, the one being <hi>gratia gratis da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>a,</hi> the other <hi>gratia gratum faciens,</hi> this being given only to the godly, and the other sometimes to the wicked. Yet doubtlesse the best faith in us is defective, and arrives not to the point it should, which if it did, it would doe more, then it does. And miracle-working as it may be severed from justifying faith, so it may be a fruit of it, and an exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. 1. IOHN. 5. 14.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="note">
      <head>To the 94. CONSID.</head>
      <p>By <hi>Hebrew piety,</hi> he meaneth not the very C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>remonies of the
<pb facs="7"/>
Iewes, which no Christian observes now, but an analogat observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ecclesiasticall, and Canonicall lawes, supe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>duced to the scriptures, like to that of Iewes, which they added to their divine law. This being well weighed, will make the Consideration easy, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry observeable: For at least, some of the Papist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> are come no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, to what the Pharisees were come in our Saviours time.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>