<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>W. T. To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1530</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1193_Bo1_1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13203</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2350</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1193</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>W. T. To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Pentateuch</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1530</date>
                 <publisher>Hoochstraten (Hillenius Hoochstratanus), Joannes.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Luft, Hans, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>755 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>W. T. To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had translated the newe testament / I added a pistle vnto the latter ende / In which I desyred them y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re learned to amend if ought were founde amysse. But oure mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious and wylye hypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crytes which are so stubburne and hard herted in their weked abhominaciōs that it is not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssible for them to amend any thinge atall (as we see by dayly experience when their both ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinges and doinges are rebufed with the tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uth) saye / some of them that it is unpossible to translate the scripture in to English / some th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at it is not lawfull for the laye people to have it in their mother tonge / some that it wold make them all heretyfes / as it wold no doute from many thinges which they of longe tyme haue falsly taught / ād that is the whole cause wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they forbyd it / though they other clokes pretende. And some or rather every one / saye that it wold make them ryse ageynst the kinge / whom they them selves (vnto their damnatyō) never yet obeyed. And lefte the temporall ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars shuld see their falsehod / if the scripture cam to light / causeth them so to lye.</p>
   <p>And as for my translatid in which they affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto the laye people (as I haue hearde saye)
<pb facs="2"/>
to be I wotte not how many thousande here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syes / so that it cā not be mēded or correcte / they haue yet taken so greate payne to cramyne it / &amp; to compare it vnto that they wold fayne haue it and to their awne imaginations and iugglin ge termes / and to haue some what to rayle at / and vnder that cloke to blaspheme the treuth / that they myght with as litle laboure (as I sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pose) haue translated the moste parte of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For they which in tymes paste were wont to loke on no more scripture then they sounde in their duns or soch like develysh doctryne / haue yet now so narowlye loked on my translatyon / that there is not so moch as one I therin if it lack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a tytle over his hed / but they haue noted it / and nombre it vnto the ignorant people for anheresy. Fynallye in this they be all agreed / to dryve you from the knowledge of the scripture / &amp; that ye shall not haue the terte therof in the mother tonge / and to kepe the world styll in dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenesse / to thentent they might sirt in the consci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences of the people / thorow vayne superstition and false doctrine / to satisfye their fylthy lustes their proude ambition / and vnsatiable covetu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ousnes / and to exalte their awne honoure abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue kinge &amp; emperoure / yee &amp; aboue god him silfe</p>
   <p>¶ A thousand bokes had they lever to be put forth agensce their abhominable doynges and doctrine / then that the scripture shulde come to light. For as longe as they may kepe that dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / they will so darken the ryght way with the
<pb facs="3"/>
miste of their sophistrye / and so tangle thē that ether rebuke or despyse their abhommations with argumentes of philosophye &amp; with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly symylitudes and apparent reasons of natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall wisdom. And with wrestinge the scripture vnto their awne purpose clene contrarye vnto y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> processe / order and meaninge of the texte / and so delude them in descantynge vppon it with al ligoryes / and amase thē expoundinge it in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye senses before the vnlerned laye people (wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en it hath but one symple litterall sense whose light the owles cā not abyde) that though thou feale in thyne harte and arte sure how that all is false y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they saye / yet coudeste thou not sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve their sotle rydles.</p>
   <p>¶ Which thinge onlye moved me to translate the new testament. Because I had perceaved by experyence / how that it was impossible to stablysh the laye people in any truth / excepte y<seg rend="sup">o</seg> scripture were playnly layde besore their eyes in their mother tonge / that they might se the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cesse / ordre and meaninge of the texte: for els what so ever truth is taught them / these enny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of all truth qwench it ageyne / partly wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th the smoke of their bottomlesse pyite wherof thou readest apocalipsis .ix. that is / with appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reasons of sophistrye &amp; traditions of their awne makynge / founded with out grounde of scripture / and partely in iugglinge with the tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / expoundinge it in soch a sense as is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="3"/>
to gether of the texte / if thou see the processe ordre and meaninge therof.</p>
   <p>¶ And even in the bisshope of londons house I entended to have done it. For when I was so turmoyled in the conire where I was that I coude no lenger there dwell (the processe w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herof were to longe here to reherce) I this wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se thought in my silfe / this I suffre because the prestes of the contre be vnlerned / as god it kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth there are a full ignorant sorte which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue sene no more latyn then that they read in their portesses and missales which yet many of them can scacely read (excepte it be Albertus desecretis mulierū in which yet / thought they be never so soryly lerned / they pore day and ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght and make notes therin and all to teach the mydwyves as they say / and linwod a boke of constitutions together tithes / mortuaryes / offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringes / customs / and other pillage / which they calle / not theirs / but godes parte and the deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holye chirch / to discharge their conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with all for they are bound that they shall not dimynysh / but encreace all thinge vnto the vttmost of their powers) and therfore (becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se they are thus vnlerned thought I) when they come to gedder to the alehouse / which is their preachinge place / they afferme that my sainges are heresy. And besydes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they adde to of thir awne heddes which I never spake / as the maner is to prolonge the tale to shorte
<pb facs="4"/>
the tyme with all / and accuse me secretly to the chauncelare and other the bishopes officers / And indeade when I cam before the chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare / he thretened me grevously / and rexyled me and rated me as though I had bene a dogge / and layd to my charge wherof there coude be none accuser brought forth (as their maner is not to bringe forth the accuser) and yet all the prestes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> contre were y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> same daye there. As I this thought the bishope of london came to my remembrance whom Erasmus (whose ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge maketh of litle gnattes greate elephātes and lifteth vpp aboue the starres whosoever geveth him a litle exhibition) prayseth excedingly amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge other in his annotatyons on the new testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his great learninge. Then thought I / if I might come to this mannes service / I we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re happye. And so I gate me to london / &amp; tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the accoyntaunce of my master came to sir harry gilford the kinges graces countroller / ād brought him an oration of Isocrates which I had translated out of greke in to English / and desyred him to speake vnto my lorde of london for me / which he also did as he shewed me / ād willed me to write a pistle to my lorde / and to god to him my silf which I also did / and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered my pistle to a servant of his awne / one wyllyam he bil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hwayte / a mā of myne old acco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yntaūce. But god which kneweth what is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin hypocrites / sawe that I was begyled / ād that that councell was not the nexte way vnto
<pb facs="4"/>
my purpose. And therfore he gate me no favou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in my lordes sight ¶ Wherevppō my lorde an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swered me / his house was full / he had mo thē he coude well finde / and advised me to seke in london / wher he sayd I coude not lacke a servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / And so in london I abode almoste an yere / and marked the course of the worlde / and her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de oure pratars / I wold say oure preachers how they bosted them selves and their hye au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite / and beheld the pompe of oure prelates and how besyed they were as they yet are / to set peace and vnite in the worlde (though it be not possible for them that walke in darkenesse to cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue longe in peace / for they can not but ether stōble or dash them selves at one thinge or a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother that shall clene vnquyer all togedder) &amp; sawe thinges wherof I deferre to speake at this tyme and vnderstode at the laste not only that there was no rowme in my lorde of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons palace to translate the new testament / but also that there was no place to do it in all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glonde / as experience doth now openly declare. ¶ Vnder what maner therfore shuld I now submitte this boke to be corrected and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of them / which can suffer nothinge to be well▪ Or what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rotestacyon shuld I make in soch a matter vnto oure prelates those stubbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tne N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mrothes which so mightely fight agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste god and resiste his holy spirite / enforceynge with all crafte and sotelte to qwench the light of the everlastinge testament / promyses / and as
<pb facs="5"/>
poyntemente made betwene god &amp; vs: and hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinge the sirce wrath of god vppon all princes and rulars / mockinge thē with falfe fayned na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of hypocrysye / and servinge their lustes at all poyntes / &amp; dispensinge with thē even of the very lawes of god / os which Christe him silf te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifieth Mathew .v. y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> not so moch as one tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle therof maye perish or be brokē. And of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch the prophete fayth Psalme .cxvii. Thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste cōmaunded thy lawes to be kepte meod / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is in hebrew excedingly / with all diligēce / mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght &amp; power / and haue made thē so mad with their iugglinge charmes and crafty persuasiōs that they thinke it full satisfaction for all their weked lyvinge / to tormē<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> soch as tell thē trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th / &amp; to borne the worde of their soules helth &amp; sle whosoever beleve theron.</p>
   <p>¶ Notwithstōdinge yet I submytte this boke and all other that I haue other made or trāsla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / or shall in tyme to come (if it be goddes will that I shall further laboure in his her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest) vnto all them that submytte thē selves vn to the worde of god / to be corrected of thē / yee and moreover to be disalewed &amp; also burnte / if it seme worthy when they have examyned it wyth the hebrue / so that they first put forth of their awne translatinge a nother that is more correcte.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>