<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the yong Men of London, as well Gentlemen as others.</title>
           <author>I., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119332_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14261</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14676</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119332</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the yong Men of London, as well Gentlemen as others.</title>
                 <author>I., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Looke on me London : I am an honest English-man, ripping vp the bowels of mischiefe, luring in thy sub-vrbs and precincts. Take heed the hangmans halter, and the beadles whip, will make the foole dance, and the knaue to skip</title>
                 <author>Johnson, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the yong Men of <hi>London,</hi> as <hi>well Gentlemen as others.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am perswaded, that in this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, I doe salute the most part of all the yong Gentlemen of <hi>England,</hi> in that they either dwell, or haue beene in this worthy Citty of <hi>London,</hi> where they haue seene many wanton alectiues to vnthriftines, which like to inchanting Adamant rockes, drawes gold and siluer as fast as Iron and steele.</p>
   <p>Therefore (yong men) you must bee armed with more experience then the capacity of yong yeares, or else, assure your selues, repentance will vn-loose your fetters: For truely, I cannot see, how yong men of the best education can scape vntangled, when vice is so conuersant with elder yeares. O how happy were it for your posterity, if all Dicing-houses, and allies of gaming were suppressed in, and about this Citty: From which, if you cannot bee drawne, this little booke will guide you safe, and giue you faire warnings of many of your Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions falles: I beseech you bee aduised, and learne to shun these mischiefes by other mens harmes,
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>that the reward of this my writing may proue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, and my selfe happy to see you thriue and flourish.</p>
   <p>I dedicate this Booke to the <hi>Honourable Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> to whom appertaineth the correction of euill liuers, your worst enemies; I meane the sucking shifters now secretly lurking in the circuits of this famous Citty, of whom his good Honour, I hope, will ease you, and make you prosperous by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. So leauing to trouble you with a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Induction, I end at this time, but in no time will leaue to be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your wel-wishing friend. <hi>R. I.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>