<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE right VVorshipfull, Sir William Skipwith knight, and one of his Maiesties Iusti∣ces of the peace in the county of Leicester, the rich blessings of God, to his comfort in this life, and eternall saluation in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Ward, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119471_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14760</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25057</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119471</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE right VVorshipfull, Sir William Skipwith knight, and one of his Maiesties Iusti∣ces of the peace in the county of Leicester, the rich blessings of God, to his comfort in this life, and eternall saluation in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Ward, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods arrovves, or, Two sermons, concerning the visitation of God by the pestilence. Very profitable to be read at all times, but especially in the time of Gods visitation. By William Warde Minister of the word of God.</title>
                 <author>Ward, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ballard, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>[4], 41, [1] leaves ;  8⁰</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE right VVorshipfull, Sir <hi>William Skipwith</hi> knight, and one of his Maiesties Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the peace in the county of <hi>Leicester,</hi> the rich blessings of God, to his comfort in this life, and eternall saluation in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese two ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons (right worshipfull) were penned by me, at the instance of a neere friend, presently after they were preached, but (I protest) not with a purpose euer to haue had them put foorth in print.
<pb facs="4"/> Notwithstanding, the partie that hath them in possession, is growen so resolute, that they shall to the presse, (how vnpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished soeuer) that I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to yeelde thereto, though against my will, because I see no remedy. Onely thus much, I haue obtained, that they may go foorth vnder your protection, to whom next vnder God, I am beholding, and from whom, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your deceased fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I haue receiued maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and vnder whom I haue spent my time by labouring in the Lords vineyard now full twenty and seuen yeeres: Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading my selfe, that as you loue the Word, and the teachers
<pb facs="4"/> thereof, so you will vouchsafe to accept of this my litle worke, though simple, yet agreeable to the sincere word of God, not so much respecting the worke-man far vnworthy to vndergo such a waight, as in regard of him who first opened my mouth, and made me able to deliuer it to his people. And the rather for that, as the Euangelist Saint Luke did of loue, (being inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therunto by the holy Ghost) dedicate his booke to the most noble Theophilus: so I, though no way by the abundance of Gods Spirit so enabled, yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that piece of a Talent giuen me of the Lord, haue out of that dutifull loue I alwayes
<pb facs="5"/> bare towards you, presumed to commend vnto you these abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue first fruits of my publique abours by writing, presented like the widowes mite into the treasury of your fauourable tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition, to be protected from the poyson of Momus and Zoilus, and others of that viperous brood. And thus I humbly take my leaue, committing you to him who neuer leaueth his, &amp;c.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Lord. <hi>William Ward.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>