<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Liues of the Authour of this VVorke, BENEDETTO VARCHI, and of FRANCESCO SANSOVINO, the publisher of the same, whose EPISTLE is before.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119026_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14277</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24593</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Liues of the Authour of this VVorke, BENEDETTO VARCHI, and of FRANCESCO SANSOVINO, the publisher of the same, whose EPISTLE is before.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blazon of iealousie· : A subiect not written of by any heretofore· First written in Italian, by that learned gentleman Benedetto Varchi, sometimes Lord Chauncelor vnto the Signorie of Venice: and translated into English, with speciall notes vpon the same; by R.T. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Varchi, Benedetto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 87, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biographies">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Liues of the Authour of this VVorke, BENEDETTO VARCHI, and of FRANCESCO SANSOVINO, the publisher of the same, whose <hi>EPISTLE</hi> is before.</head>
   <div n="Benedetto Varchi" type="biography">
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ENEDETTO VARCHI, borne in <hi>Florence,</hi> (the chiefe Citie for Beauty and Wealth, in all <hi>Tus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canie)</hi> had to his Schoole-master one <hi>Gasper Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>scotto,</hi> of <hi>Maradi,</hi> (a small Towne in <hi>Lombardie)</hi> who taught him as wel Latine as Greeke, but could not by any meanes endure his Schollers should read any Booke in their owne Mother Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. As he grew in yeeres, so did hee profit in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and in his youthfull time deuoted himselfe vnto the vertuous Seruice of a faire and learned Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, called <hi>Gaspara Stampa,</hi> (as by the Epistle written before you may perceiue) hee making account of her, more for the beautie of her minde, than for that of her body; she being as much admired for her excellent Qualities, as any one Gentlewoman of her time in all <hi>Italy.</hi> Hee wrote many learned workes, especially, that called L'HERCOLANO, where hee discourseth of all Languages in generall; but especially of the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Tuscane tongue. Hee liued in good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit all his life time, being very gratious with <hi>Cosmo,</hi>
         <pb facs="6"/>
Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> and with the Signorie of <hi>Venice:</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a most bountifull pension from them, for being one of the chiefe Readers in their famous Vniuersitie of <hi>Padoa</hi>; about which time (he being the President of that learned Academic of the IMFIAMATI there) deliuered this Oration, in an honourable Assembly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Duke himselfe, and many other noble Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, with great commendation, and kinde applause of them all. But after this (being growne in yeeres) hee returned backe into <hi>Tuscanie,</hi> his natiue Countrey, where after he had seene many fayre and happy yeeres: hee dyed at a Summer-house hee had, not farre from <hi>Florence,</hi> leauing <hi>Thomazo Lenzo,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Fermo,</hi> and <hi>Girolamo Razzi,</hi> a Carthusian Frier, his Executors; and lyeth buried in the <hi>Domo,</hi> the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Florence.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="Francesco Sansovino" type="biography">
      <head>The Life of FRANCESCO SANSOVINO, the first Publisher of this Worke in the Italian tongue.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for FRANCESCO SANSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINO, hee also was a <hi>Florentine</hi> borne; and besides his Schollership, was so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table an Architect, as for his skill hee was surnamed <hi>Archa de Noe,</hi> The Arke of NOAH. Hee was of familiar acquaintance with this Authour BENEDETTO VARCHI, and with a Brother of the foresaid Ladyes, <hi>Gaspara Stampa,</hi> called <hi>Balthazar Stampa,</hi> (a Sonnet of which Gentlemans I haue translated, and set downe amongst mine other Notes, in the Description of Care. To conclude, this
<pb facs="6"/>
         <hi>Francis Sansouino</hi> liued (in his youth) much in <hi>Rome,</hi> but growing in yeeres, hee came to <hi>Venice,</hi> where the Signorie, imploying him about their buildings of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Marke,</hi> bestowed an ancient pension on him, during his life: he dying about the yeere 1570. Hee had a Kinseman about that time liuing in <hi>Florence,</hi> called <hi>Iacomo Sansouino,</hi> so sincere and honest a man of life, as he was surnamed <hi>Spaeculum Florentiae,</hi> (the Mirrour, or Looking-glasse of <hi>Florence.</hi>) Hee dyed of the Gowte, and was buried in the same Graue his Cosin <hi>Francis Sansouino</hi> was enterred (who after his death was brought from <hi>Venice</hi> to <hi>Florence)</hi> in the famous Church of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> (called in Italian <hi>Il Battesimo,</hi>) the Saint and Patron of the aforesaid Citie.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>