<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A discription of the seuen liberall Sciences, into whose company the eight hath intruded her selfe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119694_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01351</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11472</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119694</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A discription of the seuen liberall Sciences, into whose company the eight hath intruded her selfe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first parte, of the eyghth liberall science: entituled, Ars adulandi, the arte of flatterie : with the confutation therof, both very pleasaunt and profitable, deuised and compiled, by Vlpian Fulwell</title>
                 <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ A discription of the seuen liberall <hi>Sciences, into whose company the eight hath intruded her selfe.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <head>Grammer.</head>
      <l>IF learning may delight thy youthfull brest</l>
      <l>If tender yeares to skilfull lore bee bent</l>
      <l>Approche to mee, voutchsafe to bee my guest:</l>
      <l>My entertaynement shall thy minde content.</l>
      <l>My key in hand shall ope the gate of skill,</l>
      <l>My Booke on brest shall teach thy tongue and quill.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Logick.</head>
      <l>FRom <hi>Grammers</hi> Schoole approch to mee with speede,</l>
      <l>Where thou maist learne the rule to reason right,</l>
      <l>I geue the fruit, though <hi>Grammer</hi> sow the seede:</l>
      <l>In mee thou maist decerne the darke from light.</l>
      <l>My fastened fist much matter doth import,</l>
      <l>Coucht in few wordes fit for the learned sort.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Rethorick.</head>
      <l>WHen <hi>Grammers</hi> grace, and <hi>Logickes</hi> learned lore,</l>
      <l>Hath deckt thy minde, and mended nature well,</l>
      <l>My golden study shall yeeld thee such store,</l>
      <l>Of flowing wordes and phrases that excell.</l>
      <l>Lo here with open hand I do display,</l>
      <l>The flowing flood of eloquence alway.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Musick.</head>
      <l>WHen mistie clowde of drouping dumpish head</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
Doth driue thy minde to plunge in pensiue poole,</l>
      <l>The clog of care that soking sorowes bread,</l>
      <l>Is cleane shakte of, by entring to my Schoole.</l>
      <l>My dainty tunes do yeeld such sugred sap,</l>
      <l>As drawes ech blisse, and driues eche foule mishap.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Arrithmetick.</head>
      <l>BY Sciphering Science, lo my summes I cast,</l>
      <l>By wit and weight, I wonderous thinges contriue,</l>
      <l>With bunch of keyes, my counts are lockt vp fast:</l>
      <l>In mee thou maist see how thy wealth doth thriue.</l>
      <l>My armes and brest, my legs eke naked bee,</l>
      <l>To shew that trueth and plainenesse rests in mee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Astronomy.</head>
      <l>FRom earthly skill vnto the lofty skies,</l>
      <l>My globe and I, will shew the lore of light</l>
      <l>Thou shalt foresee what tempest will arise,</l>
      <l>To thee such secrets shall appeare in sight.</l>
      <l>That Starres and Planets shall thy matesremain,</l>
      <l>And thou a fellow with celestiall traine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Geometry.</head>
      <l>BEholde the Compasse and the other tooles,</l>
      <l>Wherwith I worke such wonders as seeme straunge,</l>
      <l>My Rule and Quadrant, are no bookes for fooles,</l>
      <l>A learned scull must in my precepts range.</l>
      <l>Now when thou hast vs Sisters seauen obtainde.</l>
      <l>A worlde of wealth and wisdome thou hast gainde.</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <lg>
      <head>Adulatior, or flatterie.</head>
      <l>BEholde the bragges that Sisters seauen haue made,</l>
      <l>Suruiew their vaunts that seeme to shine so bright</l>
      <l>My glittering skill shall clips them in the shade:</l>
      <l>In mee appeares the beames of perfect light.</l>
      <l>My flattering tongue shall gaine more then they all,</l>
      <l>I geue the trip and they shall take the fall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Grammarians</hi> gaine nought els but bread and cheese,</l>
      <l>Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>hance dame <hi>Logick</hi> haue a small reward,</l>
      <l>Nete <hi>Eloquence</hi> will pleade for slender fees:</l>
      <l>Nice <hi>Musick</hi> as a Minstrel men regard.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Arrithmatick</hi> obtaines but litle thrift,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Astronomy</hi> serues for a simple shift.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Geometrie</hi> may iog on barrels bun,</l>
      <l>And drinke the dregs when liquor al is spent,</l>
      <l>My golden Art the game and gole hath won:</l>
      <l>To my sweete skill, eche hart and eare is bent.</l>
      <l>The Well of wealth my Science doth contriue,</l>
      <l>Then learne my lore all ye that meane to thriue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To mee doth flow the flood of happy state,</l>
      <l>In mee is matcht a masse of worldly blisse,</l>
      <l>No sturdy storme my fauour may abate:</l>
      <l>For Princely eares my presence may not misse.</l>
      <l>I spin the threed and weaue the web of hap,</l>
      <l>And none but I may sit in Fortunes lap.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>