<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119016_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14268</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24581</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119016</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two treatises : the first, of the liues of the popes, and their doctrine. The second, of the masse: the one and the other collected of that, which the doctors, and ancient councels, and the sacred Scripture do teach. Also, a swarme of false miracles, wherewith Marie de la Visitacion, prioresse de la Annuntiada of Lisbon, deceiued very many: and how she was discouered, and condemned. The second edition in Spanish augmented by the author himselfe, M. Cyprian Valera, and translated into English by Iohn Golburne. 1600</title>
                 <author>Valera, Cipriano de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison (Harison), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 256, 267-398, 401-431, 422-445, 1 page, table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue pained my selfe (gentle Reader) to doe thee
pleasure, and therefore craue but that curtesie of
thee, which in common right is my due: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
thy good conceit and fauourable censure of
my trauell: which albeit not pollished with fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of phrase yet it is beautified with truth of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
as God gaue abilitie, my small knowledge in
the tongue, and the misery of the place aforded. If
any will charge me with folly and presumption in
attempting this translation, better beseeming some
of riper iudgement. I graunt there is cause: yet thou forward taxer of faultes, in
others, why doest thou not rather iudge &amp; condemne thy self? that hauing a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
talent, hast worse imployed it, nay hast buried the same: &amp; in ten yeares space
sithens this worthy worke was first published, hast not bettered thy country by thy
paines taking, nor benefited others by translating it thy selfe. For my part, I hold
it fitter, that the body rather brooke a meane repast then starue for want of foode:
And had rather my rash ignorance should be published in print, and so noted of
thee (for of better minds I expect better thoughts) then that so heauenly a light of
Christian knowledge, should rest obscured in the mysty darknesse of a strange
language: and so precious a treasure be buried in rustie silence, without comfort
or commoditie to my countrey. For among so many worthy labourers in the Lords
vineyard, raised vp by God in this latter age, there is none (pardon me good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
if my simple iudgement faile me) that hath exceeded, nay few or none that
hath equalled this Authour, in the matter and method of this booke. Wherein by
way of Antithesis, are liuely set forth Christ and Antichrist. To the end that two
contraries opposed, Christ the true light may appeare more glorious: and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ
the child of darkenes may be viewed in his proper colour, that the one may be
imbraced with all obedience, and the other abandoned with all detestation and
horror. For if thou wouldest know by the word of God, and be assured by the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
of his holy Spirit that Ancichrist foretold by the Prophets and Apostles, is
already come, and the sonne of perdition renealed, if thou wouldest know the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
time, the place, the maner and markes of his reuelation. If thou wouldest
know and be acertained by the same Spirit, that the Pope is a false Priest, &amp; that
very same Antichrist, so proued by his abominable life and doctrine, by the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie
of Gods sacred word, and vnrefutable arguments drawne from the same. If
thou wouldest know and be assured likewise, that the Masse is a diuelish prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the holy Supper of the Lord, a most blasphemous, idolatrous, and false sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
derogating from the most precious bloud, death &amp; passion of Iesus Christ. If thou
wouldest know &amp; by the same Spirit be assured that the same Iesus Christ, true God
&amp; true man is the only Lord, Sauiour and redeemer of the world: the onlie aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
Intercessor &amp; Mediator betweene God and man: the only &amp; alone king Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
and true high Priest, which entred into the holy place once for all, and found
eternall redemption. If thou wouldest know that his body and bloud once offred vpō
the altar of the crosse, is the only &amp; alone true sacrifice of a sweet smelling sauor in
<pb facs="4"/>
the nosethrils of God his Father, for the remission of sins: whereby onlie Gods wrath
is appeased, we obtaine pardon, peace &amp; reconciliation with God, grace, fauor
and euerlasting life. If thou wouldest know and be likewise assured, that this most
holy sacrifice of Christ one only time offered is all sufficient for the sins of all men, &amp;
that no place remaineth for any other reiteration of the same sacrifice. If thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest
know the true meaning, vse &amp; practise of the holy Supper of the Lord Iesus, &amp;
the benfit thereof to the Faithfull. If thou wouldest certainlie know, and be fully as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured
by the same Spirit of Grace, which is the ancient doctrin of God, leading to all
blisse and true blessednesse, confirmed with his sacred word, contained in the bookes
of the old &amp; new Testament, and penned by the finger of the holy Ghost: and which
is the new doctrine of men, pointing the pathway to hell, death &amp; destruction, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
with vaine apparitions, dreames, false miracles, and illusions of the diuell.
Come and see, &amp; except the god of this world hath blinded thy mind, that the light
of Christes glorious Gospell should not shine vnto thee: except thou list to grope
at noone day, and wilfully say, I will not see: except thou hast shaken hands with
death, and made a couenant with hell: except God for thy wilfull obstinacie, hath
giuen thee ouer vnto a reprobate sence, to oppose thy selfe against him &amp; his knowne
truth. In reading this booke without partiall preiudication, thou canst not but see,
exactly perceiue and tast to thine vnspeakeable comfort, how sweet are the mercies
of the Lord, in reuealing to thee (dust and ashes) the mysterie both of the one and
the other, which the wise of this world neither haue vnderstood, nor can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend:
but is reuealed vnto babes, his Saints, to whom he would make knowne the
riches of his glorie to confound and make foolishnes the vvisdom of the wise. Which
if thou shalt find (as if in singlenesse of heart thou seeke, thou canst not but find.)
Then praise Iehouah, the author of all goodnesse be thankefull to this Author, the
meanes of thy good, and take in worth my simple trauell, an inferiour furtherance
thereunto, who hartily wish thee no lesse comfort and ioy in reading, then my mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
selfe receiued in translating of this booke. And because it seemeth a thing
difficult to translate the Prouerbs, wherein not the letter, but the sence is to be follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed:
that course haue I obserued, &amp; set downe withall the proper phrase of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish
and Portugal tongues, both in them and some other hard &amp; doubtfull words:
that thou (gentle Reader) indued with better gifts maist iudge, and curteously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
by thy knowledge, what my vnskilfulnesse hath missed: hoping that my desire
herein to do well, may excuse in thy Chistian conceit, whatsoeuer is (if any thing)
misdone. And so I leaue thee to him that is able to keepe thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
I. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>