<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IVDICIOVS VNDERSTANDER: To the Ignorant READER: and to the base CARPER whatsoeuer.</title>
           <author>T., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119026_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14277</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24593</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IVDICIOVS VNDERSTANDER: To the Ignorant READER: and to the base CARPER whatsoeuer.</title>
                 <author>T., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blazon of iealousie· : A subiect not written of by any heretofore· First written in Italian, by that learned gentleman Benedetto Varchi, sometimes Lord Chauncelor vnto the Signorie of Venice: and translated into English, with speciall notes vpon the same; by R.T. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Varchi, Benedetto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 87, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE IVDICIOVS VNDERSTANDER: To the Ignorant READER: and to the base CARPER whatsoeuer.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earned) to you, whose true Gentilitie</l>
   <l>Is match't with Vertue in Affinitie,</l>
   <l>Into whose fluent Vaine, the Muses nine</l>
   <l>Distill all Knowledge, Humane and Diuine,</l>
   <l>Who haue the gifts of Tongues to vnderstand,</l>
   <l>(Pure Linguists right) the state of euery Land:</l>
   <l>VVhose Eglets Spirits to mount on high are found,</l>
   <l>And not as fearefull Swallow, lowe on ground:</l>
   <l>VVhose boundlesse Ocean of Intelligence,</l>
   <l>Containes (of Artes) the subtile Quintessence.</l>
   <l>Your curteous Nature, being so sweetly fram'd,</l>
   <l>As it commends, what's worthier to be blam'd:</l>
   <l>To you alone, and vnto none but you,</l>
   <l>I offer vp my Selfe, and Booke, as due.</l>
   <l>As for that golden Skonse with leaden VVit,</l>
   <l>I scorne, for scorne, doth Ignorance best fit.</l>
   <l>Rich dunghill <hi>Midas</hi> with his Asses eares,</l>
   <l>VVho (with his Heeles) not with Discretion heares:</l>
   <l>The perfum'd gilt-Spurre Muske-Cat, Valours shame,</l>
   <l>VVho is not (as he counterseits) the same:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>Wearing a siluer Sword for fashion sake,</l>
   <l>And yet disgracefull Blowes and words will take:</l>
   <l>Whose Speech and Ruffe seeme Both, as One to be,</l>
   <l>Of the new Set, (Twins in Formalitie,)</l>
   <l>Where, if you barre him from his Common places,</l>
   <l>He is tongue-tide then, for therein his chiefe grace is,</l>
   <l>Whose Apish Trickes and Nods, with ducking low,</l>
   <l>The perfect Type of Vanitie doth show,</l>
   <l>Whilst (capring for the nonce) his Coyne must ijngle,</l>
   <l>His sole Attendance being his loathsome Ingle:</l>
   <l>Thinking he should be prays'd for his pyde Cloathes,</l>
   <l>(For he no better parts (than these are) showes:)</l>
   <l>All such, I barre, and banish from my Booke,</l>
   <l>Lest they profane it with vnhallowed Looke.</l>
   <l>Their musty Scoffes I bandy them againe,</l>
   <l>As strucken Ball flyes backe from whence it came.</l>
   <l>These wry-mouth'd Curs that barke, but dare not bite;</l>
   <l>(Their Mothers (but not Fathers) Children right;)</l>
   <l>Ile scourge from hence, and gaule them to the quicke,</l>
   <l>Whilst on themselues, not me, they poison spit.</l>
   <l>But vnto you (Iudicious) all Respect,</l>
   <l>Ass to the Scoffers Hate and base Neglect:</l>
   <l>Nor (if they are marryed) doe I wish them worse,</l>
   <l>Then to be plagu'd with <hi>IEALOVSIES</hi> blacke Curse.</l>
   <l>And he that (causelesse) with my Booke findes fault,</l>
   <l>I will maintaine with <hi>Vulcans</hi> Crest doth halt;</l>
   <l>Iudge (mildely) with sober Discretion then,</l>
   <l>So shall you be like Angels, and not Men.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>