<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sr. JOHN HOBART, Of Blickling in the County of Norfolke, Knight Baronet, one of his Ma∣jesties Deputies Lieutenant, Justice of Peace and Quorum, Captaine and Colonell of part of his Majesties Forces there: Prime Heire of the Right Honourable, and reverend Judge, Sr. Henry Hobart, Knight and Baronet, Lord chiefe Justice of his Mties Horable Court of Common Pleas. John Welles Wisheth much increase of Honour, and all true comfort in this life, a blessed end, and eternall happinesse in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Welles, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119607_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14923</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119607</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sr. JOHN HOBART, Of Blickling in the County of Norfolke, Knight Baronet, one of his Ma∣jesties Deputies Lieutenant, Justice of Peace and Quorum, Captaine and Colonell of part of his Majesties Forces there: Prime Heire of the Right Honourable, and reverend Judge, Sr. Henry Hobart, Knight and Baronet, Lord chiefe Justice of his Mties Horable Court of Common Pleas. John Welles Wisheth much increase of Honour, and all true comfort in this life, a blessed end, and eternall happinesse in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Welles, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules progresse to the celestiall Canaan, or heavenly Jerusalem : By way of godly meditation, and holy contemplation: accompanied with divers learned exhortations, and pithy perswasions, tending to Christianity and humanity. Divided into two parts. The first part treateth of the divine essence, quality and nature of God, and his holy attributs: and of the creation, fall, state, death, and misery of an unregenerated man, both in this life and in the world to come: put for the whole scope of the Old Testament. The second part is put for the summe and compendium of the Gospell, and treateth of the Incarnation, Nativity, words, works, and sufferings of Christ, and of the happinesse and blessednesse of a godly man in his state of renovation, being reconciled to God in Christ. Collected out of the Scriptures, and out of the writings of the ancient fathers of the primitive Church, and other orthodoxall divines: by John Welles, of Beccles in the County of Suffolk</title>
                 <author>Welles, John, of Beccles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Shepherd (Sheppard), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 304, 1, 308-372, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL S<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>JOHN HOBART,</hi> Of <hi>Blickling</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> Knight Baronet, one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Deputies Lieutenant, Justice of Peace and Quorum, Captaine and Colonell of part of his Majesties Forces there: Prime Heire of the Right Honourable, and reverend Judge, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Henry Hobart,</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord chiefe Justice of his M<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> Ho<seg rend="sup">rable</seg> Court of Common Pleas. <hi>John Welles</hi> Wisheth much increase of Honour, and all true comfort in this life, a blessed end, and eternall happinesse in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have presumed to dedicate these my labours unto you, Right noble sir, the off-spring and undoubted Heire of my
<pb facs="3"/> noble friend your father de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased; and inheritour of his Lands and Livings, and the chiefe of that great and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned family. And as you doe inherit his Lands and Livings, so my prayer is, that you may inherit him in his integrity, zeale, &amp; wisdome. I speak not this out of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full feare, but in officious love; and herein take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, I beseech you, of this happinesse and blessing of God, cast upon you, not only to be the chiefe of this great and worthy family; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so take notice of the true cause of the worth and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of your Ancestours, and
<pb facs="3"/> imitate them therein, and then inheriting their worth together with their wealth, you shall also most undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly enrich your selfe with the obsequious attendance and hearty affection of your native Countrymen, and so grow in grace and favour with God and man. For which cause I have presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to present you with this Tractate, and to publish the same under the protection of your name, hoping of your courteous acceptance; and beseeching you to grant it your favourable protection and Patronage: which though it be but indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="4"/> contrived, yet strongly warranted, for it hath the undoubted truth of God for its authority. There may be many Tractates found ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to these ends; but all that I have seene of others, though they may bee more pithy, yet certaine I am, this is more plaine; I trust not unpleasant, nor unprofitable. God give all grace to make right use of it. And so commending my labours, with all the desired good that may be unto your good Worship, and both you and it to the speciall grace and protection of the Almighty, who is aboundantly able to
<pb facs="4"/> fill your heart with grace, to crowne your daies with blessing, and to finish them with eternall comfort, life, and glory, <hi>Amen.</hi> I rest, a true desirer of your best good,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>And your Worships in all Christian duty to be commanded,</hi> JOHN WELLES.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>October</hi> 22. 1638.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>