<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119283_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16566</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3471</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119283</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration or proffer of the Archdukes of Brabant : concerning a truce betweene them and the States of the Free vnited Netherlandish Prouinces, tending to the treatie for a perpetuall peace betweene them: or for a surceasance of armes for certaine yeares. Contained in letter sent vnto the said states. Also the ansvver and acceptance of the states of the vnited prouinces vnto the arch-dukes. Translated out of Netherlandish printed copie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raworth, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ferbrand (Firebrand, Forbrand), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 6, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all the temporall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings that God of his free boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bestowes vpon any King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or Nation, there is not any thing more inualuable thē that heauen-bred happines, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quietnes:</hi> it was a harmony from Angelicall voyces, at the birth of our Sauiour, when those diuine Embassadours brought glad tidings of great ioy, pronouncing <hi>Peace on earth, and vnto all men good will:</hi> when our Sauiour departed from his Disciples, hee left <hi>Peace</hi> with them; when hee came amongst them after his resurrection, the doores beeing shut, hee spake <hi>Peace</hi> vnto them: and <hi>Peace</hi> is that, without which, all other things are distastfull and vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant.</p>
   <p>What is it in this world, either for honour, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, plenty, aliance, artes, friendship, or any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane good, but with <hi>Peace</hi> it flowrisheth in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious sun-shine?</p>
   <p>We our selues, of any Nation vnder the cope
<pb facs="8"/>of heauen, can euidence this to the whole world, that haue had the Palme-tree spread ouer this Kingdome, the long raigne of a peacefull Queen, and continueth in flowrishing state the present raigne of her worthy successor, who is the mirror of <hi>Peace</hi> to all Nations of the earth. But what we haue not feared, others haue most grieuously felt, especially our neere neighbours, (the vnited Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands) whose tragedy begun by rugged warre, hath continued in bloody action, many yeares of terror; thei<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> calamities and miseries, which of vs can be ignorant of? English eares haue heard their roaring Canons eccho in the ayre, imitating <hi>Ioues</hi> thunder, their Trumpets sound the fatall knell of infinit thousands, and their Drummes allarmes laden the earth with millions of dead carkasses.</p>
   <p>English eies haue seene the deuastations, spoiles, sieges, ransackings, &amp; flaming cities, of those coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: English liues haue beene liberally spent in their martiall businesse, followed their fortunes, bled in their quarrels, and died in their battels.</p>
   <p>But now, after all these bloody affaires, this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed endlesse warre, these reputed irreuocable cruelties, behold a strange and admirable alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that such implacable aduersaries, shall most readily and willingly propound loue and amitie, offering to sheath the sword till it rust (euen a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall <hi>Peace,</hi>) or a Truce limited, or any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of faithfull triall.</p>
   <p>From whence proceedeth the originall of these designes? to whom must the efficient cause bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed?
<pb facs="8"/>but onely to that Almightie Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker, who hath the ruling and ordering of hearts in his owne hand, to dispose of them as hee pleaseth, be they neuer so potent, powerfull, or opposite.</p>
   <p>For as in Iustice hee hath a seuere and cruell whip of three cordes, to punish sinners (to wit of <hi>Famine, Sword,</hi> and <hi>Pestilence,</hi>) so in his Mercie he hath <hi>Plentie, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Health:</hi> freely to bestow on whome his mercie shall please to extend them. It is to be hoped that the Lords wrath will be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peased, towards them that the sword hath destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for such a long continuance of years. And that he will rather powre out his wrath and heauie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure vpon the heathen that haue not knowne him, nor called vpon his name. And it is a dutie wherunto euery Christian man is obliged, to pray vnto the great God of Heauen, that hee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue his hand of Iustice from his poore weake and fraile creatures, whom with one angry frown, he can at once destroy from the face of the earth. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> saith, <hi>It is a good and ioyfull thing, for brethren to dwell in vnity.</hi> All that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse Christ, are taught by him, in prayer to call him father, and the sonnes of one father must needs be brethren.</p>
   <p>This motion of <hi>Peace</hi> and concord (if it bee faithfull and vnfained, to preuent effusion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian blood) is most honourable, and the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof, of as high worthinesse: he that made the heart knowes it, and hath the dispose of it: hee that is called the Lord of Hosts can command an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb facs="9"/>to fight his battell, with terrible slaughter: and againe, can beyond all expectation of humane creature, cease stearne fac't warre, with mild im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements of smiling Peace.</p>
   <p>To conclude, let all bee referred to his will, who hath power, and whose power no mortall is able to resist, and let our affections ioyne with those heauenly souldiers, that sounded forth <hi>Peace</hi> on earth, &amp; good will with men.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <trailer type="illustration">
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>