<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Roger Portington Esquier, in commen∣dation
of the booke.</title>
           <author>Portington, Roger</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119748_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02129</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12269</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119748</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Roger Portington Esquier, in commen∣dation
of the booke.</title>
                 <author>Portington, Roger</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mamillia : A mirrour or looking-glasse for the ladies of Englande. Wherein is disciphered, howe gentlemen vnder the perfect substaunce of pure loue, are oft inueigled with the shadowe of lewde lust: and their firme faith, brought a sleepe by fading fancie: vntil with ioyned with wisedome, doth awake it by the helpe of reason. By Robert Greene graduate in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 37 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Roger Portington Esquier, in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
of the booke.</head>
   <l>IF Grecia soyle may vaunt her hap and lucky chaunce,</l>
   <l>as nurse of Clios clarkely crue, her state t'aduaunce,</l>
   <l>Or Smirna boast of Homers skil, for hope of fame,</l>
   <l>If royall Rome may reape renowne by Tullies name,</l>
   <l>Or Virgils countrie village vaunt that she excell,</l>
   <l>Dan Ouids natiue land may striue to beare the bell:</l>
   <l>Then Britaine soyle may brauely boast her state in fine,</l>
   <l>That she a new Pernassus is, the Muses shrine.</l>
   <l>No finer wittes in Grecia raigned then Britayne breedes,</l>
   <l>No brauer workes in Smirna wrought then English deeds.</l>
   <l>If passing port of Poets praise was euer founde</l>
   <l>In Mantua, the like is got in Britayne ground.</l>
   <l>If Tullie wan the golden spurres of fame by prose,</l>
   <l>And reaped in Rome such rich renowne as wel as those:</l>
   <l>Our Authour beautifies this Brittayne soyle for why?</l>
   <l>His stately style in English prose doth climbe the skie.</l>
   <l>His filed phrase deserues in learnings throne to sit,</l>
   <l>And his Mamillia darkens quite the Frenchmens wit.</l>
   <l>Yea if that any haue beene crowned with laurel greene,</l>
   <l>This Greene deserues a laurel braunch I weene:</l>
   <l>For why? his pen hath paynted out dan Cupids craft,</l>
   <l>And set at large the doubtfull chance of fancies drafte:</l>
   <l>Yea in such comely colours sure his workes enbost,</l>
   <l>As he for English phrase may sit amidst the most.</l>
   <l>And thogh he thinks his booke too rude to win such fame,</l>
   <l>His foes would say that he by right deserues the same.</l>
   <signed>Roger Portington.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>