<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right honourable Sir Wylli∣am Parre knight, Lord Parre, Erle of Essex, Mar∣quesse of Northampton, Lorde great Chamberlaine of Englande, and Knight of the moste noble ordre of ȳ Garter, Nicolas Udall wisheth grace and peace in Christ, with helthe honour and longe prosperitee.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119144_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24665</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119144</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right honourable Sir Wylli∣am Parre knight, Lord Parre, Erle of Essex, Mar∣quesse of Northampton, Lorde great Chamberlaine of Englande, and Knight of the moste noble ordre of ȳ Garter, Nicolas Udall wisheth grace and peace in Christ, with helthe honour and longe prosperitee.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse or traictise of Petur Martyr Vermilla Flore [n] tine, the publyque reader of diuinitee in the Vniuersitee of Oxford : wherein he openly declared his whole and determinate iudgemente concernynge the sacrament of the Lordes supper in the sayde Vniuersitee</title>
                 <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Udall, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 <publisher>Stoughton, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, cx leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right honourable Sir Wylli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Parre knight, Lord Parre, Erle of Essex, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse of Northampton, Lorde great Chamberlaine of Englande, and Knight of the moste noble ordre of ȳ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Garter, Nicolas Udall wisheth grace and peace in Christ, with helthe honour and longe prosperitee.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erusyng of late righte honourable and my synguler good Lorde, a certayne dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the righte excellente Clerke Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Martyr wryten in Latin concerning the Sacramente of the bodye and bloud of Christ, whiche is of the Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>kes called <hi>Eucha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>istia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it pertayneth to the remembraunce of his moste tendre goodnesse in redemyng the worlde, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreyng of perpetuall thankes vnto hym therfore: I confesse I was with the sayde treatise woondrefully rauished. For first and formost wheras by reason of innumerable abuses, detestable erroures and foule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominacions through the crafty conueighaūce of the purpurate whore of Babylon by litel &amp; litell conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed into the Churche, there is no poynet concerninge oure religion, so ferre entrieked or darkned as the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rie of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>acrament: this wryter throughe his sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler gifte of grace, his right profounde learnynge, and his highe iudgemente aswell in the scriptures, as also in the doctours, and in the generall councell wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth so depein searchyng and boultyng out the trueth of this mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er, that he maketh it so clere so plaine and so eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dent to all mennes y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es whiche either can or wyl
<pb facs="3"/>
see that neither there can now be any ferther doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of the veritee, and trueth of thys sacramente. What it is nor any more bee saied for the right insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion and ordre therof how it should be vsed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore me thought I could not better employ or bestow my trauaill then in translatynge this tractise into the Englyshe tounge, to thentente that so profytable a thinge might not bee hiddden from the people, which hauynge bothe an earnest zele to enbrace the trueth: and a readye wille to folowe the kynges maiestees moste godly procedynges, are muche hindred, and kept backe from their desire, partelye through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce because thei are not duely enstructed &amp; taught th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rin, and partely through the malice of the moste peruerse Papistycall leaueners of Chystes doctryne whiche to mainteyne theyr owne luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and glorye, ceasse not as Antechrystes owne trustie knyghtes to weorke as muche as in theym lyeth, that the symple people maye styll continue in blyndenesse and errour. But all prayse, all thankes, all laude and glorye be vnto oure moste louynge heauenly father and to hys onelye begotten sonne Iesus Chryste oure lord, with the holy ghoste proceding from theim both, who haue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> these oure dayes so opened the yies of the worlde, that not onely the iugleyng sleyghtes of the Romysh Babylon be so throughly espyed that they can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger deceiue: and hir moste cruell tyrannye so vanquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, that she maye nowe no longer reygne in Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten peoples consciences as she hath by goddes suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce for oure synfulnesse many longe yeres dooen. Neither is it possible that the excedynge mercye and
<pb facs="3"/>
fauour of god towardes this royalme of Englande maie more euidently appere, then it is by these two tokens folowinge declared, the one that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him by his moste puissaunt and mightefull arme to deliuer vs oute of the bondage of this Romishe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipte, ferre passinge the yoke &amp; seruitude whyche the children of Isarel suffred vnder Pharao, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that of his espiciall grace he hath vouchesalued to open the yies of oure hertes that we maye see the trueth, and to giue vnto thys royalme the righte knowelege concernynge thys moste holy sacramente whiche the subtille and craftie illusyon of Sathan by the instrumente of the saide purpurate whoore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bylon had made of a moste pure fountayne of water springinge vp into euerlastinge life, a foule stynking puddle of idolatrie and supersticyon to endelesse dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon: of a most precious and heauen iewel, a most vile and deyulyshe abominacyon: of a moste comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table medycyne, a most deadly, &amp; present poyson. Blis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed therfore be the name of the lord our god for euer &amp; euer, who of his infynite mercy &amp; botomlesse goodnesse hath cast his most fauourable yie vpō this royalme of Englād, illumining the hertes of the same most glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cherefully to enbrace his ghospell, and giuing vs to ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Kinge suche a Godlye Iosyas as in his tender yeares of childehoode neither forgeateth ne ceasseth with the moste feythfull aduise and trustie assistence of his moste noble &amp; sapient Counsaylours to trauayle aswell that the woorde of God maye bee syncerely and purelye set foorthe and taughte vnto all his moste derely beloued subiectes, as also that this
<pb facs="4"/>
sacramente of the Lordes body and bloude maye bee reduced to the right vse accordyng to the first institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion therof in the primatiue Churche. And forasmuch as the whole processe of this discourse is bothe conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt vnto the worde of God that it cannot be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, but that it is true, and also so iustely agreynge with the kinges Maiestees moste godly procedinges that the people maye by readyng or hearyng herof be throughly satisfied and perswaded vniuersally to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and folow the other. I thinke it (as I haue said) a weorke right expedient and necessary to be hadde in the Englishe toungue aswell for the instruction of suche as can reade, as also for the helpe of some good persones &amp; curates, whiche though they haue a good zele &amp; forwardnes to set forth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kīges maiesties most christian procedynges: yet for defaulte of sufficiente learnyng (the more is the pietee) are not of themselues hable neither throughly to enstructe their flocke of all the trueth, nor to satisfy the ignoraunt in suche doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full cases or questions, as maye haplye aryse aboute this matier, nor finally to stoppe the mouthes of sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Papistes, or of suche as are malicious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate enemies againste the pure doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes ghospell. And althoughe in treactynge of suche hygh matiers it can not bee auoided but that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of some schoole termes or argumentes there must nedes bee many thynges, that maye seme to passe the capacitee and vnderstanding of the vnlettred sorte: yet is not suche a notable good weorke as this discourse of Petur Martyr or as his disputacions vpon the same matier therfore to bee suppressed or kepte (as it
<pb facs="4"/>
wer) hidden vnder the bushel. For yf no booke should bee sette foorth but suche as euery bodye yea euen of the vnlearned and grosse multitude mighte bee hable to vnderstande whan they heare it or reade it: than what should Chauncer, Goore, Lidgate and others doe abrode, whom some euen of the learned sorte doe in some places scarcely take? than were it vayne to set foorthe Chronicles or statutes in whiche is bothe a great noumbre of wordes, and also muche matier not easie to be perceyued of euery body: than wer it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure loste to sette foorthe in Englyshe bookes of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and homelies vnto the grosse and rusticall multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, whose capacite is not hable to conceiue that is in them conteined than wer it vayn to haue translated and sette foorth the bible in Englyshe to the vulgare people, and moste vain to reade it in the Churches, forasmuche as a greate noumbre of thynges whiche the symple ignoraunt people rede and heare thereout, are ferre aboue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eache of theyr grosse vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge. But all suche good and godly bookes as wel of holy wryte as of other profane argumentes, are to this entente sette foorth and published, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye bodye maye be edifyed as ferre foorth as hys ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacyte wyll serue. And lyke as wythout any reading or hearynge at all, they shoulde continue euermore blynde and ignoraunt: so by continuall readynge and hearing the vnlearned &amp; simple maie take enstructiōs &amp; from dai to day procede &amp; growe in knowelage till at laste they shall by due vse and excercise, be hable to vnderstande as muche as shall bee necessarye or expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diēt for thē. Now this boke I haue laboured to make as plain as I could do, &amp; therfor in som places I haue
<pb facs="5"/>
either altered or leaft y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scoole termes whych otherwise would haue made the thing more derke, &amp; brought it as nere I could to the familiar phrase of English spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng, or els haue added suche circumstaunce of other woordes, as might declare it &amp; make it plain. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoughe for the cause abouesaide I maie seme in some places to haue somewhat swerued from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise woordes of the latin booke: Yet I trust it shall to the fauourable and indifferent reader appere that I haue not any thynge degressed from the autours mynde. Now as we commonly see that men where thei thinke themselues endoubted or boundē, though thei can not fully requitte or deserue the manifold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices that thei haue receiued yet (as the nature and duetie of thankfulnesse byndeth them) thei will not be negligent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o gratifye their beneficiall patrones or frē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des with suche simple tokens of their good mindes as lyeth in their power, (as the fermer to present his landlorde with some porcion of the fruictes that god sendeth hym, and the poore widowe hir patrone with a dishe of apples cheries or suche lyke:) so can not I but thynke my selfe moste bounden wyth some of the simple fruictes of mi pore studies to presēt your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship my singuler &amp; espiciall good patrone, trustynge that forasmuche as there is as Cicero saieth a certaine kynde of lyberalitee euen in takyng, ye will wyth no lesse cherfulnesse accepte these my simple labours dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vnto you, then ye haue been accustomed to geue the manifold benifites whiche I haue at your lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipes handes receiued. And thus I shall commende thesame my labours vnto youre lordshippes patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and proteccion and your selfe vnto the lordes tuicion
<pb facs="5"/>
as sone as I shal haue aduertised you of the processe that Martir foloweth in this weorke, whiche is that firste he bryngeth in the schoole Doctoures and all that euer maie bee saied for transubstantiation as strongly as is possible to bee reasoned, and as muche as can bee alleged for it. Than bringeth he in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons suche as he thinketh good, both out of the fyrst Scriptures, and generall Counceile, and also oute of the Doctoures to confirme his owne opinion against transubstantiacion. Thirdely he confuteth and soilleth al the argumentes and reasons of the schoolemen and Popishe writers one by one, in ordre as thei were propouned and this doth he so clearkely, so profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and so pitthilye, that no man can saie more Bese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching therfore youre Lordeship yf any default or lacke bee, to impute it rather to myne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficiencie in translatinge it, then to the authoure in wrytinge it, I will no longer with hold thesame frō the hearinge of Martyr himselfe speake, who shal more delighte and edifie you then my penne maye dooe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>