<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Southwell, Robert, saint</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119994_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07956</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18325</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119994</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Southwell, Robert, saint</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true relation of the trauels of M. Bush, a gentleman : who with his owne handes without any other mans helpe made a pynace, in which hee past by ayre, land, and water: from Lamborne, a place in Bark.shire, to the Custome house Key in London. 1607</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N different Readers, whose
iudgments are sophistically
mixt with humors, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits,
as many are now a
dayes, who are more ready
to condemne with their
turbulent tongues, then to
amend with sensible iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
As for them, or any
such carpers, I am reasonably perswaded to set as
lightly by their censures, as they are farre from
conceiuing well of any thing, but what agrees
with their owne humors, or fictions. To those
that are of more plausible spirits, who (for the
most part either say little, or conceit the best, and
either applaud what is good, or passe ouer with
silence what is not hurtfull: And to those that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
some vnderstanding themselues in this Arte,
as either Nauigators, or Shipwrights, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous
to be partakers of the Experiments &amp; Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises
of other mens knowledge. To the one I
commit the censure, to the other the profitte of
this Trauellors labours: knowing that such as are
<pb facs="4"/>
wise, will rather winke at samll faults, then rashly
reproue what may pleasure others. Though such
as are curious, and thinke themselues sufficiently
expert in this Arte, finde nothing herein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
that may satisfie their expectation: yet the
Gentlemans hope is, they will iudge fauourably of
his intentions and proceedings, and passe it ouer
with patience, for affections sake to the Arte it
selfe: and hereafter doubts not but to doe them
more profit and pleasure in matters of some other
deepe performances. If any thinke, that what
this booke speakes, is very strange; he may see the
very title saies as much: And it is good for an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
to be as good as his title. If any thinke it
is but a Tale, and no truth, I cite you my Tales<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maister,
(which is more then most men will doe.)
And he to auoide euery such imputation, hath his
confirmation hereof, vnder the hands and seales
of the chiefest of the Custome house in London,
besides many thousand witnesses in the Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.
Then sit downe and read it, if it
doe not profit thee, yet his trust is,
it shall not displease thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>