<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119581_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07937</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18307</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119581</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The complaint of a Christian soule : Containing certaine remedies and comforts against the trouble and conflict of conscience. Newlie written in meter</title>
                 <author>Muschet, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charteris, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a great happines to fle al vicious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, and to hold a commend able medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocritie: so it is a miserie quhilk we cannot sufficiently lament, to see (in thir latter daies amongst men quhilk make profession to beleeue in a better life) some who haue so sold them selfe to the loue of this world that they seeke not for an vther, and some who are so violently caried away with the feare and apprehension of Death, so that vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny shew of alteration in their health there is nothing to be heard bot strange sighs and grones, the witnesses of abject thoghts, and the vnworthie contesting of a soule that wolde dispute with God. The remedies against so great mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieues are very necessary: and I hope this treatise follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will furnish some-what for the purpose (gathered not in the bogs and mures of humane wisdome, but in the garden of life) quhilk is the Scriptures of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles of the ever-living God: The savory juce of the quhilk remedies digested in our soules, will make vs neither be too much rejoisd with the pleasures of this world, neither too much feard to passe out of this world, but that with a holy care, a vigilant feare, and a filiall reverence, we shall haue the eies of our soules and eares of our heartes open to the voice of the Lord, crying to all mankinde, <hi>Sonnes of men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> yea it wolde cure vs of that lethargie, palsie, and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall apoplexie, where-with so many poore soules are daily infected, quhilk never thinking of death are dead li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or rather are as the dead quhilk bury the dead, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing
<pb facs="5"/>what the kingdome of God is, neither hauing any care to be of it, or to procure or advance it. This juce will free vs from that feare quhilk congeils our spirits, and from that frencie quhilk makes vs doubt of our saife delivery, and from that spirituall melancholy quhilk subverts all true judgement in vs, and thrusts vs (as it were) in a brutishe childishnes, estranging vs from these things quhilk should cause most joy and consolation in vs. This present collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the box conteining the precious oyle the quhilk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carefully digested by you will (I hope) produce some profitable effect. Bot to giue you some greater taist of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, and to shew the summe or this little scrole. In thir few &amp; vnadvised lynes, there is breeflie (or as it wer) in a certaine a bridgment set down two things, the one is the vehement calamitie quhilk proceedes not from a sleeping soule, but from the feeling disease and excessiue trouble of a wakned conscience, not onely accused but convicted of her persew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and broght to the straite , farther nor the scaffold, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven almost to the doore of the graue, by the rememberance of sin. In the other part there is adjoind, althogh not sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately by it selfe but mixtly throgh the whole, some speciall remedies for the most diseased soule, and some medicens equivalent for the farrest dijected conscience, and some salues very necessarie for that spirituail palsie, quhilk if it be rightly applyed, will not onely banish all present feare of death, but even that quhilk no other Phisick can afford, it will furnishe perpetuall health to the soule, and leaue the minde so at ease, that no inconvenient (how great so ever) shall be able heereafter to ty the man to the bed. This is the summe Christian Reader, and albeit it be not so ripely dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, nor vttered with such grace, as he ought to haue who lets any thing go from him to the censure of this age: yet impudencie hes so prevailde with me for the time, and a care to do good with my small talent, did so continually push
<pb facs="5"/>my lukles muse that I could finde no rest in silence. But as Michall did laugh when David did dance, so I know some Michals will scorne at my singing, and yet I hope other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be welcomed of some, for if any good Davids be in this land there I shall be harbored, because this is a song whereat Davids should be delyted. So not caring for Michals taunting, nor Rabschek as railings, nor Ischmaels scofs, because it is not with such I craue to be mirrie, neither with them to communicate our spirituall melodie, to the well effected Christian (who giues lodging to the Hebrew Harpes, and who intertaines the musicall instruments of Sion) I direct this Ballad, to be set vpon their strings, to be played in their Palaces, and to be sung in their Innes, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this one that if the pleasantnes do not delite you, the long somnes shall not wearie you. And if all be not so well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as you merite (worthie Reader) nor so Poeticallie composed as the writer wolde wishe, let my want be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervailed by my good will, and when better things shall be offered, you shall not lacke.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fair well.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>