<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119043_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14315</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24631</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119043</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The foure bookes of Flauius Vegetius Renatus : briefelye contayninge a plaine forme, and perfect knowledge of martiall policye, feates of chiualrie, and vvhatsoeuer pertayneth to warre. Translated out af [sic] lattine, into Englishe, by Iohn Sadler. Anno. 1572. Seene and allovved, accordinge to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Vegetius Renatus, Flavius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 66, 8 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He difference of peace and warre is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant
to all men. Howe much the one is to be
desired, the other to be eschewed (excepte in
some respectes hereafter declared, no man I
thincke is ignoraunt. It I should but touch
the gaynes &amp; commodityes of peace:<note place="margin">The commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dityes of peace.</note> how qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etlye
&amp; pleasantly men do liue together: howe
al thinges on the earth do encrease and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie:
howe wealth and riches do abounde: how all maner of sciences
and good learninge do flourish, with other innumerable effectes there
of toiling here now to be recyted: it would requyre a large and a great
volume;<note place="margin">The calamy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of Warre</note> not a shorte and compendious preface. Againe, howe great-calamities and destructions through warres haue happened, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
to Cittyes, townes and fortresses, but also to mighty Princes with
their armyes, greate multitudes of people, and whole nations &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes:
a man might spende a good part of his time to reade throughe
the bookes that hath beene written thereof. But the more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
precious and necessarye that pleasaunt and ioyfull name of peace
is to be accompted, so much more earnestlye it ought to be sought for,
obtayned and preserued: the greater daūgers harmes and losses that
are by warres sustay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, the greater heede foresighte and pollicye to
withstande the same, is to be vsed. Neyther hath there beene, that I
haue hearde or reade of, anye common wealthe or Realme fo fortunate
and blessed, that it hath enioyned continual peace and quietnes any long
time, excepte the Prince of peace, euen God himselfe, which also is the
Lord of Hostes, haue taken in hand the defence thereof. Which thing
no doubt of his aboundant goodnes he sheeweth vpon certaine people
and countryes, when as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>endes them good and gracious Princes,
wyse and godly gouernours. Which ruled by the spirite of God, may
so order &amp; keepe the whole common wealth and state of their Realme,
throughe their great wysedome learninge and pollicye, that no disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
of subiectes to theyr Prince may be founde vncorrected, no dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes
or trouble amongest them vnappeased, no force of forraine
ennemyes vnforeseene, vnwithstoode, vnrepelled. In which happye
estate that this our Realme of England at this present is,<note place="margin">The happye estate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,
vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</note> and hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
continued euen from the first beginning of this our most noble and
gracious Queenes maiestyes raigne: All true and faythfull English
hartes to their great ioye must needes acknowledge, yeldinge to God
the onlye Author thereof, most manifoulde and hartye thankes for the
same: moste humblye besechinge his eternall goodnes longe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
her excellente maiestye to rule ouer vs: whose most noble raig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
<pb facs="5"/>
being not onlye most happye throughe the lightsome shyninge of gods
most holye word, the zelous setting forth thereof, and prosperous suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse
of the same: but also fortunate and blessed, as well with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance
and plentye of all kindes of frutes of the earth, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
quiet and safe enioyinge of them, maye be to all good Englishe
men a sure &amp; euiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e token of Gods highe fauour and especiall grace
declared ouer this Realme: and to all the worlde a spectacle of moste
wyse and polliticke gouernmente. Whereas contrariwyse it is not
vnknowen howe that a greate parte of the worlde nighe vnto vs, hath
these yeares late passed, eyther beene cruellye afflicted with greuous
warres, or not altogether free and cleare from great vexations &amp; tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.
And although some of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e here in this Realme hath gone about
by rebellion to impayre this state:<note place="margin">Rebellion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer prospered</note> yet as neyther they whiche haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted
such enterprises in former tymes haue bene knowen or harde
tell of at anye time to haue preuayled: so neyther these, nor whosoeuer
hereafter wilbe so madde to treade in such like steppes, can escape ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
like successe as they haue had, or rather worse, to speake more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,
which they seeme iustlye to haue deserued. Seinge therefore that
the good pleasure and prouidence of God hath so prepared for vs, and
bestowed vppon vs such a pearelesse Prince, so noble and worthy coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellers,
that except men will be wilfullye blinde, they all maye see wyth
their eyes the goodnes of their gouernmente: let all vs Englishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n
as true and faythfull subiectes applye oure selues by all meanes
possible to obeye her maiestye▪ to keepe her lawes, to be ready alwayes
at her commaundement. Who ceaseth not to prouide, foresee, and care
for our safegarde, wealth and quietnes, as well in time of peace as in
warre. Which thinges partlye I touched before, and nowe occasion
s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rueth to speake more of the same againe. For although the one seeme
more to be wyshed for then the other, yet be they both, by the wil &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
of God, lefte in the handes of princes to be vsed as time and other
cyrcumstances shall requyre. And for that <hi>Pax,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pax <hi>deriued</hi> A pactione.</note> seemeth to be deriued
a <hi>Pactione,</hi> as some do write: what time as Princes haue agreed and
concluded of good and holsome conditions of peace, so longe doth the
league of peace endure, as such conditions are well obserued &amp; kept:
but if the same be ones violate and broken, then commonly do warres
ensue: whiche althoughe they seeme neuer so troublesome and full of
daunger, yet must they needes be taken in hand, not only with strength
and manhoode, but also wyth skill and pollicye. For as after calme &amp;
pleasant weather when sodainly a tempestuous storme doth ryse,<note place="margin">Peace resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to fayre weather, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> to foule wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> then
by profe doth appeare what the gouernour of the shippe is able to do:
if hee lacke skill &amp; knowledge, the shippe and all therein is like to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe:
if he be cunning and expert, he may deliuer it from shipwracke:
<pb facs="6"/>
euen so when after longe continual peace, greuous warres do fortune,
then do valiante Captaynes shewe their worthye manhoode, not with
hardines alone but with pollicy and knowledge. Seing therefore that
as fayre weather manye times is altered with stormes and tempest, so
peace oftentimes is chaūged w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> warres: what thing can be more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
&amp; necessarye to the cōmon wealth, then to haue in readines, polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike
and valiante Captaynes, experte and manlye souldiours? which
with their skilfull experience and tryed knowledge, maye in daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
times of warres do highe seruice to God, their Prince, and their
countrye, while they fighte not onlye for their owne liues, their wyues
and children, but also for the common libertye and wealth of al, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure
of their Prince, the defence and sauegarde of the whole estate.</p>
   <p>For which intente and purpose the readinge not onlye of the best hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall
writers both in Greke and latine,<note place="margin">The reading of historyes &amp; other writers of Warre not v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>eete for Captaynes.</note> wherin most noble actes of
famous Captaynes are liuely set forth as notable examples to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed:
but also of such worthye Authors as haue with great studye &amp;
trauaile, gathered out of the best historyes the chiefest pointes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices
of warres: and beinge dispersed farre abroade in manye diuers
and sundrye bookes, haue brought the same into a certayne forme and
knowledge of the feates of armes: may seeme to all men of warre, and
namelye to such, to whom the charge of great multitudes oftentimes
is committed, neyther vnworthye the reading, nor altogether vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.
Wherein in myne opinion this our Author <hi>Flauius Vegetius</hi>
obteyneth the chiefest prayse:<note place="margin">Uegetius the chiefest wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of warre.</note> who beinge commaunded by <hi>Valentinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus
Augustus,</hi> to put in wryting the practises and deuises of Martiall
pollicye, hath framed &amp; compacte together such a worke, which he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
Institutiōs, that it may be accompted, as it were a very methode
or most ready &amp; compendious waye to the right knowledge and science
of the feates of warre. And althoughe the warres in these oure
dayes seeme much unlike to the <hi>Romaine</hi> warres before <hi>Vegetius</hi>
time,<note place="margin">An obiection answered.</note> by reason of a greate nomber of engines and other feates
then vsed, whereof now many are out of vse, and many mo now inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
which then were vnknowen: yet maye this worke appeare not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
vnworthye to be knowen of our men of warre, wherein as it
were in a glasse they may most clearelye see, not onlye how that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes</hi>
throughe suche skill and k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owledge, and continuall exercise
therof as is herein declared, haue vanquished and ouercome so manye
barbarous and straunge Nations, subdued so manye prouinces, and
become Lordes and rulers of the most part of the world: but also may
gather and choose out the best a and chiefest pointes of all their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
which neuerthelesse may be vsed so farre forth as shall seeme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,<note place="margin">The conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es of the .iiii. bookes of U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>getius.</note>
and as occasion may serue &amp; time requyre. Wherefore wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
the whole woorke of <hi>Vegetiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> is deuided into foure Bookes, I
<pb facs="6"/>
thinke it not vnmeete to shewe briefelye what is chiefelye intreated in
euery one of the same.</p>
   <p>In the first booke he setteth forth two thinges principallye.<note place="margin">The. 1. booke</note> First
the musteringe, chosinge, and appointinge of yonge souldiours: wher
in he requireth of the choosers, most faythfull and painfull dilligence,
that they do cyrcumspectly consider and vewe, not onlye the countryes
and places where they were bred and brought vp, their age, their sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure,
their behauiour, the good making &amp; proportion of their bodyes,
the quickenes of their eyes and countenaunce: but also the trades and
sciences wherein they haue beene most occupyed &amp; vsed, their strength,
swiftnes, nimblenes &amp; actiuitye: by which likelyhoodes and tokens it
might well appeare which would be most meete for so greate a worke.
And in the well choosing of these doth consist the chiefest hope, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
for the strength of the armye, but also for acchieuing the victorye.</p>
   <p>Secondly he setteth forth the trayninge vppe of the yonge souldiours
well chosen,<note place="margin">An armye in latine called <hi>Exercitus ab Exercitio.</hi>
      </note> with dailye vse and exercise: wherevpon it came to passe y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
an armye in latine was called <hi>Exercitus,</hi> to the intent it should be euer
in labour &amp; practise, and neuer forget to what ende it was so named.</p>
   <p>Wherein he first sheweth that they must learne and exercise to march
in battell raye, to runne, to leape, to swimme, to strike hansomely, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninglye
to vse al kinde of weapons, to shoote, to cast dartes, to cast sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
with slinges, or with hande, to mount on horses, to carrye weight,
to fortefye the Campe, to caste and scoure trenches, with other kindes
of exercises to long here at this time to be recyted.</p>
   <p>In the seconde booke he deuideth the feates of warre into certaine
kindes,<note place="margin">The .2. booke</note> he describeth the partes of an army, which amonge diuers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
were diuerslye named: but the <hi>Romaines</hi> called them Legions,
<hi>Ab eligendo,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Legio ab eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo.</note> which word he sayth requyreth their fayth and diligence,
by whom y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> souldiours are to be allowed or refused. He sheweth how
many cohortes or bandes of souldiours should be in one Legion, how
manye or how fewe Legions the <hi>Romaines</hi> vsed to leade in one army,
he setteth forth the names and degrees of the principall men of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> host,
he declareth the offices of all the Captaynes and gouernours, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt,
the Martiall, the Centurions, peticaptaines, and all other
rulers and officers of the whole armye: he describeth the troupes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
horsemen, and as well the names, as the offices of the Captaines of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye
bande. Manye other thinges also hee toucheth concerninge the
Standerds, banners, ensignes and flagges, yea and the offices of the
Trumpetters, by whose sound it is knowē when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> souldiours should
set forward to anye worke, when they should fighte or staye, when they
should followe the chase, or when they should retyre. Thus with many
other notable thinges to be knowen, and partlye with a vehement ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation
<pb facs="7"/>
to the diligent exercise of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> feates of warre, and partly with
a briefe rehersal of certaine tooles and engines, vsed to be caryed with
the armye, he concludeth the seconde booke.</p>
   <p>In the thirde hee teacheth howe an armye well appointed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed,<note place="margin">The 3. booke</note>
as is aforesayd, maye nowe be brought to the fielde and ioyne
wyth the aduersaryes. But first hee sheeweth howe the health of the
hoast should be preserued: what regarde should be had that graine fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
and victualles should be prouided for and kepte: howe the chiefe
Captaines should keepe the souldiours in quiet from sedition and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore:
howe warelye and cyrcumspectlye the armye shoulde be ledde,
when at any time it remoueth: howe to passe ryuers, and other daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
places. How greate consideration oughte to be whether they
should fight in skirmishe, or set battel? y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chiefe Captaynes great care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse
before they ioyne battell, in tryinge the courage of his souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,
in chosinge ameete place for to fighte in, in settinge them in suche
order and araye that they be not easelye ouercome. Which thinges for
that they cannot be comprehended in fewe wordes, and the Author dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courseth
of them at large in many Chapters, I referre the Readers to
the selfe same Author, who doth so perfectlye set forth such notable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises
and pollicyes, such skilfulnes and knowledge, such prouidence &amp;
warenes, as ought to be in such a man, to whom the worthye honours
of so greate power and authoritie are ascribed, that vnto his fidelitye,
vertue, and manhoode (that I maye here vse the very wordes of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getius</hi>)
the defence of Cittyes, the lyues of the souldiours, the renowne
of the common wealth, may safely be committed. After these, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
certaine generall rules of warre, and so endeth his third booke.</p>
   <p>In the fourth booke he treateth of the besieginge and defendinge of
Cittyes:<note place="margin">The 4. booke</note> wherein he first speaketh of the buildinge and fortefyinge of
the same: and what foresight should be if a Cittye be besieged, that it
suffer not famyne: what pollicy may be vsed, if water, salt, strings, or
cordes and suche like shoulde fayle in the Cittye. He reherseth also a
nomber of engines and much ordinaunce vsed in those dayes in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieginge
of Cittyes: the description whereof who so list to know more
at large, let him reade the tenth and eleuenth booke of <hi>Robertus Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turius.</hi>
Also he geueth certaine preceptes and rules of warres vppon
the sea: in which he sheweth what kinde of shippes were most necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
and commodious for the purpose: and how dilligentlye the same
were made: in what monethes and seasons of the yeare timber should
be felled: he nameth and nombreth the windes: he sheweth when it is
good to sayle, &amp; when not: he speaketh of certayne signes and tokens,
whereby mariners maye foreknowe fayre weather or foule, calme or
<pb facs="7"/>
tempest: then describing certaine armour and ordinaunce for shippes,
he briefelye teacheth howe to lye in waite, and also howe to ioyne open
battell on the sea: and thus endeth he his fourth and last booke of the
institutions of warre. In all whiche worke briefelye and plainlye is
contained, not onlye (as I saide before) a methode or compendious
waye, but also a perfect knowledge and arte of warre: to the which if
painefull dilligence and experience be ioyned,<note place="margin">Experience ioyned with knowledge, brīgeth great thinges to passe.</note> what let shoulde be, but
that no lesse worthines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ud excellencye appeare in warriours of these
our dayes, then hath beene founde in the most famous Captaynes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
our time: to the which not experience alone brought them, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligente
learninge and studyinge of the feates of warre, written and set
forth both by historicall writers &amp; Poets, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d by such also as this our
present Author <hi>Vegetius</hi> is. Innumerable examples might be here
recyted, but passing ouer all the residue for shortnes of time, two of the
chiefest may suffice.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Alexander</hi> the great.</note>
      <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, who in short space subdued
the greatest part of the world, had alwayes the Poet <hi>Homer</hi> layd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
his beddes heade, in whom he might beholde the office as well of
excellent Princes, as of most worthye Captaynes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi>
      <note place="margin">C. Iulius Caesar.</note> howe greatlye he was geeuen to this kinde of studye, it
doth most euidentlye appeare by such notable bookes as he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
and intitled Commentaryes. And surelye in mine opinion, it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
a farre better and shorter waye to attaine to the name of a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye
and perfecte Captaine to ioyne experience vnto knowledge,<note place="margin">Better to ioyne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then to gette know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</note> then
to get knowledge by experience. For mans life being short and subiect
to manye casualtyes, oftentimees is cutte of before it can come to anye
such perfection as is requyred in an excellent man of warre: whereas
small experience with diligente readinge and perfecte learninge
of feates of ware, maye frame and make manye polliticke Captaynes
in a shorter space. I do not meane that knowledge withoute experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
can do anye great thinge at all: but beinge ioyned both together,
doubtles they maye be as able to bringe to passe as great and maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
thinges in valiant men in these our dayes, as they haue beene in
manye noble men before our time, as namely in those most worthy and
famous conquerours, whom partly for breuityes sake, partly for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
sake I mentioned before: whereof <hi>Alexander</hi> the greate (as
<hi>Iustine</hi> and others do witnes) neuer foughte with anye ennemyes,
whom he did not vanquish and ouercome: and howe <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> did
preuaile, his historyes do declare, who being much inferiour in nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
to his ennemyes, was so skilfull and experte in the ordering of his
battelles,<note place="margin">The not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap> skilfulnes of Iulius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar.</note> that as it were before throughlye assured, he woulde foretell
to his men, euen in this bande (naminge and pointinge oute the same)
shall consist the victory: which should afterward euen so come to passe
<pb facs="8"/>
as you maye reade in the greatest and last conflicte betweene him and
<hi>Pompeie,</hi> besydes other places in the thirde booke of the <hi>Romayne</hi>
cyuill warres.</p>
   <p>Presupposinge that I haue sayde sufficientlye for the exhortinge of
thee gentle Reader to the ouerlookinge of this booke: as well for the
necessarye matter therein contayned, as for causes by occasion chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge
from time to time, whereby the same matter maye neede to be
practsed: with hope of thy good pardon for anye my faultes whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer,
as thou mayest seeme rather to encourage then discourage mee:
I committe thee to Almightye GOD, and to the readinge of my
Author <hi>Flauius Vegetius,</hi> rudelye, yet profitably hereafter speakinge
in Englishe.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>