<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Plaine and necessarie Preamble, wherein certaine important Obser∣uations are set downe, for the better vnderstanding of this new Oath of Allegiance.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119291_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14049</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119291</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Plaine and necessarie Preamble, wherein certaine important Obser∣uations are set downe, for the better vnderstanding of this new Oath of Allegiance.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Nevv-Yeares gift for English Catholikes, or A briefe and cleare explication of the new Oath of Allegiance : By E.I. student in Diuinitie; for a more full instruction, and appeasement of the consciences of English Catholikes, concerning the said Oath, then hath beene giuen them by I.E. student in Diuinitie, who compiled the treatise of the prelate and the prince</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 208, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preamble">
   <head>A Plaine and necessarie <hi>Preamble,</hi> wherein certaine important <hi>Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations</hi> are set downe, for the better vnderstanding of this new <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>BEfore I come to explaine the particular branches of this new
<hi>Oath</hi> established by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> I thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse to set downe by way of a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble</hi> or
<hi>Preface</hi> certaine general Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations, which may giue no little light to the better vnderstanding of the same.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <note place="margin">The <hi>First</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation.</note>1. <hi>First,</hi> therefore to know the nature and conditions of an <hi>Oath,</hi> it is to be obserued, that euerie lawfull
<hi>Oath</hi> must be <hi>discreet, iust,</hi> and <hi>true;</hi> according to that of the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem.</hi>
4.</note>
      <hi>And thou shalt sweare in Truth, and in Iustice, and in Iudgement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Iudgement</hi> is required chiefly in
<pb n="25" facs="29"/>regard of the swearer, that hee take not the Name of God in vaine, rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, irreuerently, without iust and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occasion, and not duly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth of what he sweareth; for the matter or thing which is sworne, may oftentimes bee true and iust, and yet the Name of God may bee taken in vaine, and without iust cause or necessitie to confirme the same.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Iustice</hi> is required chiefly in a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missorie Oath,</hi> to wit, wherein some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is promised for the future time to be done or omitted: and therefore as it is vnlawfull to promise any thing which is vniust, so is it more vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to confirme that vniust promise by Oath. Yet <hi>Iustice</hi> may also some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bee wanting in an
<hi>Assertorie Oath,</hi> as when one reuealeth a secret, which in Iustice hee is bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale, and confirmeth the same by Oath, for then he sweareth truly, but vniustly.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Veritie</hi> or <hi>Truth</hi> is necessarie in all Oaths, for also in a <hi>promissorie</hi> Oath two kinds of <hi>veritie</hi> are required; the
<pb n="26" facs="30"/>
      <hi>one</hi> is for the pesent time (wherein it resembleth the nature of an <hi>Assertorie Oaeth</hi>) for hee that promiseth to doe, or not to doe any thing, must haue his words agreeable to his minde, and therefore must for the present haue a minde or intent to performe what hee promiseth; otherwise hee sweareth vntruly; the
<hi>second</hi> veritie is for the future time; for he that promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth any thing, calling God for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his promise, and through his owne default doth not performe his promise at the time appointed, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sworne, and his <hi>promissorie Oath</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>veritie:</hi> But
<hi>truth</hi> and <hi>veritie</hi> is chiefly required in <hi>Assertorie Oaths,</hi> to wit, wherein some thing is affirmed to be true or false. And therefore as it is vnlawfull for one to affirme that to be true, which hee knoweth to bee false, and contrariwise, for this were expresly and formally to lye, or to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that to be true or false, whereof he is vncertaine or doubtfull, for this were to expose himselfe to danger of speaking an vntruth, so also it is much more vnlawfull to confirme the same by Oath.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <pb n="27" facs="30"/>2. Whereupon <hi>Periurie</hi> is defined by the Schoole-Diuines to be <hi>a lye confirmed by Oath.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Magister <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>dist.</hi> 39. <hi>S. Thom.</hi>
      </note> And therefore as a lye is deuided into a <hi>formall</hi> lye, to wit, when one affirmeth any thing to be true or false, and thinketh other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in his mind (for <hi>to lye,</hi> saith Saint
<hi>Augustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">August. <hi>lib de Mendacio.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>is to speake against that which hee thinketh in his minde,</hi>) and into <hi>a materiall</hi> lye, to wit, when one speaketh as hee thinketh, and yet in very deed it is otherwise; So <hi>Periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> is deuiued into <hi>materiall</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall</hi> Periurie, for that
<hi>Periurie</hi> is a <hi>lye confirmed by Oath,</hi> and only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to a
<hi>lye</hi> the calling of God to witnesse of what hee speaketh. And therefore whatsoeuer may bee affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without danger of <hi>lying,</hi> may be sworne without danger of <hi>Periurie:</hi> and as the falshood which maketh a <hi>formall</hi> lye, is not to bee taken from the thing as it is in it selfe or <hi>ex parte rei,</hi> but as it is conceiued by the spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, for that to <hi>lye</hi> is to speake against the minde, so the falshood, which maketh <hi>formall</hi> Periurie, is not to be taken from the thing which is sworn,
<pb n="28" facs="31"/>as it is in it selfe, or <hi>ex parte rei,</hi> but as it is against the mind and knowledge of the swearer.</p>
   <p n="3">3. For <hi>the veritie, which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in an Oath, consisteth in this,</hi> saith <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> &amp;
<hi>Sayrus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>Valentia <hi>tom.</hi> 3 <hi>disp.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 7.
<hi>p.</hi> 3.</p>
         <p>Sayrus <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Thesauri cap.</hi> 4.
<hi>nu.</hi> 7.</p>
      </note>
      <hi>that the thing bee true, at least wise accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reasonable iudgement of the swearer. And therefore it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued,</hi> that to iudge whether an <hi>Oath</hi> be true or false, we must not so much regard the thing sworne, as the mind and knowledge of him that sweareth. So that <hi>whosoeuer affirmeth a thing by Oath,</hi> saith <hi>Siluester</hi> and <hi>Petrus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoua,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>Siluest. <hi>verbo</hi> Periurium <hi>q.</hi> 1.</p>
         <p>Aragoua, 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 89. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</p>
      </note>
      <hi>in that manner as hee knoweth it to be true, is not formally forsworne:</hi> as if he sweare his opinion, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, or perswasion, he must be morally certaine, that he is so perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if he sweare it absolutely to bee so, he must bee morally certaine it is so, otherwise he exposeth himselfe to danger of being forsworne, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in very deed it fall out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then he is morally certain, yet he is excused in the Court of Conscience from the sinne of Periurie, and hee is not <hi>formally,</hi> but only <hi>materially</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sworne.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb n="29" facs="31"/>
      <note place="margin">The <hi>Second</hi> Obseruation.</note>4. <hi>Secondly,</hi> to know in what sense the words of euery <hi>Law,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of this <hi>Oath,</hi> which is esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by a <hi>Parliamentall Law,</hi> ought to be taken, it is to bee <hi>obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> out of the doctrine of <hi>Franciscus Suarez a famous Iesuite,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de</hi> Legibus <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> that the
<q rend="inline">"<hi>words of euery Law are commonly to be vnderstood according to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and vsuall signification, and that if any wordes haue many proper and vsual significations, that sense is to be taken, wherein the Law-maker doth vnderstand them, because vpon the will and intention of the Law-maker (which is the soule of the Law) the substance and force of the Law, doth chiefly depend. Whereupon if by any meanes the will of the Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker can bee knowne, according to it especially wee must interprete the words of the Law, because that is the true interpretation of the Law, by which we follow the meaning and will of the Law-maker. But if by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Law-maker wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not gather the meaning of any equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocall and ambiguous word or sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="30" facs="32"/>contayned in the Law, then we must vse those rules, which in all am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous and doubtfull speeches are prudently to be obserued: to wit, that the matter or contents of the Law, with the antecedents, &amp; consequents, and other circumstances be diligently considered, for by them the meaning of the words, and the will of the Law-maker will easily be gathered. And especially we must consider the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Preface or Preamble, of the Law, and with it to ioyne the rest that followeth: for to the beginning, if there be no other let, all that followeth is to be applyed; because in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or Preface of euery Law is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually contayned the finall end, cause, and reason, which chiefly moueth the Law-maker, and which is morally a sure meanes to finde out his will and meaning, and by which the ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of any word or sentence is chiefly to be determined. And finally we must alwaies, if there be no other let, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete the words of the Law, when they are doubtfull, in the more milde and fauourable sense, especially if the
<pb n="31" facs="32"/>matter be odious, and penall, aeccor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to those approued rules of the Law,</hi> Benignius <hi>leges &amp;c.</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Leg.</hi> Benignius <hi>ff de</hi> legibus. <hi>De</hi> regulis Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris <hi>in Sexin.</hi>
         </note>
      </q> Laws are to be interpreted in the more fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable sense, &amp;c. And it is meete that odious things be restrayned, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours bee enlarged.
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Yea, and if the words of the Law being taken in their proper signification should argue any iniustice, or like absurditie to bee in the minde of the Law-maker, they must bee drawne to a sense although improper, wherein the Laew may bee iust and reasonable, because this is presumed to bee the will of the Law-maker, as it hath beene declared by many Lawes</hi> in ff. tit. de Legibus. Nam in ambigua voce, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Leg.</hi> in ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua <hi>ff.</hi> de legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> For in a doubtfull word of the Law, <hi>saith the Law,</hi> that sense is rather to bee chosen, which is voide of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, especially seeing that the will also of the Law-maker may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be gathered: <hi>because it ought not to be persumed, that the Law-maker did intend to command any absurd or inconuenient thing.</hi>
      </q> Thus
<hi>Suarez.</hi> What blame then doe they deserue,
<pb n="32" facs="33"/>who seeke to wrest the wordes of this Oath, to a sense which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to bee most false and absurd, with so great preiudice to the soules and temporall States of English Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and with no lesse irreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the State whom next vnder God they are bound to honor and obey in all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall affaires, whereas they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the words, according to their proper and vsuall signification, in a true, conuenient, and fauorable sense, as the Reader may see beneath?</p>
   <p n="5">5. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> to know the end and reason of this
<hi>Oath</hi> and of the makers thereof, it is to bee <hi>obserued,</hi> that the <hi>Parliamēt</hi> in the very beginning of this Act, (to which according to <hi>Suarez,</hi> we must, if there be no other let, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all that followeth) did expresly set downe the cause, end, and reason, for which this <hi>new Oath</hi> was deuised, to wit, <hi>to make a better tryall how His</hi> Maiesties <hi>subiects stand affected in point of their loyaltie, and due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> For His <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the
<hi>State</hi> perceiuing, that the <hi>Powder-Traytors.</hi>
      <pb n="33" facs="33"/>who were all of them <hi>Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> did ground, as it doth appeare by their confessions, their barbarous and deuillish plot chiefly vpon the <hi>Popes</hi> power to take away the Crownes and liues from temporall <hi>Princes</hi> in order to spirituall good, and knowing with all, that many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Roman Catholikes</hi> did from their hearts detest, and abhorre such tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and diabolicall practises, and the wicked grounds thereof, thought it needfull, for the better discouering and repressing of such bloudie Assasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, and their disciples, to deuise such an <hi>Oath,</hi> wherein true <hi>temporall Allegiance</hi> due to all <hi>temporall Princes</hi> of what Religion soeuer, should bee demanded, and no true
<hi>spirituall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> due to the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other
<hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Pastours</hi> should be denyed, and yet the wicked principles of that most damnable Conspiracie should bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and abiured. And the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of this <hi>new Oath</hi> they did take from the <hi>Protestation</hi> of those <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene</hi> Catholike Priests (as the Lord Archbishop of Canterburie, Doctor
<pb n="34" facs="34"/>
      <hi>Bancroft</hi> told a deare friend of mine) only vsing another forme of words, and expressing some things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Popes</hi> pretended authoritie, which in their
<hi>Protestation</hi> are not expressed, but only supposed, implyed and virtually contayned, for in effect and substance they little differ, as partly you haue seen aboue, and more fully shall perceiue when you haue seene all the branches of the <hi>Oath</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned.
<note place="margin">In his <hi>Premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition pag.</hi> 9. &amp; in hir <hi>Apologie</hi> for the Oath. pag. 2. &amp; pag. 9.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="6">6. And not only the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath set downe the end and reason of this <hi>new Oath,</hi> but also His <hi>Maiestie</hi> Himselfe hath often by publike Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in expresse words declared, that He intended to exact <hi>in this Oath</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else of His Subiects,
<hi>then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of that temporall Allegiance and ciuill Obedience, which all subiects</hi> (what Religion soeuer they professe) <hi>by the Law of God and Nature do owe to their lawfull Prince with a promise to resist and disclose all contrarie vnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill violence; and to make a true distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not betwixt</hi> Catholikes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, <hi>but betwixt ciuilly obedient</hi>
      <pb n="35" facs="34"/>Catholikes, <hi>and such</hi> Catholikes
<hi>as are the Disciples of the Powder-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi> Whereupon <hi>hee caused the lower house of Parliament, who at first would haue had the Oath to contayne the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of the Popes power to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate him, to reforme that clause. So carefull was He, that nothing should be contayned in this</hi> Oath <hi>except the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of naturall Allegiance, and ciuill and temporall obedience.</hi> He said <hi>in this Oath;</hi> for as the <hi>Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie,</hi> saith His <hi>Maiestie, was deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for putting a difference betweene</hi> Papists, <hi>and them of our professions so was this</hi> Oath <hi>ordayned for making a difference betweene the ciuilly obedient</hi> Papists, <hi>and the peruerse disciples of the Powder-Treason.</hi> And againe, <hi>This Oath,</hi> saith His <hi>Maiestie, was orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned only for making a true distinction betweene</hi> Papists <hi>of quiet disposition, and in all other things good subiects, and such other</hi> Papists <hi>as in their harts maintayned the like violent bloudie maximes that the</hi> Powder-Traytours
<hi>did.</hi> The same also but in more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wordes affirmeth His
<hi>Maiestie</hi>
      <pb n="36" facs="35"/>in His <hi>Apologie</hi> for the
<hi>Oath.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="7">7. Wherefore we must distinguish betwixt the vnderstanding, beliefe, or perswasion of His <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and His will, intent, or meaning as Hee is a <hi>Law-maker.</hi> For albeit His
<hi>Maiestie</hi> should beleeue and be fully perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> is not the Supreme Head of the whole Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently that he hath not by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of Christ any power to
<hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate</hi> him, yet his will and meaning is not, that His subiects shal in <hi>this Oath</hi> professe the same, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce any spirituall obedience due to the <hi>Pope,</hi> which euery
<hi>Catholike,</hi> according to the grounds of true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, is bound to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, but only, that they make a profession of that temporall Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and ciuill obedience, which all subiects, of what Religion soeuer, do owe to their lawfull Prince. From whence it cleerly followeth, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit there were in <hi>this Oath</hi> some am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous or doubtfull sentence (as there is not) which might be applyed as well to the denying of that spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="37" facs="35"/>obedience, which, according to the grounds of Catholike Religion, is due to the <hi>Pope</hi> and other spirituall Pastours, as to the professing of that temporall Allegiance, which is due to temporall Princes, we ought to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete the words in that sense, wherein, according to the will, minde, and end of the Law, and declaration of the Law-maker, only temporall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is demanded, for that <hi>by the end and reason of the Law the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie of the words,</hi> saith
<hi>Suarez,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de</hi> Legibus
<hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>nu.</hi> 19.</note>
      <hi>is chiefly to be determined, and it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a sure meanes to finde out the will and intention of the Law-maker, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that reason which is expressed in the Law, for then the reason of the Law is in some sort a part thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is contayned and supposed therein.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="8">8. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> it is to bee <hi>obserued,</hi> that albeit <hi>English Catholikes</hi> might <hi>at the first,</hi> before they examined par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the end, reason, matter, and contents of this <hi>new Oath,</hi> iustly sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it to be vnlawfull, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne in it more then <hi>temporall Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance;</hi>
      <pb n="38" facs="36"/>and that His <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the
<hi>Parliament</hi> vnder pretence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding that <hi>temporall Allegiance,</hi> which by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is due to all <hi>temporall Princes,</hi> did intend to haue couertly at leastwise abiured some <hi>spirituall obedience,</hi> which by the institution of <hi>Christ</hi> is due to <hi>spirituall Pastours,</hi> both for that it is a new, vncouth, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted <hi>Oath</hi> of
<hi>Allegiance,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly denyeth the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, to depose wherewith other <hi>Christian Princes,</hi> in the ordinarie
<hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which they demand of their subiects, doe not in plaine and expresse termes intermeddle; and also for that it was deuised by those, who are opposite to the Catholike <hi>Romane</hi> Religion; yet this bare suspicion can bee no sufficient cause, ground, or motiue to condemne it (as likewise no man vpon a bare suspicion is to be condemned) but only to haue it exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and if after due examination it be found faulty, to reiect it, if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to approue it. But doubtlesse whosoeuer will sincerely, and with a
<pb n="39" facs="36"/>pure desire to find out the truth, and to yeeld without all partialitie as wel to <hi>Kings</hi> as to <hi>Popes</hi> that which is their due, examine the occasion, end, matter, and contents of this <hi>new</hi> and <hi>vnwonted Oath,</hi> will quickly finde, that it is condemned by some, vpon a bare and naked suspicion and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due examination; by others, vpon a blind and inconsiderate zeale to the <hi>See Apostolike,</hi> not regarding in like manner the dutie which by the
<hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> they owe to their <hi>temporall Prince;</hi> and by all that thinke it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, without sufficient ground.</p>
   <p n="9">9. For the occasion of this <hi>vnwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Oath,</hi> was that <hi>vnwonted</hi> barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Powder-plot</hi> of certaine Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who pretended to iustifie their neuer heard of <hi>Barbarisme</hi> vnder the colour of Religion, and the <hi>Popes</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to dispose of the Crownes and liues of <hi>temporall Princes</hi> in order to spirituall good; and so no maruell, that to preuent the like <hi>vnwonted</hi> crueltie was deuised this <hi>vnwonted</hi> remedie. And albeit the inuenters of this
<hi>Oath</hi> are opposite to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="40" facs="37"/>Romane Religion and are fully perswaded, that the <hi>Pope</hi> by the Law of God, hath no authoritie ouer this Kingdome, so much as in spiritualls, yet there meaning was not, as you haue seene aboue, to meddle <hi>in this Oath</hi> with that spirituall authoritie, which is granted him by all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, but only to demand a profession of that temporall Allegiance, which all the Subiects of this Land, of what Religion soeuer they be, doe owe to their <hi>temporall</hi> Prince, and not to the
<hi>Pope.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="10">10. And therefore, which is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to bee
<hi>obserued,</hi> this <hi>Oath</hi> doth not meddle <hi>positiuely</hi> with the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, for that it doth not belong to
<hi>temporall Princes</hi> to declare what authoritie the <hi>Pope</hi> hath, but it med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>positiuely</hi> with the <hi>Kings</hi> tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> and <hi>negatiuely</hi> with the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie; and it doth not declare
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> what authoritie the <hi>Pope</hi> hath, but only what authoritie hee hath not. And what man, I pray you, can bee so blinde as not to see, that whosoeuer <hi>expresly</hi> affirmeth
<hi>King
<pb n="41" facs="37"/>Iames</hi> to bee his true and rightfull
<hi>King</hi> and <hi>Soueraigne</hi> in temporalls, and to haue ouer him and his other Subiects all <hi>Kingly Power, Authority,</hi> and
<hi>Iurisdiction,</hi> doth <hi>consequently</hi> and <hi>vertually</hi> deny the same of the <hi>Pope?</hi> Wherefore if wee well examine the matter and contents of this <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted Oath,</hi> wee shall find, that His
<hi>Maiestie</hi> and the <hi>State</hi> doe herein deny no other authoritie of the <hi>Pope expresly</hi> and by name, then which not only in the
<hi>Protestation</hi> of those <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene</hi> Catholike Priests, but also in all other <hi>vsuall</hi> Oaths of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which absolute Princes are wont to demand of their Subiects, is vertual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, couertly, and in effect implyed. For whosoeuer sincerely and from his heart acknowlegeth, any Prince to be his only rightfull <hi>King</hi> and
<hi>Soueraigne</hi> in temporals (which all absolute <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in their vsuall Oaths of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance demand of their Subjects) hee must
<hi>vertually</hi> acknowledge, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is not his
<hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> in temporals, and consequently, that he hath no authoritie ouer his Prince or
<pb n="42" facs="38"/>him in temporals, and therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to depose his Prince, or to dispose of His temporall Dominions, for that these are tēporal things for what end, cause, crime, or pretext soeuer, either spirituall or temporall, they be done.</p>
   <p n="11">11. <hi>Fiftly,</hi> to know vpon what assured grounds the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depose Princes,</hi> or to attempt and practise their deposition, is by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes denyed <hi>in this Oath,</hi> it is to be <hi>obserued,</hi> that as <hi>Leonardus Lessius,</hi> a famous Iesuite, noteth very well,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Lessius</hi> in his <hi>Singleton,</hi> part. 2. <hi>nu.</hi> 38.</note>
      <hi>a power which is not altogether certaine but probable, cannot be a</hi> sufficient
<hi>ground</hi> or title, <hi>whereby immediately any man may bee punished or depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of that right, dominion, or any other thing which he actually possesseth, but such a power or title must bee most certaine, and without all doubt or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie.</hi> Wherefore neither can the
<hi>Pope,</hi> nor any other <hi>Prince,</hi> without manifest iniustice inuade the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of another <hi>Prince,</hi> make warre against him, or seeke to depose or dispossesse him vpon a probable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, or controuersed title. <hi>For
<pb n="43" facs="38"/>certes,</hi> saith the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> and the <hi>Prince,</hi> (and who is knowne to bee a famous <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Professor</hi> of Diuinity though masked vnder the name of <hi>I. E.</hi>)<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.
<hi>pag.</hi> 235.</note>
      <hi>as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustice to put one out of his land or house, who hath probable right and and withall possession, because</hi> poti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>r est conditio possidentis, better is the condition of him that is in possession, <hi>So were it open iniustice in the</hi> Pope <hi>to depriue a</hi> King <hi>of his Crowne and Kingdome, who hath probable right and withall possession.</hi> And this also is the receiued doctrine of all Diuines and Lawyers,<note place="margin">
         <p>Victoria <hi>in</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>de ture bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li. nu.</hi> 29.
<hi>&amp; seq.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Vasquez 1. 2. <hi>disp.</hi> 64. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
         <p>Gregorius <hi>de</hi> Valentia 2. 2. and Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others cited by <hi>Valentia.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> and grounded in the light of naturall reason, and declared by the approued rules of the Law, that no man can bee iustly inuaded, or be put out of his possession vpon an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine or controuersed title, because <hi>In causa dubia, siue incerta potior est conditio possidentis, In a doubtfull</hi> or disputable cause <hi>the condition of the possessor is to bee preferred,</hi> and <hi>Cum sunt iura partium obscura fauendum est reo potius quam Actori. When the rights</hi> or titles <hi>of the parties that are
<pb n="44" facs="39"/>in suite are obscure,</hi> or not cleere,
<hi>the Defendant is rather to be fauoured then the Plaintiffe.</hi> And this is the <hi>first</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured ground and principle, for which the doctrine of deposing <hi>Princes</hi> by the Popes <hi>authoritie</hi> may not only be barely and simply denyed, as it is in the <hi>second</hi> clause of the
<hi>Oath</hi> by force only of the words, but also bee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred, detested and abiured as <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, damnable,</hi> most cleerly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God, and in that sense <hi>hereticall,</hi> as it is in the
<hi>fourth</hi> clause. The <hi>second</hi> manifest principle is, that it is a controuersie among learned Catholikes, and approued by many, and therefore <hi>truely probable,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authority to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue <hi>Princes</hi> of their Regall Power and Authoritie.</p>
   <p n="12">12. For the better cleering where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is to be obserued <hi>sixtly,</hi> that, as <hi>Ioannes Azorius</hi> a famous Iesuite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly affirmeth,<note place="margin">Azor. <hi>tom.</hi> 2.
<hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>it hath euer beene a great controuersie betwixt Emperours and Kings on the one side, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Rome on the other, whether in some certaine cases the Pope hath a
<pb n="45" facs="39"/>right and power to depriue Kings of their Kingdome. For some Kings haue oftentimes</hi> (yea since the time of the great <hi>Lateran Councell</hi>) <hi>contended with Popes about this matter, saying, that they haue their Kingdome from God, and not from the Pope, and that in those things, which are ciuill and temporall the power of Kings is supreme and absolute, and that herein Kings are not subiect to the Pope, although in sacred, Ecclesiasticall and spirituall things the Pontificall power is supreme, and that herein Kings and Princes are subiect to Popes, as children to their Fathers, and sheepe to their Pastours, &amp;c. And many complayned that</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie <hi>the seuenth did excommunicate</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth, and depriue him of the administration of his Kingdom.</hi> Thus <hi>Azor. And it is a controuersie among the Schoolemen,</hi> (saith <hi>Ioannes Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi>
      <note place="margin">Trithemius <hi>in Chron. Hirsaug. ad annum</hi> 1106.</note>)
<hi>and as yet it is not decided by the Iudge, whether the Pope hath power to depose the Emperour or no. And the Ecclesiasticall power</hi> (saith
<hi>Iacobus Almainus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Almain. <hi>de d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minio natur. ciu. &amp; Eccles in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</hi> 2. <hi>conclus.</hi>
      </note> a famous Doctor of Paris, and whom
<hi>Azor</hi> relateth<note place="margin">Azor. <hi>tom.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi>
2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> among
<pb n="46" facs="40"/>Classicall Doctors) <hi>cannot by the insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of God inflict any ciuill punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as are death, exile, priuation of goods,</hi> much lesse of Kingdomes, &amp;c. <hi>Nay nor so much as imprison,</hi> vt ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris{que} Doctoribus placet, <hi>as is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of most, or of very many Doctors, but it is extended only to a spirituall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, as is Excommunication, and the other punishments, which she vseth, doe proceed from the pure positiue Law,</hi> or as
<hi>Gerson</hi> speaketh,<note place="margin">Gerson <hi>de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. Eccles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderat.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>from the grant of Princes. And the libertie of the Church of France,</hi> saith <hi>Petrus Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pithaeus <hi>in Cod. libert. Eccles. Gallicanae</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at
<hi>Paris</hi> by authoritie of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the yeere 1594.</note> (whom <hi>Antonius Posseuinus</hi> the Iesuite commendeth for a man
<hi>truely learned and a diligent searcher of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie</hi>
      <note place="margin">Posseuinus <hi>in verbo</hi> Petrus Pithaeus.</note>) <hi>is grounded in this principle, which France hath euer held for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the</hi> Pope <hi>hath not power to depriue the French King of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or in any other manner to dispose thereof; And that notwithstanding any whatsoeuer Monitions</hi> or Monitories, <hi>Excommunications, or Interdicts, which by the</hi> Pope <hi>can bee made, yet the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects are bound to yeeld obedience due to the King for temporals; neither therein
<pb n="47" facs="40"/>can they be dispenced or absolued by the Pope;</hi> Which position is in very deed the whole substance both of our
<hi>new Oath,</hi> and also of the <hi>late Oath</hi> of France, which the lower house of <hi>Parliament</hi> would haue had establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed for a
<hi>fundamentall law.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="13">13. And to omit now many other learned Catholikes cited by
<hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his Answere to <hi>Fitzherb.</hi> part. 1.</note> that it is a controuersie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Catholikes, and approued by many, and therefore truly probable, that the Pope hath no authoritie to depose Princes, it is so manifest, that no learned man, vnlesse hee will bee shamefully impudent, can denie it, and the publike Writings of learned Catholikes on both sides,<note place="margin">See beneath in the end of this <hi>Treatise,</hi> the Oath of Frāce the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> and <hi>Bell.</hi> Booke, and a decree of the
<hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> touching the doctrine of the
<hi>Popes</hi> power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</note> the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the
<hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Bookes of <hi>Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> of <hi>Schulckenius,</hi> and of <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> the propounding of the aforena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Oath</hi> by the lower house of
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> wherein of two hundred Knights and Burgesses there were but <hi>fix Protestants,</hi> besides the complaint of some Doctors of <hi>Paris</hi> to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> against the
<hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersia Anglicana</hi> of <hi>Becanus,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="48" facs="41"/>other testimonies of learned men of our owne Nation, not only of those who haue taken the Oath, or thinke it to be lawfull, but also of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, doe most cleerly conuince the same. In so much that <hi>Cardinall Peron,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Card. Peron.</hi> in his speech to the lower house of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> compelled by so manifest a truth, doth plainly confesse the same; and thereupon acknowledgeth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> himselfe doth in
<hi>France</hi> tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate those Catholikes, that hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him in this point, <hi>tolerate,</hi> I say, not as publike Vsurers, Harlots, or other notorious sinners, are in some Countries permitted, but by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to Sacraments, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Pope,</hi> nor the <hi>Prelates</hi> of
<hi>France</hi> could lawfully doe, if for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that doctrine those
<hi>Frenchmen</hi> were to bee condemned of Heresie, Errour, Temeritie, or any other dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable sinne. So that it is most cleere &amp; manifest to any man of iudgment, that it is a great controuersie among learned Catholikes, and that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by many of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truly probable, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to <hi>depose</hi> or
<hi>depriue</hi>
      <pb n="49" facs="41"/>Soueraigne Princes. See also the
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of the <hi>Potestants</hi> Apologie for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in his <hi>Preface</hi> from Sect. 19. to the end, where you may see his dislike of this doctrine for the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depose Princes, and taxeth them, who <hi>ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the supreme Pastour with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent attributes of Authoritie in temporals:</hi> and in his owne authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Manuscript he more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and expresly shewed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no Authority in temporals, <hi>either directly, or indirectly,</hi> which last words it pleased those who had commission to print his Booke to leaue out, whereof he greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to a friend of mine. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise for the dislike, which this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Authour</hi> shewed in his <hi>Preface,</hi> of this authoritie of the <hi>Pope</hi> to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of temporals, it pleased the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour,</hi> who translated his Booke into Latine, to leaue out the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> altogether, which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse is a chiefe part of his Booke, and it deserued to bee put in <hi>Latine</hi> as much if not more then any other
<pb n="50" facs="42"/>part thereof. But the <hi>Authours</hi> of Bookes must now adaies, if they looke not themselues to the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; publishing of them, speak as it pleaseth the Translators &amp; Censors.</p>
   <p n="15">15. Neither is it sufficient for a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny man, which also is to bee <hi>obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> to condemne any doctrine as temerarious or improbable, for that in his iudgement and opinion it is repugnant to
<hi>Scriptures,</hi> ancient <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, Canons,</hi> practice of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Theologicall</hi> reasons, if it bee approued by other learned Catholikes, who haue examined all the arguments on either side; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise the <hi>Thomists</hi> might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne of temeritie the
<hi>Scotists,</hi> and the <hi>Scotists</hi> the <hi>Thomists</hi> in the question of the B. <hi>Ʋirgins</hi> Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; The <hi>Diuines</hi> of
<hi>Rome</hi> might condemne of temeritie the <hi>Diuines</hi> of
<hi>Paris,</hi> and the <hi>Diuines</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> the <hi>Diuines</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in the question of the Popes infallibilitie, and supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie of the <hi>Pope</hi> and a <hi>Generall</hi> Councell; and the
<hi>Iesuites</hi> might condemne of temeritie the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi>
      <pb n="51" facs="42"/>and the <hi>Dominicans</hi> the
<hi>Iesuits,</hi> in the question of the efficacie of Grace: for all of them alledge for their opinion, <hi>Scriptures, Fathers, Councels, Canons,</hi> &amp; <hi>Theologicall</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, &amp; it is vsuall in most Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal questiōs to bring such arguments on both sides. But true probabilitie and improbabilitie, and whereof not only learned men, but also the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned without any great difficultie or perplexitie of conscience may iudge, is to be taken not from <hi>intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secall</hi> grounds, which are vnknowne to vnlearned men, but from <hi>extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secall</hi> grounds, to wit, the authoritie of learned men who are knowne to approue that doctrine. And therefore <hi>Aristotle,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aristotle <hi>lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>Top. cap.</hi> 8.</note> whome all Philosophers &amp; Diuines do herein follow, did by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsecall</hi> grounds define <hi>probable,</hi> to be that which <hi>is approued by wise, learned, and skilfull men</hi> in the Art which they professe: as in a matter of Law that is probable, which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by learned and skilfull Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers; in a matter of Physicke that is probable, which is approoued by
<pb n="52" facs="43"/>learned and skilfull Physicians, and in a matter of Theologicall learning that is probable, which is approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by learned and skilfull Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Diuines: which definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>probable</hi> is grounded in the light of naturall reason, for that it is not against prudence, and therefore no temeritie to giue credit to one in a matter wherein he is skilfull, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that vulgar maxime, <hi>Vnicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in sua arte perito credendum est, Credit is to bee giuen to euery man that is skilfull in his Art.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="16">16. These bee the <hi>two principall grounds,</hi> for which the doctrine of <hi>deposing</hi> Princes by the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie may lawfully bee denyed, and also abiured in the manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said; for if it bee <hi>certaine,</hi> that it is open iniustice to dispossesse any man vpon a <hi>probable, vncertaine,</hi> and
<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersed</hi> power or title, and it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>certaine,</hi> that it is a <hi>controuersie,</hi> and not <hi>certaine,</hi> whether the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to <hi>depose Princes</hi> or no; it followeth euidently, that it is as lawfull for any man to sweare, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to
<pb n="53" facs="43"/>
      <hi>depose</hi> Princes, as that hee hath no authoritie to commit open iniustice. But of this <hi>probabilitie</hi> see more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath in the end of this Treatise.</p>
   <p n="17">17. The <hi>Seuenth</hi> and <hi>last</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation is, that wee must carefully consider, what the swearer is bound to acknowledge and sweare in euery <hi>branch</hi> of this <hi>Oath</hi> by
<hi>force</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>expresse words, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the plaine and common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of them,</hi> to which by the <hi>seuenth branch</hi> hee is expresly tyed, and what he may lawfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and sweare by <hi>reason</hi> of the <hi>matter;</hi> for this distinction may no little auaile to the better vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of some clauses of this <hi>Oath,</hi> seeing that it may often fall out, that in regard of the <hi>matter</hi> one may lawfully sweare that, which by
<hi>force</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> hee is not bound or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to sweare. As for example, if one bee commanded to sweare, what his iudgement, opinion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion or acknowledgement is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning something, whereof not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding he is certaine; by <hi>force</hi> of the <hi>wordes</hi> hee is bound only to
<pb n="54" facs="44"/>sweare, that hee thinketh, iudgeth, is perswaded, and acknowledgeth it to bee so, yet by <hi>reason</hi> of the
<hi>matter</hi> which to him is certaine, hee may lawfully sweare that absolutely and assuredly it is so. Likewise if one bee commanded to abiure as <hi>false,</hi> and <hi>hereticall</hi> a <hi>conditionall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiue</hi> proposition, which imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a choice to take which part of the <hi>disiunction</hi> he please, by <hi>force</hi> of the wordes hee is bound to abiure but <hi>one part</hi> of the <hi>disiunction</hi> as
<hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall,</hi> because to make such a <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiue</hi> proposition to bee <hi>false</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> it sufficeth that <hi>one part</hi> only of the <hi>disiunction</hi> bee <hi>false</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> yet somtimes by <hi>vertue</hi> of the
<hi>matter,</hi> when both parts of the <hi>disiunction</hi> are
<hi>heretical,</hi> he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abiure both as heretical, albeit by
<hi>force</hi> of the <hi>wordes</hi> hee bee not bound thereunto. As these proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Any man may lawfully honour, or blaspheme God, The Pope by vertue of his Pastorall power may excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate or murther any wicked Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> are <hi>false</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> and yet
<hi>one part</hi> of the <hi>disiunction</hi> is true, and
<pb n="55" facs="44"/>only the other is <hi>false</hi> and
<hi>hereticall:</hi> but both parts of this proposition, <hi>any man may lawfully hate or blasphem God,</hi> are <hi>false</hi> and
<hi>hereticall,</hi> &amp; so by <hi>reason</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> both parts may be abiured as <hi>hereticall,</hi> although by <hi>force</hi> of the forme of words, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure the whole proposition as <hi>hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> it sufficeth to abiure only <hi>one part</hi> thereof as <hi>hereticall,</hi> And how this also may bee applyed to the <hi>fourth</hi> branch of the
<hi>Oath,</hi> wherein a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall disiunctiue</hi> proposition is contayned, and whether the <hi>doctrine</hi> not only of <hi>murthering Princes, which be excommunicated or depriued</hi> by the <hi>Pope,</hi> but also of <hi>deposing</hi> them, may bee abiured as <hi>hereticall,</hi> you shall see beneath. These <hi>Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations</hi> being considered, there will be found little or no difficultie in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part or parcell of the Oath.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>