<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT worthy and VVor∣shipfull Master ROBERT LEVYSTONE, Gentleman of his Majesties Bedchamber, all honour in this life, and Eternall glory in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Greenewood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119046_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02190</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12334</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119046</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT worthy and VVor∣shipfull Master ROBERT LEVYSTONE, Gentleman of his Majesties Bedchamber, all honour in this life, and Eternall glory in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Greenewood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Markes and no markes, of the Kingdome of Heauen: or, A treatise of things neccessary, vnnecessary, to the Kingdome of God. By Henry Greenewood Master of Art, and preacher of the word of God</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 43, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT worthy and VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Master ROBERT LEVYSTONE, Gentleman of his Majesties Bedchamber, all honour in this life, and Eternall glory in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was (worthy Sir) a chiefe care in Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gracious Apostle (who was <hi>Gentium tuba,</hi> and Gods <hi>Organum electum,</hi> set apart to preach and transveigh the liquor of life to the Gentiles, after hee had layd downe the Foundation Christ Jesus, and
<pb facs="3"/>
the body of the truth, to keepe the <hi>Corinthian</hi> and other Churches from scisme, faction, strife and contention: as in the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10, 11.</note>
      <hi>Hee beseecheth them by the Name of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, that they would all speake one thing, and that there might bee no dissentions among them, but to bee knit together in one minde, and in one judgement,</hi> and all this counsell for unanimity was but necessary, seeing the fruits of contention are so bitter.</p>
   <p>I desire to be an imitator of this blessed Apostle in this Christian endevour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering what great quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and hot contentions are found in our Brittish Church about matters of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, meere circumstances and bare ceremonies, &amp; what a Rent it made among us by the same, to the great advantage
<pb facs="3"/>
of Satans Kingdome, and much damage of the Kingdome of Christ. Now to quiet these un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary jarres and make peace about the same (peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making being a blessed thing, <hi>Beati pacifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i, Mat.</hi> 5.9.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.9</note>) I have adventured to set forth in this portion of Scripture some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about things indifferent, <hi>That we being of one minde, may live in peace, and living in peace,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.11.</note>
      <hi>the God of love and peace may bee with us.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I know in your Country they are more stiffe in contention about them, than with us here in <hi>England</hi>: I have therefore made bold to present this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of things of a middle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to your well-affected wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, not that I thinke you any way troubled or irresolved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, but that through your good approbation of this
<pb facs="4"/>
plaine dealing Tractate, many of your Country-men may bee drawne to the like: that so <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> giving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver these frivolous contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about things of no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may joyne strongly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ude 3.</note> and zealously contend for the faith and verity of the Gospell of Christ Jesus against all the adversaries of the same: I would to God that we could all learne that grave counsell of wise <hi>Salomon:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rov. 20.3</note>
      <hi>It is a mans ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to cease from strife, but every foole will bee medling.</hi> Accept then (I beseech you) of this (more than poore) present, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lively expression of mine unfained love and true thankefulnesse, for your kinde respect of mee in Court and Country, and at your best lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure peruse gladly the same.</p>
   <p>Having passed things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb facs="4"/>
in the forepart of my Text, in the second I proceed to matters of necessity for glory of our God, and the salvation of our soules, a trinity of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for number; righteousnesse, Peace, Joy: and whosoever is not powerfully acquainted with the same, shall never bee blessed of the thrice blessed Trinity in the Kingdome of Heaven: Seeke then (good sir) righteousnesse not riches, peace not pleasure, joy not mundane pompe and honour: that as you are honoured to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the presence of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match-able earthly King, so you may in Christ Jesus be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted at the Day of Judgement to stand with <hi>Gabriel</hi> and al the heavenly Hoast b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fore the Throne and face of the King of Kings, in glory everlasting.</p>
   <p>Thus praying your good
<pb facs="5"/>
Worship to pardon my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in this Dedication, and praying Gods best mercies to be multiplied upon you, I take my leave but never leave to love and honour you, alwayes resting,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to be commanded in the Lord, <hi>H. GREENEWOOD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>