<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE CHRI∣stian
Reader.</title>
           <author>V., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119016_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14268</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24581</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119016</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE CHRI∣stian
Reader.</title>
                 <author>V., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two treatises : the first, of the liues of the popes, and their doctrine. The second, of the masse: the one and the other collected of that, which the doctors, and ancient councels, and the sacred Scripture do teach. Also, a swarme of false miracles, wherewith Marie de la Visitacion, prioresse de la Annuntiada of Lisbon, deceiued very many: and how she was discouered, and condemned. The second edition in Spanish augmented by the author himselfe, M. Cyprian Valera, and translated into English by Iohn Golburne. 1600</title>
                 <author>Valera, Cipriano de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison (Harison), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 256, 267-398, 401-431, 422-445, 1 page, table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad it not bene for the great necessity, which our
country of Spaine hath to know the liues of the
Popes, that knowing them, it may beware them,
and nought esteeme their authority, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
all right diuine and humane, they haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped
ouer the consciences which Iesus Christ
our redeemer, with his death &amp; passion hath
freed, I should neuer (Christian Reader) haue
entred a labyrinth so confused, and rugged, as
is to write the liues of Popes. For thou must
know, that the Romists themselues concord not
nor agree in the number of the Popes. Some set downe more, and others
lesse. And hence it commeth that so little they agree, touching the time
that they poped (Let it be lawfull for me, as of a king, he is sayd to raigne
to say of a Pope to Pope) Some of these selfe same also, that all confesse to
haue bene Popes of some of them say great Laudes and praises, extolling
them to the heauens. Of these selfe same, say others filthie things, casting
them downe to hell. An example of the first S. <hi>Gregory</hi> (As saith Friar
<hi>Iohn de Pineda</hi> 3. part cap. 8. ¶1. of his Ecclesiasticall Monarchie) was the
66. Pope, &amp;c. And not the 63. As saith <hi>Mathew Palmer.</hi> Nor the 64. As saith
<hi>Panuinus.</hi> Nor the 65. As saith <hi>Marianus.</hi> nor lesse. 62. As saith S. <hi>Antoninus,</hi>
This farre <hi>Pineda.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Gelasius</hi> 1. after <hi>Platina,</hi> is the 51. Pope. After <hi>Panuinus,</hi> the 50. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<hi>George Cassander,</hi> and <hi>Carança</hi> the 49. Also <hi>Paule</hi> the second, after <hi>Platina</hi>
is the 220. <hi>Carança</hi> counteth him for the 219. <hi>Pero Mexia</hi> for 218. and <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinus:</hi>
For 215. fiue lesse then <hi>Platina.</hi> According to this account. <hi>Sistus</hi> 5.
which in the yeare 1588. tyrannizeth in the Church, should be after <hi>Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>
the 236. Pope: after <hi>Carança</hi> 235. After <hi>Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Mexia</hi> 234. and after <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinus</hi>
231. Most Popish authors be all these. Some Spaniards, and others
Italians. And had we alleaged more authors, more disagreement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety
should we haue found. Of this diuersitie springeth the disorder,
which is in the time that some Popes Poped. For they which reckon least
Popes put the yeares which they take from 4 or 5 Popes (whom they reckon
not) to other Popes. <hi>Carança</hi> in his <hi>Summa conciliorum,</hi> speaking of <hi>Boniface</hi> 3.
(this was the first Pope as in his life shalbe shewed) saith these words. There
is diuersitie among writers how long time <hi>Boniface</hi> 3. was Pope. For of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi>
is it gathered, that he was nine monthes. Others say 8 monethes and a
halfe: others a yeare, and 25 dayes: Others a yeare, 5 monthes, &amp; 28 daies.
Others say, that he died, hauing bene Pope 8 moneths and 22 dayes. This
farre <hi>Carança.</hi> The same might we say of many other Popes. For example of
the second, will we put <hi>Liberius</hi> and <hi>Formosus,</hi> besides many others that we
might set downe. <hi>Liberius</hi> and <hi>Formosus</hi> some of the papists themselues, do
cannonize, and others doe curse them. <hi>Platina</hi> saith: that <hi>Liberius</hi> was an
<pb facs="5"/>
Arian <hi>Panuinus</hi> saith: that he was holy. Read his life, which of diuerse au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
we haue gathered. As touching <hi>Formosus Stephen</hi> 6 or 7. condemned
him. So did also a Councell holden in the time of this <hi>Stephen</hi> condemne
him. But Romanus successor of <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>Theodorus.</hi> And <hi>Iohn</hi> 10 or 9 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<hi>Stephen,</hi> and iustified <hi>sn Formosus.</hi> And this did not these 3 Popes
onely, but a generall Councell of 74. Bishops, holden in the time of <hi>Iohn</hi>
10. did also the same. But all this notwithstanding, the third time, that
<hi>Sergius</hi> was Pope, he tooke part with <hi>Stepben</hi> against <hi>Formosus</hi> Condemding
that which 3 Popes, and the Councell had done, and was most cruell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the bodie of <hi>Formosus,</hi> vntombing it, and doing that vnto it, which
vpon his life, we will declare. Read their liues (Christian Reader) Dogges
shalt thou see that teare in peeces, and eate one another: Not men shalt
thou see: but diuels incarnate. Thou must also vnderstand, that in the
names of some Popes, there is great disagreement. Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the last, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi>
calleth the 24. and in order 214. <hi>Carança</hi> calleth him 24. But the 213.
in order, <hi>Pero Mexia</hi> calleth him the 24. Another way carrieth <hi>Panuinus</hi>
22. he calleth him, or 23. and saith: that he is the 209. in order. Thus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
he from out the Catalogue. Fiue Popes: two whereof be <hi>Iohns:</hi> And
it is also to be noted, that from <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. which was a wicked woman. All the
<hi>Iohns</hi> almost, haue bene pestilent fellowes Read their liues.</p>
   <p>Three causes there be, why some do number lesse Popes. The first is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
some Popes a very small time Poped. The 2. is, because many reckon
not for Popes, all those that were not cannonically elected. The 3. is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
some will not hold them for Popes, who albeit they were connoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
elected, yet in there Popedome wickedly gouerned. For the first rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
many reckon not for Pope, <hi>Stephen</hi> 2. who but three, or as some say, 4
dayes Poped. For the 2. reason exclude they all those, whom they call An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipopes,
chosen in the time of Schisme. 30: Schismes counteth <hi>Panuinus</hi> to
haue bene, wherein at one time were 4 Popes, another time 3. another 2.
Herehence is it, that they count not <hi>Iohn</hi> 18. Whom others call 17. nor <hi>Clemēt</hi>
nor <hi>Clement</hi> 8. And therefore <hi>Clement</hi> 9. they call 7. nor <hi>Benedict</hi> 5 nor <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi>
7. called they 6. nor <hi>Benedict</hi> 13. For these 2 reasons exclude they al thē
that by wicked artes, deceipt, force, gifts, or promises were made Popes.
Such doe the Councels and decrees of the Popes themselues not hold for
Popes. Read that which the Councell of Lateran holden in the time of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi>
2. ordained touching this matter. And so many hold not for pope,
<hi>Constantine</hi> 2. Who being a lay-man and without any orders, was by force
made Pope. Should this decree be obserued. neither <hi>Siluester</hi> 2. the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaūter,
nor <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. nor <hi>Gregory</hi> 7 nor an infinit nomber of Popes, which
by wicked artes, &amp;c. Were made Popes shuld be called Popes &amp; so very few
shuld remaine in the catalogue of the Popes. The 3. reason why some be not
counted Popes, is that albeit they were cannonically chosen, yet, during
their Popedome, either in life, or in Doctrin, or both in life &amp; Doctrin were
they abhominable. For this cause some count not Lando. Read his life. For
the same cause, some reckon not <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. a whore before, &amp; when she was
Pope. Were this reason ought worth, very few should be counted
for Popes. For all the Popes ingenerall from <hi>Boniface</hi> 3. vntill
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Sistus</hi> 5. who now tyrannizeth, haue either in life or Doctrine bene wicked.
And so, ought not to be connted. <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. Of whom say all, that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
like a Foxe, liued like a Lyon, and died like a Dogge. And alone was
not he, that did this: he had many companions. These be the causes, why
some reckon lesse Popes, then others. And in these names, <hi>Stephen, Iohn,
Clement, Benedict, Constantine, and Felix,</hi> shalbe found this abridgement
of Popes. There are no liues of kings nor Emperors, were they Christians,
pagans, Iewes, Turkes, Scithians; or of whatsoeuer other nation, so confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly
and diuersly written, as are the liues of the Popes. And that which is
more to be maruailed, written, imprinted, and approued by the papists
themselues. The holy Ghost it seemeth, hath purposely cast into the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of their liues, this confusion. For the Popes being kings and Lords of
Rome. And Rome as say Saint <hi>Ierom, Petrark, Laurentius Valla,</hi> and many
others) is Babilon. And Babilon, as much to say, as confusion, all whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer,
the Popes haue done, doe, and shall doe, is and shalbe confusion:
And so can no order be held in counting of them. And with what more
proper name then Babilon, or confusion, can that Church be called, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
they so pray and sing in straunge &amp; confused Language, that one vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth
not another. And that yet which is worse he, him selfe that praieth
of singeth, vnderstandeth not oft times that which is sayd. My desire is
(friendly Reader) to aduise thee of this confusion: That if thou shalt read
in one author that Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> 24. for the great villanies and heresies which
in his presence, and to his face were proued, was condemned in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
of Constance: and others say this happened to Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> 23. &amp; others,
to Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> 22. then nothing maruaile: For these 3 <hi>Iohns</hi> 22. 23. and 24. be
one selfe same Pope <hi>Iohn.</hi> Concerning the concurrences of the kings of
Spaine, which I place with the Pope, I haue followed <hi>Don Alonso de Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena</hi>
Bishoppe of Burgos in his Latine Historie of the kings of Spaine,
which he calleth Anacephalaeosis, as much to say, as a Recapitulation. No
other hath bene the purpose and motiue me mouing to write these 2. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises
of the Pope, and of the Masse. But the great desire I haue that they of
my nation, might enioy the same mercies, which the Lord in these last
times hath shewed to many nations in Europe, giuing them liberty of
conscience (&amp; this not to let loose the raynes to serue the lusts of the flesh,
but in spirit and truth to serue the liuing God, whom to serue, is to raigne)
I very much sorrow, that my nation to whom the Lord God, for the
things of this world, hath giuen so much wit, hability and vnderstanding
(which other nations cannot deny) In things pertayning to God, in the
things concerning the saluation of their soules, or going to heauen
or hell, is so blockish and blind, that it suffereth it selfe to be carried by
the Masse, that it suffereth it selfe to be gouerned, troden vnder foote &amp;
tyrannized of the Pope, of the man of sinne, of the sonne of perdition, of
Antichrist, whom as God, sitteth in the Temple of God, shewing himselfe
that he is God. And that moreouer which S. <hi>Paul</hi> 2. Thess 2. saith. All the
euill of the Spaniards cōmeth vnto them of a false perswasion which they
haue conceiued of the authority of the Pope. The Pope, they beleeue to
<pb facs="6"/>
be the successor of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> the Vicar of Christ, God vppon earth. They
beleeue, that all whatsoeuer the pope doth on earth, God doth it in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
and what soeuer he vndoeth in earth, God vndoeth in heauen. This first
Treatise, shall serue to open the deceipt vnto them: very palpably &amp; plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
will it shew the pope, not to be the successor of S. <hi>Peter.</hi> But of <hi>Iudas.</hi> Not
to be the Vicar of Christ, but of Sathan (whom the holy scripture calleth
prince and God of this world) And that we therefore ought not to obey the
pope, nor make more reckoning of him, nor of that, hee shal commaund,
then we doe of that which our mortall enemy commaunds vs. Mine harts
desire and prayer to God is, for my nation, that they may be saued: that
his Maiestie deliuer them from the power of darknesse, and transfer them
into the kingdome of his beloued sonne. I would if I might by any meanes
prouoke my nation. I would they had an holy enuie at other nations. Why
doe they (and not the Spaniards) read and heare the word of God, in their
owne Language, as in the holy Bible it is written? Why do they (&amp; not the
Spaniards) receiue the holy sacraments with the simplicity that Iesus Christ
did institute and celebrate them. Wherewith, without any humane inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
superstitions, and Idolatries, he commaunded his Church to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
them? This testimony giue I of my nation, that they haue the zeale
of God: and so shall you see few Spaniards to be Atheists, which haue no
religion. But this their zeale, is not according to knowledge: for by the word
of God is it not ruled: but by that which Antichrist of Rome commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.
Who hath taken from them, and forbidden them the reading of holy
scripture. For well knoweth Antichrist, that if the Spaniards shold read it,
then would they fall into account, and know the abhominable life of the
popes, and their wicked Doctrine: And so would forsake and detest them.
And should Spaine once forsake the pope, the pope would reckon (as they
say) with the <hi>Oleados</hi> or annointed, of whom there is no hope of life: O that
if God please, I may see this day. And if the pope should fall, then also in a
moment, would fall the Masse, and all the other Idolatries which the pope
hath inuented. This is the cause why our aduersaries so greatly fight, to
intertaine, and mainetaine the authority of the Pope. For very well they
know that the Pope once fallen, the popish religion of necessity must fall
to the earth. Very well did <hi>Pedro de la Fuente</hi> (or <hi>Fontidonio,</hi> as others call
him) a diuine of Seuill vnderstand this: who in a sermon which he made,
the last day of September in the Councel of Trent, greatly inueied against
the protestants, calling them heretiques, saying: that they sought to cast
downe the 2 pillars of the Church. To wit, the sacrifice of the Masse &amp; the
Pope, This Diuine sayd moreouer: that the Councell ought to employ all
it force, to sustaine and vphold them. The pillar (said he) of the seat papall
once pulled downe, that the whole Church would fal to the earth. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
which he gaue was, because the funerals and obsequies of the Church
went iointly, and accompanied with those of the Pope. There is nothing
(sayd he) that the aduersaries with deliberate purpose more endeuour to
doe, then to put downe the Pope, &amp;c. Our aduersaries haue fallen in the
reckoning, and this is the cause, why they maintaine and adore (and many
<pb facs="7"/>
of them doe it, against their owne conscience) The Pope, howsoeuer abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable,
wicked, and great an Atheist he be. I humbly beseech his maiesty
to send the true <hi>Sampson,</hi> which is Christ, who with one pluck, may wholy
pull downe these two pillars, and so the house of Dagon may fall vtterly
to the earth. Iudg. 16. 29. I know that were the Pope, and his Masse pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
built vpon the rock, vpon the cornerstone Christ, that neither the gates
of hell, nor whatsoeuer men could imagine, should euer preuaile against
them. But because they be not founded vppon this firme foundation: but
rather vpon humane inuentions, any small thing whatsoeuer, that carrieth
any reason, maketh them easily to stagger. The thing which wholy ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth
them, is the word of God. As by the Lordes assistaunce in these
two Treatises shalbe seene. His Maiestie I hope, whose cause we here main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
will draw some fruit out of this my trauaile. To him I commit the
charge therof. For as saith his Apostle 1. Cor. 3. 7. Neither he that plāteth is
any thing, nor he that watereth, but God, which giueth the encrease. His
cause it is, to him I commend it. That which in the meane time Christian
Reader, I beseech thee, for that which thou owest to the health of thy soule
(the which if thou loosest, what shal it profit thee to haue gained the whole
world) is that thou read, consider and weigh the reasons which we giue in
these two Treatises, for confirmation of that which we say▪ and see which
more agreeth with the word of God, with that which the ancient Doctors
and Councels, and which naturall reason, teach: that which we haue said,
or that which our aduersaries say. The holy, and true, who hath the key of
<hi>Dauid,</hi> which openeth, and no man shutteth, which shutteth, and no man
openeth; Open vnto thee the gate, that thou maiest consider and adore his
holy law. He euer bewith thee, Amen. The 25. of Iune 1588.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most affectionate brother
in the Lord.
C. V.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>