<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipful wise and learned Knight, Sir IVSTINIAN LEVVIN, T. W. wisheth euent of all FELICITIE.</title>
           <author>W., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119414_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14665</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24967</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119414</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipful wise and learned Knight, Sir IVSTINIAN LEVVIN, T. W. wisheth euent of all FELICITIE.</title>
                 <author>W., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The optick glasse of humors. Or The touchstone of a golden temperature, or the Philosophers stone to make a golden temper : wherein the foure complections sanguine, cholericke, phlegmaticke, melancholicke are succinctly painted forth, and their externall intimates laide open to the purblind eye of ignorance it selfe, by which euery one may iudge of what complection he is, and answerably learne what is most sutable to his nature. Lately pend by T.W. Master of Artes</title>
                 <author>Walkington, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke (Clerke), Martin.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 86, 2 leaves, diagrams, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipful <hi>wise and learned Knight, Sir</hi> IVSTINIAN LEVVIN, T. W. wisheth euent of all FELICITIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Riuate study wee may not vnfitly say replenisheth the vessell, wise parly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication giues the vent and easie flow, and secretariship the sale: the one loads the memorie, the other lends the smooth deliuery; the last perfects the judgement and wins chiefest glory; so that studious dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence without writing and conference
<pb facs="3"/>
is the dull picture of <hi>Harpocrates</hi> the God of silence, who is fained to weare a Wolues skin, full of eares and eyes, but sealing vp his lips with his forefin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as mute as a marble <hi>Niobe:</hi> and so writing without both, is the picture of jangling <hi>Thersites,</hi> whose words (as the Poet saith) were without measure and wit without weight, as lauish in tongue as <hi>Battus.</hi> The Hieroglyphicke of a true Scholer is the Hare, that sleepes<note place="margin">Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rius.</note> waking with her eyes open, and wakes sleeping with her eyes shut; that is who seemes to meditate when he is in action, and to practise when hee is in meditatiō: or as other Emblemists haue limd forth a right student, euer to haue one eye shutte and an other open, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in his right hand <hi>Phospohr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> with his motto in one word—<hi>vigilo,</hi> and <hi>Hes perus</hi> in the other hand with this word—<hi>Dormio;</hi> to intimate that he should deuide the day &amp; night for practise and speculation, to equalize the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes of
<pb facs="3"/>
both at his fitter oportunity; neither to act <hi>Democritus</hi> (who so might worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue laught at his owne folly) that puld out his owne eyes to become a continuall contemplatour; nor to bee like <hi>Nicias,</hi> who as <hi>AElian</hi> records, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got<note place="margin">AElianus lib. 3. cap. 31.</note> his meate by being too intent on his painting; as swift torrents oft runne themselues drie by too much motion, so standing pooles do putrifie by no mo tion. There is a faire tract betweene <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis</hi> for wisedom to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in; a happy orbe betwixt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> for <hi>Phaeton</hi> to guide his choach in, so betweene all action and altogether contemplation for a student to conuerse in. For conferring I do passe it ouer, as that whereto I seldome haue beene beholden, yet much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting it, and knowing that it brings a great accrument vnto wisedome and learning: as concerning my study and reading it hath bin but meane I must needs confesse, and my writing very
<pb facs="4"/>
penurious in regard of theirs, whoe haue inriched whole reames of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with the Indian mine, and golden chaffai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of their inuention: yet for that module of these habiliments i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> me I haue euer bent my judgement so far as in it lay to limit al these vnto their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar times, obiects, &amp; places, &amp; haue tenderd my endeauour to haue especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially two, the one correspondent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other, neither to act <hi>Democritus</hi> nor <hi>Nicias,</hi> but by intercourse to mixe my sweeter meditation, with bitter, yet profitable and better action. And as in other things of greater or lesse mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, so in this also the abortiue issue of my wit begot of that aboundance of loue I owe vnto your good self, whose manifold kindnesses, if I should bury in obliuion, I might worthily seeme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, if remembring I should not in some sort requite, I might seeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and respectlesse, both of mine owne good name, and your better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert,
<pb facs="4"/>
the latter whereof is much, yet the first much more, a delicious fruite that growes from the tree of gratitude. The <hi>Eleans,</hi> therefore sayth <hi>Pausanias</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pausanias in Eliria.</note> did paint forth the three <hi>Graces,</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing these three things in their hand—<hi>Rosam, Myrrhum, Talum:</hi> to intimate that from thankfulnesse proceed three fruites. First the sweetnesse of a good name, shadowed out by the sweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smelling Rose: 2. the profit redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from it insinnuated by the <hi>Mirhe</hi> branch, and lastly chiefe comfort and hilarity vnclowded by the coccal bone which especially is competent to yong age, which three comprise all <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> three goods. Howsoeuer I may seeme to aime at the first, as may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd by precedent speach, alway high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prizing a good name as of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ointment, vapring forth a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant smell and dilicious odure in all mens nostrils; and at the last as desirous of mine own delight some contentmēt
<pb facs="5"/>
and comfort issuing from my thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, yet for the other more, agreeing to Sycophants &amp; crum-catching parasites, it moues not once within the Zodiacke of my expectation, I onely satis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ying my selfe with the former. Nether did I in the waine of my iudgment attempt this as desirous to drawe in the per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uming breath of vaine glory, to puff vp my self with self cōceit like the <hi>Camaeleō</hi> which is—<hi>nil praeter pulmones,</hi> nothing but lungs: but only thinking to break the ice, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely to wade farther, and to imploy my selfe in greater taskes, as fitter opor tunity shall obiect her selfe vnto me, if the prefinit tear me and limit of my life permit, and withall in lue of gratitude, to presēt your self▪ with this little which seems much in regard of my wants, and labour, as much seems little in respect of of your euer kind fauour. For this as also your other endowments, my penne might worthily fill whole pages: but your splendent vertues can easily b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
<pb facs="5"/>
their owne Herauldes to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mme forth their owne armory, and to extoll in presence, is more glauering and poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, then true-louing and patheticall. This onely my affection cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale, your gratious demeanour, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cariage, curtuous nature, studious endeauour, and wisedome for mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging your selfe each where, (when you happely were a flourishing braunche, engrafted in the fruitfull Oliue tree of this our <hi>Athenes,</hi> that thrise famous v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersity of <hi>Cambridge</hi>) were first the sympathizing adamants of my affection: your continuance after in all studious actions, constancy in your fauours and kind disposition (for I must needs say as hee of <hi>Augustus—Rarus tu quidem</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sextus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor▪</note>
      <hi>ad recipiendas amicitias, ad retinendas vero constantissimus</hi>) these incited mee to cause that which as a sparke lay shrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in embers in my breast, to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit it selfe more apparantly in this little flame.
<pb facs="6"/>
Take this my endeauour I pray you in worth, cheerish and foster this defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med brood of my braine, in the lap (if I may so tearme it) of your good li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> king, and in loue esteeme it faire thogh badly penzeld ouer, to wish as <hi>Daphnis</hi> said to <hi>Dam.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>—<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </q>
   <q>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> minime sunt pulchra, en pulchra videntur amāt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</q>
   <note place="margin">Theocrit. Eidyll. 6.</note>
   <p>If the happie <hi>Daemon</hi> of <hi>Vlisses</hi> direct not the wandering planet of my witte within the decent orbe of wisedome, my stammering pen seeming far ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon with superfluitie of phrase, yet wanting matter I answer with the poet one only word inuerted:</p>
   <q>Qui non est hodie, cras magis aptus erit.</q>
   <p>He that is <hi>Homers Irus</hi> for facultie to day, may bee a rich <hi>Craesus</hi> for iuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to morrow, as it is with cogitations
<pb facs="6"/>
so with actions, the second relish more of wisedome: perfection requires tract of time; <hi>Romes</hi> Capitoll was not built the first day; nor was <hi>Zeuxis</hi> his <hi>Helena</hi> sudddenly lim'd forth with one pencill. Looke not on these rapsodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed lines, I pray you with a pittying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie: I had rather far bee enuied then pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied.</p>
   <q>—<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.<note place="margin">Pindar. Pyth. od. 1.</note>
   </q>
   <q>Melior est inuidentia commiseratione</q>
   <p>better by much is a case hatefull then wofull. Now will I humbly take my leaue committing you to the tuition of that heauenly Tutour, whose pupils we are all: from my study in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> X. Calend. <hi>March.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Euer most deuoted vnto you in all faithfulnesse.
T. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>