<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The true Copie of a Letter Certifi∣catorie, written in commendation of Captaine King of Ratcliffe, M. VVilliam Bardwell and Alexander Child of Red∣riffe, Masters of three Shipps of London, for their memorable seruice against the Swethens, being thereto compelled in Summer last, 1608.</title>
           <author>Chodkiewicke, Iohannes Carolus</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119996_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08260</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119996</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The true Copie of a Letter Certifi∣catorie, written in commendation of Captaine King of Ratcliffe, M. VVilliam Bardwell and Alexander Child of Red∣riffe, Masters of three Shipps of London, for their memorable seruice against the Swethens, being thereto compelled in Summer last, 1608.</title>
                 <author>Chodkiewicke, Iohannes Carolus</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvarres of Svvethland : With the ground and originall of the said vvarres, begun and continued betwixt Sigismond King of Poland, and Duke Charles his vnkle, lately crowned King of Swethland. As also the state and condition of that kingdome, as it standeth to this day</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The true Copie of a Letter Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorie, written in commendation of Captaine <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Ratcliffe,</hi> M. <hi>VVilliam Bardwell</hi> and <hi>Alexander Child</hi> of <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe,</hi> Masters of three Shipps of <hi>London,</hi> for their memorable seruice against the <hi>Swethens,</hi> being thereto compelled in Summer last, 1608.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohannes Carolus Chod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiewich</hi> Earle of <hi>Seckloro Bychor,</hi> and of <hi>Misra,</hi> Captaine of <hi>Samogitia</hi> and <hi>Porpatie,</hi> Generall Commissioner of <hi>Lyffeland,</hi> and chiefe Generall of the Army of the great Dukedome of <hi>Lytawe.</hi> To all and singular, to whome it may appertaine, or that shall reade these Presents, I doe let to weet, that whereas <hi>VVilliam Bardwell, VVilliam King,</hi> and <hi>Alexander Childe</hi> English Gentlemen, came
<pb facs="5"/>
with three Shippes at <hi>Riga,</hi> when the Earle of <hi>Mansfielde</hi> Generall of the Army of Duke <hi>Charles Suderman,</hi> periniuriously breaking the Truce, made warre in <hi>Lyffeland,</hi> I helde them there, and employed them in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Warre for the most excellent King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> my most gratious Lord, and they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to defend the Dunn, wherein they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themselues very faithfully, manfully and valiantly, so that the said Earle of Mansfield was often by them driuen backe againe to his great losse and shame, and likewise hee was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten assaulted by them, so that hee lost not onely his strength of men and his courage, but also lost some Shippes with many men and goods, which the saide Englishmen with a memorable courage, and to the notable glory of the English Nation, did set on fire and burne. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue thought good to grant vnto them this Testimoniall, to the end that they may haue great thanks for their deserts, purchased by their good renowne and name▪ and that others may see, that as fame &amp; immortality belongeth chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to noble minds, so also it is gotten by vertuous and valiant deedes: </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Written in the Campe at <pb facs="5"/> the new Mill in <hi>Lyffeland</hi>
         <date>the seauenteenth of Nouember, <hi>Anno Domini 1608.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>And is subscribed by <hi>Iohannes Carolus Chod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiewicke, manu propria,</hi> and sealed with a Seale in Redde waxe, Printed thereupon, <hi>Ita testatur</hi> Carolus Demetrius, <hi>Notarius Publicus.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>