<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To my verie good Fa∣ther Master Luke Clapham con∣tentment of minde in this life, and continuance of ioy in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Clapham, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119209_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09793</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20059</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119209</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To my verie good Fa∣ther Master Luke Clapham con∣tentment of minde in this life, and continuance of ioy in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Clapham, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A philosophicall treatise concerning the quietnes of the mind. Taken out of the morall workes written in Greeke, by the most famous philosopher, &amp; historiographer, Plutarch of Cherronea, counsellor to Traian the emperour. And translated out of Greeke into French by Iames Amyor Bishop of Auxerre, and great almoner to the most Christian King of Fraunce Charles the ninth. And now turned out of French into English by Iohn Clapham</title>
                 <author>Plutarch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To my verie good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Master Luke Clapham con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of minde in this life, and continuance of ioy in the life to come.</head>
   <p>SIR, after I had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophicall Treatise, (which was my chiefe woorke these long Winter nightes:) I purposed to send the written copy vnto you, not minding then to publish it. Howbeit being since perswaded that it might be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to others (considering the necessitie of the argument) I haue now made that common to al which
<pb facs="4"/>
at the first was intended onely to you, wherein whatsoeuer my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, I can hardlie excuse my selfe of rashnes in publishing it to the view and censure of the learned, &amp; skilfull in the French tongue (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of my selfe haue but a tast) who will easilie perceiue my wants, &amp; errors in the translatiō. And yet seeing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes that endeuor supplieth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of sufficiencie, and a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning counteruaileth a bad perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: J haue at all aduentures (as you see) stripped this morall treatise out of a rich French attire into a poore English weed, (I would be loth that some French man should take it as an iniurie) thrusting it out to
<pb facs="4"/>
the eie of the world vnder your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, being the first fruites of my labour in this kind, not doubting of your fauourable acceptance thereof, as proceeding from him, that in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and dutie is most bownd vnto you, and to whom he oweth himselfe and all that hee hath.</p>
   <p>If the paines I haue taken herein may either please or profit the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I shall bee glad: if both, I require no more. Jf neither, yet for the first time, <hi>Sit voluisse satis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And thus in my hartie praiers I commend you with my good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, whom J beseech to send yee manie happie yeares to your ioy
<pb facs="5"/>
and contentment in this world, and euerlasting peace to your endlesse comfort in his Kingdome. From the Court at Richmond, the <hi>2.</hi> of Ianuarie. <hi>1589.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent sonne. Iohn Clapham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>