<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The true Copie of my Letter in answere hereof.</title>
           <author>U., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119623_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24508.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The true Copie of my Letter in answere hereof.</title>
                 <author>U., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe vievve of the weake grounds of popery : as it was propounded to D. Norrice, priest, by T.V. gent: and returned without answere</title>
                 <author>Udall, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Cooke, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Macham, Samuel 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 101, 9 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <head>The true Copie of my Letter in answere hereof.</head>
   <p>TO accuse without proofe, to say and shewe no reason (of all which, you in your Letter may iustly be taxed) might truely argue mee to want both substance, order, learning and trueth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your owne phrase. And, to free your selfe from the same imputation, haue you yeelded any other reason against my booke (which you intitie a vaine bundle of words) than a boasting bundle of vaine brags? <hi>Turpe est doctori, &amp;c.</hi> But you would seem to giue a reason why your bare censure (as you rightly haue censured your selfe) should be a sufficient answere to my booke; vnlesse I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure two or three of the best learned of our side, to
<pb facs="11"/> auow it vnder their hands to be the doctrine of our Church: Else you knowe (or else you are a false prophet) they will all disclaime from it, hauing seen the errors and weakenesse thereof. But lest I seeme to taxe you with want of learning and truth, with bare words onely, without proofe; as you in the height and eminency of your iudgement haue cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured me: Can there be greater shew of ignorance, thā to require that to be auowed to be the doctrine of our Church, which hath beene already by the learned of our side published to the whole world in many of their seueral books daily extāt to be seen? And, that I cōmit not your fault, To speake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proofe: do you but instance any one point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in all my booke; and if I doe not shew where the same is iustified by the learned of our side; I will willingly acknowledge that error wherewith I haue here charged your selfe. And to make it yet more euident: if I should require you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the doctrine you should deliuer by two or three of your best Diuines; when the same had been published already by <hi>Bellarmine, Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Valencia,</hi> your <hi>Rhemists</hi> and others: could any thing conuince me of grosser ignorance? It seemes (notwithstanding your vaine brag, That that you would prooue <hi>15.</hi> particularities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you haue charged me and my booke) that you are but meanely read in controuersies: otherwise
<pb facs="11"/> you could not be ignorant, that there is no doctrine in my booke that is not auowed &amp; published, either by <hi>Iewel</hi> against <hi>Harding,</hi> or the B. of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester</hi> that now is, or by D. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> D. <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker,</hi> D. <hi>Fulke,</hi> D. <hi>Sparke,</hi> with many others. And albeit I could not haue cōfirmed thus much by these cleere testimonies: yet if you had Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly and charitably weighed with what mind my request was made in my Preface to my Kinsmen (wherin I had intreated in these very words, That if I had not truely layd downe the Grounds of your Religion for the substance; or, if they had been mistaken by mee; or, vsing that breuity I had done, they might more strongly haue been vrged; or, if the reasons I had vrged, had been falsly allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; or not truely handled &amp;c. That I would haue taken it as a speciall grace done vnto me, &amp;c. to haue had the faults thereof manifested &amp; shewed, that I might haue been drawen to haue been of the same profession with them, &amp;c.) you would neuer haue insisted vpon such a subscription of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest schollers of our Sect, thereby to haue cauilled and shifted off the answere of my booke; how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned soeuer it had been, either for the methode, or matter. But you imagined, your wordes were so powerfull; that it was sufficient for your follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that you had onely giuen your censure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out shewing any further reason. Besides (my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
<pb facs="12"/> being so charitable &amp; reasonable) it seemes you haue small care of winning of soules: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise I perswade my selfe (if you had been assured of your owne sufficiencie to haue answered the booke) you would neuer haue insisted vpon so fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous a request: Nor haue preferred the vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory of hauing a learned aduersary, before the hope you might (not without good probabilitie) haue conceiued in reducing many by my conuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (or rather indeede peruersion) to haue been of your profession. I professe, for my part, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see any other ground of your Letter directed to me, than to inlarge your own ostentation and glory to your followers. For, to vndertake that you would prooue this, and this, and not to haue returned the booke, whereunto you required the subscription; what can be inferred thereof, but that you would winne time to delay and shift off the answere? But if you will proceede according to my request in the Preface of my booke, &amp; proue as much as by your Letter you haue presumed, without seeking some new shift to delay the time further: I will engage my selfe, that the same shall bee replied to, by one euery way equall to your selfe in all knowledge and literature: who (notwithstanding the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage you promise to your selfe, of the absurdities committed by me) shall defend the cause I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and subscribe the same defence with his
<pb facs="12"/> owne hand: Otherwise, you shall gaine thus much by your trauell, that I wil willingly submit my selfe to be a member of your Church. If you refuse these reasonable conditions, I must vse your owne olde phrase, and tell you, that I must needs thinke your cause so weake, that it cannot bee maintained. I omit to charge you with inciuility, in giuing me the Lie: For that I cannot but pitie your ignorance that cannot, as it seemes (though all were false I had sayd, speaking by relation) distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a lie and vntrueth. And whereas you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre me, in the conclusion of your Letter, to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin de Pont. &amp; de Concilijs,</hi> where you say, I shall find most of my obiections of the errors of Popes and Councels refuted: So can I whensoeuer you shall instance any such particular refutation (which may ease you of some paines, if it be so suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently performed) referre you to some of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of our side, where the same reasons haue been with no lesse sufficiencie handled and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to: assuring my selfe; That neither any of you haue, or can, make any obiections against the doctrine, we professe, that hath not beene alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obiected, and likewise by vs answered. And if any will shew me the contrary, I will be beholding to him, neither will I shut mine eyes against the trueth. If this which I haue sayd may any whit preuaile with you to make shew of that great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="13"/> whereof in your Letter you haue boasted, by your liberall vndertaking to proue so many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars (which hitherto as great Clerkes, as your selfe haue failed in) I shall be ready and willing to performe whatsoeuer I haue herein promised. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise I pray you returne the booke, as you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it; and you shall see, that some such course shal be taken, as shal make you blush to haue censured so rashly.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your friend, in Christianity and Charitie,</hi> T. Ʋ.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>