<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119967_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15431</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119967</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tetrastylon papisticum, that is, The foure principal pillers of papistrie : the first conteyning their raylings, slanders, forgeries, vntruthes: the second their blasphemies, flat contradictions to scripture, heresies, absurdities: the third their loose arguments, weake solutions, subtill distinctions: the fourth and last the repugnant opinions of new papistes with the old; of the new one with an other; of the same writers with themselues: yea of popish religion with and in it selfe. Compiled as a necessarie supplement or fit appertinance to the authors former worke, intituled Synopsis papismi: to the glorie of God for the dissuading of light-minded men from trusting to the sandie foundation of poperie, and to exhort good Christians stedfastlie to hold the rockie foundation of faith in the Gospell</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 170, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>❧ The preface to the <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the common and vsuall practise of wrangling and cauilling spirites, who to preuent other mens accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doe themselues first begin to accuse and challenge others of the same crimes, which they are guiltie of: Thus Sathan the accuser of the brethren, sometime dealt with <hi>Iob,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 1</note> saying vnto God, that if he would but stretch foorth his hand a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and touch all he had, hee would not spare to blaspheme God to his face, whereas nothing is more common with that old Serpent, then to curse and blaspheme God. Thus our aduersaries of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish religion (which indeed is no religion, but meere superstition) haue subtillie sought to vndermine vs, crying out against vs, that wee are lyers, Idolaters, blasphemers, and such like, which are titles and epithetes fitter and more proper to themselues. They charge vs with rayling: <hi>Harding Confut. apolog. cap.</hi> 16. <hi>diuis.</hi> 2. with lying: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fens. apolog. pag.</hi> 597. with corrupting and altering of scripture: <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist.</hi> 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. <hi>sect.</hi> 8. with fables. <hi>Rhemist.</hi> 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 1. <hi>sect.</hi> 4. with execrations and blasphemies: <hi>Iud.</hi> 3. with heresies, <hi>Bellarm. de notis eccles. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. They obiect against vs the weaknes of our proofes, and arguments: <hi>Harding. defeus. apolog. p.</hi> 625. often innouating and changing of Religion. <hi>Rhemist.</hi> 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 8. Diuisions &amp; dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions among ourselues: <hi>Harding. defens. apolog. p.</hi> 239. Yea that wee may see how true their other accusations are, they are not ashamed to charge vs with Idolatrie, and worshipping of Idols, <hi>Rhemist.</hi> 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10. <hi>sect.</hi> 9. Wherfore that it may appeare to the world, how vniustly they haue accused vs, &amp; how subtilly they would vnburden &amp; exonerate thēselues of those crimes which are theirs &amp; not ours,
<pb facs="7"/>
to this ende I haue vndertaken this labour in this treatise, to detect and bewray their guiltines in this behalfe, that we may bee purged from their slaunders, and our cause iustified, and that the shame &amp; blame may fall vpon them, that haue deserued it.</p>
   <p>As for vs, wee raile not, neither vse reuiling speech, yet some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time we tell them roundly their owne, and this may bee done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rayling: vnlesse they will say Christ rayled, when he tolde the Iewes, that they had made his fathers house a denne of theeues. But their rayling, and venemous dartes, which they shoot at vs, are notoriouslie knowen and cannot be hide. It is the grace of popish writers both old and new, to stuffe their bookes full with cursing &amp; rayling: <hi>Stapleton,</hi> that blacke-mouthed Sophister of <hi>Louaine,</hi> hath of late set foorth a booke against <hi>D. Whitakers,</hi> wherein beside the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his cause, he hath disgraced his profession, with bitter and filthie tearmes, calling that learned and godly man, <hi>Rusticum, fatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, asinum, asininum professorem, morionem, stolidum:</hi> Foole, clowne, asse, doit: yea he is so impudent, that he spareth not to reuile the deade,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. sect. 8.</note> most shamefully calling <hi>Caluine,</hi> that worthie Minister of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Egregium Nebulonem,</hi> a notable knaue: I thinke <hi>Stapletons</hi> owne friendes and patrones here in England, will blush and be ashamed of him, when they find such stuffe in his booke.</p>
   <p>Neither doth <hi>Stapleton</hi> thus take on in his moode, as carried away with some intemperate heate, but being in his wittes (if in his right wittes) and well aduised, and of purpose he falleth into this cogging vaine: giuing <hi>M. Whitakers</hi> warning thereof aforehande, <hi>age Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t ad patientiam te compone:</hi> willing him to take patiently, what<note place="margin">Admonit. ad Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> he saith. Indeed <hi>M. Stapleton</hi> your counsell is good, for shoote out your venemous dartes as long, as yee will, wee care not, wee haue a sense for them, and a buckler to latch thē, as <hi>Augustine</hi> saith verie well: <hi>Quaeso mi frater, quasi has diaboli sagittas, ad petram, quae est</hi>
      <note place="margin">De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. docum, c. 12.</note>
      <hi>Christus, allidens, sume scutum fidei.</hi> I giue thee counsel (my brother) to rebound these arrowes of Sathan, vpon the rocke, which is Christ, taking the shield of faith: And such patience is in this case neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie for <hi>M. Whitakers,</hi> and the rest of vs protestantes, as the same fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther speaketh of else where: <hi>Quemadmodum parentes a filis vel pueris,</hi>
      <note place="margin">De ser in monto ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>vel phreneticis multa patiuntur, donec infantia, vel aegritude transeat, ita</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Christianus ab impijs tanquam phreneticis multa pati debet:</hi> Like as parents<note place="margin">De ser in monto. cap. 34.</note> do suffer manie things at their sons hands, while they are children or phrentick, til their childishnes or phrensie be past: thus Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans must patiently beare manie things of the wicked, as of men ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with phrensie. Such intemperate and railing speeches then of Papistes, we attribute either to their childish ignorance or phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike malitiousnes.</p>
   <p>Concerning the other accusations, of heresie, blasphemie, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, corruption of scriptures and such other, it shal appeare, I trust, in this discourse, that they are the men, &amp; none other, that are faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie herein. As for fables, they do vs great wrong to cast them vpon vs: their owne legend of lies and infinite fabulous stories, do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie tell vs, that poperie is fuller of fables, then the heresies of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinians</hi> or the <hi>Manichees.</hi> Their other charge concerning iunoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dissention is returned vpon themselues: for who knoweth not, that the Iesuites of these daies, haue innouated and changed in the most pointes, the old popish profession, and haue cast it into a newe mould, and brought in a new forme of Pope catholike do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: But we in substance retaine the same Religion, which at the first reuiuing of the Gospel was maintained 40. yeares ago by the Protestants. As for dissensions in fundamental pointes and articles concerning faith, we haue none. In other matters, there haue bene some contentions among vs, more we graunt then needed, &amp; more hotely pursued of some then was requisite: yet they are neither in weight so great, or in number so many, nor so egerly prosecuted, as dissentions among papistes haue beene, for <hi>anno.</hi> 1509. wee reade that the <hi>Franciscane</hi> friers pursued the poore <hi>Dominicks</hi> to death: and the contention began about the conception of the Virgin Marie. <hi>Fox. pag.</hi> 802. Such rigour and fiercenes hath not yet beene seene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong protestantes, neither I trust, shall.</p>
   <p>But in saying that Protestants are Idolaters, they make too lewd a lie, for it is wel knowen vnto thē, that we haue no Images or Idols of brasse, woode, stone, siluer, at all in our Churches, as they haue nor any pictures, carued, painted or grauen, set vp to bee worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: If two men shoulde bee set before vs: the one lifteth vp his, eyes to heauen, and calleth vppon the name of God, hauing no
<pb facs="8"/>
similitude or resemblance before him, the other praieth before a stocke or stone Image: is anie man so senseles, as to say the other is an Idolater, rather then this? But thus blinde and sottish are the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes in their iudgement. Take heede ye English pope catholickes, doe ye not see, how your ghostly fathers goe about to make fooles of you?</p>
   <p>Now then, to the intent our aduersaries slaunderous mouthes should be stopped, and their falsehoode descried, I haue giuen a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall taste in this worke, in euerie kinde of their fraudulent dealing with vs, and of their vnseemely behauiour, &amp; vngodlie shifts, which they vse in oppugning of the trueth, and defense of their bad cause. The whole booke I haue deuided into 4. partes, shewing the foure principall pillers of papistrie, and euerie piller conteineth diuerse partes beside, as it is set foorth in the title of this booke: I trust, throughout this treatise, that our aduersaries shall not iustly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge me for dealing vntruely or deceiptfullie with them, seeing I haue set downe their sayings and opinions, as I find them, quoting the places, and citing the authors, whence I haue them: so that I doubt not to say with Augustine, <hi>Ego omnia, quòd bona fide coram deo dixerim, sine vllo studio contentionis, sine aliqua dubitatione veritatis, sine ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo praeiudicio diligentioris tractatus exposui:</hi> I trust I may say, with a good<note place="margin">Lib. 2. de genes cap. 29.</note> conscience before God, that I haue set downe all things without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of contention, or doubting of the trueth, and without preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing other mens more exact labours herein. If sometime I shall seeme to speake somewhat roundlie or sharply, I hope the discreete reader will iudge it to bee done, not without cause, &amp; to say, as that good father in the like case: <hi>Noui fratrem meum, si quid in disputatione</hi>
      <note place="margin">August. epist. 14▪</note>
      <hi>pro side sua dixit feruētius, non illa contumacia, sed fiducia dicenda est:</hi> I know if our brother bee sometime seruent and hote, in the defence of saith, that it proceedeth not of contumacie, but his full resolution in the trueth.</p>
   <p>Concerning our aduersaries, I would haue them thinke, that I haue vndertaken these labours for their good, if they could so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue it, that seeing now the nakednes of their cause, they may at the length be better aduised: We haue not cast off all loue and care of our enemies: We say of them, as Augustine did sometime of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius the heretike, <hi>Nos non solum diligimus, sed dileximus eos, sed aliter</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aepist. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>6.</note>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>vunc diligimus, aliter aliquando dileximus, tunc, quia nobis rectae fidei videban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nunc vt ab errore liberentur:</hi> Wee both loue them now, and loued them before, but otherwise now then before, then we loued them, because we thought they were of a right faith, but now we loue thē, to the end they might bee deliuered from errour. Now vnto my brethren of the same faith and religion, thus much I say, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer blasphemies, heresies, absurdities, they reade here to bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and maintained by papistes, they would take no offence thereby, nor seeme to stumble thereat: <hi>Sed facite inde quod fecit domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. tract▪ in Ioh. 6.</note>
      <hi>cum illi obtulerunt amarum potum, gustauit, &amp; respuit, sic vos audite &amp; abijcite:</hi> But doe ye as Christ did, when they offered him vineger to drinke, he tasted and refused it, so giue you the hearing and reading of these things, but in iudgement cast them away, and reiect them.</p>
   <p>Thus I haue, by the Lords assistance finished my taske, &amp; ended my trauell for this time: I will now sit me downe a while and rest my wearie penne, and giue place to others. This I haue done, partly to discharge my duetie to God, and debt to his Church; partly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke others by this example to put foorth their talent: who for skill are more able, for their leasure more fit, for outwarde helpes haue better incouragement, &amp; in respect of their reward are more bound: I would we might now at the length spare our selues at home, and forbeare to prouoke one another by writing, and ioyne our strength against the common aduersarie. If our wittes want whetting, our pennes exercise, our bodies labour, our aduersaries abroad can and may afford vs worke enough: we need not hew one at another. Let vs do as Moses did, slay the Aegyptian, it is not seemely for one He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew to striue with another. The timber, that must make the house, should be prepared and hewen in the fielde, Prouerb. 24. 27. when it commeth to be set together, not so much as the noise of an ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer should be heard, as we read of Salomons temple: so we should labour to hew and cut off popish superstition &amp; corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as in the field abroad, but we ought to build peaceably, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noyse among our selues. One saith well, <hi>Omnia alia bona, aurum, argentum, diuitiae diuidi possunt; non potest diuidi (pacem meam do vobis:)</hi> Al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods, gold, siluer, riches, may be deuided; this inheritāce onely cannot be deuided, my peace I leaue with you. And therefore, saith he, <hi>Christus noluit fiers iudex ad diuisionem:</hi> Christ refused to be a iudge
<pb facs="9"/>
or deuider of the inheritance. God grant, that we may at the length, learne, as carefull children, or faithfull stewardes, to keepe whole Christes inheritance lent vnto vs, that rich patrimonie of brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue and peace: that we may one yeeld to another in the trueth, euerie one to studi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to amend what is amisse, and all ioyne together to seeke Gods glorie.</p>
   <p>Thus shall we be sure to imbrace and enioy peace: for what else is the cause of contention among vs: <hi>Nisi</hi> (as one saith) <hi>quia displicet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus angelica illa partitio, qua gloria deo, pax hominibus nuntiatur: quonam</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bernard. epist. 127.</note>
      <hi>modo stabit pax hominum coram deo, si deo apud homines non potest tuta esse sua gloria?</hi> Because mortall men like not that Angelical partition, whē they pronounced glorie vnto God, and peace in earth: for howe can the peace of men stand in force before God, when Gods glory is not kept safe and sound amongst men? This then is the way to procure peace, and to nourish it, to remoue and auoid dissention, euery one in his seuerall place and calling to labour to amend what is amisse, to restore what is decayed, to supplie what is wanting, and to redresse what is out of order, and so to seeke chiefly to aduance Gods glorie. Thus shall we haue peace at home, &amp; peace abroad, our dissensions shall slacke within, and by our peace our strength and courage shall increase against our enemies without. We shal runne vpon them, as one man: ten shall chase an hundred, and an hundred a thousand. Thus the Gospell by Gods grace shall still florish in this land, super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition shall decrease and weare away, and poperie shall bee weeded and rooted out, which God grant for his welbeloued and onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonnes sake Iesus Christ our Lord, to whom bee praise for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>