<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An Iniunction geuen by the kyng our soueraigne Lord his most excellent maiesty to all scholemasters and teachers of youthe, within all his Graces realme and dominions, for auctorising and establyshyng the vse of thys Cathe∣chisme.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119226_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18174</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4812</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119226</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An Iniunction geuen by the kyng our soueraigne Lord his most excellent maiesty to all scholemasters and teachers of youthe, within all his Graces realme and dominions, for auctorising and establyshyng the vse of thys Cathe∣chisme.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short catechisme, or playne instruction, conteynynge the su [m] me of Christian learninge : sett fourth by the kings maiesties authoritie, for all scholemaisters to teache. To thys catechisme are adioyned the Articles agreed vpon by the bishoppes [and] other learned and godly men, in the last conuocatio [n] at London, in the yeare of our Lorde, M.D.LII. for to roote out the discord of of [sic] opinions, and stablish the agreme [n] t of trew religion: Likewyse published by the Kinges maiesties authoritie. 1553</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, lxxxviii leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="royal_injunction">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ An Iniunction geuen by the kyng our soueraigne Lord his most excellent maiesty to all scholemasters and teachers of youthe, within all his Graces realme and dominions, for auctorising and establyshyng the vse of thys Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Dwarde the Sixte, by the grace of God king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Fraūce and Irelād: defēdoure of the faith: and of the church of Englande and also of Ireland in earthe the Supreme head: to all Scholemasters and teachers of youthe.</p>
   <p>¶ When there was presented vnto vs, to be perused, a short and playne order of Catechisme writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a certayne godlye and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="3"/>
man: we committed the deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, and diligente examination therof, to certain Byshoppes, and other learned men, whose iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we haue in greate estimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And because it semed agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the scriptures, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunces of oure Realme, we thought it good, not onely, for that agreement to put it forthe abrode to Print: but also, for the plainesse and shortnes, to appoint it out for al Scholemasters to teach. That the yet vnskilfull and yong age, hauynge the foundations layed, both of religion and good letters, mai learn godlines together with wysdome: and haue a rule for the rest of theyr lyfe, what iudgement they ought to haue of god: to whō all oure lyfe is applyed: and howe they maye please God, wherin we oughte, wyth all the doynges and
<pb facs="3"/>
dutyes of oure lyfe, to trauayle.</p>
   <p>¶ We wyll therfore and cōmaūd, both all and eche of you, as ye ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der oure fauoure, and as ye mind to auoyde the iust punishmente of transgressing our aucthoriti, that ye truely and diligently teach this Catechisme in your schooles, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after the other brief Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techisme whych we haue alreadye setforth: that yonge age, yet ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and wauerynge, beyng by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of good lessōs and instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of true religion stablyshed, maye haue a greate furtherance to the ryght worshipping of God: &amp; good helpes to lyue in alpointes accordinge to duety. Wherewyth beinge furnyshed, by better vsing dewe godlynes towarde God the author of all thynges: obedyence towarde their Kynge, the sheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde of the people: Louynge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb facs="4"/>
to the common weale, the generall mother of all: they maye seeme not borne for theym selues: but bee profytable and dewtyfull, toward God, theyr Kynge, and theyr coūtrey.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>¶ Geuen at Grenewyche <date>the. xx. of May the. vii. yere of oure Reigne.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>