<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119892_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15091</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25390</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119892</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Way to the trve Church against A.D. his reply : Wherein the motives leading to papistry, and qvestions, touching the rule of faith, the avthoritie of the Church, the svccession of the truth, and the beginning of Romish innouations: are handled and fully disputed. By Iohn White Doctor of Diuinity, sometime of Gunwell and Caius Coll. in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>White, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Barrett, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 320, 325-528, 527-557, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now fiue yeares since I published a booke called <hi>THE WAY TO THE TRVE CHVRCH,</hi> wherein my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose was nothing else but onely to shew the weakenesse and insuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of those Motiues which leade so many to Papistrie, and to bring to triall such reasons as the Iesuites and Seminaries ground themselues vpon, in perswading their people against vs: making it more then plaine that the corruptions of the Church of Rome are maintained, and the communion of our Church in the doctrine, preaching, and the Sacraments thereof, is refused, by such as follow the Papacy, vpon weake and false grounds that cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. This poore booke, it seemes, hath not a little incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed my Aduersary, and discontented many that yet should follow reason and the truth of things, and not be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with rumor and common impression. For man being a noble creature, endued with reason, and faculty to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, and hauing a rule left him of God, whereby to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine things, should not tie his faith and conscience to the authority, or person of any, more then the truth and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and euidence of that be saies will beare him out. It was neuer heard of in the world, till now of late yeares, that the Pope and his definitions were the rule of faith, or that men were bound to follow whatsoeuer he should appoint; but the
<pb facs="13"/> Church of God, euery where, till tyranny oppressed it, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined his doctrine, accepting and allowing that which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with the sacred Scriptures, and the first antiquity, and reiecting the rest; and albeit many errors had long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription, yet the godly still held them to that rule of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: <hi>BVT FROM THE BEGINNING IT WAS NOT SO.</hi> Mat. <hi>19.8.</hi> Our Aduersaries therefore may, in some points possible, pretend <hi>antiquitie;</hi> but <hi>PRIORITIE,</hi> which is the first and best antiquitie, they cannot in any one thing wherein they refuse vs: and whether the zealous and resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Recusants will beleeue it or no, yet it is certainely true, there is no one point of Papistry Catholicke, that is to say, such as hath bene from the beginning, generally receiued as an article of faith by the vniuersall Church. And though it be granted that many parts of his religion haue long continued in the world, yet were they neuer the certaine or generall doctrines of the Church, but the corruptions of some therein, which, in time and by degrees, obtained that strength and credit which now they haue: it being the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siest thing of a thousand for the Pope and his clergie sitting at the sterne, when themselues had once imbraced them, with their strength and learning to giue them authority in the world: when Mahomet himselfe by policy and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie was able, in time, to spread abroad, and a vniuersally, the doctrine of his Alchoran, which now is <hi>800</hi> yeare old, and is followed by many and great nations, as close as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistrie is either in England or Italy. But whē the Scripture makes it plaine, that <hi>FROM THE BEGINNING IT WAS NOT SO;</hi> and the Histories and monuments of antiquity, and the bookes of the elder Papists and such as were chiefe in the Church of Rome, beare witnesse that these things were misliked, and in all ages complained of; and that
<pb facs="13"/> which the Church of England now professes was the faith of most godly men and holy Bishops (though, the power of the gouernors in the Church of Rome increasing, they were suppresed) they do but deceiue themselues that thinke our faith a new faith, or the points of Papistrie the old religion. I haue, as well as I haue bene able, and as diligently as I could, with an vnpartiall eie, and many teares to God, for his direction in the businesse, and with a heart hating con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and possessed as much as any mans liuing, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of peace and vnity: (whereof my <hi>17</hi> yeares residence in Lancashire can giue plentifull witnesse) read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and trauelled through the writings of the Fathers, and obserued the course of former times, and well aduised my selfe of that which the learned of the Church of Rome in later times haue written from the elder Schoolemen to the later Iesuites; (though with all humility I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my selfe to be the meanest of any that haue taken this course; and much lament my owne weaknesse) yet am I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, whensoeuer God, the Iudge of all secrets, and the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reuenger of falsehood and partiality, shall call me foorth of this world, to testifie that my faith and religion and the points thereof maintained in my writings and preaching, is the truth; agreeable to the first antiquity; and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, defended by the Iesuites, and followed by Romish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusants, error and vncatholicke. And if any persons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to be learned, on the other side, haue either in their life or death, shewed extraordinary zeale for their Roman faith; I desire I may be allowed my owne knowledge, both of some such persons and of their iudgement, and outward cariage: and not be importuned to follow that which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull and vnable, and partiall friends haue apprehended, rather then my owne cleare knowledge both of them and
<pb facs="14"/> their cause. And if the Church of Rome haue in it diuers learned (betweene whom and vs, my Aduersaries will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no comparison) that write against vs, yet my certaine experience of their manner of writing one against ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and against knowne antiquitie, and their strange maintenance of the foulest and vnworthiest things that are; and my knowledge of the meanes whereby, and the ends whereto, they are trained vp to this writing; and my daily exercise in their bookes, haue long since remooued from me all opinion of them; and taught me that learning, as beawty, can play the baude, and make them loue it that shall fall by it, and inamoured of it, that little know the danger of it. Let the seuerall points of their faith, which with that learning they maintaine, be well vnderstood, and considered, (for the most vnderstand them not) and let the manner of their proceeding in that they defend be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciously looked into, and it will easily appeare that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and wit,
<note place="margin">Gen. 38.</note> like Thamar, hath prostituted her selfe, and sits in the highway, and so she may haue children, she will deceiue Iudah her owne father. And when all learning, and the ripest wits, and holiest Diuines the Church of Rome hath, are now wholly imploied in maintaining the Popes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer Princes, absoluing subiects from their alleagiance, excusing equiuocating, and the <hi>POWDER-TREASON;</hi> and making the actors Martyrs; and dissoluing the very ioints and bands whereby the world, and Christian society, is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den together; it is high time to let the authoritie of mens persons alone, and looke another while into the reasons and causes they maintaine; and when they haue found the truth to cease from contending, and labour by obedience and submission therunto to bring glory to God, that our tongues may professe, and our liues glorifie his heauenly Maiestie.</p>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <p>Hauing therefore written, in my former booke to this effect, and plainely shewed all this and much more; that my countreymen, and the people of our nation, if they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, might see the triall of things: it is fallen out, that the Romish side findes it selfe, in an extraordinary manner; touched therewith: &amp; after many rumors, &amp; vowes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute me, at last, about <hi>18.</hi> monethes since, I receaued this Reply which here thou seest. And, although I take no pleasure in contentious writings, but (as time shall shew, if I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue my course and God giue meanes) intend that which shall cleare the controuersies without contention; yet when I had heard many reports of something that would be done, with effect, against me, I was willing to giue satisfaction againe, least the ignorant might be perswaded something was writtē indeed that could not be answered. It is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely but others also (for they haue more helps, meanes, and leasure then I haue) as soone as they can be furnished, wil be doing: &amp; more may yet be written: for so he sends me word that writ the last Triumph of Purgatory (an Author that sure will ouerthrow the Chariot and lay all in the mire if he be set to driue it) and so I haue bene often told, and sent word: and therefore if any shall chance to write in forme and without passion (whereof this man is full) and with modesty will say what he thinks, speaking directly and home to that I haue said, without declining or shrinking from the point that presses him, that I may finde him an honest minded man, and not a Mercurialist; I will gratifie him againe, with the same that he brings; and freely reuoke and confesse any error that he shall shew to haue escaped me. If I be otherwise dealt with that nothing be sought but the disgrace of my persō, &amp; vndirect discrediting of my booke; it is likely that I shall take my resolution from the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances
<pb facs="15"/> of my aduersary when I see him, and do as his booke against me shall deserue. In the meane time, be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed of <hi>4.</hi> things touching this Reply and my owne Defence. First, that whereas he hath in the same booke, written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst M. wootton, a learned Diuine, as well as me; I med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle onely with that which concernes my selfe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, taking his booke before me, I answer onely the passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are against me. Next, all that I meddle with is set downe <hi>verbatim</hi> as it lies; and the number of his page in the margent ouer against his text. Then I haue in this sort gone through his whole booke, til within a little of the end; which containing no new matter, but the same that I had occasion to answer diuers times afore, I would lose no time about it. Fourthly, I haue answered fully and directly to euery word he saieth: by which diligence, I haue benefited the Reader so much, that howsoeuer my Aduersary may seeme meane, and vnworthy confuting, yet he shall not lose his labour in reading, but finde my paines bestowed profitably vpon him such as he is: who yet (to giue him his due, though he raile hard and vnciuilly, and write an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure and vnpleasing stile) hath replied with all the best and sutablest arguments he could finde in Stapleton, Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and Valentia; touching the points depending, and onely failes in replying to that which I had answered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
   <p>Hereafter let me intreate the good and courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if he will vouchsafe to vse my writings, not to iudge of them but by his owne triall and examination. For they haue secretly to their wel-willers, laid imputations vpon them, who being surprised with conceit are afraid to make the triall or to meete the truth. The quotations, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or Authors alledged may be challenged, &amp; reported to
<pb facs="15"/> be false: yet this Reply hath charged but onely one in all his booke: and they which haue bene lowdest and earnestest, may finde in such a multitude possible some, to proue that the diligentest writer may be ouerseene: but the substance they cannot discredit. If I haue erred in any thing, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken an Author, I acknowledge my selfe to be a man that may erre; and I humbly submit what I haue done, not onely to the Church wherein I liue, but to euery moderate and peaceable minded man therein: yea I will, with all respect of his person, heare, and aduise of, any thing that an <hi>aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary</hi> shall informe me of, if he will hold the rules of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an truth and charity; and go forward with me in that course to seeke the truth: which all men see euermore to be lost where words and wrangling giue the sound. And I intreate, euen those that cleaue most to the Church of Rome, to perswade themselues that whatsoeuer I haue written is for their sakes, that if it were possible they might discerne the truth offered them, and the wickednesse of the Iesuites that leade them. I maligne no mans person, I hate none that is among them; but being called to be a Preacher of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, I am desirous to bestow my spare houres in maintenance of that I preach: and for the which I were ready to sacrifice my life, much more to bestow my time and trauell; that if it might so please God, we might be all as one; and the state and gouernement wherein we liue, be no longer tossed and intangled with our disagreements. They cannot but see that God, by establishing the Kings throne, and blessing it against the malice &amp; vnnatural practises of their Church, giues testimony on our side, and checks the Pope and all his counsels, thereby to inuite them to peace and vnity: they know that we inuocate one God, and beleeue all the articles of the Creed and rule of faith, and preach and presse godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="16"/> of life without partiality, punishing sinne and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well doing, as much as can be done in any kingdome or state that themselues allow: they haue seene, within the memory of man, innumerable soules giuing their life for the testimony of that we beleeue: onely we differ in diuers articles, which potent and skilfull aduersaries, at seuerall times, in ages past, brought into the Church: let our writings be vnpartially weighed, and the Scriptures be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently read, and the first Antiquity well considered, and it will appeare they are in an error, and kept in bondage thereto, onely through the subtilty and cunning of their masse Priests. God of his goodnesse open their eyes and eares that they may embrace the truth and come forth of Babylon, and, shaking off their superstition, content themselues with the Testament of Iesus Christ, to whom be all honour and power ascribed for euer. Amen. <hi>xij. Maij 1614.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>