<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Publisher to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119070_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14258</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24571</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119070</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Publisher to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hundred and ten considerations of Signior Iohn Valdesso : treating of those things which are most profitable, most necessary, and most perfect in our Christian profession. Written in Spanish, brought out of Italy by Vergerius, and first set forth in Italian at Basil b Coelius Secundus Curio, anno 1550. Afterward translated into French, and printed at Lions 1563. and again at Paris 1565. And now translated out of the Italian copy into English, with notes. Whereunto is added an epistle of the authors, or a preface to his divine commentary upon the Romans</title>
                 <author>Valdés, Juan de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 311, 13 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Publisher to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese truly Divine Meditations or Considerations of <hi>Signior</hi> IOHN VALDESSO, a noble man of Spaine, (who died almost an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares agoe) having been so acceptable to pious <hi>Vergerius,</hi> to learned <hi>Coelius Secundus Curio,</hi> and to many other both French and Italian Protestants, that they have been trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated out of the originall Spanish Copy, and printed three or foure times in those languages; It seemeth to mee a reasonable and charitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to print them now in English, without any alteration at all from the Italian copy; the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish being either not at all extant, or not easy to be found. It is certain that the book containeth many very worthy discourses of experimentall and practicall Divinity, well expressed and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly illustrated; especially concerning the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>trine of justification and mortification: and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>otwithstanding there be some few expressions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d similitudes in it, at which not only the weak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>der may stumble, and the curious quarrell, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o the wise and charitable reader may justly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>lame. To have removed these few stumbling
<pb facs="3"/>
blocks, or offensive passages, by leaving them out, or by altering them, had not been the worke of a Translator, but of an Author; besides the ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of altering antient Authors, which is one of the greatest causes of the corruption of truth and learning. Therefore it hath been thought fit to print the Book, according to the Authors own Copy, but withall to give particular notice of some suspitious places, and of some manifest er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, which follow particularly expressed in the ensuing folios; referring the rest (if any there be) to the judgement of the reader. He lived where the Scriptures were in no reputation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no marveil that he should speak so slightly of them; but rather on the contrary, it may seem a marveilous thing in our eyes, to have a States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in those parts, at that time, so farre illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and taught of God as he was. May it please the Divine goodnesse, that every reader may reap the like comfort and profit to his soule by it, as the Translator and Publisher humbly and thankfully acknowledge that they have done, and they have their main scope and aime in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing it.</p>
   <trailer>Glory be to God on high!</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>