<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faultes escaped.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119651_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14926</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25235</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119651</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faultes escaped.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reply against M. Gilbert Brovvne priest : Wherein is handled many of the greatest and weightiest pointes of controuersie betweene vs and the papists, and the truth of our doctrine clearely proued, and the falset of their religion and doctrine laide open, and most euidentlie conuicted and confuted, by the testimonies of the Scripture and auncient fathers; and also by some of their own popes, doctors, cardinals, and of their owne writters. Whereunto is anexed a seuerall treatise, concerning the masse and Antichrist. By M. Iohn Welsche, preacher of Christs Gospell at Aire</title>
                 <author>Welch, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 363, 1 page, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>Faultes escaped.</head>
   <p>PAge 20. line 15. read Apostles, pag 28. l. 1. for and by, r. others. pag. 31. l. 3. r. if in. pag. 32. l. 4. r decicets. pag. 33. l. 2. for he was, r. they were. pag. 40. l. 5 for theirs, r. heresie. pag 48 l. 36 r. the soules. pag. 56. l. 16. r. therfore. &amp; l. 34 for do, r. dow. pag 67. l. 7. r is, &amp; l. 16, for whilk, r. whill. pag. 68. l. 4 r the. pag. 73. l. 4. for three, 1. third. pag, 74, l, 28. for yet, r. yea. pag, 75, l, 3 for imputes, r imports. &amp; l, 20 for the, r. this pag. 80. l 32. for euery, r. euer any. pag, 89, l, 20 r. expresse contrar. pag. 121, l, 26. for our, r. your. pag, 184, l, 13. for ye, r, they. &amp; l, 16. for ye, r. they pag. 185, l, 30. for your, r. their. pag, 211, l, 22. r. fulfilled pag, 229, l, 33. for priest, r. Prouests. pag 230, l, 12. r in the. pag, 244, l, 29. for offers, r. offered. pag, 252. l. 21, for for, r. from pag. 263. l, 7, for ciphers, r. ciners. pag, 297, l, 7, r. not the. pag. 324, l, 8, for Franciscus, r, Dominicus, &amp; l. 9. for made, r. maine: pag 325, l, 4. for and r. one pag, 327, l, 10. fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> same, r. some. pag. 341. l, 37, for Papistes, r, Popes. And in the epist, to the Reader, and to M, Gilb. Browne. for this country read that country of Niddisdaill and Galloway, euery where.</p>
   <p>Good Reader, if thou shalt finde any more faultes, then these aboue corrected, eitherr in the matter, or marginall quotations, excuse the authour by reason of his far absence, in the time of the imprinting of this worke</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>