<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of the author shewing how and why these notes were
gathered, and the principal parts to be treated, &amp;c. 1596.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119803_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09105</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19411</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119803</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of the author shewing how and why these notes were
gathered, and the principal parts to be treated, &amp;c. 1596.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manifestation of the great folly and bad spirit of certayne in England calling themselues secular priestes : VVho set forth dayly most infamous and contumelious libels against worthy men of their owne religion, and diuers of them their lawful superiors, of which libels sundry are heer examined and refuted. By priestes lyuing in obedience</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 114 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>The Preface of the author shewing how and why these notes were
gathered, and the principal parts to be treated, &amp;c. 1596.</head>
   <p>The notes and obseruations of this memorial following,<note place="margin">The preface of the Memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rial of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note>
were gathered &amp; layd togeather in tyme of persecution, when
there was no place to execute or put them in vre, and it is now
more then 17. or 18. yeares past, that the gatherer began first to
put some of them in wryting, and hauing had the experience
of the yeares which haue insued since, and his part also of
trauel in the Cath. affayre of his coūtrey, and seene the practise
of diuers other Cath. nations abroad, he was desyrous (in
case that himselfe should not liue to see the desyred day of
the reduction of England) yet that some of his cogitations
and intentions for the publike good therof might worke some
<pb n="57" facs="64"/>
effect after his death, and that therby other men might be the
sooner mooued to enter into more mature consideration of
these, and such other like points, yea and to descend also vnto
many more particulars then heere are set downe, for that the
gatherers meaning was only to open the way,<note place="margin">The motiues and meaning of gathering these notes of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial.</note> &amp; to insinuate
certayne general and principal heads that might serue for
an awaking and remembrance at that happy day of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion
of our countrey vnto such persons as shalbe then able
and desyrous to further the common good, and to aduaunce
almighty Gods glory with an holy zeale of perfect reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
who yet perhaps may be so intangled with multitude of
other busines and cogitations at that tyme as they wil not so
easily enter into these, except they be put in mynd therof by
some such memorial, and aduertisments as heere are touched.
And what is said in this Treatise for the kingdome of England
is meant also for Ireland so farre forth as it may do good, seing
the author desireth as much benefit for Gods seruice and good
of the nation to the one countrey, as to the other.</p>
   <p>And for that the principal members and braunches whome
this memorial may concerne are three,<note place="margin">Three parts of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the 3. cheef mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>vvelth.</note> to wit, the whole body
of the realme iointly, and then the Cleargie, and temporalty
apart: therfore the same order shalbe obserued for more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuityes
sake in treating the matters, that are to be handled,
according to these three parts: First of things that appertayne
to the whole body of the Realme in general, and then to the
Cleargie and Laytie in particular, deuiding each one of these
two later members into his particular braunches also, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely
the Cleargie and spiritualty into Bishops, priests and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
men, and the laytie or temporality into the Prince
with his counsel, the nobility and commons, making of
euery one of these cheefe members their particular Chapters
also a part, as in prosecution of this Treatese shal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
   <p>And to the performance of this,<note place="margin">Tvvo point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of encorag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the gatherer.</note> the author was encoraged
especially by two points, which for diuers yeares he hath byn
persuaded in; the first that God wil most certainly at his tyme
appointed restore the realme of England to the Catholike
<pb facs="65"/>
faith againe, as may appeare by the euident hand he holdeth
now in the worke: the other that England being once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
may be made the spectacle of all the world, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of perfection to all other Catholike countreys and
churches round about it, if want of zeale and good wil do
not hinder it, in those that God shal bring to see that blessed
day, which the gatherer of this memorial hopeth wil not.
And with this hope he setteth downe the notes and aduertis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
ensuing.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>