<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Catholike Readers in England.</title>
           <author>Taylor, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119155_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14418</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24738</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119155</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Catholike Readers in England.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An appendix of the saints lately canonized, and beatifyed by Paule the fift, and Gregorie the Fifteenth</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Taylor, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>304, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Catholike Readers in England.</head>
   <p>DEare Countrimen, If my abilitie in Health, Wealth, or Vnderstanding were answereable to my desire of your good, you should heare from mee oftner: But these gifts are at the disposure of a higher power: And therefore at the abounding in any one, or all of these ought to tend vnto his glorie, so their want shall not inforce mee to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate either from that, or hinder mee from laboring to the vtmost of my power to bring you such merchandize as may refresh your soules with spirituall delight and comfort. Wherefore I haue reprinted the Appendix of such Saints liues as were lately Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and beatified by <hi>Paule</hi> the fift and <hi>Gregorie</hi> the fifteenth; translated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish by M. <hi>Ed. Kinsman</hi> The motiues vrging mee hereunto, next after your good was the generall approbation and likeing of the booke amongst all which had it, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of it amongst many which desirde it; it being annexed to the Saints liues of the
<pb facs="3"/>wholl yeare, and therfore cannot bee had, without the byeing of the wholl volume, which many will not, for that they haue those liues all ready, and others cannot, the volume being of so great a price exceeding their poore ability. These are the reasons mouing mee to this I haue heere done, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope you will take it in as good part at I meane it, &amp; therest of my indeauours to you which, is sincerely, wishing they may proue happie Mediums to bring you safe to the peaceable harbour of Eternall blisse, still resting.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in what he is, Henry Taylor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>