<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTE∣OVS READER.</title>
           <author>Whately, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119726_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68877</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25306</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119726</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTE∣OVS READER.</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods hvsbandry: the first part. Tending to shew the difference betwixt the hypocrite and the true-hearted Christian. As it was deliuered in certaine sermons, and is now published by William Whately, preacher of the Word of God in Banbury in Oxfordsheire</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 152, 8, 158, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="84"/>
   <pb facs="84"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Make bold (good Reader) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto thy view, this second part of <hi>Gods Husbandry,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a few Sermons, which I preached vpon the words of Christ, in the fifteenth of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Gospell. My maine inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herein was, to helpe the people of God, against that miserable sinne of Hypocrisie, which in the former Treatise I sought to discouer. Doubtlesse all our paines, and all our preaching, is little enough, and too little, to make men see, and reforme so perillous, and withall so subtill a vice. This is a disease of so darke a working, as will hardly be discerned, vntill it be past cure. And though a man bee not so totally possessed and ouercome by it, as that he deserue to bee called an Hypocrite, yet are the remainders of it (which abide in the most san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified hearts, as the Canaanites amongst the sonnes of <hi>Abraham</hi>) exceeding troublesome, and exceeding noysome, calling for all diligence and labour to expell them. It is the daughter of ignorance and selfe-loue, the mother of pride and selfe-conceitednesse, the sister of vaine-glory and contention. It is, of all sinnes, one of
<pb facs="85"/>the most hideous, because it damneth those, that seeme to themselues little lesse then free from all other sinnes. When the whole army of vices is fled before the face of vertue, and seemes to haue yeelded a full victory, then doth this vice (as it were by stratagems and deuices) vndermine victorious vertue, and rob it of the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which it seemed to haue gotten. It is the refuge and hiding place of all other faults: neither can wee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preuaile against any corruption, then we preuaile against this: neither can any corruption further foyle vs, then this doth lend it aide and succour. This vice maketh those things abominable in Gods sight, which to menward seeme praiseable, and causeth that heauen doth detest, what earth applauds. It comes to Church with men, and poysons preaching, praying, hearing, reading, receiuing the Communion, and all the parts of Gods seruice. It is bold to creepe into the clozet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so with some men, and doth many times corrupt their most retired deuotions. It maketh that the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts himselfe but mocked, when men account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to haue well worshipped him. It turnes mercy, iustice, chastity, into vices after a sort, and causeth that they be in true iudgement, but faire and guilded sins. It marreth in one word, all good things, and changeth the not committing of sinne, into a sinne, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of the most commendable duties, into very loathsome euill. A deuout Hypocrite, is little better then a profane Epicure, and a painted Sepulohre, is little different from a very dunghill. Happy shall that man be, that is carefull to spy out the working of this crooked and deceitfull vice in himselfe, and that with earnestnesse, diligence, warinesse, and constancy, doth
<pb facs="85"/>striue to chase it out of his owne heart. When the Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phites, (wretched claw-backes as they were) came to waken <hi>Sauls</hi> sleeping malice, by offering him their ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to deliuer vp <hi>Dauid:</hi> the Story tels vs, that he sent them backe with this instruction, <hi>Goe and prepare yet, and know, and see his place, and where his haunt is, and who hath seene him there; for it is told me, that he dealeth very subtilly. See there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and take knowledge of all his lurking pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where hee hideth himselfe, and come yee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to me with the certainty, and I will goe with you; and it shall come to passe, if hee be in the Land, I will search him throughout all the thousands of Iudah.</hi> This was maliciously spoken by an enuious Prince, against his faithfull subiect and sonne. But well were it with vs, if wee could all make vse of his words, in the pursuit of our hidden guile, and follow it as close as euer <hi>Saul</hi> did follow <hi>Dauid,</hi> euen to seeke and search, and spy out all its lurking pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and neuer cease seeking, till we haue found it, nor fighting, till we haue vanquished it, as one of the most dangerous of all our spirituall enemies, the very soule of the body of death, and that, that giueth life to all the rest. I beseech the liuing God for thee, Reader, that he will please to sanctifie, as other meanes, so these my weake indeuours, (if thou please to make vse of them) to helpe thee against this pestilent fault. And I craue thy prayers for mee also, that my selfe may be able to practise what I haue taught theē, and that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing befall me not, which <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh of, vpon another occasion, <hi>that hauing preached to others, I my selfe should be a reprobate.</hi> For this hatefull
<pb facs="86"/>and banefull vice, the worst of vices, doth sometimes step into the Pulpit also, and causeth euen Ministers to condemne themselues in iudging others, because they that iudge, doe the same things; and because they lay heauy burthens vpon other mens shoulders, and themselues resuse to touch them, that is to say, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry earnest exactors of good duties, and very slow per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers. But from this most mischieuous mischiefe, the good Lord vouchsafe to deliuer me, and thee, and all his people: with which prayer, because I cannot make a better, I commend thee, and my selfe to God, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A well-willer to thy soules happinesse, WILLIAM WHATELY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>