<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The faults escaped correct thus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119389_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19884</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6310</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119389</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The faults escaped correct thus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologeticall reply to a booke called an ansvver to the unjust complaint of VV.B : Also an answer to Mr. I.D. touching his report of some passages. His allegation of Scriptures against the baptising of some kind of infants. His protestation about the publishing of his wrightings. By Iohn Davenporte BD</title>
                 <author>Davenport, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waesberghe, Isaac van</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Rotterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 326 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>The faults escaped correct thus.</head>
   <p n="1">1. Words or points to be altered. p: stands for page, l: for line, r. for read.</p>
   <p>P: 6. <hi>l:</hi> 7. <hi>r. all together. p:</hi> 25. <hi>l:</hi> 25. <hi>r:</hi> operantis. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l:</hi> 6. <hi>r. Emden for Ments. p:</hi> 46. <hi>l:</hi> 2. <hi>r. answereth. p:</hi> 48. <hi>l:</hi> 27. <hi>r: holesom. l:</hi> 37. <hi>r: up. p:</hi> 54. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r: injury. p:</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>r: consequence. p:</hi> 56. <hi>l:</hi> 3. <hi>r: open. p:</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>r: specially. p:</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r:</hi> of <hi>for</hi> to. <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>and. p.</hi> 70. <hi>l:</hi> 7. <hi>r: 20. for</hi> 21. <hi>p.</hi> 79. <hi>l:</hi> 23. <hi>r: that the Doct: p:</hi> 81. <hi>l:</hi> 26. <hi>r: held. p.</hi> 88. <hi>l:</hi> 11. <hi>r:</hi> in ter Veer, where he. <hi>p.</hi> 89. <hi>l:</hi> 4. <hi>r: with arrogating. p.</hi> 118. <hi>l:</hi> 29. <hi>r: to the. p:</hi> 148. <hi>l:</hi> 5. <hi>r: yet. p:</hi> 174. <hi>l:</hi> 2. <hi>r: coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sail. p:</hi> 177. <hi>l:</hi> 27. <hi>r: was, for w, as. p:</hi> 191. <hi>l:</hi> 33. <hi>r: against it, for against, it. p:</hi> 223. <hi>l:</hi> 12. <hi>r: impute. p:</hi> 242. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r: the, for, th. p:</hi> 245. <hi>l:</hi> 7. <hi>r: was, for wae. p:</hi> 265 <hi>l:</hi> 23. <hi>r. injustice. p:</hi> 266. <hi>l:</hi> 20. <hi>r: devised, p.</hi> 268. <hi>l:</hi> 7, <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>r: further. p:</hi> 288. <hi>l:</hi> 31. <hi>r: these, p:</hi> 295. <hi>l:</hi> 4. <hi>r: either, for, neither.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. Words or points to be added. a: stands for, add. <hi>p:</hi> 9. <hi>l:</hi> 20. <hi>a: about, after satisfactiō. p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>a. secondly, before, Is. p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>a. not, after, &amp;. p.</hi> 82. <hi>l.</hi> 1 <hi>a. he, after, fit. p.</hi> 106. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>a, the, before, Iesuits. p.</hi> 113. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r. moneths absence. p.</hi> 163. <hi>l.</hi> 36. <hi>a. of marriages, after condition. p.</hi> 165. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>a. ?, after, day. p.</hi> 183 <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r. ministers. p.</hi> 202. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>a. that, after, not. p.</hi> 213. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r. constitution. p.</hi> 229. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>a. is, after, it.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">3. Words to be blotted out. d: stands for dele. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>d. h, in where. p.</hi> 56 <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>d. First. p.</hi> 66. <hi>in the margin. d. s. in epist. p.</hi> 82. <hi>l.</hi> 31. <hi>d. s, in places. p.</hi> 86. <hi>l.</hi> 31. <hi>d. s. in Maties. p.</hi> 106. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>d. the, before, Machiavells. p.</hi> 138. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>d. be,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Other faults which doe not so much hinder the Readers understanding I leave to his owne observation. As, when t, is put, for, c, s, for c, ei, for, i, for, e, u, for, n, p, for b. s, for f. m, for n. n, for, m. y, for, i. &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>