<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Kingsmill, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119470_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14343</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15007</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119470</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Kingsmill, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A complaint against securitie in these perillous times: vvritten by M. Tho. Kingsmill, sometime fellow of Magdalen College in Oxford: and lately her Maiesties publicke professour of the Hebrew tongue, in the same Vniuersitie</title>
                 <author>Kingsmill, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bishop, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>152 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I thought to complain of mens security, as alwaies; so in these perilous times, (good christian Reader) I remembred our sinful body of death, as the best excuse, expressed in these two<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Scripturae per Antono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masiam:</hi> for some speciall writing taken out of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: as is this booke.</note> scriptures; the first, in the ninth of Wisedome, which is this: <hi>Corpus quod corrumpitur, aggrauat animam: &amp; terrenum domicilium plenam curarum men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem deprimit:</hi> A corruptible body is heauie to the soule: and the earthly mansion, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth downe, that vnderstanding, that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth vpon meane things. The second in the seuenth to the Romans where S. Paul saith: <hi>Noui quod non habitet in me, hoc est, in carne mea bonum: Nam velle, adest mihi: &amp; vt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam bonum, non reperio.</hi> I know that in me, that is in my flesh, dwelleth no good thing; for to will is present with mee, but I find no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>anes, to performe that which is good:
<pb facs="3"/> as also that knowne verse of the Poet:
<q>Sors tua mortalis, non est mortale, quod optas.</q> Thy state is mortall, but the thing which thou seekest is immortall: which although it be well aunswered, by that godly father: S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> where he saith: That the soule is immortall, and therefore cannot, be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but with immortality: yet because con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the bodie, wee are but flesh, and earth, it is our excuse (if wee haue any) for the secure minde, in heauenly matters: No maruaile, if earth minde earthly thinges, though faith, and sence it selfe may accuse man of so carefull seeking of the earth, and so carelesse a minde towards the health of the soule: which being iudges are against vs, in seeking either of them aboue our reach, or measure: But how not more forceably, when men are secure, concerning the better part of their creation, and become vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surable, or vnsatiable, to preferre the worse, before the better? which how euill it is the Apostle sheweth in the third to the Phillip. saying: <hi>Many walke of whom, I haue told you often, and now tell you weeping, that they are the enemies of the crosse of Christ, whose ende, is damnation, whose god, is their belly, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to their shame, which minde earthly things.</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> Now what may be more horrible, then that our ende should be damnation? what more abhominable, then that our bellie should be our god? what more intolerable, then that our glory should be our shame? And what doth S. Paul lay as the efficient, or sufficient cause, or causes of all these things? but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this: for that mens mindes are set vpon earthly things; from the which minde set vpon earthly things, as a most dangerous roote of such euils, wee are recouered and raysed by the Apostle in this place, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>But our conuersation is in heauen, from whence also wee looke for the Sauiour the Lord Iesus Christ.</hi> Secondly, by S. Paul in the third to the Collossians, saying: <hi>If ye be risen with Christ, seeke those things which are aboue, where Christ sitteth at the right hand of God the father.</hi> Thirdly, by S. Paul 1. Cor. 15. saying: <hi>The glorie of the earthly, is one, and the glorie of the celestiall is another:</hi> As it is written: <hi>The first man Adam was made a liuing soule, and the last Adam was made a quickning spirit, the first man is of the earth, earthlie, the second man is the Lord from heauen: as wee haue borne the image of the earthie, so wee shall also beare the image of the heauenly: for yee are dead</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>and your life is hid
<pb facs="4"/> with Christ in God:</hi> And in so much as wee are dead in Christ he concludeth, that wee should set our affections on things aboue, and not on things vpon the earth.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Coloss.</hi> 3.</note> This ought to be the soules thirst; as it appeareth in the Saints of God: but being cloathed with flesh, clouded with the bodie, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with sinne, our weakenesse is offended at the vnspeakeable blessednes, at the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting time, at the glory, honour, ioy, peace, and immortalitie, which are too much, too high, &amp; too inestimable for vs. As we looke not, nor hearken after that which is too farre off, to see, or heare, which may happily so quench the smoking flaxe, and bruse the broken reede, that not only of our manifold sinnes &amp; wickednes, but also of the vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of flesh and bloud, dust and ashes, we may not so much as looke towards it: the treasures whereof, if they were conferred from a mightie King of this world vpon a poore Lazar, or low subiect, I should aduise him to be secure of the Kings fauour, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to seek any measure of such inestimable felicities, but being betweene vs and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies, and God of all consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which hath vouchsafed vs to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his heauenly kingdome, and hath
<pb facs="4"/> not left vs vnprouided of most gratious meanes to come vnto it, and withall, not without most dreadfull comminations and threatnings, if we depart or diuert from this calling. As it is an euill thing when there is hope of any benefit, or feare of any danger to be secure; so, how are we not presently ashamed? why should we not stand in awe of vtter confusion? how should we escape that euerlasting destruction of hell? If ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther strong vnbeliefe, as if there were no such matter, by the loue of this world, as though the whole world being compared with the losse of the soule, hath not bin waighed in the ballance, and is found too light; or if the care of fields, houses, wiues, and such like, whereof it is in the Gospell, should cause vs to be found carelesse of that heauenly kingdome. Wherefore, hauing a feruent desire (good Reader) to awake men out of this securitie, according to S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 5. to the Ephes. <hi>Expergiscere qui dormis, &amp; surge a mortuis; &amp; illucescet tibi Christus:</hi> Awake thou that sleepest, &amp; stand vp from the dead, and Christ shall giue thee light: I testifie, and that because of these perilous times<note n="b" place="margin">A true vse of the word catholike for generall: as also page 110 agreable with our confession of catholike church, which Trent cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme canno-deny: though the papists im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriat <hi>orbem</hi> in <hi>vrbem:</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike for Romane: that is generall for particular: therefore a wise and iust part to restore a word of that moment to the primitiue vse.</note> Catholike warres, forreine &amp; ciuill daungers, late seditions, and vprores; that
<pb facs="5"/> it is not a time to inioy vines or oliues, to rest in chaires or footstooles; that <hi>Vlisses</hi> chymney though long, would not serue; that the boord or the bedde are but lawfull things; that it hinders not, to be poore, nor helps not, to be rich; that in all estates it hinders to be carelesse; it helpes to be vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and faithfull; that as it is too much to say: I am rich, and increased with goods: Soule take thine ease: So it is not ynough to say, I am poore the Lord helpe me; As it is too much to say, I haue neede of nothing: so it is not all to say: I am well contented with that, that I haue; because we haue need of a smach or taste <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of the wheat of heauen: neither ought to be satisfied with all that the world yeeldeth. In so much that albeit great vertues, as constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, grauitie, reuerence, discipline, regiment, authoritie be knowne as the contraries, and aduersaries to confusion, disorder and euill; yet while these good guifts are vnchriste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, euen our christian catechisme teacheth, that they are vnable to indue vs with the best blessednesse: according to that saying of S. Hugh: who naming these or the like vertues <hi>luminosas, &amp; validas;</hi> strong and lightsome: saith, that they should be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
<pb facs="5"/> to men: <hi>Non tantū propter istam vitā honestissime gerendam, nec tantum propter ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis terrenae concordissimam societatem: verum etiam propter adipiscendam sempiternam salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tē, diuinamque rempublicā: cui nos ciues asciscit fides, spes, charitas,</hi> continencie, loue, iustice, concord, pietie, and other vertues (saith he) are perswaded, not onely for the leading of a most orderly life, neither only for a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able societie of an earthly citie, but also that we might obtaine euerlasting saluation, and that diuine common wealth, to the which faith, hope, and charitie doth gather vs as ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens. And againe, <hi>Deus sic ostendit in opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentissimo, &amp; praeclaro imperio Romanorum quantum valerent ciuiles, etiam sine vera reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione virtutes: vt intelligeretur hac addita, fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri homines, ciues alterius ciuitatis, cuius Rex veritas: cuius lex charitas: cuius modus aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas.</hi> God hath so shewed in the most rich and famous Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> how forcible ciuill vertues may be without true religion, that it might be considered, that true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being adioyned, men become citizens of an other citie, the king whereof is Veritie; the law Charitie; the measure Eternitie; the treasures therefore of this citie, are veritie, charitie, and aeternitie, euen the wheate of
<pb facs="6"/> heauen, which before they are attained, our hunger and thirst would not be satisfied. And therefore neither the bodie of life, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the bodie of death, neither worldly worthinesse, nor mortall weakenesse, much lesse sinne and euill, the glorie of this life, the cares of this world, voluptuous liuing, riches, and other sensuall delights, ought to be respected otherwise, then as stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks in the way to life, and steps to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the way to death; and are to bee eschewed as the nutriments of this securitie, which we seeke to remoue, being found to abound, to be ripe, and rife in this old age of the world, whereby the most righteous, or best allowed are but offensiue, and scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous farre behinde hand, esteeming the guifts, comforts, and blessings of this life ouermuch; and are satisfied within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to become ciuill, courteous, gentle, vertuous, or not maligmant, iniurious, wrongfull, or tyrannous. Now they haue wells which they digged not, houses which they builded not, vineyards which they planted not, all which with the rest, which digge, build, or plant with them, I awake out of this dead sleepe, and darke mist of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, which is able to make euen the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liest
<pb facs="6"/> men, as when all are asleepe, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liest reward, not to differ frō faithlesse, idle, and vaine persons. In deed we cannot, but haue a good opinion of such as are sagely, sadly, or seriously occupied; a better of such as are studious, then of the laborious; a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the laborious then of the carefull: yet what may be the reward of studie, but a forme of knowledge? what of labours but a state of rest, and comfort? what of cares, but a ioy of life and safetie: and might it not be answered, to euery of these from our Sauiour: <hi>Verilie I say vnto you, ye haue your reward?</hi> or from the Apostle: <hi>Ye haue whereof to reioice, but not with God.</hi> For shall it be enough to be baptized assoone as we are borne? or to be catechised assoone as we are able? <hi>Fiunt, non nascuntur Christiani,</hi> saith <hi>Tertullian:</hi> Men are made in time, and are not borne Christians. For behold, men, women and children, liuing as if a childe should liue, in the time of <hi>Moses,</hi> vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cized, or since Christianitie, vnbaptized; beholde, men building, planting, plucking downe, setting vp, rooting out, buying, sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, marrying and giving in marriage, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out respect of the life to come, without the eie of faith, without that fire wherewith
<pb facs="7"/> euerie man should bee salted, and that salt wherwith euery sacrifice should be seasoned. Now who? or where are they at this day to whō the Lord saith:<note place="margin">Hosee 13.</note>
      <hi>I did know thee in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes in the land of drought:</hi> but when they were well fed, and had ynough, they waxed proud and forgat me: for shall not onely Iacob but Iudah also be found well fedde, and proud, or rather among fornicators, vnbeleeuers, Idolaters? shall they at any time be found among the vngodly or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous: or themselues be vngodly and vnrighteous. <hi>Caesar,</hi> when his time was come to be slaine in the Senate of Rome, aswell by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Cassius,</hi> as other conspiratours, saith to <hi>Brutus: Etiam tu fili?</hi> what art thou also my sonne, among these conspiratours? euen so our heauenly father, whose onely begotten sonne we crucifie againe, by falling from the loue wherein we were first establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, saith to euerie such: <hi>Etiam tu fili mi?</hi> what art thou also my child among conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours? among wilfull and audatious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, among fornicators, among extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, louers of this world, vnbeleeuers, scis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiks, scribes, pharisees, hypocrites. <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Cassius</hi> were sonnes in law to <hi>Caesar,</hi> and not his sonnes indeed: all Israell as one
<pb facs="7"/> sonne, is called the first borne of God, but were not so indeede: <hi>Reges in benevolentia Ioues sunt,</hi> saith <hi>Homer.</hi> In like manner, the great and mightie withall that prosper in this life, are soone of opinion, that they are in high fauour with God; a philautie, a fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, a fame, a name to soone resumed, presumed, and receiued:<note place="margin">Iohn 2.</note> verily S. Iohn saith. <hi>They went out from vs, but they were not of vs, for if they had beene of vs:</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note>
      <hi>they would no doubt haue continued with vs.</hi> Verily Saint Paul saith: <hi>The strong foundation of God stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth still, hauing this seale: the Lord knoweth them that are his: and let euerie one that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the name of Christ depart from iniquitie.</hi> Verily our Sauiour saith: <hi>By their fruits yee shall know them;</hi> this is all the sight or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge we haue, or ought to haue, one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in this life, after, God iudgeth, and how may any promise to themselues other then heauie iudgement,<note place="margin">4. Esdras 9.</note> if their fruits be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, or if they depart not from iniquitie. <hi>They (saith the Lord to</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Thus the discreete de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of this reuerend man maketh vse of auncient mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, but yet plainly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing them from apostles and prophets page 70 79. 81.</note> Esdras) <hi>that haue ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred my lawe, while they had yet freedome, and when they had yet open leisure of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and conuersion, the same must knowe it after death in paines.</hi> And therefore be thou no more carefull how the vngodly shall be
<pb facs="8"/> punished: but inquire how the righteous shall be saued, and whose the world is? &amp; for whō the world is; &amp; when? Vnder the name of <hi>Esdras,</hi> are not the most righteous admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished to inquire how they shall be saued? Shall the righteous be saued? how? or when? for the promise is made to Abraham and his seede,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> that he should be heire of the world. Of a truth (good Reader) heauen gate is so straight, the way so full of dangers, the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles so manifold, the temptations so subtile, the enemies so mightie, the impediments so hard to ouercome, the reward so farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue our reach, or measure, that it may be feared, but that with Abraham we learne to hope beyond hope, that the best or most righteous, shall by the best they can doe, or at least, by the best that they doe, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but this world. All the Israelites peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed which came out of Egypt, and not one entred into the land of Canaan. Are there two or three excepted? for vnlesse the priests and Leuites carrie the Arke before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more zealously; vnlesse the people be more vigilant to follow the cloud which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by day, or the pillar which lightneth by night, more deuoutly; vnlesse sincerely we eate the passeouer,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> as with vnleauened
<pb facs="8"/> bread, with our loines girded, with our shooes on our feete, and with our staues in our hands: how should we not dwell in this side of Iordan still? how should we passe the red-sea? howe should wee ouercome the caues, dennes, mountaines, and wildernes of the earth?<note place="margin">Esdras 7.</note> doth not <hi>Esdras</hi> tell of a citie giuen to a man for an inheritance? and doth he not protest, that the entrance to it is like, as if there were a fire on the right hand, and a deepe water on the left, and but one onely straight path betweene them both, between the fire, and the water, so small, that there could but one man goe there at once: and is not mused, by <hi>Esdras</hi> himselfe how this man should receiue his inheritance? goe on therfore straight: tread not awry: looke not aside: straine out both camells and gnatts: espie both motes, and beames; giue both loaues and crummes, the honie, and the honie comb, to thy poore brethren. Do wee not know that when Nabuchadnezer, should be chased from men, and his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was to be with the beasts of the field: how it is answered by Daniell:<note place="margin">Daniel 4.</note>
      <hi>wherefore receiue my counsell O king: breake of thy sins by righteousnesse, and thine iniquitie by mercie toward the poore.</hi> Now how long wil school<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="9"/> dispute vpon this: whether righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and mercie to the poore,<note n="d" place="margin">Thus this zealous man calleth men from dispute to practise, lest some vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of plucking vp Popish merit, should plucke vp the wheat of good works.</note> are meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius to saluation, which as it was spoken first, to Nebuchadnezar: so is left for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, vppon whom the endes of the world are come: that we also should breake our sinnes by righteousnesse, and our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie by mercy toward the poore. And are not the endes of the world come vpon vs? Is it not time to stretch out both the right hand, and the left, to such friends, as may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs, into the euerlasting tabernacles? wherefore then doe we not call vpon righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse and mercie, as materiall, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary causes <hi>sine quibus non,</hi> (as the logician speaketh) without which, mercy is shut from vs: I deenie not (christian Reader) but zeale should call vpon charitie, that it might be kindled; as also other good gifts, that they might be raised: The <hi>Amalekites</hi> for vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritablenesse had warres for euer, with the Lord and his people: All our Lords labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are to few, to fell the haruest of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: yet I haue intituled this paper, <hi>A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint against securitie alone.</hi> All the world sitteth still, and is carelesse, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> The earth was without forme, and was void, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="9"/> was vpon the face of the deepe. These two scriptures, I commend to euery reader, shewing with what contemplation, men may take a view of this latter age of the world. Beware (christian reader) of this generall securitie, beware of vnbeliefe, knowing for a suretie, that it is most vnaduised, to care for all things of this life, and to be carelesse of Gods fauour, of the rewards reserued in heauen, or the punishments remaining in hell, for vs. To God the father; God the sonne; and God the holy Ghost; be all honor, glory, and dominion for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ, THO. KINGSMILL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>