<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>CELIO SECVN∣DO CVRIONE, A SERVANT OF IESVS CHRIST, to all those, that are Sanctified by God the Father, &amp; saved, and called by Iesus Christ our Lord,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119070_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14258</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24571</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119070</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>CELIO SECVN∣DO CVRIONE, A SERVANT OF IESVS CHRIST, to all those, that are Sanctified by God the Father, &amp; saved, and called by Iesus Christ our Lord,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hundred and ten considerations of Signior Iohn Valdesso : treating of those things which are most profitable, most necessary, and most perfect in our Christian profession. Written in Spanish, brought out of Italy by Vergerius, and first set forth in Italian at Basil b Coelius Secundus Curio, anno 1550. Afterward translated into French, and printed at Lions 1563. and again at Paris 1565. And now translated out of the Italian copy into English, with notes. Whereunto is added an epistle of the authors, or a preface to his divine commentary upon the Romans</title>
                 <author>Valdés, Juan de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 311, 13 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="Italian_translators_note_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>CELIO SECVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DO CVRIONE, A SERVANT OF IESVS CHRIST, to all those, that are Sanctified by God the Father, &amp; saved, and called by <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> our <hi>Lord,</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">The Mercy, the Peace, and the love of God be multiplied unto you.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EE here (Brethren) we make tender unto you, not of Boccace his Hundred Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but of the Hundred and ten Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of</hi> Valdesso; <hi>the great importance whereof I shall declare unto you.</hi> Many both Ancient and Modern, have written, of Christian afsayres, <hi>and of them, some better then others; but who he is, next the Apostles of our Lord, and the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists, that hath written more substantially, and Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, then</hi> Iohn Valdesso, <hi>would perhaps be hard to finde. There be some of them that have left indeede many great and laborious Bookes; but amongst them there are also</hi>
      <q>many of little importance, and that are not much necessary</q>
      <hi>to a Christian life, being fraught with unprofitable Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>and Philosophicall dtsputations, from whence hath</hi>
      <q>sprung a thousand inconveniences in the Church of Christ. And to give a proofe that I say the trueth in this matter, I set downe some of these inconveniences, whereby Iudgment may easily be given of the rest.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>
         <hi>First therefore, in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> much as they have written huge Bookes, they could not avoid many falsities, follies, and vanities: For as the wise man testifieth,</hi> many words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want much vanity.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>Next, these great Writers have drawne all the Srip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to Questions, and Disputations, and made as it were an Academy thereof, raising such doubts in every thing as they have made the Doctrine of the Son of God, and of his Apostles, and our most certaine, and infallible hope of Eternall life to become a matter altogether doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And this which I shall now adde, is not of lesse impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then the other inconveniences; and that is, that with their ample, and infinite volumes they have withdrawn, and estranged men from the study of the truly holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and from the Contemplation of simple verity, and instead of Christ's Disciples have made them mens Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; So that we are come to that passe, as more and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter credit is given to those which are termed Doctors (as if so be Christ and his Apostles were not the true, and Eternall Doctors and masters of the Church) then to the simple Doctrine of Christ himselfe.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>This is the benefit and the edification that the Church hath reaped from these huge volumes;</q>
      <hi>which our Lord and Saviour Iesus Christ seeing, (the safety of his Church being more deare unto him, then his owne life) hee hath stirred, and raised up some, and opened their eyes, to the intent, that they should by litle and litle reduce his sheepe to the greene and healthfull pastures of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to the pure, cleare, and sweet Fountaines of God's Word. And herein every one hath busied himselfe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his talent, that is, the gift which hee hath received.</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
But to me it seemes, and I hope it will doe so likewise to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> that have a true relish of Christs Doctrine, that this our Author in these divine Considerations, and some other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of his, hath so well considered and propounded to all our Considerations the duties of a Christian man, that there are but a few, very few, that can goe before him. He hath not indeed writ so huge a Volume, nor scribled so much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: No, the Bookes which he hath written, are litle, and few, but pure, cleare, and truly Divine.</p>
   <p>Many have written of the vertues, manners, and duties of a wise and good man, as <hi>Aristotle, Panetius,</hi> and <hi>Cicero,</hi> and amongst Christians, <hi>Ambrose;</hi> and in our age, <hi>Thomas Venatorius:</hi> But none of all these hath intreated with such sublimity, nor made such effectuall demonstration, nor discoursed with such sweetnesse, nor with such Maiesty, nor with such authority, nor with such grace, as our <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desso.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This, this is that which truly deserves to be entitled the Booke of Christian duties, the Booke of Christian demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rations, and of truly divine speculations.</p>
   <p>Herein is shewed the Originall, the Cause, the Progresse, and the End of every motion, of every action, of every event, that is done under heaven, either by God or the Divell, or by the godly, or by the wicked man; and all this from cleare, certaine, and unquestionable Principles of holy Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ure, accompanied with so good, and proper examples, and simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, and compassions, and divisions, and definitions, that unlesse we will be too too obstinate, and out of common sense, we must needs come to agreement touching that which a man owes unto God, to himselfe, and to his Neighbour. And further, what the benefit of Christ is, and to whom it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, what the infirmity, and what the Power of Christ is, his abasement, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> his exaltation, our owne Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and our Vivification, Election, and Reprobation, and a thousand other like good and profitable heads are here to be clearly learned in such manner, as growing practique in
<pb facs="9"/>
this Booke you shall come to understand all things necessary to holy Scripture better then by the great and many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries of many others.</p>
   <p>Now for this great, and heavenly treasure we are all deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to <hi>M. Peter Paul Vergerius,</hi> as the instrument of the divine Providence in causing it to be printed for the view, &amp; enioyment of every one. He comming from Italy, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his feigned Bishoprick to come unto a true Apostle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe, whereunto he was called by Christ, brought with him many excellent compositions, doing herein, as men use to doe, when their houses are on fire, or their City sack'd, and ruin'd; every one endeavours to escape away with the best, and most precious things that he hath: so our <hi>Vergerius</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeming nothing more deare then the glory of our Lord and Saviour Iesus Christ, brought away with him those things, which might best serve to the illustration and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement thereof. Hee abandoned therefore the earthly treasures, and brought away with him the heavenly, and divine treasures, amongst which this is one of the best, and most rare that can be imagined. And knowing that good, and excellent things become so much greater, better, and more praise-worthy, as they become more common, hee left unto me these hundred and ten Considerations, that I should cause them to be put in print, which I have, as you see accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly performed with as much diligence as I have known, or beene able to use.</p>
   <p>These Considerations, as many well know, were first written by the Author in the Spanish language, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by a certaine pious and worthy person translated into Italian. Yet have they not beene able altogether to quit those forms of speech which are proper to Spain. And besides there are some words, though not many, of the language of the Author For <hi>Iohn Valdesso</hi> was by Natiō a Spaniard of noble kindred of an honourable degree, and a resplendent Chevali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>r of the Emperour, but a much more honourable &amp; resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Chevalier of Christ. True it is, he did not much follow
<pb facs="10"/>
the Court, after that Christ had revealed himselfe unto him, but abode in Italy, spending the greatest part of his life at Naples, where with the sweetnesse of his Doctrine, and the sanctity of his life hee gained many Disciples unto Christ; and especially among the gentlemen, and Cavaliers, and some Ladies: he was very eminent, and most praise-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in all kind of praise. It seemed that hee was appointed by God for a Teacher, and Pastor of noble and illustrious Personages: Although hee was of such benignity, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that hee accounted himselfe debtor of his Talent to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very me ane and rude person, and became all things to all men, that he might gaine all to Christ. And not this alone, but he gave light to some of the most famous Preachers of Italy, which I very well know, having conversed with them themselves.</p>
   <p>He never had wife, but lived most continently, nor did he attend to ought else, as much as he could, then unto tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Mortification, in which death overtaking him, hee became perfectly mortified, so to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> perfectly quickned in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the Iust, and to enioy our Lord Christ. He died in Naples about the yeare 1540. Hee hath left behinde him also certaine other good, and pious Compositions, which as I hope shall by <hi>Vergerius</hi> his meanes be communicated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
   <p>Goe to then, Brethren, and Sisters, in the Love of God, and in the precious blood of Christ Iesus, take this Treasure, and thinke withall, that the benefit lies not in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and possessing it, but in the use and fruit, that is thence to be gathered. He hath made Consideration of these good things not to give nourishment to the imagination only, but likewise to put in execution that which hath been conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and resolved on. It is necessary indeed, that wee should have the knowledge, but it is necessary like wise to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the practice therewith, in as much as the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation of every v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rtue▪ and art consisteth in the practice, and in the performance of action agreeable to that
<pb facs="10"/>
vertue and Art.</p>
   <p>And you that wast all your time idly in reading of Boccace his hundred Novelties, and the like, lay them a while aside, and read these Considerations of <hi>Valdesso,</hi> which are indeed tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Novelties. For in them is treated of that great Divine, and ioyfull new and gladsome tydings of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, of the great Pardon for sins, of the Reconciliation made with God by the death of the Sonne of God. Here you shall finde the true and holy Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourments of God, and of Christ with mankind. Here you shall understand the true Embraces, and the true Kisses gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by meanes of the holy Spirit. And last of all you shall here finde where the true delights and pleasures of those soules are, which are enamoured of God and of Christ, and disenamoured of the world.</p>
   <p>And if happily the language se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>me not so spruce and dainty, as that of Boccace, call to minde that which great Paul the Apostle of Christ Iesus hath said, that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God stands in the power of the Spirit, and not in excellency of speech. Howbeit to say truth, neither is this manner of speech to be slighted: For I verily find it excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding proper, and good to expresse that which is intended; and that is the chiefe vertue of every Writer.</p>
   <p>But I will here put an end to my discourse, that I may no longer deprive you of the sacred reading of these divine Considerations, which you also reading, and that with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and praiers to God for me and all others, shall take into due Consideration: To the end, that we may came all to be enamoured of Christ, and incorporated in him, as hee is incorporated in us; To whom be Honour and Glory ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting!</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Basill <date>the 1 of MAY, 1550.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>