<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The most excellent, god∣lie, vertuous, learned, our gracious Soue∣raigne Lord, IAMES, by the grace of God of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the true, Christian Catholique Fayth.</title>
           <author>Wentworth, Paul</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119655_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119655</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The most excellent, god∣lie, vertuous, learned, our gracious Soue∣raigne Lord, IAMES, by the grace of God of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the true, Christian Catholique Fayth.</title>
                 <author>Wentworth, Paul</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The miscellanie, or, A registrie, and methodicall directorie of orizons : Exhibiting a presentment of the soules requestes in the high court of the heauenly parliament: prefaced with meditations of a three-fold distinct nature, preparatiuely instructing the Christian soul</title>
                 <author>Wentworth, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 4.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 199, 120-126, 2, 40, 39-102, 203-213, 1, 111-126, 227-256 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO The most excellent, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, vertuous, learned, our gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, <hi>IAMES,</hi> by the grace of God of great <hi>Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, defender of the true, Christian Catholique Fayth.</head>
   <head>RIGHT-NOBLE, MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOWNED, MY DREAD SOVERAIGNE;</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an ancient saying of a diuine</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher, <hi>that</hi> Common-wealths <hi>are then happie and fortunate, when either the</hi> Wise <hi>and</hi> Learned, <hi>called</hi> Philosophers, <hi>gouerne them, or their</hi> Gouernours <hi>and</hi> Rulers <hi>be</hi> Philosophers; <hi>that is,</hi> louers of Wisedome <hi>and</hi> Learning. <hi>Some, to make resemblance of this</hi> Truth, <hi>doe Emblematize it in the Picture of</hi> Pallas, (<hi>whom the</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie <hi>deemed the</hi> Goddsse of Wisedome) <hi>portraicted with a</hi> Sheild <hi>or</hi> Target: <hi>by which they would giue vs to vnderstand, that the</hi> whole World, <hi>figured vnder the forme of that</hi> Sheild, <hi>is gouerned of</hi> Wisedome; <hi>and by meanes hereof, a</hi> Prince <hi>to be inuested, as it were, into a possession of</hi> two Kingdoms; <hi>the one, of</hi> Saturne, <hi>which is</hi> Contemplation: <hi>The other of</hi> Iupiter, <hi>which is</hi> Action. <hi>And to make this to appeare more plaine, the</hi> Astronomer <hi>is bold to say, That no great matters for weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, nor firme for perpetuitie, can be done by any, but in whom</hi> Saturne <hi>the</hi> Philosopher, <hi>and</hi> Iupiter <hi>the</hi> King, <hi>are vnited,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> (<hi>like</hi> Hippocrates Twinnes) <hi>sympathizing in one, and the same person of a</hi> chiefe Gouernour, <hi>whom for that cause, they call most happie, as hauing the</hi> Dietie <hi>of</hi> Pallas (<hi>to vse their wordes) residing in his</hi> Brest; <hi>both to possesse</hi> Knowledge, <hi>and to carrie the</hi> Launce: <hi>For that</hi> Knowledge <hi>without</hi> Power <hi>and</hi> Might, profiteth few; <hi>and</hi> Power, <hi>without</hi> Knowledge <hi>and</hi> Wisedome, <hi>doth</hi> hurt many. <hi>This seemeth to haue been a receiued Truth of the</hi> Antiquitie: <hi>For, in this sense wee read, that the</hi> Kings <hi>or</hi> Rulers <hi>of former times were chosen such, as should both at home prouide for the</hi> aduauncing Vertue, <hi>and</hi> repressing Vice; <hi>And also repell</hi> Foreine forces <hi>from</hi> Inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions; <hi>yea vpon occasions likewise,</hi> Lead an Armie abroad: <hi>shewing that in these two thinges, was necessarily comprized the</hi> very chiefe Office <hi>of</hi> Kinges <hi>and</hi> Rulers: <hi>The one to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by</hi> good Lawes, <hi>and</hi> administring Iustice alwayes: <hi>The other, by</hi> Armes, <hi>and</hi> Martiall Cheualrie, <hi>as the times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: For this last, is</hi> extraordinarie, <hi>and in</hi> case it must be so: <hi>But that former is</hi> ordinarie <hi>and</hi> perpetually in vse, <hi>and not to be omitted. For this cause in those</hi> heroicall Times, <hi>all</hi> Kings <hi>were both</hi> Iudges, <hi>and</hi> Captaines of Warre, <hi>as sayth</hi> Aristotle <hi>This is manifested in the first</hi> Kings <hi>of the auncient</hi> Grecians, 1 Aeacus, 2 Minos, <hi>and</hi> 3 Rhodamanthus, <hi>who</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. 2. 3.</note>
      <hi>all three were called by no other name vsually, then by the name and title of</hi> Iudges; <hi>manifested likewse in those</hi> Epithets <hi>attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to</hi> Kings, <hi>by</hi> Homer, <hi>calling them,</hi> Shepheards of the people; <hi>to note a speciall care appropriated to them of</hi> Legall protection <hi>euery way, which also is the very same argument that the</hi> holy Ghost <hi>is pleased to vse in S.</hi> Paul, <hi>shewing the end for which</hi> Rulers <hi>and</hi> Kings <hi>are appoynted, euen that they by Gods fauour, faythfully executing their Office, the people vnder them</hi> may <note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 2.</note> lead a quiet, and a peaceable life in all godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and honestie. <hi>And for specialtie the said Poet</hi> Homer <hi>celebrateth</hi> Agamemnon King <hi>and</hi> Generall <hi>of the</hi> Grecian Armie <hi>against</hi> Troy. <hi>And to speake out of Historie, we read in</hi> Herodotus, <hi>that</hi> Dioces <hi>among the Medes, was first made</hi> Iudge, <hi>and afterwards</hi> King: <hi>hauing appoynted to him a</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb facs="3"/> Guard, <hi>aswell for his owne</hi> safetie, <hi>as also to keepe in awe the</hi> Potent <hi>and</hi> Mightie, <hi>and to represse in them</hi> insolent Wronges <hi>against the</hi> weaker sort <hi>of inferiour note. Againe, the</hi> Laced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>monian Kinges, <hi>as in time of peace they ruled by the</hi> Sword of Iustice; <hi>So in the Field against</hi> their Enemie, <hi>they had an</hi> absolute Commaund, (<hi>though perhaps herein, some will say; by a speciall Commission from the</hi> Ephori, <hi>deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them enclosed in that round peece of Wood, called their</hi> Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale,) <hi>both for a</hi> good King, <hi>and a</hi> stout Warriour, <hi>by those two epitheted adiunctes defining him a fit</hi> Gouernour <hi>of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, aswlll for</hi> Warre, <hi>as for</hi> Peace. <hi>Neither the</hi> Romans, <hi>who succeeded the</hi> Grecians <hi>in the</hi> Empire, <hi>were herein wanting to themselues; for they also after their example, constituted</hi> Kings <hi>for</hi> Iustice <hi>sake, as</hi> Tullie <hi>sayth, by their Authoritie to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained among them for the</hi> common good. <hi>Now this name of</hi> King, <hi>hauing the stile of</hi> great State <hi>and</hi> Maiestie, (<hi>as being most eminent amongst men) was therefore so plausible to the</hi> Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, <hi>and so liuely in their Eye, as that they thought themselues inferiour to the</hi> Ethniques, <hi>so long as they were without a</hi> Ruler <hi>by</hi> that Name; <hi>and therefore asked of</hi> Samuel <hi>a</hi> King, <hi>first to</hi> Iudge <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 8. 5. 20</note> them only: <hi>But afterwards they would haue a</hi> King like other Nations, <hi>both</hi> to iudge them, <hi>and also</hi> to goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>them, and to</hi> fight their Battailes. <hi>And so they had a</hi> King <hi>by appoyntment from</hi> GOD, <hi>promised them</hi> before <hi>in</hi> Deuteronomie, <note n="b" place="margin">Deut 17. 14. 15.</note>
      <hi>if they should aske one when they</hi> were come into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which he would giue them to possesse; <hi>For as then</hi> GOD <hi>was their sole and onely</hi> King; <hi>and being the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Kings, <hi>was instead of all, and vouchsafing them alwayes</hi> his one presence, <hi>was still among them betweene the</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam. 4. 4</note> Cherubims, <hi>fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> whence the</hi> Lord <hi>answered, &amp; gaue out</hi> Oracles <hi>in all weightie matters, by</hi> 1. Dreames <note n="d" place="margin">1. Sam. 28. 6</note>
      <hi>by</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Vrim, <hi>or by his</hi> 3. Prophets; <hi>in this manner designeing</hi> Iudges for Peace, <hi>and appoynting</hi> Captaines for Warre <hi>extraordinarily, as</hi> Ioshua, <note n="e" place="margin">Num. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>8.</note> Iudah, <note n="f" place="margin">Iudg. 1. 2.</note> Othniel, <note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 3. 9.</note> Deborah, <note n="h" place="margin">Iudg. 4. 4.</note> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion, <note n="i" place="margin">Iudg. 6. 14.</note> &amp;c. <hi>And so to</hi> Samuel, <note n="k" place="margin">1. Sam. 7. 15</note> who iudged Israel al the dayes of his life: <hi>And annoynted</hi> Saul <note n="l" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Sam. 10. 1.</note>
      <hi>the</hi> first King to
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>be the</hi> Gouernour of the Lords inheritance. <hi>But to goe on in the matter proposed, it appeareth by those former allegations of</hi> Testimonies <hi>and</hi> Examples, <hi>that Men at the first were made</hi> Rulers <hi>and</hi> Gouernours <hi>ouer people for a common defence to them both in</hi> Warre <hi>and</hi> Peace: <hi>and therefore wee may not thinke but they were qualified through</hi> Wisedome <hi>thereto, as hauing that</hi> Eye <hi>of</hi> the Learned, <hi>defined to be the</hi> Iudicious discreete Eye, <hi>clearely insighted in the precepts of</hi> true Policie; <hi>which said</hi> Eie, <hi>is framed &amp; fashioned, as it were, first out of a</hi> wit <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> perspectiue, <hi>to inquire into the qualitie of</hi> State-affaires. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <hi>out of a</hi> Iudgement deliberatiue, <hi>fitted by much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to define and determine them: And lastly, out of a</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Minde resolute <hi>and</hi> expedit <hi>for speedie execution accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. For this</hi> Eye <hi>weighing, in the</hi> Balance <hi>of a</hi> Well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed discretion, <hi>the differences of former Times passed, with the late Customes of our</hi> moderne <hi>Times, and now present in esse, both 1. abrogateth, 2. reformeth, and also 3. establisheth</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. 2. 3.</note> Lawes; <hi>prudently attemperating the reason and vse of them, to the distinct formes of</hi> Gouernment <hi>in seuerall; which by reason of Change in the manners of the People, must of necessitie admit also Change and alteration in themselues: and so in the sense of that</hi> Ciuill Law maxime, <hi>as</hi> thinges that happen a new, haue need of new reforming Remedies: <hi>Which none can be excogitated fitly, and set for good, without this</hi> iudicious Eye of the Learned; <hi>for which cause it hath been in very high esteeme alwayes among</hi> Kinges, Princes, <hi>and</hi> men of State, <hi>in that ranke for Wisedome remarkable. A matter therefore for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie not only in Confession deseruing approouement, but much more in Action (suffragating thereto) singulerly applauded; as is pregnantly related in</hi> Histories <hi>of former age. But what needs any recitall of forreine examples for testimonie of this truth. To write</hi> personall Commendations <hi>of</hi> liuing Princes, <hi>es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to themselues, may be held a</hi> verball Simonie; <hi>yet, Shall true prayses be smothered in silence, for feare of vniust blame? Onely I doe deprecat the suspition of</hi> Flatterie, <hi>and craue to be bold to vtter a</hi> true thought <hi>of a</hi> loyall Heart, <hi>and say,</hi> Your
<pb facs="4"/> Highnes, ô most Noble, (<hi>worthely so tearmed</hi>) defender of the Fayth, (<hi>which indeed is the</hi> very true, auncient, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Fayth) <hi>beeing not onely Learned</hi> your selfe <hi>in all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges fitting (for Ornament) the stately personage of a</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall Gouernour, (<hi>for this cause to be truely accompted a</hi> LIVING LIBRARIE, <hi>and a</hi> Walking Studie); <hi>But also singulerly affecting, and charily forstering the</hi> professors of Learning <hi>and</hi> good Artes, (<hi>in both these names a</hi> myrrour <hi>of</hi> Kings) <hi>doe make alone, without example, the asseueration of the former assertion good, in asmuch as thus ordering the</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment politique <hi>of your</hi> Realmes <hi>and</hi> Kingdomes <hi>by</hi> Wisedome <hi>through</hi> holesome Lawes, <hi>you haue setled and established them in a</hi> blessed Christian Peace <hi>and</hi> tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>beautifying, and beatifying, both</hi> Church <hi>and</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth <hi>thereby. This apparantly manifested to all your</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, (<hi>I meane</hi> Subiectes of the best note for true loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to your Royall Scepter) <hi>who seeing, (and confessing also an acknowledgment of the same) doe rightly and willingly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to that</hi> iudiciously discreete Eye of Learning <hi>and</hi> Wisedome, <hi>spoken of before; and is in</hi> your Maiestie <hi>the better quick-sighted, and more clearely perspicuous, for that it hath receiued illumination from the</hi> Spirit <hi>of</hi> that Wisedome <hi>which</hi> Salomon <hi>calleth,</hi> The <note n="a" place="margin">Wisdo 7. 26.</note> Brightnesse of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting Light, <hi>and,</hi> The image of Gods goodnesse. <hi>In the vertue and power whereof, your</hi> Maiestie <hi>being alwayes guided, can at no time be deceiued in the course of</hi> your Gouernement; <hi>which as it is now in apparance, wilbe hereafter better made knowne in the</hi> publique good, <hi>being the</hi> chiefe end <hi>of a</hi> well setled State. <hi>For this</hi> Wisedome <hi>telleth</hi> Kinges <hi>and</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>that they are appoynted</hi> Rulers <hi>ouer Men for</hi> Mens sake. <hi>And as by this, they are</hi> Lordes; <hi>so are they</hi> Tutors <hi>and</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors <hi>of their</hi> People. <hi>O truely iust and most lawfully ruling</hi> Prince! <hi>who in this sublimious state of a preheminenced</hi> Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie, <hi>hath notwithstanding adioyned, and (as it were conser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>) reuerend Modestie <hi>to</hi> Princely Maiestie, <hi>desirous to be held and reputed of his</hi> Vassals <hi>rather</hi> Good for Clemencie,
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>then</hi> Great for Power; <hi>a</hi> Father <hi>of</hi> his Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntrie, <hi>much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ore, then a</hi> Lord ouer Men: <hi>whom he knowing to be giuen him of</hi> God, <hi>for their</hi> speciall good <hi>and</hi> benefite, <hi>is not sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by</hi> high thoughts <hi>of</hi> his stately▪ Dignitie, <hi>from executing the kind, and loue-meriting partes of that</hi> necessarie Charge <hi>committed to him from aboue, acknowledging with</hi> Adrian <hi>the</hi> Emperour, <hi>the</hi> Common-wealth <hi>to be the</hi> Wealth <hi>and</hi> Welfare <hi>of</hi> his People, <hi>and not</hi> his owne in proper. <hi>A true and plausible effect of</hi> Wisedome <hi>and</hi> Learning <hi>specified in that worthy saying mentioned before, and much celebrated in the writinges of the best</hi> learned Politiques <hi>of either</hi> Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phying Rulers, <hi>or</hi> Ruling Philosophers, <hi>making happie</hi> Common-wealthes <hi>by the vse thereof, and for</hi> it worth <hi>hath carried a long my Pen vnto this discourse, the rather because it hath a true conformitie with</hi> your Maiesties Royall deportment, <hi>in the whole course of your</hi> Highnesse Rule <hi>ouer vs with great correspondence. But this notwithstanding (though verie plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible both in opinion and example.</hi>) Religion, <hi>in specialtie, is that, which first</hi> reduceth <hi>the Throane of a</hi> Prince <hi>into a forme of</hi> gouernment <hi>by</hi> wisdome; <hi>&amp; afterwards</hi> raiseth <hi>and setleth it in an</hi> Eminent height <hi>of a most florishing state; For those</hi> Common-wealthes <hi>are in the Eye and speech of all men religiously wise, most</hi> firme, <hi>&amp;</hi> permanent, <hi>in whose</hi> middest <hi>is seated the</hi> Temple of God, <hi>yea who themselues are in deed the</hi> very Temple of God; <hi>so as all</hi> Kings <hi>and</hi> Princes, <hi>which doe reigne with</hi> God, <hi>doe reigne most happely and best secured; as of your Maiestie is acknowledged to bee well vnderstood for a truth, euen at the first entrance and commencement of</hi> your Reigne <hi>ouer vs. For, (may it please</hi> your Grace my most gracious Soueraigne) <hi>to giue me leaue, I shall remember vnto</hi>
      <note place="margin">This Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eld at Hampton Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anu. 14. 1603.</note>
      <hi>your</hi> Highnesse <hi>your owne words, making proofe thereof, in that</hi> Conference <hi>had with the</hi> Lords, Bishops, <hi>and others of the</hi> Clergie, <hi>about</hi> Church-matters <hi>when to declare your</hi> Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie meaning <hi>in calling that</hi> assemblie, <hi>you sayd,</hi> It was after the example of all Christian Princes, to take the first course for the establishing of the Church, both for Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb facs="5"/> and Policie: <hi>Wherein your</hi> Highnes <hi>manifested that</hi>
      <note place="margin">See <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> religious Care, <hi>which is best fitting the</hi> Royall person <hi>of a</hi> Christian Prince, <hi>knowing, and doing to your</hi> Subiectes <hi>also thereby to know, that the</hi> maine Piller <hi>of a</hi> Politique State <hi>for</hi> happinesse, <hi>in</hi> permanencie <hi>and</hi> stabilitie <hi>in</hi> Religion; <hi>which cannot be setled, but by that true</hi> Wisedome <hi>whereof</hi> Salomon <hi>speaketh, calling it,</hi> The <note n="a" place="margin">Wisd. 7. 25.</note> Breath of the Power of God: <hi>For, if</hi> God <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 12. 18.</note> looseth the Coller of Kinges, <hi>and</hi> girdeth their Loynes with a Girdle, <hi>as</hi> Iob <hi>speaketh, which as by interpretation out of</hi> Daniel, <note n="c" place="margin">Dani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2. 21.</note> taketh away Kings, <hi>and</hi> setteth vp Kinges; <hi>it is out of question, that the</hi> Throane <hi>of</hi> Princes <hi>is the</hi> Throane of God; <hi>So acknowledged, and in words confessed of the</hi> Queene of Sheba, <hi>when she sayed to</hi> Salomon, <note n="d" place="margin">2. Chro. 9. 8.</note> Blessed be the Lord thy God, which loued thee, to set thee on his Throane as King in stead of the Lord thy God. <hi>And this</hi> Throane, Dauid <hi>calleth the</hi> Throane <note n="e" place="margin">1. Chro. 28. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> of the Kingdome of the Lord ouer Israel. <hi>And in a fit correspondence hereto,</hi> Salomō <hi>testifieth vnto</hi> God, <hi>that he</hi> made <note n="f" place="margin">2. Chrno. 1. 8. 9.</note> him King ouer a great people, to reigne in his father Dauids stead, <hi>Therefore in the</hi> Prouerbs <hi>the</hi> Wisedome of God <hi>challengeth this power of</hi> Constituting Kings, <hi>to her selfe only, saying,</hi> By <note n="g" place="margin">Prou. 8. 15 16.</note> me Kings reigne, <hi>and</hi> by me Princes rule. <hi>This is that</hi> wisedome of God, <hi>which</hi> dwelleth with prudence, <hi>and</hi> findeth out knowledge, <hi>and</hi>
      <note place="margin">ver. 12.</note> Counsell, <hi>euen the</hi> true knowledge <hi>of the</hi> King of Heauen; <hi>without which no</hi> King <hi>can well reigne, nor beare rule</hi> on Earth. <hi>In this sence speaketh</hi> Lactantius <hi>verie soundly to the purpose:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 5. Instit. 8.</note> Therefore doth all euill and mischiefe (<hi>saith hee</hi>) daylie encrease, lying heauy and weightie vpon man, because God the maker and gouernour of this world is forsaken, and wicked Religions professed against his true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: <hi>For,</hi> All the wisedeme of man, (<hi>sayeth the same Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>)<note place="margin">See</note> consisteth in this one thing: first, to know God;<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> pag. 1. 2. 3, lati. Lib. 1.</note>
      <hi>then</hi> to worship him: <hi>So,</hi> Wisedome preceading, <hi>and</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>attending, it must be, that</hi> true Worshiping of God, <hi>is a</hi> Consequent, <hi>to a</hi> Sound knowing <hi>him, as</hi> Hee <hi>is to be</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> worshipped. <hi>Writing of this matter to</hi> your sacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>I beseech</hi> your Highnes, <hi>let mee vse here your owne words</hi>
      <note place="margin">See <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> pag. 1. 2. 3. Lattin.</note>
      <hi>for proofe to be alleaged out of your owne</hi> Booke <hi>of the Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that most noble and heroicall</hi> Prince <hi>HENRIE,</hi> our late Prince <hi>of the best and greatest hopes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the beginning of which</hi> your said Booke, your selfe <hi>doth professe,</hi> None to be meete to gouerne a Christian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nation, who doth not (how great soeuer) from his heart, worship and reuerence the diuine Godhead. <hi>And</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 1. 6. in the Latin.</note>
      <hi>proceeding further in this Argument,</hi> your Maiestie <hi>setteth downe</hi> Two degrees <hi>of this</hi> Worship <hi>from</hi> Mah to God: <hi>The one</hi> Inferiour, <hi>which</hi> ascendeth: <hi>The other</hi> Exteriour,<note place="margin">1. 2.</note>
      <hi>which</hi> descendeth. <hi>The former consisting in</hi> Prayer, <hi>and in</hi> Fayth towardes God: <hi>The latter, in</hi> Actions issuing from that Fountaine: <hi>so as that</hi> former <hi>conteineth nothing else but a right vse of</hi> Religion <hi>to be exhibited</hi> vnto God: <hi>That other, respecteth the</hi> Rule of Christ; <note n="a" place="margin">Math. 7. 12 Luke 6. 31.</note> What you would Men should doe vnto you, euen so doe yee vnto them; <hi>which is the</hi> Rule of Iustice <hi>and</hi> Equabilitie, <hi>preceptiue in the</hi> Law <hi>and</hi> Ghospell <hi>for</hi> Loue <hi>and</hi> Charitie <hi>to each other. Heere to continue this Discourse, (into which I am willingly entred, as being fitted in part to the Argument of this my Booke, treating of</hi>
      <note place="margin">See <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. pag. 7. in the Latin.</note> Prayer) <hi>I humbly craue leaue of your</hi> Maiestie, <hi>to speake here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto you, out of that your</hi> learned Treatise <hi>truly</hi> Religious, <hi>and</hi> Christianly Politique. <hi>I find in it</hi> Religion <hi>defined, that manner of worshipping God, which himselfe hath appoynted out of his manifest reuealed</hi> Will, <hi>receiuing life from a</hi> true Fayth; <hi>and so by it seemeth to be animated and quickened vnto all good Workes: also preserued by a</hi> right Conscience, <hi>and so continued in that</hi> knowledge of God, (<hi>with which he hath enlightned the</hi> Minde <hi>of man) both against</hi> Reprobation, <hi>and</hi> Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie,<note place="margin">pag. 16. lat 19.</note>
      <hi>the</hi> Leprosie <hi>of the</hi> Soule; <hi>and also against</hi> Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>the very Nurse and Fosterer of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rronious opinions perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily derogating from the truth</hi> of Gods word. <hi>This then kept sincerely pure from pollution of</hi> Sinne <hi>in</hi> Manners, <hi>and of</hi> errours <hi>in the</hi> doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> Fayth, <hi>that</hi> interiour worship of
<pb facs="6"/> God <hi>which your</hi> Grace <hi>there mentioneth, will haue an easie ascent vnto</hi> him, <hi>and be the more plausible in</hi> his sight <hi>for accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, religiously commended by</hi> Deuotion, <hi>and</hi> Zeale <hi>in</hi> Prayer.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>To enforce heere a necessitie of</hi> Prayer <hi>by Arguments (which is sufficiently treated of in the</hi> Preface, <hi>or fore-speech of this my Booke) were to set a Candle in the Sunne flaming to giue light at noone-day: For although</hi> Diuinitie, (<hi>as it is ōccupied in the</hi> Theorie <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>and</hi> heauenly thinges, <hi>both to be</hi> beleeued, <hi>and</hi> hoped for,) <hi>may seeme a</hi> speculatiue Discipline, <hi>onely for the</hi> Soules bare knowledge; <hi>yet, if the Schoole-men graunt (which argue this poynt) that</hi> Consent <hi>in beleeuing the</hi> Doctrine of Christian Fayth, <hi>is an</hi> Action <hi>of the</hi> Will <hi>and</hi> Minde <hi>of Man; it must needes follow, that</hi> Diuinitie <hi>is also a</hi> Practicque Doctrine, <hi>which requireth the same of Man: For what respecteth</hi> Consent, <hi>but</hi> Action <hi>in consequence vnto</hi> Knowledge, <hi>which was in precedence to it?</hi> Christianitie <hi>consisteth not in</hi> Wording: <hi>It is meere Vanitie, yea dissolute Securitie, to</hi> dicourse <hi>of</hi> Fayth, <hi>out of the</hi> Scriptures, <hi>and for defence thereof to alleage</hi> Theologicall reasons, <hi>and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, if also there be no</hi> Consent, <hi>and</hi> Agreement <hi>for acting the</hi> Workes <hi>thereof.</hi> Christ <hi>said to his</hi> Disciples, <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 13. 17.</note> If yee Know these thinges; blessed are yee, if yee Doe them. Doing <hi>therefore, and not</hi> Knowing <hi>onely, blesseth the</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian▪ <hi>For,</hi> Hee that <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 12. 47.</note> Knoweth▪ and Doeth not, shalbe beaten with many stripes. <hi>As so by all true consequence,</hi> Diuinitie <hi>is a</hi> Practicque Doctrine, <hi>and not onely</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricque, <hi>and</hi> Speculatiue.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>To come then to the matter of</hi> Prayer <hi>purposed, for asmuch as our</hi> Soule <hi>hath no habilitie of it selfe to deserue any thing, but must depend wholie vpon</hi> Christ; <hi>who is the</hi> true bright shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light of righteousnes <hi>for all grace working acceptance before</hi> God, (<hi>which not obteined, all</hi> knowledge contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue <hi>is idle, and vnprofitable) wee must needs holdit very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary (The state of the</hi> Soule, <hi>thus disabled through it owne infirmities) that wee attend vpon</hi> Prayer <hi>sedulously and seriously,
<pb facs="7"/> by it in</hi> Christs <hi>name to call vnto</hi> God <hi>for his</hi> Spirit, <hi>to lighten our</hi> vnderstanding <hi>with the iufluences of his</hi> Grace, <hi>which is only powerfull vnto all virtue, as [to analogize great things to small] may be obserued in the</hi> Moone, <hi>to worke vpon these in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour</hi> Sublimarie bodies, <hi>in euerie one (after their seuerall qualities and natures) conformably to the</hi> Light <hi>it receiueth from the</hi> Sunne. <hi>There is no assurance to the</hi> Elect <hi>and</hi> Godly <hi>of obteining either</hi> spirituall Graces, <hi>or otherwise the</hi> fauour of God, <hi>for any other</hi> temperall Benefites, <hi>but by</hi> Fayth. <hi>This is the</hi> Sollicitor, <hi>that maketh the motions in the</hi> celestiall Star-chamber <hi>befort the</hi> Throane of the high Iudge <hi>of our</hi> Souls <hi>for accesse of our</hi> Supplicatorie Requestes, <hi>to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented and pleaded there, by our</hi> Aduocat Christ. <hi>And how doth</hi> Fayth <hi>make these motions, but by</hi> Prayer <hi>onely? For as</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, Lib. 1. pag. 11 in the latin.</note> Fayth <hi>in that your</hi> Maiesties Princely Institution <hi>is truely sayd to bee the</hi> Nurse, <hi>and</hi> Cherisher <hi>of all</hi> Religion, <hi>and</hi> Pietie. <hi>So is</hi> Prayer <hi>there also said to be the fosterer, aduancer, and mainteynor of this religiouse</hi> true Catholicque Fayth; <hi>by which is wrought in our mindes a firme perswasion, and sure ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehention of</hi> God his Promises; <hi>as</hi> your Highnesse <hi>hath there defined, calling it that</hi> Golden Chaine, <hi>by which the</hi> faythfull Soule <hi>is lincked, and annexed vnto</hi> Christ: <hi>for in him onely are they made; and to the</hi> godly <hi>by him, and for him, shallbe alwayes</hi> yea <hi>and</hi> Amen.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The</hi> Faythfull assurance <hi>of the</hi> Godly, <hi>is in</hi> 1. grounding, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <hi>and</hi> 2. guarding. <hi>If then the</hi> Godly <hi>will be</hi> grounded <hi>as the</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Mount Sion, <hi>which cannot bee remoued but standeth fast for euer; And</hi> guarded <hi>as</hi> Ierusalem, <hi>which is compassed about with Hilles on euery side; Let them bee intentiue to</hi> continuall Prayer, <hi>which cherisheth their</hi> fayth, <hi>setling it in</hi> Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, <hi>whereby it is made strang against</hi> all <note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 6. 16.</note> the firie Darts <hi>of</hi> the wicked, <hi>And to</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Pet. 5. 9.</note> resist the Diuell. <hi>So as</hi> Prayer, <hi>next to</hi> Preaching the Word, <hi>ought most specially to bee had in esteeme and regard of vs: But first in place, is the</hi> diuine Word, <hi>out of which</hi> God <hi>speaketh vnto vs by his</hi> Ministers, <hi>and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structeth our Consciences in the</hi> true knowledge of his Fayth,
<pb facs="7"/> (<hi>for</hi> Fayth <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10. 17</note> is by hearing,) <hi>and therefore great care, and diligence is to be vsed, in hearing frequently the</hi> sacred Doctrine <hi>with</hi> attention <hi>and</hi> reuerence, <hi>as</hi> your Maiestie<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. pag. 5.</note> aduiseth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Next to it, succeedeth</hi> Prayer, <hi>for the very speciall vse and necessitie thereof as may appeare prooued both in the</hi> examples <hi>of the</hi> godly <hi>practizing it, &amp; also in the</hi> exhortatiue precepts <hi>giuen for it throughout the whole body of the</hi> Scripture, <hi>and so</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. pag. 12. in the Lattin</note> (<hi>as I take it) vnderstood of your</hi> Highnesse <hi>commending next to that most</hi> absolute forme of Prayer <hi>made by our</hi> Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christ, <hi>the</hi> diuine Psalms <hi>of</hi> Dauid, <hi>from whence▪ as out of a rich Ʋaine, and pure Fountaine, may plentifully bee taken, those formes of</hi> Prayers <hi>and</hi> Supplica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ions <hi>that may make for either</hi> 1. Necessitie, <hi>or for</hi> 2. Comfort▪ <hi>Now that the</hi> Ministry<note place="margin">1. 2.</note>
      <hi>of the</hi> word preached, <hi>hath of right a precedence to</hi> Praier; <hi>and that</hi> Prayer, <hi>in the next place is subordinated therto as a subsequent, may thus appeare; For that the</hi> Word, <hi>being the</hi> ground <hi>of</hi> Gods promises <hi>in</hi> Christ, <hi>signed to vs by the</hi> Seale <hi>of</hi> his Spirit, <hi>wee had neede to bee first instructed by it, how that</hi> God <hi>being not as man that hee should lie, or repent him of the good hee purposeth to his Children, is verie</hi> Truth it selfe, <hi>and so secureth them of performance, in asmuch. as hee knoweth it to bee a part of his</hi> glorie (<hi>whereof hee is alwayes ielouse) to performe what hee promiseth in his Word.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Againe, the</hi> Nature <hi>and</hi> Effectes <hi>of</hi> Prayer, <hi>both what it is in it selfe, and how to be confined, and also, what force it hath in working to the good of them that vse it, is also first to be learned; which cannot be had before it be taught out of the said</hi> diuine Word. <hi>Hereby our</hi> Fayth <hi>well instructed, addresseth it selfe the more boldly and soundly to</hi> Prayer, <hi>which is a singuler prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue</hi> of Gods high seruice <hi>for his</hi> Glorie <hi>vouchsafed his</hi> Children; <hi>Yea, and commaunded to be offered vp of them at all times, for the supplying all their wantes, both in</hi> spirituall Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>to the</hi> Soules good, <hi>and also in</hi> Temporall commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>to the</hi> welfare <hi>of the</hi> Body. <hi>At all which times, wee are specially to haue good respect of our</hi> behauiour <hi>and</hi> gesture <hi>in</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/> Praying, <hi>that it be with all</hi> Reuerence <hi>due to such a</hi> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, <hi>that filleth the</hi> Heauens. <hi>For if a</hi> Subiect <hi>may not dare</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>at▪</note>
      <hi>to present himselfe before the</hi> King (<hi>whether by Petition, or otherwise) but submissely and accommodately; How much lesse is any</hi> Man▪ (<hi>who is mortall) to presume to call vnto the</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie GOD, <hi>as to his companion and fellow?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In deed a wise discreete Man will not appeare before any of</hi> eminent Superioritie, <hi>to aske any thing at his hands, but well pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pared euery way in</hi> reuerent Gesture, <hi>and</hi> fitting Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; <hi>for hee bringeth his Errand with him well furnished▪ If then such prouident care be had of worldly</hi> Authoritie <hi>for worldly respectes how ought we to be aduised in what sort &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wee doe present our selues, and our speaches, before the</hi> Lord God, <hi>crauing of him</hi> Spirituall graces. <hi>Of all these pointes, I haue spoken in the</hi> Preface, <hi>to my Booke sufficiently (I hope,) and I may say also of purpose, for the instruction of some</hi> Readers, <hi>perhaps not so throughly learned in the knowledge of them, as the necessitie thereof requireth: Needlesse therefore may seeme heere any commentation vpon a Subiect of this Nature. But vouchsas▪ mee herein your most</hi> Gracious <hi>aspect, I hambly craue it; and bee pleased to know, that your</hi> Highnes first Booke <hi>of your <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> in concurrence of this matter corresponding to mine, did first induce mee to insert this Discourse, and hath continued mee also in it vnto this extent of longitude; the which being graciously pardoned of</hi> your Maiestie, <hi>J may hope of a fauourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction in the</hi> Argument <hi>it selfe thus discussed: For, as in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussing the</hi> matter <hi>and</hi> subiect <hi>of my</hi> Booke (<hi>which is made specially for</hi> Prayer,) <hi>I follow the common stile of</hi> Dedicatories <hi>for example, which all in a manner doe the same: So, hauing in purpose to consecrate it vnto</hi> your Highnes, <hi>I thought it very meete for appl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>use to fashion, in some sort, the handling of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contayned therein out of that</hi> your Maiesties Booke, <hi>as it were by a suffragie from</hi> your owne mouth <hi>witnessing the</hi> Truth <hi>of what is alleaged from thence in</hi> my writing, <hi>and so to commende it to the</hi> censure <hi>of the indicious and wise</hi> Reader. <hi>Were I either able for</hi> Learning, <hi>or for my</hi> Person <hi>worthy to
<pb facs="8"/> blaze, and decipher the singuler, and most eminent endowments of nature (wherewith the</hi> Diuine Maiestie, <hi>from aboue hath boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully enriched, and gratiously blessed</hi> your sacred Maiestie) <hi>I would most gladly (as already acknowledged of others) so to their learned</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udgments <hi>ascribe my opinion also in particuler, for a testimonie of my</hi> Loyall heart <hi>vnfeinedly deuoted to the best and highest thoughts that is fit for</hi> Subiects <hi>of</hi> true allegeance <hi>and</hi> Fealtie <hi>to carrie of your</hi> Highnesse <hi>honourable, heroicall, and well deseruing</hi> Prayses. <hi>Notwithstanding that I may not seeme to forget carelesly the Lawes of dedicatorie writings or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose neglect, for feare to bee reputed a flatterer in following them (which drawing to the conclusion, doe commonly insert in the</hi> Catastrophe <hi>a commemoration of personall commendations▪) J will capitulate some few speaches of that sense, such as I haue read, recorded, and published in other mens</hi> Writinges, <hi>and so after this manner onely, as it were by my</hi> bare suffragie, <hi>applaude in assent to the</hi> truth <hi>of their</hi> renowming encomies. <hi>Your</hi> Maiesties Kingdomes <hi>and</hi> Dominions <hi>consisting of a</hi> Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold gouernement; <hi>the one</hi> Spirituall <hi>in all</hi> Church-causes, <hi>and ouer</hi> all Persons: <hi>The other</hi> Temporall, <hi>for the managing of</hi> Ciuill <hi>and</hi> Politique affayres <hi>with great dexteritie both</hi> supreame <hi>and</hi> soueraigne, <hi>is therefore celebrated to be</hi> beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified highly, <hi>in the wordes of</hi> excellent Knowledge, Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Prudence, Iustice, Religion, <hi>and</hi> Godlinesse: <hi>which must needes be those</hi> Princely qualities▪ <hi>for which</hi> your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse (<hi>as one sayeth) beeing eminent, wee▪</hi> your Subiectes <hi>are, and shalbe, the happier.—Your</hi> Theologicall Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>and</hi> Learning <hi>in matters of</hi> Religion; <hi>your witten <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, and other</hi> your Bookes, <hi>and</hi> sundry Speaches, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant &amp; in the</hi> Eye <hi>of the</hi> World, <hi>can sufficiently witnesse: yet for more specialtie it is made knowne, &amp; manifessed in that</hi> int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutorie Conference <hi>mentioned of mee before in this</hi> Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie; <hi>Of which I reade these seuerall</hi> Iudgments <hi>giuen out by great</hi> persons <hi>of</hi> State, <hi>and</hi> High note, eare-witnesses <hi>the same time of your</hi> Maiesties <hi>entercourse speeches, then vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered &amp; auerred, to haue been such as that one sayeth, J</hi> am fully
<pb facs="9"/> perswaded, that his Maiestie spake by the instinct of the<note place="margin">Conference. pag. 83. 84.</note> spirit of God. <hi>Another saith, that</hi> hee had often heard <hi>and</hi> read, <hi>that,</hi> Rex est mixta persona cum Sacerdote; <hi>But</hi> hee neuer saw the truth thereof, till that day. <hi>And a third, accomodating his testimonie in truth to these, writeth; That the Title of a</hi> liuing Librarie, <hi>and of</hi> walking Studie, <hi>might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/>
      <hi>fit</hi> your Maiestie: <hi>for which cause he sayth further; That</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the Preface to the Reader.</note>
      <hi>it was pittie to loose</hi> one Sillable <hi>of your</hi> admirable Speeches: <hi>The</hi> words <hi>whereof there, and then vttered by</hi> your Highnes <hi>in that Conference bieng</hi> like Apples of Gold, with pictures of Siluer <hi>for the apt fitting them in their places conueniently, and iudiciously. Nay the same partie sayth further, That your</hi> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie <hi>did so admirably both for</hi> vnderstanding, Speech, <hi>and</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 20.</note> Iudgment, <hi>handle the points there propounded, as that they were sent away (vpon the breaking vp) not with</hi> Contentment <hi>onely, but</hi> astonishment.—<hi>And as touching your</hi> Politicque wisdome, Prudence, <hi>and</hi> Iustice <hi>in</hi> State affaires, <hi>thereby administred and brought into</hi> good Gouernment: <hi>Yea, as one</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the Preface to the Reader</note>
      <hi>sayeth, (to vse his owne wordes) beautifying it to</hi> Gods glorie, <hi>with the</hi> Churches good, <hi>as many may with truth acknowledge</hi>
      <note place="margin">Conference.</note>
      <hi>it, as haue</hi> loyall Hearts <hi>deuoted to a truth, and will be well affected in sinceritie to testifie and confesse the same vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But neither is here wanting publique Testimonie hereof, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s to the Catholicques Supplication</note>
      <hi>as I finde it also auouched in print; Such to be the</hi> rare Perfections,▪ <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d</hi> admirable Guiftes <hi>of the aboue-said</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues <hi>wherewith the bountifull hand of</hi> Gods diuine Maiestie <hi>hath endued</hi> your Maiestie, <hi>as in the</hi> deapth <hi>of</hi> your proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Iudgement, <hi>wee doubt not, but you foresee, what concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth both the</hi> Spirituall, <hi>and</hi> Temporall gouernment <hi>of all your</hi> Kingdomes <hi>and</hi> Dominions.—<hi>Then well said hee, who thus said.</hi> Our dutie, <hi>as wee are Men (yea, I may say, as wee are</hi> true Subiectes,) <hi>to be</hi> an acknowledgment of our setled State in your Royall person.—<hi>Many more Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Preface to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</note>
      <hi>of a deserued Truth in this kind, might be heere alleadged. But to</hi> your Maiestie (<hi>whose</hi> humble deportment <hi>in those
<pb facs="9"/> your</hi> most eminent Sublimities <hi>hath alwayes held suspected all</hi> wordes <hi>of</hi> Prayses <hi>in</hi> commendation <hi>of</hi> your owne person) <hi>these alreadie cited, may seeme perhaps, distastfull, and so reiected, as not acceptance-worthy. If it be offensiue thus in the Phrase and Stile of others to write vnto</hi> your Maiestie <hi>of</hi> your selfe, <hi>as it were,</hi> in os laudare; <hi>yet because it hath the Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a</hi> loyall Heart <hi>deuoted to the</hi> best Thoughts (<hi>as I haue said) of your</hi> rare Virtues <hi>much</hi> prayse worthy; <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meete to be vttered at all times, as occasion fitly serueth, both in</hi> writing <hi>and</hi> speaking <hi>without d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssimulation, I may hope also it to be pardonable; And therefore am yet further bold in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie to craue</hi> your Graces most gracious fauourable leaue <hi>to adioyne to these former, mine owne priuate commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your</hi> singuler clemencie, <hi>and</hi> benignitie <hi>towards</hi> your Subiectes. <hi>For among all those guiftes of</hi> Grace, <hi>and</hi> Nature, (<hi>which are in</hi> your Maiestie <hi>for</hi> varietie <hi>manifold, and for their</hi> worth <hi>very</hi> singuler) <hi>none yet for</hi> applause <hi>generally may seeme rightly superiorating that of</hi> Bountie, <hi>and</hi> Clemencie, <hi>noted of all in</hi> your Grace <hi>more eminent, as remarkable for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie presidented particulers. A memorable virtue, and eternizing Memorie; the which as it is best agreeable to mans Nature; so, beseeming none more then</hi> Kinges <hi>and</hi> Princes, (<hi>as they write,) because it conciliateth and breedeth the</hi> loue <hi>of</hi> their Subiectes; <hi>by which both</hi> Securitie, <hi>issuing therefrom, and also</hi> Stabilitie; <hi>proceeding out of it, is gotten, and procured to the</hi> common good <hi>of all subiected to their</hi> gouernment; <hi>whom, rather to</hi> finde good, <hi>and</hi> dutifull, <hi>then otherwise to</hi> make such, <hi>is</hi> honour <hi>to them; which is, to feare not a King, but for a King: And this to doe▪ is a strengthning</hi> safetie <hi>both to</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Subiectes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Wise</hi> Tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tus, <hi>giueth this Precept of a</hi> pittying Iustice, <hi>To</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Agric.</note>
      <hi>be</hi> content <hi>most often with the</hi> Repentance of one offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>and not often to</hi> punish all offenses: <hi>Yea, saith</hi> Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian <hi>the</hi> Poet; <hi>It is a kind of</hi> Punishment <hi>to see an</hi> Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour <hi>deiected with</hi> true Sorrow <hi>for his</hi> faultes, submisly entreating pardon. <hi>This is that</hi> true Magnanimitie, <hi>which your</hi> Basilicon <hi>treateth of, and aduiseth to be imbraced: Not</hi> in
<pb facs="10"/> taking reuengement, <hi>but</hi> by accompting him, <hi>that</hi> hath offended, vnworthy your Anger; <hi>and so by</hi> ouer-swaying that Passion, <hi>to</hi> triumph, <hi>and</hi> ioy greatly in this, <hi>that you</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 2. pag. 100.</note>
      <hi>haue commaunded</hi> your selfe, (<hi>yea against your owne will) to</hi> graunt Pardon.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And this by way of Counsell there written of</hi> your Maiestie, <hi>appeareth through your owne practize in this</hi> your Graces milde gouernment <hi>ouer vs, to haue been set downe</hi> in great iudgement, <hi>long premedit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ted and purposed for</hi> action; <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and rightly vnderstanding, that it causeth</hi> Man <hi>by imitation, to draw</hi> neerest vnto God, <hi>whose</hi> Mercie, <hi>and</hi> louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, <hi>is aboue all his</hi> Workes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>For this cause, are</hi> Kinges <hi>and</hi> Princes <hi>in the</hi> Scripture,<note place="margin">Psal. 82. 6.</note>
      <hi>tearmed</hi> Gods, <hi>that they being by function</hi> Lieuetenants <hi>to</hi> GOD <hi>vpon</hi> Earth, <hi>should also expressely imitate, in their Rule</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioel. 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>and Gouernment, this</hi> diuine Virtue (<hi>appropriated to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,) of</hi> Clemencie, Patience, <hi>and</hi> long Suffering. <hi>A virtue so highly applauded and magnified of the</hi> Heathen, <hi>that (as</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle <hi>writeth) Many</hi> Philosophers haue attributed diuine honours to it, <hi>calling it</hi> Beneficence <hi>of</hi> doing good. <hi>And</hi> Seneca <hi>will haue</hi> that onely Lightning <hi>which</hi> Iupiter <hi>sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth foorth, to be most plaucible and milde; herein hauing refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to those kind of</hi> Lightnings <hi>which the</hi> Latines <hi>call</hi> albas Manubias, <hi>and sayd to be harmelesse, for that they are made by</hi> Iupiter <hi>in a friendly traiection, and shooting foorth to the Sunne without offence to any.—This was a constant opinion of</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie; <hi>doing thereby to vnderstand, that</hi> Iupiter (<hi>whom they tooke to be the</hi> Prince <hi>of the</hi> Gods,) <hi>is neuer</hi> angrie <hi>at any, neuer</hi> hurteth <hi>or</hi> violateth; <hi>neither</hi> iudgeth <hi>&amp;</hi> condemneth <hi>any. This, though fabulously deliuered in the writinges of those auncient, both</hi> Philosophers <hi>and</hi> Poets, <hi>doth yet seeme paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelwise to keepe the same proportion, with the like, au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rred by the</hi> Hebrewes, <hi>concerning the common calamities of</hi> Plagues, Pestilence, Diseases, <hi>and other</hi> Casualties, <hi>happening to Man for a</hi> chastisement of Sinne: <hi>in which respect, all such kind of Euill, is called</hi> Malum paenae, <hi>and in this name sent from</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/> God, <hi>as the</hi> Scripture <hi>teacheth.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isay 45 7. Amos 3. 6.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Notwithstanding (say they) these Euils come not from</hi> God immediatly, <hi>as from the</hi> efficient prime cause <hi>to be taken for the</hi> chiefe Author <hi>of them; but are deriued by a</hi> certaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent<note place="margin">Bodin de repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. lib. 4.</note>
      <hi>from a</hi> middle intercurrent cause not inhibiting <hi>and</hi> restraining <hi>the ordinarie or extraordinarie course of them; the which</hi> cause, <hi>they in their vsuall speach expresse by the word</hi> Hiphil: <hi>Not thereby denying his</hi> Iustice, <hi>but preferring his</hi> Mercie <hi>and</hi> Clemencie; forgiuing <hi>rather then</hi> punishing:<note place="margin">Psal. 103. 8, Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 9. 9.</note>
      <hi>which causeth in his</hi> Children <hi>a</hi> Sonly feare, <hi>tempered with an</hi> obseruant Loue, <hi>prescribed to</hi> Kings <hi>as an example for imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that so they doe honour</hi> God in Heauen <hi>by this virtue of whom</hi> themselues <hi>are honoured on</hi> Earth, <hi>by that his owne</hi> Title. <hi>How, and in what Tearmes this is performed,</hi> your<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 2. pag. 23. 25. 24. 25.</note> Maiestie <hi>sheweth in that your Comparison of a</hi> King, <hi>and a</hi> Tyrant, <hi>by apt Notes differencing them: where you define a</hi> King <hi>to be as a</hi> Father indulgent, <hi>and a</hi> Lord, Soueraigne, <hi>but not</hi> vnkind: <hi>one, not so much</hi> borne <hi>to his people a</hi> King, <hi>as</hi> giuen <hi>of</hi> God <hi>from aboue, for their</hi> good <hi>and</hi> tranquillitie, <hi>conserued through holesome</hi> Lawes, <hi>thereby procuring</hi> Loue; <hi>which he must accompt for his</hi> Sanctuarie, <hi>and onely</hi> Refuge. <hi>A most luculent</hi> Testimonie, <hi>seeming to be instructed from out the voice of</hi> Nature it selfe, <hi>suffragating thereto in Truth; and so to receiue a worthy allowance the more plausibly. For</hi> Nature <hi>hath framed the</hi> chiefe Maister-ruling Bee, <hi>which is the</hi> King <hi>in the</hi> Swarme <hi>of</hi> Bees, <hi>without</hi> Sting, <hi>of purpose, that it might not annoy and hurt any of the</hi> lesser Bees, <hi>which are vnto him as his</hi> Subiectes, <hi>to follow, and attend him at commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>This Discourse,</hi> my dread Soueraigne, <hi>wherein speaking to</hi> your selfe, <hi>I haue spoken of</hi> your selfe (<hi>I trust not too boldly, because truly loyally,) I will end with the words of</hi> Cassiodorus;<note place="margin">In Agric.</note> Mercie <hi>and</hi> Clemencie <hi>is that</hi> only virtue, <hi>to which</hi> all other virtues <hi>refuse not in honour to giue</hi> the preheminence. <hi>If to haue taken in hand this</hi> Argument, <hi>and to haue accommodated it to</hi> your Royall person <hi>in this manner prayseably, bee an</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/> ouer-fight blame-worthy, <hi>I may say (vnder your</hi> Highnes <hi>reformation) that I presumed vpon the nature and qualitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and so hope for the</hi> Argument <hi>sake, which is of</hi> Clemencie, <hi>a resplendent virtue in your person, (being also entertained in</hi> Truth, <hi>and discoursed in</hi> Loyaltie,) <hi>to finde accordingly a</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable pardoning Construction; <hi>which most humbly I craue of your</hi> Maiestie, <hi>to be the same (if you please) which</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonsus King of Aragon, (<hi>a most</hi> victorious, <hi>and</hi> learned King) <hi>gaue of one</hi> Lucas <hi>a</hi> Phisicions <hi>demonstratiue Oration, in it, highly commending the</hi> King <hi>to his face. If those thinges, saith</hi> Alphonsus, <hi>which thou hast reported of mee, be true,</hi> I heartily thanke the immortall Gods: <hi>If otherwise,</hi> I humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beseech them <hi>to cause, that they may be true in mee.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Howsoeuer this my commendatorie is accepted of</hi> your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, <hi>I for mine owne part, am so well instructed in those former Testimonies of</hi> your Regall virtues, <hi>and alleadged of mee, of right, (so occasioned for the credite of them) as to conclude this matter, by your Gracious patience. I rest in the iudgmentes of sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> great personages (both sometimes of</hi> you honourable pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Councell) <hi>now deceased, and say with them in their wordes: The first speaking thus.</hi> This whole Land was much bound to GOD, for setting ouer vs, a King so Wise, Learned, and Iudicious. <hi>The other thus acknowledged; that,</hi> We were very much bound to GOD▪ that had giuen vs a King of an vnderstanding Heart: <hi>Which appearing manifestly in sundry particulers of</hi> your blessed Gouernment, <hi>is yet chiefely and most singulerly ennobled by</hi> your Maiesties heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Spirit, <hi>diuinely instincted to plead</hi> Gods cause <hi>against his, and your</hi> Enemies; <hi>whose</hi> Supplication <hi>offred vp to your</hi> Highnes <hi>in the beginning of your</hi> Reigne <hi>ouer vs for</hi> Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Anno Domi. 1603.</note> of Poperie, (<hi>a</hi> false vsurped Cathollecisime (<hi>in right tearmes) an</hi> Idolatrous Superstition, <hi>diametrally opposite to the</hi> very true Catholicque Religion, <hi>as blending of</hi> Truth, <hi>and</hi> Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sehood,) <hi>your</hi> Maiestie <hi>hath repelled; and is well accepted, with ominous acclamations (as I may say) of all</hi> true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Subiectes, <hi>to the best secured safeite of</hi> your sacred
<pb facs="11"/> Royall person <hi>vnder</hi> GOD, <hi>whose Houour you haue thus vnidicated, by continuing the</hi> Ghospell <hi>among vs, to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ine foorth for the enlightning the</hi> Hemisphere <hi>of this our</hi> Church, <hi>vnder whose roofe the</hi> Arke of God <hi>may not permit the</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listims <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam 5. 3. 4.</note> Dagon of Ashdod <hi>to haue footing. For away with all them, who with the</hi> same Tongue <hi>sweare by the</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Zeph. 1. 5.</note> Lord, <hi>and sweare by</hi> Milcham, <hi>and yet pretend a</hi> holy Worship to him, <hi>whose</hi> Name <hi>they doe thus dishonour. Hee is a plaine</hi> Ephraimite, <hi>that for</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Iudg. 12 6.</note> Shiboleth, <hi>pronounceth</hi> Sibboleth. <hi>No</hi> lisping-halting Laodicean hypocrite, <hi>can be a</hi> True professer of Gods Religion. Neutralitie <hi>is a Birth of</hi> Luke-warmenesse; <hi>which is, and is not: Would bee, but dare not bee; aad therefore</hi> seemeth onely, <hi>as temporizing with the present. Who are such, are meere</hi> Politicians, double-faced <hi>like</hi> Ianus; <hi>yea</hi> blind, <hi>though</hi> seeing: <hi>and</hi> deafe, <hi>though</hi> hearing: <hi>without all Sense, and feeling of</hi> Truth, <hi>because they are possessed with</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ares; <hi>and</hi> faint-hearted, doubting <hi>all thinges, and</hi> mistrustfull <hi>of all: Which make</hi> Religion, <hi>a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of</hi> indifferencie, <hi>and</hi> arbitrarie, <hi>left to their</hi> choyse, <hi>to make the</hi> Lord, <hi>or</hi> Baal. GOD: <hi>yea, and if they</hi> refuse Baal, <hi>in</hi> this sense; <hi>yet to follow the</hi> Lord <hi>that is the</hi> true GOD, <hi>as themselues please, and so to</hi> Worship <hi>him in</hi> part, <hi>after their owne corrupt fancies, But the</hi> wrath <hi>of</hi> God <hi>is vpon such, and Iudgement hath alreadie taken hold of them, which is theate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in</hi> Isaiah: <hi>To</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Isa. 6. 9. 10.</note> Heare in deed, and not to vnderstand: <hi>To</hi> See plainely, and not to perceiue; <hi>by reason, that</hi> their Heart <hi>is made</hi> fatte, <hi>both to a</hi> heauinesse of the Eares, <hi>and</hi> to the shutting vp of the Eyes, <hi>that they might</hi> not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert and be healed. <hi>A heauie Iudgement. But the</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>of</hi> GOD, <hi>and the</hi> Altar (<hi>which</hi> Iohn <hi>meant by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntment of the</hi> Angell <hi>in the</hi> Apocalips,) <hi>is not for these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Reue. 11. 1.</note> Worship <hi>therein: for they being prophane and reprobate, are for the</hi> Court (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) <hi>onely with-out the</hi> Temple, <hi>not measured, but refused, and giuen to the</hi> Gentiles. <hi>To whom</hi> God <hi>speaketh in</hi> Ezekiel; <note n="f" place="margin">Ezek. 20. 39</note> Goe yee, and serue euery one his Idole, seeing yee will not obey mee. <hi>And</hi> Christ <hi>telleth
<pb facs="12"/> them, that</hi> he will <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 10 33.</note> denie them before his Father in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>because they haue</hi> denied him before Men in Earth.<note place="margin">2. Timo. 2. 12.</note>
      <hi>Who these bee, are knowne by the print of the</hi> Name <hi>of the</hi> Beast, <hi>whom they</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Reue. 14. 9.</note> Worship, marked in their foreheads: <hi>whose punishment is there also set downe, euen</hi> Torments in Fire <hi>and</hi>
      <note place="margin">ver. 10. 11.</note> Brimstone <hi>without ceasing: A most iust reward of all</hi> Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, <hi>and</hi> Apostataes, <hi>which either</hi> counterfeite Holines, <hi>or</hi> reuolt from their Fayth; <hi>and so are lincked in fast to the</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Reue. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Whore <hi>of</hi> Babilon, <hi>and</hi> drunke of the Wine of her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. <hi>But on the other side, they, which</hi> feare God, and <note n="e" place="margin">Reue 14. 7.</note> worship him that made Heauen, and Earth, the Sea, and the Fountaines of Waters; <hi>are also knowne by a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent note, euen</hi> by their <note n="f" place="margin">Reuel. 14. 1.</note> Fathers Name, written in their foreheads, <hi>for they are not ashamed of their</hi> Profession, <hi>beeing the</hi> Sainctes <hi>which keepe the</hi> Commandements of God, <hi>and</hi>
      <note place="margin">ver. 12.</note> the Fayth of Iesus: <hi>All such▪ shall</hi> cease from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,<note place="margin">ver. 13.</note> and their Workes follow them: <hi>For,</hi> these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing <note n="g" place="margin">Math. 10. 32.</note> Christ <hi>here,</hi> before Men, <hi>are</hi> also confessed of Christ before his Father, which is in Heauen: <hi>and</hi> before <note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 12. 8.</note> the Angels of God, <hi>I was put in minde of this Note, by your</hi> Maiesties wordes <hi>of</hi> your selfe, <hi>in your</hi> Basilicon, <hi>say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. pag. 4.</note> I haue neuer been ashamed to professe openly, what I thought of GOD. <hi>True, for what</hi> your Highnes <hi>haue thought of</hi> God, <hi>and of his</hi> Worship, <hi>is so well manifested, as there needes no disputation to satisfie any not parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lly minded; much lesse the euill</hi> Tounged, <hi>and the</hi> malicious Carpers, <hi>who calumniously, and faulsely, haue otherwise traduced</hi> your Maiesties Name <hi>by that imputation. If Wishes may take effect, they are not wanting to your</hi> good Subiectes, <hi>against as many as</hi> haue euill will at Sion, <hi>and seeke to disturbe the</hi> Peace of Israel, <hi>laying</hi> Cockatrices Egges <hi>in the shade of secret</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, <hi>to haue them hatched by some</hi> thunderclaps of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>and other</hi> Trecherous practises <hi>whatsoeuer. O that these of</hi> Pelops race <hi>were all abandoned from hence, if any be</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ic. ad Att. lib. 15. ept.▪ 1.</note>
      <hi>here yet residing in your</hi> Maiesties Realme <hi>or</hi> Realmes, <hi>so as their</hi> Names <hi>be not once heard amongst vs.</hi> Paul <hi>taxeth the</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/> Corinthians, <hi>in that they had entred into fellowship with</hi> Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, <hi>partaking with them</hi> in outward Idolatrie, <hi>as forsaking their first loue: seeming thereby, to haue</hi> receiued the Grace of God in vaine, <hi>to which they were called; and telleth them, that they were</hi> vnequally <note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 6. ver 14 ver. 15. ver. 16.</note> yoaked, <hi>for,</hi> Light hath no communion with Darknesse; <hi>nor,</hi> Christ with Beliall hath any concord; <hi>nor,</hi> the Temple of God, with Idols. <hi>So likewise, what part hath the</hi> Protestant <hi>with the</hi> Papist; <hi>and the true</hi> Ghospellers, <hi>with the</hi> hollow-hearted Neuters? <hi>There can be nothing betweene these: though they</hi> are <note n="b" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 19.</note> among vs, <hi>yet</hi> are they not of vs: <hi>For, can their</hi> Leprous rotten<note place="margin">See the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoise. Sect. 12.</note> affections <hi>entertaine any</hi> true Thought <hi>of either</hi> Zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes GOD, <hi>or of</hi> Loyaltie <hi>to</hi> your Maiestie, <hi>who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> Positions <hi>most dangerously Trayterous in opposition di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly against both the</hi> one <hi>and the</hi> other. <hi>The Emperour</hi> Constantine <hi>by his</hi> politicque Proclamation, <hi>discouered</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 1. Tripart. hist. cap. 7.</note>
      <hi>the</hi> dissembling of Christianitie <hi>in some of his</hi> Subiectes; <hi>whom therevpon hee banished, and sayd,</hi> Seeing they were not faythfull to God, much lesse would they be to him. <hi>I leaue this concluded with</hi> S. Hieroms <hi>Iudgement;</hi> There can bee no sound affection of them to each other, whose Profession of Fayth, and Religion, is not the same, but diuerse.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And now to come to the matter, for which this</hi> Dedicatorie <hi>is to</hi> your Maiestie, <hi>that I might put my selfe and others in minde of</hi> our dutie <hi>towardes</hi> GOD; <hi>the which beeing first knowne, is subordinatly next, and the more readily, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully discharged vnto</hi> your Highnesse person.—<hi>I haue written this</hi> Treatise <hi>intituled the</hi> Miscellanie of Orizons, <hi>being the</hi> Argument <hi>in chiefe; prefacing it with certaine</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler preparatiues <hi>instructing the</hi> deuotion <hi>vnto</hi> Prayer. <hi>To which also are annexed certaine</hi> Meditations <hi>of the</hi> Lords Supper, <hi>and of</hi> Mortalitie; <hi>all for the aduauncing the</hi> Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare <hi>of the</hi> Christian Soule. <hi>An</hi> Argument <hi>of necessarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence in this great dotage, of the World possessed generally with the</hi> Spirit of slumber, <hi>and</hi> securitie; <hi>through which,</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>is become cold, as seeming altogeather deaded in the frozen dregges of</hi> Sensualitie, <hi>obdurating the</hi> Consciences <hi>for want of</hi> Fayth, <hi>which by no meanes is better cherished, encreased, and mainetained, then by</hi> Praier; <hi>as to</hi> your Maiestie <hi>is wel knowne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Lib. 1. pag. 12. lat. 14.</note>
      <hi>appoynting it to be</hi> frequent, solitarie, <hi>and</hi> priuate, <hi>yea specially in Bed aswell as</hi> publicque; at all times vpon occasion, as the Minde suggested, with exception to all vnlawfull Matters, which cannot be of Fayth: <hi>And,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 14. 23.</note> Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not of Fayth, is sinne.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>It is a</hi> Worke <hi>framed to the seuerall vses of all sorts of Men, of all degrees in a manner, to be practized by them as</hi> necessitie <hi>requireth (my hope is) to the</hi> benefite, <hi>and</hi> comfort in the Lord, <hi>of as many, as shall delight in the practize of a</hi> Christian Fayth by Prayer. <hi>For it cannot bee, (in whom soeuor the</hi> cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiall fire <hi>of a</hi> feruent Fayth <hi>is</hi> kindled, <hi>though for a time it may seeme perhaps to be suppressed) but the same will breake foorth into a flame of that Godly zeale which</hi> Paul <hi>testifit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Coloss. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13.</note> Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras <hi>to haue had for the</hi> Colossians, <hi>striuing for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that they might stand perfect, and full in all the will of God. <hi>This</hi> Worke <hi>I huue presumed to publish vnder the</hi> Protection <hi>and</hi> Patronage <hi>of</hi> your Maiesties name, <hi>for the better acceptance abroad with applause.—It beareth a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of my</hi> Loyall Heart <hi>towardes</hi> your Highnesse; <hi>to whom all my endeuours, of what nature soeuer, are most specially due. And for my</hi> Religious intention <hi>to doe thereby also a</hi> common good, <hi>my hope is, it will the rather be well accepted. For I may not doubt, least it be preiudiced by the hard censure of a</hi> needlesse, <hi>and</hi> superfluous Writing, <hi>because of the great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie, and multitude of</hi> Bookes <hi>of</hi> the same Argument.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The</hi> materiall Temple, <hi>was re-edified vnder</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>by the labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s, paines, and imployments of sundry &amp; diuers</hi> Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>euen by accommodating</hi> things <hi>of the</hi> same Nature, <hi>as Lime, Stones, Wood Yron, &amp;c. So may it be said of the</hi> studies <hi>and</hi> endeuors of learned Wittes, <hi>which labour in</hi> their Writings, <hi>by</hi> knowledge <hi>to further &amp; erect the</hi> Building <hi>of</hi> the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Temple, <hi>though for</hi> matter <hi>and</hi> subiect, <hi>one and the same.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <p>
      <hi>The manner of penning</hi> this Worke, <hi>may seeme strange for order and composition: likewise for</hi> Matter <hi>and</hi> Subiect <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps much borrowed from others; so as I may say,</hi> All heere, <hi>and</hi> nothing heere, <hi>to be</hi> truly Mine: <hi>For, as the compiling the</hi> instructing Preparatiues, <hi>with the</hi> Prayers, <hi>and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesting them vnder their</hi> certaine Heades, <hi>and the</hi> Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>vpon the</hi> Lords Supper, <hi>and</hi> Mortalitie, <hi>is all</hi> mine owne; <hi>so yet I doe confesse, I haue excerpted, and culled out of</hi> Authors, <hi>both</hi> Wordes, <hi>and</hi> Sentences; <hi>sometimes</hi> whole, <hi>sometimes the</hi> Clauses, <hi>and</hi> Members <hi>of them; not alwayes</hi> the same, <hi>but</hi> in part, <hi>as they were to be accommodated to</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>in hand. Neither doe I feare herein to be stigmatized by</hi> S. Hieromes <hi>censure, with a branding J▪ for I haue to some places cited by mee, ascribed the</hi> Authors Names, <hi>vpon whose credite I might warrant the</hi> Allegations: <hi>other</hi> Writers <hi>of a</hi> sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected note, <hi>and so not of that</hi> Authoritie <hi>with vs, as to be allowed, especially in a subiect of this Nature, (they differencing from vs in some</hi> Materiall poyntes) <hi>I haue for that reason, concealed, to auoyde</hi> preiudice, <hi>and</hi> wrong, <hi>which often is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned</hi> through scrupulositie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>J say then, I doe ingenuously acknowledge, that the</hi> Matter, <hi>and</hi> Stuffe <hi>of this Worke, is in part borrowed: But I may truly claime to my selfe the</hi> framing <hi>and</hi> fashioning it in order <hi>as it is set foorth. Let not the</hi> Spiders Webbe, <hi>wrought of the threddes which the</hi> Spider it selfe <hi>doth weaue, be of greater accompt and esteeme, then is that</hi> iuyce <hi>of sundry</hi> mellifluuous Hearbes <hi>which the</hi> Bee <hi>gathereth, and by a certaine</hi> mixture <hi>and</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie <hi>of her</hi> Breath, (<hi>as</hi> Seneca <hi>writeth,) altereth into that</hi> sauour <hi>and</hi> taste of pleasant sweete moysture <hi>which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Hony. <hi>Wee see also, that</hi> Embroderers <hi>worke</hi> Tapistrie, <hi>and</hi> Arras <hi>with</hi> partited Threddes <hi>of</hi> sundry colours, <hi>which themselues doe not first make. I doe not by this, argue the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of</hi> this Worke: <hi>Bee it, as they which read it, shall censure it. If all herein written be ascribed to others for</hi> Inuention, <hi>as not mine, being aptly disposed, and well applyed</hi> for sense, <hi>it shalbe to mee a thing indifferent; so that out of</hi> this Worke <hi>thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
<pb facs="14"/> by me &amp; ordered for</hi> phrase, <hi>&amp;</hi> stile, <hi>hauing both in</hi> word <hi>and</hi> Sense, <hi>a fit correspondence with the</hi> analogie of Fayth, <hi>this principally: then next that, such</hi> fruite <hi>&amp;</hi> profit <hi>doe redounde to the</hi> Sonnes <hi>of the</hi> Church, <hi>as may cause (if but one) godly and truly sanctified</hi> Cogitation (<hi>gayned thereby) to arise and settle in some one</hi> Christian soule <hi>at one moment. If</hi> God <hi>out of</hi> his Mercie <hi>shall be pleased thus to blesse these my Labours what-soeuer, I haue</hi> my Wish <hi>and</hi> Desire; <hi>which is the end of</hi> my Proiect <hi>in the first attempting hereof: Most humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching</hi> your Maiestie, <hi>that of</hi> your gracious clemencie, (<hi>wherewith you</hi> glad <hi>and</hi> comfort <hi>the</hi> hearts <hi>of your</hi> Subiects louingly loyall) <hi>you will be pleased to vouchsafe a</hi> fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aspect <hi>in the acceptation hereof, not</hi> presumptuously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, <hi>in an opinion of</hi> worth; <hi>but vpon a</hi> confidence <hi>of your</hi> wonted grace, submissely craued <hi>in the name of</hi> true, <hi>and</hi> vnfeigned loyaltie. Plinie <hi>writeth, that the</hi> Idoll <hi>of</hi> Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, <hi>which was mute at all other Times, did then (as seeming so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly to be reuiued) discourse at large, when the</hi> Sunne <hi>casting foorth his</hi> quickening comfortable Raies, <hi>appeared</hi> bright shining <hi>in the</hi> Face <hi>of it. And that many of</hi> Apolloes <hi>not</hi> Idols, <hi>but</hi> Sonnes, (<hi>which before kept silence, in a manner mute, and dumbe, encircled (I may say) within the confined</hi> shadie Couerts <hi>of their</hi> priuate readinges,) <hi>since enlightned by your</hi> Maiesties serene Countenance, gracing their Studies, <hi>haue been encouraged, and (as it were) receiuing</hi> Life <hi>from thence, haue</hi> breathed foorth <hi>in</hi> publicque Writinges, <hi>is euident (as a matter to be confessed and acknowledged of all.) For euen our</hi> Life, <hi>and our</hi> action (<hi>which is manifested thereby) must needes proceed from the</hi> strength <hi>and</hi> vigor <hi>that harbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth within</hi> your most royall Heart, <hi>by reason that</hi> all the Arteries <hi>of</hi> this Common-wealth, <hi>doe dayly</hi> beat <hi>in the</hi> sweete temper <hi>of that</hi> regall Authoritie, <hi>and this</hi> Fatherly indulging Clemencie; <hi>in that,</hi> excelling <hi>all your</hi> Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, <hi>in this</hi> equalizing the best, <hi>in both</hi> happy, <hi>because</hi> profitably eminent; <hi>and thereby also making all</hi> your Subiectes <hi>most</hi> fortunate. <hi>So then</hi> (most Gracious <hi>and</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/> dread Soueraigne) <hi>our</hi> dutie (<hi>as wee are your</hi> Subiectes, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying this happinesse by you) is first, a</hi> true acknowledgment <hi>of a</hi> setled state <hi>in</hi> your Person; <hi>with a protestation</hi> before God <hi>for all</hi> Loyall obedience <hi>in all</hi> dutifull deuoted Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission: <hi>Next, (as wee are</hi> Christians) <hi>to render our</hi> most heartie, <hi>and</hi> humble Thankes <hi>vnto</hi> God, (<hi>who) in mercie vouchsafing fauour to this</hi> Realme, <hi>hath placed</hi> your Highnes King <hi>ouer the same a</hi> Wise, virtuous, peaceable, <hi>and</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Prince, <hi>to the inestimable good and happinesse of</hi> your people; <hi>vnder whose</hi> tuition, <hi>and</hi> patrocinie, true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, godly Discipline, <hi>the</hi> best studies <hi>of</hi> Learning, <hi>by</hi> holesome Lawes <hi>administred in</hi> equitie, <hi>doe flourish, and are maintained. In this name therefore, (which is also a duty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in the</hi> Scripture, <hi>and now properly ours,) doe we</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missely offer vp <hi>the</hi> Calues of our Lippes, <hi>for</hi> a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>and</hi> Euening Sacrifice; <hi>euen earnest</hi> Supplications, <hi>and feruent</hi> Prayers <hi>dayly to that</hi> diuine Powerfull Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie in Heauen, (<hi>who giueth</hi> safetie <hi>vnto</hi> Kinges, <hi>and is the</hi> keeper <hi>and</hi> onely defender <hi>of all</hi> politicque States, <hi>that harbour</hi> the Ghospell <hi>of</hi> Christ,) <hi>for the perpetuall safeguar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and prescruing</hi> your Scepter, <hi>and</hi> Regall dignities, <hi>in all</hi> Christian peace, <hi>and</hi> Tranquilitie; <hi>beseeching him▪ to bee</hi> GOD <hi>to</hi> you, <hi>and</hi> your Seed, <hi>as hee promised to bee vnto</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17. 7.</note> Abraham, <hi>and to</hi> his Seed <hi>after him; that accordingly</hi> hee <hi>blesse the gouernment of all your</hi> Maiesties Dominions and Kingdomes, <hi>in</hi> your selfe <hi>now</hi> Ruling; <hi>and in</hi> your Sonne, <hi>our</hi> noble Prince Charles <hi>after you: Who being your</hi> lawfull Heire <hi>and</hi> Successour <hi>to those your Kingdomes, may in like manner be the</hi> liuely representatiue Image <hi>of your rare, and singuler endowments of</hi> Nature, <hi>and</hi> Grace; <hi>and so by your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to become a</hi> Nursing Father, <hi>in defending, preseruing, and propagating the truth of the</hi> Ghospell; <hi>hauing in minde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that saying of the</hi> euerlasting Wisedome the Sonne of God, <hi>in the</hi> Prouerbes: <note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 4. ver. 8. ver. 9.</note> Exalt her, and shee shall exalt thee. Shee shall giue thee a comely Ornament to thy Head, <hi>yea,</hi> a Crowne of Glory shall shee giue thee. <hi>For,</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/> I <note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 8. ver. 17. ver. 15. ver. 16.</note> loue them, that loue mee; <hi>euen to glorifie them: For,</hi> By mee Kings reigne, <hi>and</hi> Princes rule. <hi>This</hi> Memoriall <hi>beeing as a</hi> Frontlet before his Eyes, <hi>must needes tell him, that</hi> Hee <hi>is to bee as</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> burning Torch <hi>of all</hi> Virtue, <hi>and</hi> Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <hi>aboue others; by the</hi> Light <hi>thereof, to direct the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps of his Citizens in the whole course of their liues; as</hi> your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> he <hi>admonisheth in your</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>by the name of</hi> a demie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>God▪<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>. 1. pag. 2. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>t.</note>
      <hi>sitting vpon this</hi> Throane <hi>of</hi> GOD, <hi>to be his</hi> Lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere on Earth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The which</hi> Throane <hi>and</hi> Seate of Maiestie, (<hi>my Prayers</hi> vnto God <hi>for your</hi> Highnes <hi>to be continued vnto</hi> your owne Person <hi>in all happinesse all your life long first and chiefly premit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;) I humbly craue at</hi> Gods hands <hi>next, that</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Sam 7. ver 12.</note> When your dayes be fulfilled, <hi>and</hi> you sleepe with your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>to reigne with them in Heauen, that then the same</hi> your hereditarie Throane, <hi>may be</hi> the Throane of Dauid <hi>vnto</hi> your Sonne, <hi>in</hi> him, <hi>and in</hi> his Seed, <hi>which shall proceed out of his</hi> Body <hi>to be established.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I conclude with the wordes of</hi> Salomon: <hi>Let</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Reg. 2. 45.</note> King <hi>IAMES</hi> be blessed, <hi>and</hi> his Throane be established before the Lord for euer. <hi>And to this, let all</hi> Loyall faithfull Subiectes <hi>of an</hi> immaculate allegience, <hi>giuing their assent in the wordes of</hi> Nehemiah, <note n="d" place="margin">Nehem. 2. ver. 3.</note> God saue the King for euer: <hi>and say with</hi> one heart, <hi>and</hi> voyce: Amen, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your sacred Maiesties most loyall true hearted subiect, Paule Wentwourth.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>