<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A RELATION OF THE COMMING OF THE CATHOLIKE PRINCES KING PHILIPPE THE THIRD AND QVEENE Margaret to the English Colledge of Valla∣dolid, and of there receiuing theire the 22. of August. 1600.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119506_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08539</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18858</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119506</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A RELATION OF THE COMMING OF THE CATHOLIKE PRINCES KING PHILIPPE THE THIRD AND QVEENE Margaret to the English Colledge of Valla∣dolid, and of there receiuing theire the 22. of August. 1600.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A relation of the solemnetie : wherewith the Catholike princes K. Phillip the III. and Quene Margaret were receyued in the Inglish Colledge of Valladolid the 22. of August. 1600. VVritten in Spanish by Don Ant. Ortiz and translated by Frauncis Riuers and dedicated to the right honorable the Lord Chamberlayne</title>
                 <author>Ortiz, Antonio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>79, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="7" facs="5"/>
   <head>A RELATION OF THE COMMING OF THE CATHOLIKE PRINCES KING PHILIPPE THE THIRD AND QVEENE Margaret to the English Colledge of Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid, and of there receiuing theire the 22. of August. 1600.</head>
   <head type="sub">To the Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, Infante of Spayne.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>ING Philippe the third, Brother to your highnes, and Queene Margaret his wyf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered this famous Citie of Valliadolid vpon S. Margarets euen, the 19. of Iulij a day of great ioy and solemnitie, and of no lesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte to all this Citie, as it is like your highnes hath bene informed, and for that the weather was then very hotte in the Canicular dayes, and his Magesties Palace in the farthest parte of the Citie, a greate way from the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Colledge, they deferred to desire theire Magesties to fauoure this theire Colledge with theire Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, for having receiued the like honour of his Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie and of your highnes eight yeares agoe with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, vpon the inuention of the holly Protomartyre S. Stephen, which day is yet fresh in memorie in this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: it seamed they had the vvay open to expect and receiue this newe fauour of his Magestie.</p>
   <p>At this very tyme there came a good number of schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers frō the Colledge of S. Omers, of those your highnes
<pb facs="6"/>
Estates, erected by the King his Magestie that now is, eight yeares since (not without the speciall prouidēce of God) wherein the Catholike children of Englad might be brought vp and instructed in vertue from theire tēder yeares, and learne the Latine tongue, Poetrie and Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, and from thence be sent to the Seminaries of Spay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> other more protounde sciences as your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doth knowe. Among these studientes there came some to yonge in yeares, that it semed they could scarse speake latine, but being examined they weare foūde to be good Poetes and Rhetoricians, and two of the yongest were appointed to do obeysance and giue to theire Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesties humble thākes in the name of theire Colledge: &amp; so with six others of theire company were conducted to the Pallace by their superior and presently admitted to audience, where hauing made the reuerence accustomed, one of them of fourteene yeares of age with good grace and modest countenance offered to speake: But for that he was so younge &amp; so lately ariued, and that it might be feared least with the presence and Magestie of so great a kinge, he might be dismayed and driuen out of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, the father thought good to preuent his Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and so told him the youth had a worde or two to speake in the behalfe of his Colledge, but he feared his bashfulnes &amp; that his harte would not serue him to spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in presence of his Magestie. The Kinge smiled and willed him with such courtesie to speake, that the childe tooke courage, and deliuered his Oration with so good a grace, so chearefully with so modest and decent action and so good pronuntiation and voice that he was well vnderstoode, and his speache very gratefull to his Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and to all that weare present who much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the liuelines and good courage of the childe, and for that his Oration was liked and commended of diuers graue and learned personnages that heard it, I suppose it wil be gratefull to your highnes that I sette it downe in this place.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>