<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Dowland, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119394_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20694</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7097</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Dowland, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lachrimæ, or Seauen teares figured in seauen passionate pauans : vvith diuers other pauans, galiards, and almands, set forth for the lute, viols, or violons, in fiue parts: By Iohn Dowland Bacheler of Musicke, and lutenist to the most royall and magnificent, Christian the fourth, King of Denmarke, Norway, Vandales, and Gothes, Duke of Sleswicke, Holsten, Stormaria, and Ditmarsh: Earle of Oldenburge and Delmenhorst</title>
                 <author>Dowland, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dowland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>50 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing in forren parts met diuers Lute-lessons of my compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, publisht by strangers without my name or approbation; I thought it much more conuenient, that my labours should passe forth vnder mine owne allowance, receiuing from me their last foile and polishment; for which consideration I haue vndergone this long and troublesome worke, wherein I haue mixed new songs with olde, graue with light, that euery eare may receiue his seuer all content. And as I had in these an earnest desire to satisfie all, I do likewise hope that the peruser will as gratefully entertaine my endeuours, as they were friendly meant.</p>
   <p>This onely obseruation I must set downe in the playing of my Lute-lessons for tuning of the Lute, which is, that the <hi>7.8.9.</hi> string open, do answere in the eight the base string aboue, what letter soeuer it be that carries the base: As for example.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Example.</hi>
      <q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="music">
               <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours <hi>IOHN DOVVLAND.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>