<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE, NOBLE, AND MOST WORTHY LORD, THOMAS LORD BVRGH, BARON GAINS BVRGHE, LORD GOVERNOVR FOR HER MAIESTY OF HER TOWNE OF BREILL, AND THE FORTS OF CLAYBVRGH AND MEWENNOORT IN THE COVNTIE OF HOLLAND IN THE LOWE COVNTRYES, KNIGHT OF THE MOST HONORABLE ORDER OF THE GARTIER, LORD DEPVTY AND GOVER∣NOR GENERALL FOR HER MAIESTY OF HER REALME OF IRELAND.</title>
           <author>Holborne, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119009_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03441</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13562</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119009</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE, NOBLE, AND MOST WORTHY LORD, THOMAS LORD BVRGH, BARON GAINS BVRGHE, LORD GOVERNOVR FOR HER MAIESTY OF HER TOWNE OF BREILL, AND THE FORTS OF CLAYBVRGH AND MEWENNOORT IN THE COVNTIE OF HOLLAND IN THE LOWE COVNTRYES, KNIGHT OF THE MOST HONORABLE ORDER OF THE GARTIER, LORD DEPVTY AND GOVER∣NOR GENERALL FOR HER MAIESTY OF HER REALME OF IRELAND.</title>
                 <author>Holborne, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The cittharn schoole, by Antony Holborne gentleman, and seruant to her most excellent Maiestie. Hereunto are added sixe short aers Neopolitan like to three voyces, without the instrument: done by his brother William Holborne</title>
                 <author>Holborne, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, NOBLE, AND MOST <hi>WORTHY LORD,</hi> THOMAS <hi>LORD</hi> BVRGH, BARON GAINS BVRGHE, LORD <hi>GOVERNOVR FOR HER MAIESTY OF HER</hi> TOWNE OF <hi>BREILL,</hi> AND THE FORTS OF CLAYBVRGH <hi>AND</hi> MEWENNOORT <hi>IN THE</hi> COVNTIE OF <hi>HOLLAND</hi> IN THE LOWE <hi>COVNTRYES, KNIGHT OF THE MOST</hi> HONORABLE ORDER OF THE GARTIER, LORD DEPVTY AND GOVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOR GENERALL FOR HER MAIESTY OF HER REALME OF IRELAND.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honorable and thrise no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord: (the sole true patron of all vertue and my poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruings)</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I haue long wrastled in the labor of my best wits, to betoken to your L. selfe as the choise of a world, some accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table pledge or testimoniall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of my loue, duety and thankefulnes: which in the b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st allowaunce from my weake fortunes I can in no sort better appoint then by this my silly Citharn Schoole. For as among other your many graceful vertues I know your L. liueth iudicially accompanied with a loue to <hi>Musique</hi> irremoueable, both art and nature tying
<pb facs="3"/> you therevnto in a bond of great right by your owne most excellent managing of all kinds of <hi>Instruments gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi> so am I most assured that this little <hi>Wanton</hi> hath not the least, but a prime place in the commaunding per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of your pleasures: wherein as well others as my selfe which hould it in profession, are bound euen in a generall assent to humble our best doings to your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and learned fingers. By which reason alone were there none other (vnder your L. good fauour I speake it) this slender worke of mine may as in a law full birthright challenge the inheritance of protection from you. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, neither arrogantly nor too presumptuously do I dare to present it vnto you, but dutifully, reuerently, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good sort best becomming me, as an open badge by which the world shall not deny, but know me to be yours. Most humbly therefore beseeching your L. good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance hereof, and in the continuance of your honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fauors, to hould of mee as the man that hath euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in a religious desire to do you all honor and seruice, I take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your L. euer most</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie deuoted <hi>ANTONY HOLBORNE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q xml:lang="lat">Ni merear moriar.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>