<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY LOVING FRIENDS AND READERS IN LONDON.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119864_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68224</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14068</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119864</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY LOVING FRIENDS AND READERS IN LONDON.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A miracle, of miracles : As fearefull as euer was seene or heard of in the memorie of man. Which lately happened at Dichet in Sommersetshire, and sent by diuers credible witnesses to be published in London. Also a prophesie reuealed by a poore countrey maide, who being dead the first of October last, 1613. 24. houres, reuiued againe, and lay fiue dayes weeping, and continued prophesying of strange euents to come, and so died the 5. day following. Witnessed by M. Nicholas Faber, parson of the towne, and diuers worthy gentlemen of the same countrey. 1613, withall, Lincolnshire teares. For a great deluge, in which fiue villages were lamentably drovvned this present month</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Trundle, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY LOVING FRIENDS AND READERS IN LONDON.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ELOVED and courteous friends and Readers, wee haue to consider by this strange discourse, how ready Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than is to take hold on vs, if wee fall from GOD neuer so little. Hee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually runneth vp and downe, seeking whom hee may deuoure: But notwithstanding his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are great, the mercie of God is greater, who neuer faileth to send comfort in temptation, if we accept thereof.</p>
   <p>Great are the examples both of Gods mercie and might, to put vs in remembrance of our sinnes which are infinite and loathsome, wherein if wee continue, let vs vndoubtedly looke for the reward thereof, which is an euerlasting destruction both of bodie and soule.</p>
   <p>Let not this which is heere declared seeme a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fable vnto thee, but assure thy selfe that all such things are sent as warnings for our wickednes, and to put vs in mind of the stay of our saluation, which
<pb facs="3"/>
is an assured faith in Christ Iesus: from which piller if wee once shrinke, the Tempter is readie to driue vs into despaire of Gods mercie.</p>
   <p>Many are the wonders which haue lately happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as of sodaine and strange death vpon periured persons, strange sights in the Ayre, strange births on the Earth, Earthquakes, Commets, and fierie Impressions, with the execution of GOD himselfe from his holy fire in heauen, on the wretched man and his wife, at <hi>Holnhurst</hi> in Hampshire; written by that worthy Minister maister <hi>Hilliard;</hi> and all to put vs in minde of God, whose workes are wonderfull.</p>
   <p>These and such like examples (good Reader) war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs to bee watchfull for the day of the Lord which is at hand, least sodainely his wrath be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led against vs. Let vs therefore pray to Almightie God to hold back his rodde, to be mercifull to vs, and to forgiue vs that is past: that through the assistance of his Spirit, wee may with pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent hearts liue in his feare to our liues end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend, <hi>T.I.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>