<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERY NOBLE AND POTENT EARLE, THOMAS, Earle of MELROS, L. Byir's, and Binning, Praesident of the Colledge of Iustice; Principall Secretary to his MAIESTIE of Scotland, and one of his MAIESTIES Privie Councell in both Kingdomes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119602_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16291</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25210</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119602</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERY NOBLE AND POTENT EARLE, THOMAS, Earle of MELROS, L. Byir's, and Binning, Praesident of the Colledge of Iustice; Principall Secretary to his MAIESTIE of Scotland, and one of his MAIESTIES Privie Councell in both Kingdomes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian synagogue : Wherein is contayned the diverse reading, the right poynting, translation, and collation of scripture with scripture. With the customes of the Hebrewes and proselytes, and of all those nations, with whom they were conversant. Digested into three bookes. The first, shewing the meanes both inward and outward, to attaine to the knowledge of the sense of the whole Scripture. The second, vnfolding the true sense of the Scripture it selfe ... The third, teaching the true manner of confirmation, illustration, and application of doctrines ... Serving generally for a helpe to the vnderstanding, of all; that desire to know and obey the will of God in holy Writ: but more specially for all young students in divinitie, that they may more easily vnderstand the languages of Canaan, and Greece, and make a profitable vse of them in preaching. B Iohn Weemse of Lathoquar, in Scotland, preacher of Christs Gospell</title>
                 <author>Weemes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 221, 3, 86 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERY NOBLE AND POTENT EARLE, THOMAS, Earle of MELROS, L. <hi>Byir's,</hi> and <hi>Binning,</hi> Praesident of the <hi>Colledge of Iustice; Principall Secretary</hi> to his MAIESTIE of <hi>Scotland, and one of his</hi> MAIESTIES Privie Councell in both <hi>Kingdomes.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE auncient <hi>Jewes</hi>
      <note place="margin">Talmud l. Iuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sin. Folio. 13.</note> testifie, that there were three Crownes, which made ISRAELL renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: The first was the Crowne of the <hi>Law;</hi> the second, the Crowne of the <hi>King;</hi> the third, the Crowne of the <hi>Priest:</hi> And of those three Crownes, they say, that
<pb facs="3"/> the Crowne of the <hi>Law</hi> was most glorious; because <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. 15, 16. it is said, <hi>By me Princes Raigne.</hi> It was this <hi>Law</hi> of God, which <hi>David</hi> made his Counsellour, <note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 119.</note>
      <hi>In the morning when he rose, and at night when he went to bed.</hi> It was this <hi>Law</hi> which made not onely Kings and Princes wise, but also States-men and Counsellours: as <note n="b" place="margin">Esa. 22. 20</note>
      <hi>Eliacim</hi> the Chancelour, <note n="c" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er. 38. 7.</note>
      <hi>Ebed-melech</hi> the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopian</hi> (King <hi>Zedekiah's</hi> Courtier) <note n="d" place="margin">Tit. 3. 13.</note>
      <hi>Zenas</hi> the Lawyer, <note n="e" place="margin">Col. 4. 14.</note>
      <hi>Luke</hi> the Physitian, <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 17. 34</note>
      <hi>Dionysius Areopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gita</hi> the Philosopher. So that, <hi>from him that sits vpon the Throne,</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Deut. 29. 11.</note>
      <hi>to him who hewes the wood, and drawes the water,</hi> (that is, from the highest to the basest) this Law should ever be their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector.</p>
   <p>The Scriptures of God, haue beene directed to divers sorts of persons, both noble and base: <hi>Luke</hi> Dedicated his Gospell, and Acts of <note place="margin">Luke 1. 1. Act. 1. 1.</note> the Apostles to noble <hi>Theophilus: Iohn</hi> dedicated his second Epistle to the <hi>Elect Ladie:</hi> and his third Epistle to his Hoste <hi>Caius,</hi> a meane man, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Ioh. 1 1.</note> but yet a good Christian. Some make choyce of Patrons onely for Nobilitie, but haue no respect of vertue, then it were better to chuse such a Patron as <hi>Caius<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>:</hi> but where Nobilitie is grac'd with vertue, such a man is a most fit Patron, as <hi>Theophilus.</hi> Now because I find both those combin'd in your Lordship, I am bold
<pb facs="3"/> to put these my latter gleanings vnder your Lordships Patrocinie.</p>
   <p>A second reason, which moved me to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer these my travels to your Lordship, is this: I remembred that Apologue in the Talmud: <note place="margin">Talmud Cholin. 62. 1.</note> The grapes in <hi>Babell</hi> sent vpon a time to the vine leaues in <hi>Iudaea,</hi> desiring them to come and overshadow them, otherwise the heate would consume them, and so neuer come to maturitie. Your Lordship knowes well the mythologie of this Apologue: If learning be not sheltred by those who are in eminent pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and if they cast not their shadow over it, it will soone perish: but where they favour it, then it prospers. If the spring be cold, then plants, herbs, and the blossome of the Trees wither; but where the influence is seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then all things reviue: So where great men are averse to Learning, the spirits which otherwise could blossome, wither, and deay: but where it is vpholden by men of higher place, it is like a Fountaine of liuing water. <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note>
   </p>
   <p>A third reason, which moved me to offer these my travels to your Lordship, is, your Lordships ingenuitie, who will cover such things as are said amisse here, (for who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating of such Antiquities, and so diverse, will still touch the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) If any thing be said
<pb facs="4"/> to the purpose, your Lordship will soone note it, who vnderstands matters of deeper insight then these are. For these and many moe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and your Lordships vndeserved favour towards me. I offer most willingly these my travels to your Lordship, craving of God that you may continue like <hi>Eliacim, as a fastened nayle</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isay 22. 23.</note>
      <hi>in a sure place,</hi> to doe good in that place, which God and his Maiestie haue placed you in. I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships,</hi> In all Christian duties, I. W. of <hi>Lathoquar.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>