<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL AND MY VERY REVE∣rend freind M. Doctor Goad, Provost of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
           <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119045_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03281</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13398</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119045</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL AND MY VERY REVE∣rend freind M. Doctor Goad, Provost of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                 <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dignitie of the Scripture togither with the indignity which the vnthankfull world offereth thereunto : In three sermons vpon Hose. 8. 12. By Samuel Hieron</title>
                 <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London ; Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 41, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL AND MY VERY REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend freind M. Doctor <hi>Goad,</hi> Provost of the <hi>Kings Colledge in</hi> Cambridge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I remember the times and furtherances of my education, and consider with my selfe by whose free choise, I was preferred into that worthy societie (the head-ship whereof your worship hath so many yeares enioyed) I cannot but say to you as Hierome did to a freind of his, <hi>Tibi &amp; quod possū debeo,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hiero. Sephron.</note>
      <hi>&amp; quod non possum:</hi> I am indebted to you both to the vtmost extent of my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and in much more then I can performe. Giue me leaue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I beseech you) not as by way of requitall (for I will not so much either vnder-value your fauour, or abridge my debt) but as by way of acknowledgement (leauing this, as it were a bill of my hand what I haue receiued, and how deepely I am engaged) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent you with these three sermons. They are of the Dignitie of the scripture, and therefore (their subiect considered) are not vnworthy your patronage, being so auncient and so indicious a professour of Theologie. The manner of handling, because, as it is liable to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in this taxing age, so it may perhaps through my want either of skill or care deserue reproofe, therefore I doe submit it wholly to your worships triall, that after, it may either step further into pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view, or els stop where it is, according as you shall please to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. How soeuer it be, albeit I must confesse, that I should much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in your approouing furtherance, yet at the least I shall herein find contentment, that I haue endeuoured out of my vnfained sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siblenes of your worships respectiue kindnesse, to make the world a witnes of my thankefullnes. And so in the fulnes of my desire, that he in whom <hi>all Fulnes dwelleth</hi> may so replenish you with <hi>spirituall blessings in heauenly things,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Col. 1.19. Eph. 1.3. Psa. 92.13.14.</note> that like the <hi>Trees planted in the house of the Lord,</hi> you may <hi>still euen in your Age bring forth fruit, and be fatte &amp; flourishing,</hi> I humbly take my leaue. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Modbury in</hi> Deuonshire <date>
            <hi>this 2. of Iuly. 1607.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your worships euer in the Lord, <hi>Samuell Hieron.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>