<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119027_Bo1_1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14278</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119027</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ionah's contestation about his gourd : In a sermon deliuered at Pauls Crosse. Septemb. 19. 1624. By R.V. preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Vase, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bird, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 63, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <p>NOw, to call thee backe a little, friendly Reader, to the matter of my text, and withall, if I may persume to communicate my selfe vnto thy good nature, I would intreat thee for the Author thus to iudge.</p>
   <pb n="59" facs="34"/>
   <p> That he fell not by his hap-hazard vpon his text, or that hee hath not had a feeling of the same. What learning call you that which doth carry in hir bosome a sense or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of hir knowen principles? It hath the name of <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge experimentall,</hi> which cannot be attained by all the search of meere study, and is to bee preferred before all humane learning acquired by the documents and precepts of men.</p>
   <p>Who can describe the image of God the father, or pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray out the shape of the holy Ghost, or expresse the glory of the blessed Trinity? The meanest Christian who hath God in his heart doth retaine a sounder knowledge of his maker by those hidden operations felt within, then the stou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Philosopher in the height and sublimity of his soring spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, or those better learned clearkes; who can dispute subtilly aboue the Trinity, yet want power to please the holy Trinity.</p>
   <p>O but that knowledge is full of danger my text speaks of, and who would wish to be possessed with such a feeling as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> was? not I, not thou, nor any man; yet take heede, thou maiest be over-rash in iudging. For why? anger doeth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and that ordinarily presuppose love. O fearefull case, is <hi>Ionah</hi> angry with God, saist thou? an other is of this minde, is it possible in a fraile man, to conceive anger against the great God? whence springs this familiarity betweene heaven and earth? <hi>aut quam nuper è coelo descendisti Ionah,</hi> how lately camest thou out of heaven <hi>O Ionah?</hi> yea sure, by the very nature of the speech must be implyed a certaine intercourse of favour and loving commerce betweene the heavenly God and vs. Why els is any man angry with his fellow, but in a conceyt that he hath bin requited euill for good, and the fruits of hate where hee looked for the effects of loue?</p>
   <p>Why then, euen hence in like manner arise those manifold heart-burnings and great disturbances of the Saints quiet; since they have bin assured of Gods love, but want all signes thereof in their distresses. Is this the part of a loving father think his misbeleeving children, to neglect their suites who call day and night vnto him? what's become of his promises and those mervailous workes our forefathers have told vs of
<pb n="60" facs="35"/>wherefore doth he not arise and helpe vs and that early? O my God, I cry in the day time and thou hearest not, and and in the night season also my soule refuseth comfort. Here our faith begins to stagger, for what? hath God forgotten to be gracious, and will he be no more intreated, and is his mercy cleane gone for evermore?</p>
   <p>Then the spirit is almost tyred with waiting, and the flesh growes monstrous vnruly. God is not so good as his word, for he hath promised, if in trouble we call vpon him, he will helpe vs, but he regards neither our calling, nor cryes, nor teares. O now the spirit waxeth hot, and the blood doth boyle within the veines: and thus our anger ariseth against God, a thing not impossible, as you see, nor yet allowable, to the Saints most incident, and to the best of Saints, more ordinarily then to the worst of hypocrites, or any other to the state of grace not yet called.</p>
   <p>Indeede, for these, I doe not reade of many, or any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in this kinde, to have entred Contestation with the Lord, as <hi>Ionah</hi> here hath done, nor is it the <hi>Nabals</hi> of the world, but the <hi>Davids</hi> who mourne in their prayer, and are vexed. For vpon what grounds can they challenge God of his promise, and expostulate? where hath God bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe vnto these with an oath, that he will be their God, and of their seede for ever? how oft have they called vpon him in faith, and wept vnto him in zeale? what love to his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, what trust to his Word, what assurance of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, what consolation in his promises, hath beene at any time in their hearts residing?</p>
   <p>I am not angry with the Sunne when it shineth to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes, nor with the Starres, because they runne round; I am not angry with the Windes at Sea, when my house by fire is burnt at home; or lastly, why should the Malefactor, who cryes guiltie at the Barre, be angry with the Iudge, who gives sentence according to the law vpon his offence?</p>
   <p>Even so truly, the wicked foolish, who say in their hearts there is no God, and doe impute their good and bad hap to blinde chance or fortune, who are men of an other world, and strangers to godlinesse: I see no reason their anger should
<pb n="61" facs="35"/>reach, whether their beleefe doth not. Yea truly when they are haled before Gods iudgement Seat, as Malefactors ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, their guiltie consciences proclaime woe immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but then begins their anger and desperate rage, when the scalding plagues of Gods wrath doe begin to torment their bodies, and the horrour of deadly darkenesse doth cease vpon their soules for their wilfull blindnesse and folly, and their rage is not only against God, but in a remarkeable kinde of iustice, against their owne members, they gnawed their tongues and blasphemed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.</p>
   <p>But if their malice breake out against God or his Saints sooner (as oft it doth) it is then a fearefull preparation to these eternall woes mentioned, and hath more properly the name of malice then of anger. For what difference is there betweene the anger of Gods Saints, and of his enemies? even such as I have shewed, as is the anger betweene two friends, and two most contrary enemies.</p>
   <p>These things (gentle Reader) I have more deepely searcht into by occasion of my Text, not that I presume herein to commend vnto thee any rare point of skill: for that which may fall out to be rare in the course of my studies may have beene more soundly noted in the labours of other men, and perhaps is not new vnto thy iudgement; nor to this end doe I it, to commend the feeling of this knowledge vnto any, not so farre experimented in this kinde of learning which wee have from <hi>Ionah;</hi> but to this end rather, that wee may bee wise to put a difference, and be suspended from rash iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the state of divers Gods Elect, wrastling here in this vale of misery, falling and rising, foyled, and sometimes foyling like prevailers, and that herein we studie true thankfulnesse to the sole-worker of our salvation, who preserveth the soules of his Saints from going downe into the pit of desperation.</p>
   <p>For my selfe (Christian Reader) I was angry with my God, and knewit not; very angry but did not well consider it. How manifold are thy tryalls? O how various and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull art thou in the exercising of vs thy fraile creatures? <hi>Vsque quo Domine, vsque quo,</hi> shal not my griefes and groanes,
<pb n="62" facs="36"/>my deepe sighings and often teares, and strong cryes, be full effectuall in thy fight, to manifest thy power within, to vtter thy praise abroad? O those hills of peace, where are they? why hast thou caused me to hope in thy word &amp; hast nor fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht me vnto the battel? why was I called —? but returne now vnto thy rest, O my soule, and hope yet confidently. I was angry and mourned in my prayer and was vexed: was it not in thy temple, O God, in thy temple that my soule was exceedingly cast downe and troubled? in thy temple there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I praise thee, because there thou spakest peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my troubled soule, and did'st allay the heat of all my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented passions, saying as sometime thou didst vnto thy servant <hi>Ionah, Doest thou well to be angry?</hi> Thus, even thus thou rebukedst the windes and the waves of all my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward commotions, and there followed immediately a great calme, praise the Lord O my soule and all that is within me praise his holy name. For it was not flesh nor blood then which then was in the strength of impariency and stamped with the foot, it was not flesh and blood that did reveale, that did put this good motion into my breast, but my father in heaven, therefore praise the Lord O my soule.</p>
   <p>At this time I was assigned to the Crosse, &amp; had not yet cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen the Text I meant to treat of: the choise was soone made; For what more acceptable service to our God, more pleasing to his Church, more effectual for the preachers of his word to deale in, then to expresse their minds vpon those Themes, the power whereof hauing first subdued their owne affections doth with greater force from them flow forth vnto others, and procure more ample glory to his name, vnto whom the whole action and efficacy of the worke is in speciall wise to be referred.</p>
   <p>Thus have I made my selfe a foole in glorying, but it is in my infirmityes, and if for this I be disdained of the <hi>Michals</hi> of the world, I will study to become yet viler in their eyes, that Gods power by my weaknes may be exalted. Is not this the end of all our beings? and ought we not by all meanes whether by precept or example or however labour here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? whether we be besides our selues saith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the
<pb n="63" facs="36"/>
      <hi>Corinthians</hi> it is to God, or whether wee bee sober it is for your cause and hee is no follower of <hi>Paul</hi> as hee followed Christ in this, who will not thus indeavour to become all things to all men, that of all sorts he may gaine some to God and he that respecteth his owne credit private opinion and speeches of others, before the winning of souls, he is ashamed of the Gospell of Christ; a shame of all others most shamefull and one most vnworthy to be a minister of the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
   <p>Thus Christian and friendly Reader and one of the hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith whose love I doe onely imbrace, have I not made my selfe strange vnto thee, and for this cause desire the fruit of thy prayes to be assistant vnto me that I may open my mouth with boldnesse in the cause of the Gospel wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I have traviled and am yet in paine. I beleeved and therefore did I speake saith <hi>David,</hi> but I was sore greived. I also beleeved, the same have I preached, the same againe have I penned. Now to all those who love the Lord Iesus, I conclude, Grace be vnto them, and Mercy, and vpon the Israel of God.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>