<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>Clerimond, B. D. de</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119940_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22060</idno>
           <idno type="STC">8448</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119940</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>Clerimond, B. D. de</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A proclamation published vnder the name of Iames King of Great Britanny. With a briefe &amp; moderate answere therunto. Whereto are added the penall statutes, made in the same kingdome, against Catholikes. Togeather with a letter which sheweth the said Catholikes piety: and diuers aduertisements also, for better vnderstanding of the whole matter. Translated out of Latin into English</title>
                 <author>England and Wales, Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>English College Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 178, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Christian and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Reader vvill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue by this Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiō, into vvhat hāds the Kingdome of England, so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novvned for Religion and piety in ancient times, is novv fallen: And hovv much vve, that in other Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys enioy freely the meanes of our saluation, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ex alijs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculū facito tibi quod ex vsu fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. <hi>ex Comico.</hi>
      </note> ovve to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and to our Catholike Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
   <p>Wherfore lighting by chāce v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this Proclamation, and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="2" facs="3"/> the good vse that might be made of it, I vvould not follovv the example of another faithfull &amp; zealous Christiā, vvho did teare in peeces vvith publik reproach, such another Edict set vp in <note n="(b)" place="margin">Euseb. lib. 8. hist. cap 3.</note> Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia by Cōmandement of Dioclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: but haue caused it to be trāslated vvord for vvord, into Latin and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther languages, to the end, that the same vvhich the Aduersaries giue out in their priuate tongue, to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify the people of England, being published in other languages, may be of generall <note n="(c)" place="margin">Omnia ad aedificationē fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 26.</note> edification, vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and example, to all other Countreys.</p>
   <p>He canot be trulie said to liue in Christ, nor doth he participate vvith his holy spirit, that hath no feeling of the grieuous vvoundes, vvhich are daily inflicted in the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Multi v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num corpus su<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus in Christo; singuli autē al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alterius mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra. <hi>Rom</hi> 12. 5.</note> body of Christ, nor compassion of
<pb n="5" facs="3"/> the sufferings of his poore brethrē, and of the blindnes and obstinacy of those that persecute them.</p>
   <p>Wherfore let vs aske of God <note n="(e)" place="margin">Vt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tātur à tenebris ad lucem, &amp; de potestate Sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ad Deum. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 18.</note> light for the Persecutors, &amp; pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for them that suffer and for our selues, that by this Exāple vve may learne to feare his iudgments, and to knovv &amp; distinguish the <note n="(f)" place="margin">Quomodo tunc, is qui se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum carnē natus fuerat, persequebatur eum qui secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum spiritum: ita &amp; nunc. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29.</note> tvvo differēt spirits, that appeare in this Letter and Proclamation, and take such vvarning by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiō of the one side, that vve may be partakers of the others revvard, in that charity, and <note n="(g)" place="margin">Totum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, per nexus &amp; coniūctiones constructum &amp; subministratum crescit in ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Dei. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 19.</note> cōmunion of Saintes, vvhich vve Christians acknovvledge, and Christ our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour intendeth to quicken in our harts by these examples: to the end that by these afflictions, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, vvhich his Fatherly goodnes doth suffer to be shed, his Church may increase in number and
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
         <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="6" facs="4"/> Gods glory, and aduancement of his truth, that they testify openly vvhat they belieue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>B. D. de Clerimond.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>