<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS COVNTRIMEN, the Papists in ENGLAND, R. W. wisheth all encrease of knowledge in Spirituall things, with a desire to know the Truth, and power of CHRIST crucified.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119311_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14601</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119311</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS COVNTRIMEN, the Papists in ENGLAND, R. W. wisheth all encrease of knowledge in Spirituall things, with a desire to know the Truth, and power of CHRIST crucified.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A looking-glasse for papists : to see their owne deformities in matters of faith, and religion: and for formall protestants; to make them more carefull of the true profession of Iesus Christ: lest at any time they fall away from the sinceritie of the Gospell of Christ. With a briefe history of the Popes liues, from the first three hundred yeeres after Christ, vntill Paul the fift</title>
                 <author>R. W., minister in Norfolk</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Newbery, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 107, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS COVNTRIMEN, the Papists in ENGLAND, R. W. wisheth all encrease of knowledge in Spirituall things, with a desire to know the Truth, and power of CHRIST crucified.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>RETHREN,</hi> my hearts desire (with <hi>Paul)</hi> and earnest prayer to God for you, is, that you might be saued. For of many of you I may say, <hi>You haue a zeale, but not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> whom I chiefly pitty. But I can not so say of many: who <hi>with-hold the truth in vnrighteousnesse,</hi> their consciences daily accusing them, that they striue against the light, which shineth in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; namely, the word of God: <hi>which is a Lanterne vnto our feete, and a light vnto our paths,</hi> to direct vs in all doubts and difficulties in matters of saluation: The want of the knowledge whereof, is the maine cause of all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as sayth our Sauiour Christ, <hi>Math. 22. 29. Ye erre, not knowing the Scriptures, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>Iohn 5. 39. Search the Scriptures, for in them yee haue eternall life:
<pb facs="3"/> and they are they that testifie of me.</hi> But indeede the god of this world, euen the Diuell, and Sathanas (who knoweth that his kingdome is assaulted by them, and finally shall be ouerthrowne by this breath of his mouth) laboureth by all possible meanes, to stoppe the course thereof. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath set his Agent, the <hi>Pope,</hi> on worke, to take from you the knowledge thereof, to the end, to keepe you in the darkenesse of Idolatrie and superstition; that so his king dome may be continued, and increased, amongst the chilaren of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe. Else why hath hee caused the Scriptures in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue to be publiquely burnt? and the owners of such Bookes, held, and condemned for heretickes, and their bodies also consumed with fire? Againe, why doth hee deliuer the small portions, or fragments of Scripture (which hee vseth in his Lyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rgie vnto the people) in an vnknowne tongue: Teaching them also to pray in Latine, which they vnderstand not; whereas the Apostle, <hi>1 Cor. 14. 19.</hi> sayth: <hi>I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Congregation, speake fiue words to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then tenne thousand words in a strange tongue:</hi> verse 11. and <hi>16. how shall they that occupy the roome of the vnlearned say,</hi> Amen, <hi>at the giuing of thankes?</hi> And againe, verse <hi>23. If one come in vnlearned, will he not say, yee are out of your wittes? &amp;c.</hi> See the whole Chapter: Notwithstanding the Pope, as the Diuels instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath taken from you the vse of your owne language in Gods seruice (pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ended) the fountaine of liuing water, I mean the Scriptures, and <hi>haue digged pits that will holde no water;</hi> I meane their owne decrees, traditions, and constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: which they put vpon the people instead of the word of God, as a rule of life to be obserued, and kept, vpon paine of the Popes curse. Beloued Countreymen, consider I beseech you, what I say, and suffer not the Diuell, by him, to keepe
<pb facs="3"/> your soules captiue, and refuse not the voyce of the <hi>wise Charmers, Psalme 58. 5.</hi> Come, and heare our Ministerie, our prayers, and preaching: and suspect betimes (as others haue done of late, as zealous in your profession as your selues) that all is not well on your side: while they keepe from you the knowledge of your owne euidence, I meane the Scriptures, which propoundeth vnto you your right in that immortall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in heauen; purchased vnto you onely by his most precious bloud-shedding: and by faith in him alone obtained. The Lord giue you a right vnderstanding in all things. And accept, I pray you, of my poore Labours, which is but the glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after other mens haruests. Let not preiudice, or olde er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, cause you to refuse the gift of a friend, that meaneth well vnto you. It will ease you of the search of many Authors, and most of them Papists, for religion, as your selues, &amp;c. You dwell not in <hi>Rome,</hi> nor vnder the Popes command (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the fault be in your selues;) where indeed it would be the danger of your liues to haue any English Booke of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or other bookes against the Pope, or any point of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: But in a kingdome (which thorow Gods mercy) hath ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the Pope and Poperie many dayes since. Vse therefore your libertie: and see what they whom you hold for enemies, can say against your errours. If you refuse this aduice, it is not the Pope that can stand you in stead in the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>but your condemnation shal be so much the more iust, because you haue refused counsell, Ezech. 2. 5.</hi> The Lord giue you a heart to consider of these things aright.</p>
   <p>Your well-willer in Christ Iesus, <hi>R. W.</hi> a poore Minister in Norffolke; <hi>Aetatis suae. 74.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>