<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IVDITIOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119585_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14869</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25173</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119585</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IVDITIOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The deuils law-case. Or, VVhen vvomen goe to law, the Deuill is full of businesse : A new tragecomædy. The true and perfect copie from the originall. As it was approouedly well acted by her Maiesties Seruants. Written by Iohn VVebster</title>
                 <author>Webster, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE IVDITIOVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hold it, in these kind of Poems with that of <hi>Horace, Sap<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ntia prima, stultitia caruisle;</hi> to bee free from those vices, which proceed from ignorance; of which I take it, this Play will ingeniously acquit it selfe. I doe ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ly therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t to the Iudicious: <hi>Locus est, &amp; pluribus Vmb<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is,</hi> oth<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> haue leaue to sit downe, and reade it, who come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. But to these, should a man present them with the most excellent Musicke, it would delight them no more, then <hi>Auriculas Citherae collecta sorde dolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> I will not further insist vpon the approouement of it, for I am so farre from praising my selfe, that I haue not giuen way to diuers of my Friends, whose vnbeg'd Commendatory Verses offered themselues to doe me ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in the Front of this Poeme. A great part of the grace of this (I confesse) lay in Action; yet can no Action euer be gracious, where the decency of the Language, and Ingenious structure of the Scaene, arriue not to make vp a perfect Harmony. What I haue fayl'd of this, You that haue approoued my other Workes, (when you haue read this) taxe me of. For the rest, <hi>Non ego Ventosae Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, Suffragia venor.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>