<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE STVDIOVS YOVNG DIVINES, VVHO ARE DESIROVS To attaine to the knowledge of the Scriptures, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119602_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16291</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25210</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119602</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE STVDIOVS YOVNG DIVINES, VVHO ARE DESIROVS To attaine to the knowledge of the Scriptures, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian synagogue : Wherein is contayned the diverse reading, the right poynting, translation, and collation of scripture with scripture. With the customes of the Hebrewes and proselytes, and of all those nations, with whom they were conversant. Digested into three bookes. The first, shewing the meanes both inward and outward, to attaine to the knowledge of the sense of the whole Scripture. The second, vnfolding the true sense of the Scripture it selfe ... The third, teaching the true manner of confirmation, illustration, and application of doctrines ... Serving generally for a helpe to the vnderstanding, of all; that desire to know and obey the will of God in holy Writ: but more specially for all young students in divinitie, that they may more easily vnderstand the languages of Canaan, and Greece, and make a profitable vse of them in preaching. B Iohn Weemse of Lathoquar, in Scotland, preacher of Christs Gospell</title>
                 <author>Weemes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 221, 3, 86 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE STVDIOVS YOVNG DIVINES, VVHO ARE DESIROVS To attaine to the knowledge of <hi>the Scriptures, Grace, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the earnest Prayer of the <note place="margin">Talmud <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Iewes</hi> (deare Brethren) that, <hi>Aarons rod might flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,</hi> (that is) the children of the Priests might prosper: <hi>Children</hi> in <hi>Iob</hi> are called <hi>budds:</hi> Therefore they called <note place="margin">Iob 29. 5.</note> the children of the Priests <hi>Flores sacerdotales:</hi> when <hi>Aarons</hi> rod flourished it was a token that the Priesthood should continue. It is my heartie prayer to God that <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> rod may still flourish, that there may be a hopefull seed to succeed, and that the Schooles and Vniversities may <note place="margin">Plin. l. 3. c. 12.</note> be like the Pom-citron, that goodly tree, which beareth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="5"/> at all times, some falling off, some ripe, and some bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, out: So, as many notable lights decay, other may sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their places. Now that this may be effectuate, first it is requisite, that yee studie to be holy: for as the ornaments which <hi>Aaron</hi> the high priest put vpon him, were nothing, if he had not <hi>(HOLINES TO THE LORD)</hi> written <note place="margin">Exod. 28. 36.</note> vpon his forehead in a plate of Gold. So, if yee should speake with the tongue of Men and Angels, and be profane, what availeth all your learning. <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, that <hi>beautie</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 22.</note>
      <hi>in a woman without goodnesse, is as a Ring in a Swines snout.</hi> So is learning without grace in a profane Youth.</p>
   <p>The second thing which I would recommend to you (my brethren) is, the studie of the holy Scriptures in their owne proper language, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and the <hi>Greeke;</hi> so that they speake not to you by an interpreter; and that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> may not be applied to you, <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zoma semper foris est: this man is never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in:</hi> for to reade the Scriptures without considering the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, is nothing but a standing in the doore, and never entring within the house, you either cannot, or else you will not. Those that cannot, are to be excused, but those that will not, Let them heare what God saith in the prophecie of <hi>Hosea, Because thou hast despised know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I will also despise thee, that thou shalt be no more Priest to me.</hi> Looke first to the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the Hebrew tongue, which is knowne, first, <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monice,</hi> (by the sound thereof) comparing it with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="5"/> tongues, it borrowes of none, but all borrow of it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is knowne <hi>Etymologice,</hi> by the derivation thereof, for the names that are derived, are either true, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lusiue, or false. Allusiue, <hi>his name is Naball, for he</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 36 1 Sam. 25. 25.</note>
      <hi>is a foole indeed.</hi> False, he is called <hi>Iacob, a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planter.</hi> But the names which the Lord imposed first, were all true, and carry a reason with them why they are so called: as <hi>Adam,</hi> because he was formed out of <hi>redd</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7.</note>
      <hi>earth,</hi> and <hi>Chava,</hi> because she was <hi>the mother of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 20.</note>
      <hi>all living creatures, Abraham,</hi> because he was <hi>the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 16. 5.</note>
      <hi>Father of many Nations, &amp;c.</hi> They cannot therefore be imposed by chance, nor are they allusiue, or false. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the grace, efficacie, and perspicuitie of this Language be considered, it will stirre vp a great delight in thee. Here yee shall not finde the stammering tongue of <hi>Moses,</hi> nor <note place="margin">Exod 4. 10.</note> the polluted lippes of <hi>Esay,</hi> nor <hi>Ieremy</hi> speaking as a <note place="margin">Esay 6. 5. Iere. 1. 6.</note> childe: but yee shall heare the Lord himselfe speaking: <hi>Who spake as never▪man spake.</hi> Leaue the rotten <note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 46.</note> Cisternes, praise the Rivers, but commend the Fountaines aboue all. Yee haue many helps now, which your Fathers had not in former ages. It was the complaint of one <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hhagiga</hi> in his time, that the Fathers had plowed, sowen, reaped, fanned the Wheat, and set the Bread vpon the Table: but the children had not a mouth to eate it. Let it not be so said of you, when all things are so prepared for you.</p>
   <p>Many worthy Divines haue travelled in this subiect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, chiefly that worthy Divine <hi>M. Perkins,</hi> in his
<pb facs="6"/> Prophetico <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>cuius memoria in benedictione.</hi> So <hi>Hyperius,</hi> and <hi>Keckerman;</hi> but that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> incouraged me. <hi>1 Cor. 14. 30.</hi> (When he sayes) <hi>If any thing be revealed to him that sitteth by, let the first hold his peace, for ye may all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie one by one, that all may learne, and all may haue comfort.</hi> Some little gleanings perhaps ye may finde here, for the Lords harvest is so great that all cannot be gathered in A Dwarfe set vpon the shoulders of a Giant, will see some thing which the Giant himselfe cannot see.</p>
   <p>As for you who haue your senses exercised, I take not <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 11</note> vpon m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to giue any directions to you, but submit my selfe most humbly to your charitable censure: wishing that some of you who haue greater light, would prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this kinde of studie, which is so profitable to the Church of God, remembring that saying of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Buxtorf. abbrev.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Math 25. 19.</note>
      <hi>qui addunt ipsis addetur, &amp; qui sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strahit, substrahetur ipsi▪ vnto every man that hath, it shall be given, and from him that hath not, even that he hath, shall be taken away.</hi> If any thing be said amisse, reproue me, and it shall be like a precious oyle that shall not breake my head: If any thing be <note place="margin">Psal 141. 5.</note> well done, giue the Lord the first fruits, and take the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to your selues. Thus leaving my travels to your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iudgement, I bid you farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>