<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To RABBONI: My deare Lord and Master, my soueraigne Sauiour IESVS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119401_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14669</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24970</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To RABBONI: My deare Lord and Master, my soueraigne Sauiour IESVS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rabboni : Mary Magdalens teares, of sorrow, solace. The one for her Lord being lost. The other for him being found. In way of questioning. Wondring. Reioycing. ... Preached at S. Pauls Crosse, after the rehearsall, and newly reuised and enlarged: by Thomas Walkington, Docto in Diuinity, and minister of the Word at Fulham</title>
                 <author>Walkington, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitaker, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To RABBONI: My deare Lord and Master, my soueraigne Sauiour IESVS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F all our limbes, ô Lord, were turned into tongues, they all were far vnfit, and most vnable, to limbe and pencill frrth thy praises, to pay their due debt of dutifull thanksgiuings, for all thy gracious mercies and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances: Thy heauenly worth may be
<pb facs="3"/>
be much more adored by silence, then by our ruder vtterance, In lieu of that my humblest deuotion I owe vnto thy Sacred Selfe (the Beame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of that euer-glorious Sunne) I haue selected no other Patron, but Thee, ô Lord, my sole Aduancer, whose deuoted (though vnworthy) Chaplaine I euer wish to bee: To whom I dedicate and consecrate these few lines, the true coppy of my loyallest affections, the <hi>Widowes Mite,</hi> this poore <hi>Corban,</hi> which I cast into thy Treasury, not out of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, but meere penury: desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to bee inriched with thine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant mercy.</p>
   <p>I am (ô my <hi>Rabboni</hi>) obliged much more: I owe my selfe, and that Ile pay, and would pay more, if more I had: but all I haue, and all that is within me, praise thy holy name.</p>
   <p>The good things, ô Lord, I haue
<pb facs="3"/>
receiued of thy bounteous hands of mercy, I merit not, and the euills which I haue not receiued at thy hand of Iustice, I doe deserue: O let mee partake of the sweet influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thy blessings, from the mount <hi>Gerisin,</hi> and free me from thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses on that mount <hi>Ebal.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I aime not at the guerdon of this respectlesse world, the mouldring rubbidge and remainder of our fall, the defaced Embleme of our ruine: for wee know that euery creature groneth with vs also, and trauelleth in paine together vnto this present.</p>
   <p>I breath and pant after true per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that vnfathomed blisse of thine: who will giue me the wings of a Doue (hauing the Oliue-branch of peace of conscience and ioy in the Holy Ghost) then would I flye away, and be at rest, and set footing in that thy Celestiall Arke, free from all sublunary inundations. Let the
<pb facs="4"/>
impure Rauens, who vsually ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne the day of their conuersion, continue still to feed on putrid cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the garbidge of transgression, and neuer haue any care thither, to returne vnto thy Arke againe, I sure will feede on Thee, the Bread of life, the <hi>Manna</hi> that came downe from <hi>Beth-lechem,</hi> the house of Bread.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Omnia amarescunt, vt tu mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi Domine dulcescas:</hi> All things of this life doe vtterly distaste my soule, like vineger and gall, and myrrhed wine, in respect of that true gust and relish of thy goodnesse and sweetnes, which in this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pilgrimage to heauenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> that flowes with milke and hony of eternity, thou exhibitest vnto vs all, as a <hi>viaticum,</hi> or iournall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision in that holy <hi>Eucharist,</hi> thy pure flesh, our meat; thy prizelesse drops of bloud, our drinke,</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Lord, I haue lou'd the beauty of thine house, and the place where thine Honour dwelleth: my soule gaspeth after God, as a thirsty and dry land where no water is: My soule thirsteth for God, euen for the liuing God, ô when shall I appeare before thy presence?</p>
   <p>There is my true Treasury, and there my heart also.</p>
   <p>O good <hi>Iesu,</hi> be vnto me a <hi>Iesus,</hi> a Sauiour (thus will I cry with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout <hi>Anselmus</hi>) and to all that doe beleeue in thee: Else when thou sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test on that glorious Tribunall to iudge the quicke and dead, when those bookes shall once be opened, of all our <hi>Item'd</hi> accounts, and of all our consciences, each line writ in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall red letters accusing vs, euery letter condemning vs, (for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter kills) then with <hi>Iob</hi> wee'l say, Loe wee are vile, and cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb facs="5"/>
thee, one of a thousand, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy sweet prompting mercies.</p>
   <p>We humbly beg at thy rich hands, by thy brinish teares, and precious bloud thou once didst shed, and by that vnparalleld loue, that shed both teares &amp; bloud, blot out that <hi>Cheirograph,</hi> the hand-writing of ordinances against vs all. Though wee haue committed that which iustly might condemne vs, Thou hast nor lost, nor forgot that, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou canst assoyle and saue vs: O say vnto our soules, that thou art our saluation.</p>
   <p>O let thy crimson prizelesse drops of bloud, that yet thrill and trickle downe thy azur'd veines, to each beleeuing soule (they being not yet dry) let that truest Purgatorie expiate our crimson scarlet sins.</p>
   <p>O our good and gracious <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boni,</hi> what are we (vile wretches)
<pb facs="5"/>
without thee: Lodges of sin: cages of all impurity: lothsome and nasty carcasses; scarce fit to bee repast for wormes, who iustly might expect and gape for far more dainty mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells: satchells full of all corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: vnrinsed vessels of dishonour: and fuell for <hi>Tophet</hi> in <hi>Geben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinnom.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>All our hopes is in thy death, ó Iesu: thy death is my merit, my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit thy mercy, and thy mercy the pulley, to draw on that death, to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some mee, and make mee merit. I neuer can be bankrupt in merit, so long as thou, ô Lord, art so rich in mercy.</p>
   <p>O good Iesu, my <hi>Rabboni,</hi> thou that didst daigne to descend from the <hi>Zenith</hi> of all glory, to dwell in the <hi>Nadir</hi> of all obscurity; the pure crystalline spring, that issued from the boundlesse sea of all blessednesse:
<pb facs="6"/>
Thou euer-flourishing Spray, and Science of Eternity: The delicious Fruit of the Virgins wombe; the sacred Inne where thou vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedst to take vp lodging in: The Sourcing Fountaine of all Graces, and of all our Actions: The Hope of all the ends of the Earth: The Sanctuary and Refuge of all our sinfull soules: The Anchor of our hopes, euen from our mothers brests: The Crowner of our patient Triumphes: Our sweetest Solace and Companion, in this wildernesse of Sin, as wee goe along vnto the Land of Promise: The Hauen and Harbour of our Rest: The Consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Blisse: Accept, ô Lord, our meaner sacrifice, our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locaust, that Burnt-offering of praise, we tender and present vpon the Altars of our hearts, wholly enflamed with the loue of Thee.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>O Lord, lodge in the poore Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of our soules: bee Thou there entombed, ô good Iesu, stay thou there in that Sepulcher, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in neuer man (as our maine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) but God and Man was yet layd: roll away the heauy Tomb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, our flintinesse of heart, that presseth Thee downe, as a Cart with sheafes: yet Lord abide there still: Abide with vs, for it draweth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night, and the day of our life is far spent: O let it neuer bee sayd of Thee, — <hi>Resurrexit, non est hîc:</hi> He is risen, he is not heere. Lord ouer-mantle vs with thy mercy: illumine our darkned capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city: accept this our loyall duty: can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell all our debts: create in vs cleane hearts: support and vnder-shore vs with thy diuine and gracious hand, from future further lapsing: binde vs vp all in the bundle of</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>