<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authour to his Book.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119865_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15139</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25437</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119865</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authour to his Book.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasante historie, of Albino and Bellama : A poeme. To which is annexed the vindication of poesie. by N.W</title>
                 <author>Whiting, Nathaneel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fussell, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 143, 25 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_his_book">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Authour to his Book.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>GOe gall-lesse infant of my teeming Quill,</l>
      <l>Not yet bedewd in Syracusa's rill,</l>
      <l>And like a forward Plover gadst abroad,</l>
      <l>Ere shell free, or before full age has strowd</l>
      <l>On thy smooth backe a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te of feathers,</l>
      <l>To arme thee 'gainst the force of weathers,</l>
      <l>Doomd to the censure of all Ages,</l>
      <l>Ere m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l'd against the youngest rages,</l>
      <l>Perchance some Nobles will thee view,</l>
      <l>Smile at thee, on thee, like thee new,</l>
      <l>But when white age has wrinkled thee,</l>
      <l>Will slight thy measures laugh at mee,</l>
      <l>At first view called pritty,</l>
      <l>And perchance stiled witty</l>
      <l>By some Ladies, untill thou</l>
      <l>Wearest surrowes on thy brow.</l>
      <l>Some plumed G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>llants, may</l>
      <l>Vnclasp thy leaves and say,</l>
      <l>Th'art mirthful, but er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> long</l>
      <l>Give place unto a Song.</l>
      <l>Some courteous Scholler</l>
      <l>Turg'd from all choller,</l>
      <l>May like, but at last,</l>
      <l>Say thou spoylst his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st,</l>
      <l>First, Lawyers whl</l>
      <l>Commend thy skil,</l>
      <l>Last, throw thy wit</l>
      <l>With Trin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ts writ</l>
      <l>Chamber shees</l>
      <l>On their knees</l>
      <l>wil thee praise,</l>
      <l>and thy bayes,</l>
      <l>At first,</l>
      <l>till thirst</l>
      <l>of newe</l>
      <l>death you,</l>
      <l>then all</l>
      <l>men shal</l>
      <l>Flee</l>
      <l>thee</l>
      <l>Bee</l>
      <l>me.</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <lg>
      <l>THis is thy doome, I by prophetick spirit,</l>
      <l>Presage will be the guerdon of my merit:</l>
      <l>Yet be no Burre, no trencher-flye, nor hound,</l>
      <l>To fawn on them whose tongs thy measures wound.</l>
      <l>Nor beg those niggards eyes, who grudge to see</l>
      <l>A watch unwinded in perusing thee.</l>
      <l>And if state-scratchers doe condemne thy jests,</l>
      <l>For ruffling sattens, and bespangled vests,</l>
      <l>Tell them they're cosend, and in vain they puffe,</l>
      <l>Thou neither aim'st at halfe-ell band or ruffe;</l>
      <l>And if thy lines perchance some <hi>Ermins</hi> gash,</l>
      <l>Tis not thy fault, twas no intended lash.</l>
      <l>Thy pensill limbs <hi>Don Fuco's</hi> portraicture,</l>
      <l>And onely dost his native worth immure</l>
      <l>Within these tilick rindes: nor is thy rage</l>
      <l>Against the Cow lists of this yongest age.</l>
      <l>Thy rithmes cry <hi>Pax</hi> to all, nor dost thou scatter</l>
      <l>Abuses on their shrines, their Saints, or water;</l>
      <l>And if some civill Satyr lash thee backe,</l>
      <l>Because he reads my title, sees my black,</l>
      <l>Answer ith' Poets phrase, and tell them more,</l>
      <l>My tale of yeares had scarce out-sum'd a score</l>
      <l>When my young phansie these light measures meant</l>
      <l>The Presse: but Fate since canceld that intent,</l>
      <l>Nor claim'd the Church as then a greater part</l>
      <l>In me than others, bate my title Art—</l>
      <l>But now the scean is chang'd? confest it is</l>
      <l>Must we abjure all youth, borne, bury this?</l>
      <l>Such closet death's desertlesse, in this glasse</l>
      <l>Read not what now I am, but then I was:</l>
      <l>In this reflection may the gravest see</l>
      <l>How true we suite, I, this, and this with mee.</l>
      <l>These thornes pickt out, whose venome might have bred</l>
      <l>A gangtene in thy Reader, struck thee dead,</l>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <l>Thou mayst perhaps invited be to court,</l>
      <l>And have a brace of smiles t'approve thy sport.</l>
      <l>Those, whose grave wisdomes, <hi>Wise</hi> do them entitle</l>
      <l>(Whose learned nods lowd ignorance can stifle)</l>
      <l>Some of times numbers on thy lines will scatter,</l>
      <l>If not cald from thee by some higher matter,</l>
      <l>Laugh out a rubber, like, and say 'tis good</l>
      <l>For pleasure, youth and leasure, wholesome food.</l>
      <l>Some jigging Silk-canary, newly bloom'd,</l>
      <l>When he is crisped, bathed, oyld, perfum'd,</l>
      <l>(Which till the second chime, will scarce be done)</l>
      <l>Vpon thy feet will make his chrystals run,</l>
      <l>Commend the author, vow him service ever,</l>
      <l>But from such things his Genius him deliver.</l>
      <l>Some sleeked Nymphs, of countrey, citie, court,</l>
      <l>Will, next their Dogges and Monkies, like thy sport,</l>
      <l>Smile, and admire, and wearied will (perhaps)</l>
      <l>Lay thee to sleepe encurtaind in their laps,</l>
      <l>Oh happy thou! who would not wish to be</l>
      <l>(To gaine such dainty lodging) such, or thee?</l>
      <l>Say, to please them, the Poet undertooke</l>
      <l>To make thee from a sheet thrive to a booke,</l>
      <l>And if he has to beauty giv'n a gem,</l>
      <l>He challengeth a deck of thankes from them:</l>
      <l>And if some winning creature smile on thee,</l>
      <l>She shall his L. and his <hi>Bellama</hi> bee.</l>
      <l>Betwixt eleven and one, some <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Will snatch a phansie from thee, and put on</l>
      <l>A glove or ring of thine to court his lasse,</l>
      <l>Twixt Tearme and Tearme, when they are turnd to grasse.</l>
      <l>Some <hi>Titius</hi> will lay by his wax and bookes,</l>
      <l>And nim a phrase to bait his amorous hookes.</l>
      <l>But stay, I shall be chid, me thinkes I heare</l>
      <l>A censure spread its wings to reach my eare.</l>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <l>Tell me I am conceited: then no more,</l>
      <l>Go take thy chance, I turne thee out oth' dore.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>