<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120313_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15734</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26003</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120313</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dangerous plot discovered : By a discourse, wherein is proved, that, Mr: Richard Mountague, in his two bookes; the one, called A new gagg; the other, A iust appeale: laboureth to bring in the faith of Rome, and Arminius: vnder the name and pretence of the doctrine and faith of the Church of England. A worke very necessary for all them which haue received the truth of God in loue, and desire to escape errour. The reader shall finde: 1. A catalogue of his erroneous poynts annexed to the epistle to the reader. 2. A demonstration of the danger of them. cap. 21. num 7. &amp;c. pag. 178. 3. A list of the heads of all the chapters contained in this booke</title>
                 <author>Wotton, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 84, 190, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough, I haue no delight in making a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face: for I see not any great need of it: yet I here present thee with one, because, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome calls for it. In this Preface, I will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise thee of some things, even of such (and no more) as shall helpe thee, to make the better vse of the ensuing Discourse; which, I will doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so with as much brevitie as I can. First know, That, this Treatise was chiefly intended for my owne satisfaction, but is now published for the benefit of others. The manner of handling the poynts in it, is scholasticall; and it might be no other; because the things themselues, and the partie opposed, require it. Besides, this course of writing is profitable for thee; for thereby, 1. The matters in question, are layd before thee nakedly, and, as it were, in both ends of the Ballance. 2. All impertinent Discourses are prevented, and all ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings avoyded: so as, now thou hast nothing to iudge of, but the matter it selfe. I haue directed my Disputation against both of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>: <hi>Mountague</hi> his Bookes; The <hi>Gagge,</hi> and the Appeale: because the whole evill, could not be found out, in any one of them alone. All the sentences, and severall pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, in this Discourse, pretended to be collected, and framed out of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>: <hi>Mountague</hi> his Bookes, are truly, and plainly, and ingenuously collected, and framed according as they are in his Bookes themselues. If any errour be committed in them, it ariseth from the greatnes of their number, or from his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure
<pb facs="6"/> manner of setting downe his intent. It may be, some will account the publishing hereof to be needlesse: because o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done so much already, as is fit to be done, in this businesse. I answer; The publishing hereof, is to good purpose: For, many witnesses to the truth▪ giues the greater glory to it, and procures a freer passage for it, amongst men: Besides, I doubt not, but, by this Discourse, the Reader shall be put in minde, of some things, which he would haue forgotten, or not observed, in the Bookes that are published already. Lastly, None of this kinde▪ haue beene published already: For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, more poynts are handled, then were touched in them: and, these which are discussed in this, are framed in another manner, and doe tend to an end, which they did not. I haue concealed my name: not because I am, (or haue cause to be) vnwilling it should be knowne: But because, I desire to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stall personall quarrells; so frequent with M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>: <hi>Mountague:</hi> And, because, I suppose, the annexing of my name hereto, is of no great vse vnto the Reader; for as much, as he must receiue satisfaction, in the poynts of faith, from the divine testimony, not from any humane authoritie whatsoever. One thing (onely) remaines: That is, That, I intreat thee, to seeke for satisfaction, and an assured ground, for thy faith, in the present questions: For, it is thy dutie so to doe. The Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stle <hi>Iude</hi> doth exhort that <hi>we contend, for the faith, once given to the Saints.</hi> If thou standest an Idle behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not regarding which end goes forward: what wilt thou say? How wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t thou answer it vnto God? Wilt thou say, This sentence of the Apostle <hi>Iude,</hi> is not a Commandement? I answer; the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stles phrase, and manner of speaking, will then refute thee: For, every such exhortation, is either a Commandement, or presumes a dutie alreadie commanded other-where: as wee may see by the like places of Scripture,
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>1 Thes. 4. 2. 2 Thes. 3. 12.</hi> Wilt thou answer, That, it is no Commandement vnto thee? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e words will then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue thee also; for, they are extended vnto all men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limitation: And that Epistle is called a generall Epist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. Wilt thou say, it is an affirmatiue Commandement; and▪ therefore it may not, binde thee at this time: because such Commandements doe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t binde to all times? I answer; Thou canst not be free from this Commandement, (even) it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> time, vnlesse thou canst find, some part of the div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that shall free thee: For, Thy selfe canst not free thy selfe there-from: seeing thou art to be at Gods dispose: not at thine owne choyse. Therefore, If thou wilt fancy to thy selfe, this, or that reason, to exempt thy selfe from this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, thou art no other, but, the man that sayth: <hi>A Lyon is in the way, I shall be slaine in the streets.</hi> Lastly, when wilt thou then thinke thy selfe bound by this law, if thou be free at this time? Is not the faith of God now at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>take? Doe not the Foxes out of their holes, seek to eat vp the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Vine? Does not the Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re out of the Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rest labour to root vp the Lords Plant? Now, now, therefore is the time, yea, high time for thee to take thy selfe bound by this law of God, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Wilt thou imagine, that thou shalt not giue an account of thy neglect of this dutie? Surely, then thy thoughts are most vaine; for, canst thou forget the Lords voyce, that saith, <hi>Arise, O you dead, and come vnto Iudgement;</hi> and sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> we come to Iudgement, and not account with the Lord▪ Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, canst thou forget that voyce, which saith: <hi>Every man shall giue an account, for every idle word▪</hi> much more, for every fruitlesse deed? I say, this thy negligence is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪ because it is voluntary, thou doest choose to be negligent. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> fruitlesse, because, no good comes of it, vnto Gods glory, or thine owne salvation. Wherefore, I will conclude, fould thy
<pb facs="7"/> hands no longer together, like the sluggard: giue thy eyes no rest, nor thy eye-lids no slumber; spare for no labour; grutch not for cost, till thou be setled, and grounded vpon the Rocke of Gods revealed truth: so shalt thou stand in the perillous time, and be readie to goe into the Bride-chamber, when the Bridegroome commeth. And, this is all I will say to thee.</p>
   <p>For thy furtherance, I haue annexed herevnto,
<list>
         <item>1. A Catalogue of the erroneous poynts which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in his Booke, and the places where they are.</item>
         <item>2. A list of the heads of every Chapter in the Booke.</item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <p>His poynts of the <hi>Popish Faith,</hi> are these which follow.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1. THe Church is Iudge in Divinitie questions, that be in Controversie.</item>
      <item>2. We receiue the decisions of the Catholike Church, as the dictates of the holy Spirit. cap. 2.</item>
      <item>3. The Church representatiue, cannot erre in poynts of faith. cap. 4. at the beginning, and num. 2. pag. 12.</item>
      <item>4. There ever was, and will be vpon earth, a visible Church, vnto which Complaints may be made. cap. 5. at the beginning, num. 4. p. 26.</item>
      <item>5. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is a true Church of Christ, a part of the Catholike Church, which wee professe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in our Creed. cap. 6. at the beginning, and num. 7. p. 37.</item>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <item>6. We grant the generall being, working, and concurring of Free-will with Gods grace: after preventing grace, man doth freely renounce the calling of grace, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly runne. cap. 7. p. 53.</item>
      <item>7. Iustification consisteth in remission of sinnes primarily, and grace infused secondarily. cap. 9. pag. 83. cap. 10. num. 17. &amp;c.</item>
      <item>8. Both remission of sinnes, and grace infused, are the acts of Gods spirit in man cap. 9. p. 83. c. 10. num. 23. &amp;c.</item>
      <item>9. A man (yea the Elect) may loose the habit of grace cap. 11. p. 37.</item>
      <item>10. Sinne is mortall, and veniall.</item>
      <item>11. The habit of grace is common to the predestinate, and not predestinate. cap. 12. num. 2. &amp; 3.</item>
      <item>12. Every child duly baptized, is thereby put into the state of grace and salvation. cap. 12. num. 11. p. 55.</item>
      <item>13. Mortall sinne onely disobeyeth Gods law. cap. 12. num. 17. p. 64. &amp; 65.</item>
      <item>14. A man habituated by grace, may commit mortall sin. cap. 12. num. 17. p. 63. &amp; 64.</item>
      <item>15. There is no difference between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and ours, in the poynt of Reall presence. cap. 13 p. 81. The onely difference betweene vs, is about <hi>Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation.</hi> cap. 14. num. 2. p: 82. 83.</item>
      <item>16. The pictures of Christ, the blessed Virgin, and Saints, may be set vp in Churches. Respect is due, and honour
<pb facs="8"/> given Relatiuely vnto them. They may be vsed for helps of pietie: To represent the prototype: Instruct the vnlearned, renew remembrance. cap. 15. p. 94. &amp; 95.</item>
      <item>17. A man may doe more then he is tyed vnto by any Law of God. cap. 17. p: 107.</item>
      <item>These workes are left to a mans choyse; They procure reward to him that doth them, and he that doth them not, is without danger of punishment therfore. cap. 18. num. 2. p. 109. They are to be found in Virginitie, and wilfull Povertie. cap. 18. num. 12. p. 120.</item>
      <item>18. Finall persevering in obedience, is the instrumentall cause of mans salvation. cap. 20. num. 27. p. 161. 162.</item>
   </list>
   <p>The poynts of the false Faith of <hi>Arminius</hi> doe follow.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1. I <hi>Conceiue of predestinatiō, that it is Gods act of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out which tooke hold of mercy. cap. 19. p. 126. 127. cap. 20. num. 3. &amp; 4. &amp; num. 7. p.</hi> 139.</item>
      <item>2. <hi>Man being prevented by grace, he putteth to his hand to procure augmentation of that grace.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Man being drawne, he runneth as his assistance, his owne agilitie and disposition is. cap. 7. p. 53. cap. 8. num. 22. &amp;</hi> 23.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>