<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Consideration of the Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120763_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09880</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20142</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Consideration of the Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A consideration of the depriued and silenced ministers arguments, for their restitution to the vse and libertie of their ministerie : exhibited in their late supplication, vnto the honorable states assembled in this present Parliament. By Gabriel Powel</title>
                 <author>Powel, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="10" facs="7"/>
   <head>A Consideration of the Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Preface, by way of Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, the Authors of this Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation labour to expresse their meaning more plainely, and to cleare some wordes and phrases, which otherwise might seeme subiect to missin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and (as they speake) to <hi>vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble construction:</hi> which cautelous dealing verily is most necessarie in this carping age, wherein the common Aduersarie, to couer his own shame for his rebellious and traiterous Positions and Practises, lieth houering in the winde, ready to catch at any thing that may aduantage himselfe, and preiudice our cause.</p>
   <p>And surely for my own part, I am so farre from taking any exception against my Brethren in this kinde,<note place="margin">Of the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians towards their Prince.</note> that I verily thinke, that all wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the Gospell within this kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, howsoeuer some haue folishly made a breach &amp; diuision amongst vs, about Crosse, Surplice, &amp;c. doe as hartily and faithfully loue, &amp; as dutifully affect and imbrace our Prince or King (yea of whatsoeuer Religion) and are as ready and willing to defend his Person and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour against all aduersarie power or treacherous attempt whatsoeuer, as any other people or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnder the sunne.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, as I cannot allow the opinion of such as giue out, that these our factious Brethren, <hi>are as dangerous enemies vnto the State, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes,</hi> those Antichristian and bloody Traytours,
<pb n="11" facs="7"/>that neuer are faithfull vnto any, but vnto the Pope and the Diuell: So I cannot but worthily commend that memorable apothegme of that reuerend and learned Prelate <hi>Doctor Elmer</hi> of happy memory, sometimes L. Byshop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, who when this question was debated in his hearing, grauely answered. <hi>If I were in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but of one Papist, I might iustly feare the losse of my life, but being amongst ten thousand Precisians well might I be affrayde of my Byshoprike, but neuer of my throate.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">An Apotheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Bishop Elmer,</note>
      <hi>The one would cut my coate, and the other my throate.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neither doe I speake this, absolutely to free such as be Refractarie among vs, from all disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto Magistrates, but onely from suspici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Treason and Rebellion. For otherwise it cannot be denied,<note place="margin">That Precisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and turbulent.</note> but that presumptuously and wilfully they contend with the Magistrate, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning his authoritie in things indifferent, and soueraigntie in Ecclesiastical causes (though not in the same sense and degree as the Papistes do) and also that they make a faction and manifest Schisme in the Church of GOD: which all of them do for carnall respectes:<note place="margin">And why</note> some because they knowe not otherwise howe to be maintayned but by depending vpon that faction, some to gratifie their Benefactors and Patrons, and to please their Friends, some for discontentment and want of preferment, some for giddinesse of innouation, some for pride of heart and self-loue, some for hatred of order and restraint of their libertie, some still to retaine the opinion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy
<pb n="12" facs="8"/>in perseuering singular, and others of mere ignorance. which yet is wilful and affected, seeing they will not learne the State of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie which they are bound to know, and therefore cannot be excused.</p>
   <p>But two things specially may be iustly censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and taxed in this Preface: whereof the first is, that herein they haue quite altered the state of the question in controuersie, betweene vs: which surely argueth a desperate diffidence to preuaile in their suite, by declining the
<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall matter of difference: For, whereas it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed by themselues, aswell in the very Title, as afterwards in the Booke it selfe <hi>Arg.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; Arg.</hi> 18. that the whole controuersie betweene vs is, but about <hi>Subscription, Ceremonies, the strict obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the booke of Commen Prayer, and other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie</hi> vnto the Discipline and order of our Church (for this I take to bee their meaning) which are but matters of indifferency and of smal moment in themselues: Now they seeme to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt it, forsooth, <hi>the Cause of GOD, the Ministerie of the Gospell, the saluation of the people, the maine cause of the land, of all the States</hi> of this kingdome
<hi>and all their posteritie;</hi> and such a cause, as is <hi>to be preferred before al other causes whatsoeuer, either cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any particular persons, or the whole Cōmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:</hi> as if all Religion and Pietie depended vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on refusing of Crosse &amp; Surplice, and such other accidentall circumstances.</p>
   <p>The Latter is, that they boldly, presumptuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vndutifully censure his Maiestie, for coldenesse in Religion, in relinquishing his former
<pb n="13" facs="8"/>profession, or at least for deepe dissembling in see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to pretend one thing, &amp; to intend another: as if he had bin trained vp &amp; taught in the Iesuits schooles, to Equivocate: (which fault, would God, some of their factiō &amp; followers did so little practise, as his Highnes abhors it.) Whereas his Highnesse religious heart is euidently and easily discerned, to be fully seasoned with true pietie and devotion, aswell by his present sincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the Gospell, and vnfained loue vnto the Ministers thereof, as also by daily effects of saith and a good conscience, which as sweete smelling fruites do liuely demonstrate the goodnesse and excellencie of the tree. But I referre the farther consideration of this point vnto your graue wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: onely it suffiseth me to haue detected the license of their raving pens, the restraint of which furie, specially belongeth vnto your Honourable &amp; iudicious Court. Which (questionles) your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours will the rather performe, considering what an vnchristian conceipt they haue aswell of your Honourable Assemblie, as also of all other his Maiesties louing Subiects and Seruants, who loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obey him &amp; serue the Lord of Hostes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the Religion established; as is manifest by their instance and allegation of that example of the Emperour
<hi>Constantius</hi> his Nobles, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Idolaters and Atheists, to curry fauour with the Emperour: as also because afterwards, <hi>in the</hi>
8. <hi>Argument,</hi> they boldly censure your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, as <hi>not regarding the Church, nor the cause of God,</hi> faining moreouer, how <hi>GOD and his sonne
<pb n="14" facs="9"/>CHRIST IESVS stand, as it were, at your Parliament House dore knocking, and crauing to be let in,</hi> insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating thereby, that GOD is not President of your honorable Assemblie, and that all your godly and Religious Acts haue beene hetherto decreed and concluded, I know not by what spirit. Now let vs examine their Arguments.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>