<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>CERTAYNE ADVERTISMENTS necessary for the better making of
our Prayer. §. 4.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120493_Ba1_1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11539</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>CERTAYNE ADVERTISMENTS necessary for the better making of
our Prayer. §. 4.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An abridgement of Christian perfection : Conteining many excellent precepts, &amp; aduertisments, touching the holy, and sacred mysticall diuinity. Written in Italian, by Fa. Achilles Galliardi of the Society of Iesus, &amp;translated into English, A.H. of the same society</title>
                 <author>Galliardi, Achilles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>216 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="advice">
   <head>CERTAYNE ADVERTISMENTS necessary for the better making of
our Prayer. §. 4.</head>
   <p>BEFORE Prayer, the Soule must exercise it selfe in some
acts of Humility, by considering its owne basenes, and the greatnes of God,
with whom it is to treate, and falling down vpon our knees we must begin with
the signe of the Crosse, blessing our selues, and crauing of the
diuine Maiesty grace, to spend that short tyme <pb n="213" facs="98"/>well,
which we are to imploy in that holy Exercise; so as all out thoughts,
words, and workes may be sincerely addressed to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory of
God. Moreouer we must imagine a certayne Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of place, and therein
accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate our selues in such manner as is taught vs, by our spirituall
Father and Directour in that case. Finally we must perswade out selues,
that we stand in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God, who is both within &amp; round about
vs, to the end that the imagination therof may incite vs to greater attention,
cōfidence, and reuerence. Next we must aske of the diuine goodnes that,
which we desire, answerable to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherof the meditation is to be
made. For example, if I meditate of sin, I will craue pardon for my owne
&amp;c.</p>
   <p>We must also make one, or more <pb n="214" facs="99"/>Colloquies at the end, according to the motions, &amp; affection which
the soule shall feele in it selfe, in speaking sometimes to the
Blessed Trinity, sometymes to euery one of the three Diuine Persons, or
to the B. Virgin, or the Saints, giuing thankes other whiles for benefits
receiued, other whiles crauing Gods help, for getting of some one vertue in
particuler.</p>
   <p>The repetitions, that our B. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther S.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gnatius teacheth in the first
Weeke of his Spirituall Exercises must be made after two, or three
meditations, in such manner, as is specified in the same place, making
three Colloquies, to wit, to the Father, to the Sonne, and to the B.
Virgin.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>