<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLY-DESCENDED, AND VERTVOVSLY-ACCOMPLISHED Mr. RICHARD GARGRAVE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120945_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08538</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18857</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120945</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLY-DESCENDED, AND VERTVOVSLY-ACCOMPLISHED Mr. RICHARD GARGRAVE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epitome of Ortelivs his Theatre of the vvorld : vvherein the principal regions of the earth are described in smalle mappes. VVith a brief declaration annexed to ech mappe. And donne in more exact manner, then the lyke declarations in Latin, French, or other languages. It is also amplyfied with new mappes wanting in the Latin editions</title>
                 <author>Ortelius, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Swingen (Swingenius), Hendrik</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 110, 3, 13, 1 leave, maps (metal cuts), oblong 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLY-DESCENDED, AND VERTVOVSLY-ACCOMPLISHED M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. RICHARD GARGRAVE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST vvoorthy sir, no sooner did this stranger my friend set foot on English shore, but being desirous to trauail North, I could not devise vvhere he should finde more condigne &amp; respectiue intertainment then vnder your most fauourable roof. It appears by his many languages, namely Latin, Italian, French, Spanish, high &amp; lovv Dutch, and novv lastly English, that he hath sometimes bin a traueler. And so indeed if you examin him throughly, you shall finde he hath, asvvell by sea as by land. In his discourses he is vnlike the greatest part of our trauellers, vvho vvith their tedious &amp; fabulous narrations vvill bring either deafnes to your eares or slumber to your eyes. But this man speakes nothing but matter, and that so succinctly, as by his conference you may reap delight, &amp; yet not hinder your affaires of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance or recreation. Giue him incouragement in the North, and ere long you shall see him come ouer in another habit, to try vvhat acceptance the south vvill affourd him. Thus doing, you shall not onely grace him &amp; benefit your country, but in all dutifull seruices you shall make mee his poore vvel-vviller,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours Most truly deuoted.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>