<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>POSTSCRIPT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120679_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02702</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12836</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120679</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>POSTSCRIPT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hezekiah's recovery. Or, A sermon, shevving what use Hezekiah did, and all should make of their deliverance from sickenesse. First preached, and now published by Robert Harris, pastor of Hanwell</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb n="41" facs="26"/>
   <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
   <p>ANd here London, let mee addresse one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to thee: Hitherto we have stood amazed at thy miserie and sudden change, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time sorrow hath thrust out sad complaints, <hi>How doth the Citie sit solitary that was full of people, &amp;c. Lam.</hi> 1.1. sometimes silence hath swallowed up all words and left us speechlesse, like, <hi>lob,</hi> friends: now me thought we heard thy in habitors crying, <hi>Is it nothing, &amp;c. Lam.</hi> 1.12. now again thy friends standing aloofe for feare, as once men shall for Babel crying our, <hi>Alas, alas that great Citie <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> bo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re is thy judgement come &amp;c. Rev.</hi> 18. <note place="margin">Latuimus quis tuta civitas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausta. &amp;c. Chrys. hom. <hi>11.</hi> ad pop. Ant. <hi>Sir W. Ral.</hi>
      </note> In this case thou wast not at leisure to heare not wee in case to speake: At such a time to tell thee of thy faults, had been (as one who wanted not wit, spake) to upbraid thee with thy fortune, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> than to seeke thy reformation. But now the case is altered, the heavens are cleered, and thou with them. Now its time for all thy friends to call upon thee, for thee to call upon, thy selfe. Wee have waited long to hears when thou wouldest say, O all ye that mourned for mee, now rejoyce with me, and repay as manie thankes for me, as I have had prayers from you. Take head, no thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse soone spends what prayers hath bin long in geting; forfeit not all againe for want of thankes. Looke upon <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> he was sicke and prayed, hee recovered and song. If I should say that he was sicke, of your sicknesse, I should not
<pb n="42" facs="27"/>say it without an Author: <note place="margin">V. Vales. ser. Philos. Abulens. in <hi>4.</hi> zol. c. <hi>20.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> this I can say, his sicknes was but personall, yet he is thankful; whatever his disease was, you will yeeld the plague to be a sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, yea custome saith, The sickness, The plague, The visitation. This granted, there's great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that thou shouldest be as thankfull for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand as hee for one, and adde deeds to words as well as he: To this purpose, runne his method; 1. Make thy selfe sensible and mindfull of thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie past: <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Luc. 7.21. Mic 6.9.</note> sickenesse is a rod, as the Gospell tells us; the voyce now to the Citie is, Heare the rod &amp; who appoints if. the rod hath a mouth, if thou hast an eare; that speakes its errand, &amp; gives thee thy lesson. If thou wilt heare me, Ile deliver it to thee with the same affection (degrees excepted) that <hi>Eltha</hi> did to <hi>Iob, chap.</hi> 34.31.32.</p>
   <p>Surely it is meete, <note place="margin">Iob 34.31.</note> and it becomes thee to say, and that to God, I have borne chastisement; this the first lesson. Farre be it from thee to say in thy heart, Tis true, I have buried manie children, but what were they? of the baser &amp; poorer sort, such, whose lives were burden some, whose deaths are beneficiall to me: nor let it enter into thy heart to thinke, Well, I see the error; had such a place beene scoured, such traffique stayed, such meanes used, this had beene prevented, hereafter Ile bee wiser. No, it is thy wise dome to see Gods Name written upon this rod, as <hi>Micah</hi> speakes, and to acknowledge him: we wish thee to use all secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary meanes, but not to rest there; thy experience hath taught thee, that the plague nothing feares, either thy new fields, or fresh waters, &amp;c: it comes
<pb n="43" facs="27"/>of Gods errand, and when it comes, take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, for it wil not away without its errand. Therefore in the second place, improve the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as well as feele it; proceed to the second lesson in <hi>Iob,</hi> and say, Ile sinne no more. First, <note place="margin">Iob 5.6.</note> see why the rod is sent as well as by who. The rod buds not out of the dust, it hath a roote, and that root is sinne, and that sinne is manifold. A King doth not use to smite downe his subjects by thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands for small offences; a father will not draw a sword upon his children for toyes and trifles: London, thou must take the height of thy sinnes by the compasse of the punishment, and judge of that by this.</p>
   <p>What I have thought of thee, and thy govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in generall, I have spoken elsewhere seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably enough, as I think; but now I speak to thee, I earnestly entreate thee to take into thy conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. and therein note how the Lord charges her not only with such crimes as were committed by her, but also in her, <hi>In thee,</hi> saith God, <hi>were they, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For thine owne government &amp; practise, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how to hope almost that it should be much better in so populous and various a place, nay I know not the Citieunder heaven, that's bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ordred and disciplined: neverthelesse in such a confluence of people of nations, it cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided but such sinne will be committed in thee, if not by thee; and these sinnes, so farre as conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vencie and basenesse makes thine, <note place="margin">Tuum est quad tibi non displic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t Hier.</note> will endanger thee. When therefore thou hast surveyed thine
<pb n="44" facs="28"/>own wayes, cast into the account thine-other-mens-sinnes, thine-other-land sinnes, thy Dutch sinnes, thy French sinnes, thy Spanish sinnes, thy Italian sinnes, thine-owne-countrey-sinnes; see whether there be not in thee those that eate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mountaines, and those that for lucre sake both harbour and hide them. Whether in thee there be not such as never yet saw Christs face, or heard his voyce in the Assemblies: whether in this wonderful light, there be not in thee who know not whether Christ be a man or woman: whether there be not in thee men, who study new oathes and lyes, as men doc new fashions: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thee there be not who never see the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath light, but lye eyther buried in bed, or drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in drinke: whether in thee children be not so wantonly bred, that they sleight father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and, to make short of a long bed-roll; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thee there be not wretched men that set open their doores to all the bankrupts, unthrifts, gamesters, robbers, cheaters, harlots that the countrey pursues: whether in thee there be not some that set all to sale, wife, childe, servant, name, conscience, soule, all. And if upon search these or any of these shall bee found within thy walls or reach, O glorisie God in his visitation, and save thy selfe by disclayming these sinnes. Thine they be not, if thou where thou mayest dost reforme them, and where thy power fayles dost bewaile them. Howbeit this is not all; as sinne must be seene, so must it be left: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou must proceed, <note place="margin">Iob 34.31.</note> and say, Ile offend no
<pb n="45" facs="28"/>more: as a Christian, Ile reforme my selfe; as a parent, my children; as a Master, my family; as a Magistrate, my charge; as a tradsman, my courses. And to the end thy reformation may be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, learne two things more of <hi>Elihu,</hi> first, <note place="margin">Vers. 32</note> be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to see and know thy faults; pray that GOD would adde to correction instruction, that he will open thine heart to heare, and some mouth to speake home to thy case, thy soule; <note place="margin">Psal. 94.12.</note> and when light is commin, winke not with thine eyes, shut not the doore against it. Secondly, carrie ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee this resolution, Let God teach, Ile learne; speake, Ile heare; convince me of a sinne, Ile leave it whatever becomes of me; be it my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, be it to me as my life, if God will say it is a sinne, Ile leave it in the practise, in the purpose, in the allowance of it; this murtherous sinne that hath slaine my childe, my friend, so manie of my neighbours, nay my Saviour, shall never have place againe in my heart or house. And this is not onely the way to thankefulnesse, but also a proofe and peece of it: know that so many sinnes as the love of God constraines us to leave, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie songs are presented to God; <note place="margin">Chrys. de laude Dei.</note> everie slaine lust is a gratulatorie sacrifice.</p>
   <p>Secondly, thou must proceed with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and see from what, to what God hath brought thee: shall a Citie conceive and bring forth in a day? it hath beene so with thee. I may say of thy sorrowes, what <hi>Iob</hi> speakes of his comforts, they have beene swifter than a shuttle: <note place="margin">Iob 7.</note> Didst thou or anie man living thinke, that within one Summer
<pb n="46" facs="29"/>thou shouldest burie so manie, and so few weeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? could it be imagined, that when thy channels were discovered in so low an ebbe, that thy banks should be so suddenly filled againe? O London looke upon thy selfe, and wonder at thy selfe: invert now <hi>Ieremies</hi> lamentation, and say, How is the solitarie Citie become full! how is shee that was barren, made fruitfull! Sit downe with <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See the plague at Asex in Cypr. &amp; Eus</note> and consider what thy bitternesse was when death walkt in the streets, raged in the chambers, when death was in the pot, in the bedde, in the dish, in the hall, in the parlour, when the bells spake nothing but death, the doores presented no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death, and every man thou sawest, thing thou touchedst, place thou satest in threatned thee with death: consider what thy cares, fears, griefs, thoughts were then; and now whilest thine eyes behold as it were a resurrection to life, so that now life is in the streetes, life in the house, life in the Church, trading, building, singing, &amp;c. alive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, blesse thy GOD that hath wrought this change, and get up with <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to the house of the Lord: Strange it was, that hee in so short a space should measure the whole distance betwixt death and life; yesterday dead in nature, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to live as the sunne to goe backward, and to morrow so strong that he could shew himselfe in the Lords courts: This is wonderfull, and this made him wondrous thankfull. And what (I pray) wants thy deliverance of this? how much lesse wonderfull? how fast did sicknesse come in, how fast did it gallop out? how fast did it rise from
<pb n="47" facs="29"/>scores to thousands, how fast did it fall againe from thousands to scores? London, lay these things together, and forget not him who hath done so great things for thee.</p>
   <p>In the third place, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> loves not to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch all at one journey: hee begins his song as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soone as mought be, but tis not ended yet; he hath left a patterne for thee to work by. Thinke it not sufficient to complement God with a few words, and a short song, for along deliverance; write this mercy with a pen of Diamond, in a book of Marble; call upon all within thee, <note place="margin">Psal. 103.1.</note> as <hi>David</hi> did within him, to speake of this deliverance to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children, and doe something that may set men on singing 500. yeares hence: Thou hast sonnes of all sorts; some Enginers, some Artists, some Poets, some of excellent invention, some of great activity, some very daring and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, some strong, some wise, some rich, of all ranks some; call upon them, some to write, some to build, some to invent, some to give, that cirie, country, Church, State, sea and land may take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion thence of blessing God, whilst London or England stands. Now happy <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py sicknesse of his that ended so well: his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons sent him to God with prayers, his recovery with praises; nor God nor man lost by this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: God had more service, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, we gaine a good coppy, and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> hath his lease renewed for fifteene yeares: And thus afflictions conclude, which begin with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and end in thankfulnesse. London, make thy
<pb n="48" facs="30"/>selfe againer by thy losse, joine praises to thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer prayers, grow more wise, holy, humble, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, just, mercifull, fruitfull, and thou art a winner; thy gaines exceed thy losses present, and for the future, thou hast opened a faire prospect to a constant peace. The best security from future miseries, is to profit by former; beleeve it, thou canst not take a better medecine against the Plague, than to profit by what is past. Now the Lord hath promised to teach us to profit, by <hi>Esay,</hi> and he performe it for his mercies sake, that so the controversie may end here, and the Lord may not bee put to saddle his pale horse of famine, which hath made parents to eat up their children, once, and to wish them alive againe, that they might eate them againe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>