<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Vertuous Lady, the Lady HARRINGTON; Grace and Peace.</title>
           <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120398_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02034</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120398</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Vertuous Lady, the Lady HARRINGTON; Grace and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A looking-glasse for Christians; or, The comfortable doctrine of adoption : Wherein euery true beleeuer may behold his blessed estate in the kingdome of grace. By Thomas Granger, preacher of Gods Word at Butterwike in Holland in Lincolnshire</title>
                 <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Vertuous Lady, the Lady HARRINGTON; Grace and Peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, and worthy Lady: As God hath made you three and foure times happy in your inward selfe, so hath he made you thrice happy also in your outward selfe, as in your State, in your blessed Issue, in your Name; which as the sweete odour of a pretious oyntment, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth those that are neere by, and a far off, euen the children of God, who receiue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and strength by the graces of Gods spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the more principall members, whose pleasant influence giueth vigour and more liuely motion to the inferiour and weaker. This happines the Lord still continue, that as both you and all the children of God haue receiued grace for grace, &amp; glory for glory; so you may with them be perfected in glory at that ioyfull and long expected day of our Lords appearing, and full redemption of the
<pb facs="3"/>
purchased possession. In the meane space, I being a stranger vnto you, yet a Minister of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, doe greatly reioyce to heare that you, and other persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of State and Birth, doe walke vprightly in the Truth. And as your Faith, Zeale, and Deuotion, most worthy fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are a comfort to me &amp; others: so for your comfort also, I send to you <hi>A Diuine Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glasse,</hi> wherein, I hope well, you shall behold your blessed state, euen the beauty and glory of your person in the sight of God, and in the sight of your owne soule. To the poore (in spirit) is the rich Gospell offered; from the poore (my selfe) is this rich treasure sent vnto you: in it selfe rich, but a poore mite as handled and deliuered from mee, yet such shall it be, as your Honor shall please to accept.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all<lb/>
Christian duty to be<lb/>
commanded;<lb/>
THOMAS GRANGER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>