<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull my ap∣proued good friend, Maister John Bennet Doctor of the Ciuill law, and one of her Maiesties Councell in the North partes of England.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120918_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07845</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1822</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120918</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull my ap∣proued good friend, Maister John Bennet Doctor of the Ciuill law, and one of her Maiesties Councell in the North partes of England.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden ballance of tryall : VVherein the reader shall plainly and briefely behold, as in a glasse of crystall; aswell by what rule all controuersies in religion, are to be examined, as also who is, and of right ought to be the vpright iudge in that behalfe. Whereunto is also annexed a counterblast against a masked companion, terming himself E.O. but supposed to be Robert Parsons the trayterous Iesuite</title>
                 <author>Bell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bankworth, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 58 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="47"/>
   <pb facs="47"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued good friend, Maister John Bennet Doctor of the Ciuill law, and one of her Maiesties Councell in the North partes of England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I shoulde take vppon mee (right worshipfull,) to discourse at large, of the plots, practises, dealings, and proceedings, of our Iesuites and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suited persons; time doubtles would sooner faile me, then matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to speake. I haue verie lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished a discourse of this argument, intituled <hi>The Anatomie of Popish tyrannie.</hi> In it the Reader may view at large, the doctrine, the Religion, the manners, the natures, the conuersation, the practises, and the whole proceedings, of the English traiterous hispani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Iesuites. So that now to recount the same, were <hi>actum agere,</hi> and a thing altogither needlesse. One of these Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites hath lately published a most scandalous and rayling Libell, against the reuerend and learned man of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Doctor <hi>Sutcliffe</hi>: as also agaynst master <hi>Willet.</hi> In which Libell, the said masked companion terming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe E. O. hath obiter disgorged some part of his bitter
<pb facs="48"/>
gall agaynst my selfe. For the confirmation whereof, (that all the world may see his follie, and consequently the follie of all the Iesuites, who combine and conioyne in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire,) I haue addressed this <hi>Counterblast;</hi> in which the indifferent Reader may plainly behold, that the Iesuites and Seminaries can say nothing in deed, to the doctrine contained in my Bookes; howbeit they bestirre themselues with might and maine, to dazell the eyes of the simple and sillie Papists, that they shall not see the Sunne shining at noone tide. The worke (such as it is,) I dedicate vnto your worship, in token of that gratitude which is due vnto you, for your worships manifold kinde curtesies towardes mee. Accept I pray you the present in good part, not respecting so much the gift, as the minde of the giuer. The Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie blesse your worship, with manie happie yeares; to his glorie, the good of his Church, and the benefite of your owne soule. From my studie, this <hi>14.</hi> of Februarie, <hi>1602.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships most bounden, THOMAS BELL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>