<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull, and my most worthy estee∣meed
Kinsman ANTHONY HOBART, of Hales Hall in the County of Norffolke, Esquire,
all happinesse on Earth, and the ioyes of Heauen hereafter.</title>
           <author>R., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120927_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10301</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20584</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120927</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull, and my most worthy estee∣meed
Kinsman ANTHONY HOBART, of Hales Hall in the County of Norffolke, Esquire,
all happinesse on Earth, and the ioyes of Heauen hereafter.</title>
                 <author>R., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A president for young pen-men. Or The letter-writer : Containing letters of sundry sortes, with their seuerall answeres. Full of variety, delight, and pleasure, and most necessary for the instruction of those that can write, but haue not the guift of enditing</title>
                 <author>M. R.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wilson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, and my most worthy estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meed
Kinsman ANTHONY HOBART, of Hales Hall in the County of Norffolke, Esquire,
all happinesse on Earth, and the ioyes of Heauen hereafter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N reading of Epistles, written in diuers languages, I finde
them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to such Patrones, as could iudge of their worth, and would
accordingly accept them: Some to men of great account; other to men of lower
Titles of honour, but in higher esteeme of their loue: Now finding great men
so busie in great Matters, that I should haue great adoe with their
patience, in troubling their leisures from imployment in more serious
affaires, and yet knowing my labours, in my Letters, worth the looking on, I
haue bethought me of such a Patron, as in his kindnesse will vnderstand
my<pb facs="5"/>work, and regard my loue; which hauing found in your many
fauours, giue me leaue, with my seruice, to present my Book to your
Patronage: Each Letter hath his Answer; the Subiects are diuers, so is the
manner of their enditing: Hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full I know they will not be to any; good they
may do to many, that can aptly make vse of them: and for your selfe, and
perhaps yours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you, it may be no hurt to peruse them; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, at
your idle leisure they will saue time, and perhaps yeelde you pleasure in
reading them: but loth to bee tedious in needlesse Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, I will leaue
them to your kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and my loue to your like command: and so
rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most louing Kinsman, M. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>