<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the painefull Schoolemaster, de∣sirous
to reape the fruits of his labours,
and to see the blessing of the Lord, by
the new meanes and helps which he
affordeth daily.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120970_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08657</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18963</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120970</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the painefull Schoolemaster, de∣sirous
to reape the fruits of his labours,
and to see the blessing of the Lord, by
the new meanes and helps which he
affordeth daily.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ouids Metamorphosis translated grammatically, and also according to the propriety of our English tongue, so farre as grammar and the verse will well beare. Written chiefly for the good of schooles, to be vsed according to the directions in the preface to the painefull schoole-master, and more fully in the booke called Ludus Literarius, or the Grammar-schoole, Chap. 8</title>
                 <author>Ovid</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 93, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the painefull Schoolemaster, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous
to reape the fruits of his labours,
and to see the blessing of the Lord, by
the new meanes and helps which he
affordeth daily.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you desire to finde the benefit, and
reape the fruit of this, and the like
Grammaticall translations with mee,
without inconuenience, doe these
things; at least make triall that you
may be able to iudge truely hereof.</p>
   <p>1. Cause all your schollars, who
take construction to bee very perfect in the rule of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struing,
as it is set downe in the <hi>Ludus Literarius</hi> Chapt.
8. or more shortly in the <hi>Posing of the Accidence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>2. To be able to say perfectly without book, or to turne
vnto presently any of the rules of Grammar which are vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
learned.</p>
   <p>3. For taking of their lectures, direct them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
following, and see that they can doe it.</p>
   <p>1. That one of the two Seniors of the forme which is
to vse the help hereof, hauing the translation, doe in all
more hard places reade vnto the rest of the forme either the
lecture in English first, as it is translated, or at least the brief
summe &amp; sense of it out of the inmost columnes, ouer against
the translation of the lecture, to giue them some light and
vnderstanding of the meaning of it.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
2. That one or both of the Seniors looking vpon the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation
together with the Author in Latine, cause the rest,
each in his order, first to reade his peece, and in reading to
obserue all things according to the direction in the said rule
of construing, and then to construe and giue a reason accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the same rule, why it must be so construed, and not
otherwise. And where any sticke or goe amisse, varying
from the translation, to recall them to the rule, demanding
of them what the rule teacheth to be taken first, and what
in the next place; so to help them by the translation, where
none of their fellowes can finde it out, to giue both Grammar,
sense and variety of phrase in English, according to the text
in the translation and to the third columne compared toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
by the helpe of the markes.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, when they haue construed twice or thrice ouer,
and that the very lowest and worst can construe, that they
cause them likewise to parse according as they construed, <hi>viz.</hi>
each his peece, giuing the reasons of euery word.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, afterward let them direct them to be able to
giue each thing obserued in the vttermost columne for nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
history or otherwise. And this for taking their lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
   <p>Secondly, for preparing their lectures herein;</p>
   <p>First, cause each to study and make their lectures per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
by the helpe of the translation and their Grammar, to
be able, so soone as they shall be called to say, First, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer
the English, secondly, the Latine both in prose and
verse, <hi>viz.</hi> first, in a pure Latine stile in prose, and then
turning that into the <hi>Poets</hi> verse. Which practice will be
both a good helpe for making Latine, and also a most plaine
way to enter them in making a verse. And afterwards to
be able to construe and parse without booke, rendering a
<pb facs="5"/>
reason of euery thing; to giue the phrases, to vary them,
and to doe whatsoeuer the translation directs vnto. Thus
let them doe in all the Authors thus translated, so farre as
the Author and translation afford them helpe.</p>
   <p>Secondly, Cause them at their leasure, oft to construe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
amongst themselues all which they haue learned in the
Author, the two seniors onely, or one of them directing the
rest by the translation that they construe truely. And espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
make them to construe it oft out of the translation, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
only on it, each his peece, all the rest looking vpon their
Latine books: which will be a helpe to cause them to keep all
most perfectly, and chiefly if they obserue phrase and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
as they proceed. And much more if they be warned
to construe them oft ouer, priuately at home, and sometimes
be examined of a sodaine in seuerall places.</p>
   <p>By these meanes (vnlesse daily experience can deceiue)
these translations will prooue worthie the accept<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nce and vse
of our chiefe Schooles; when hereby all the middle formes
of the schoole may both take and each waies prepare their
owne lectures of themselues, at least with very little helpe
or trouble of the master; &amp; that as profitably and surely in
euery respect, as if the master gaue, or heard the giuing of
them himself: vvhen they are caused hereby to search out
and giue a reason of each word why it must be so construed,
parsed, and vsed in that place, that the master ordinarily
shall need but onely to examine them, when they are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
Thus to auoid not onely that common toyle to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
in giuing each lecture, but also that he may saue all that
time which is so spent, to imploy much of it with his highest
formes in the chiefe Authors Latine or Greeke in giuing
their lectures, or hearing them to take their owne lectures
of themselues, for their greater furtherance &amp; better fitting
<pb facs="6"/>
for the Vniuersity, and likewise for the credit of the school,
and in examining and posing, which is the best quickner of
their wittes, and spurre to all good learning. Hereby, more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer▪
shall the children be fitted with vnderstanding and
iudgement, how many waies to make their benefit of their
Authors. Or else that the Master may bestowe the more
time and paines, amongst the lowest and first formes, for
the better entring and grounding of them, which beeing
rightly performed makes all their proceeding afterwards ful
of certainty and pleasant delight. In this one thing (and
that by meanes of these helps, there may bee many moe of a
forme, and euery one able to prepare his owne lecture, and
also that all of them may so easily and surely by oft repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and their owne priuate paines keepe all which they haue
learned) I finde so great gaine without losse, in redeeming so
much time to be imployed vpon other most necessary vses in
the schoole, yea so much freedome from many occasions of
discontentment and ouer-wearying my selfe, and so sweete
an allurement to prouoke the children to study of themselues
with contention &amp; delight, as that it makes me bould to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
the vse of them to all of this function, that they maie
be partakers of the same comforts. To omit the sundry other
benefits; and namely for beating out the right sense, &amp; Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar
rule in each place, with propriety in our owne tongue, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
as I haue beene yet able in my streights of time. Giue
them not ouermuch at a time, but that they may learne all so
perfectly as that what they haue learned may bee a schoole-master
to that which followeth, and make experiment heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:
for this <hi>Essay</hi> and the many defects and slips in it, let the
difficulty in this kinde of translating (to frame it each waie
<pb facs="6"/>
both for Grammar propriety purity, variety, and to fit it to
the childrens capacities in euery respect and meete to all the
intended purposes without inconuenience &amp; that in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
imployment in my calling) plead for me. I doubt not
but all they who haue or shall make triall of it, (as some lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
haue done) will fauourably accept it. Afford mee your
helpe in shewing how to amende it, directing your Letters to
the Printer to be deliuered, &amp; future editions shall God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
send it forth more perfectly, with all the rest. In the
meane time desiring still an increase of your loue and praiers
for finishing my worke, I commend you to him, whose this &amp;
all my labours are; and shall rest yours as his goodnesse shall
vouchsafe mercy.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>