<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY MVCH HONOVRED PATRON ENDYMION PORTER Esquire, and one of his Maiesties Bed-chamber, salvation, long life &amp; happinesse in the Lord Iesus.</title>
           <author>Widdowes, Giles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120669_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15303</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25593</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120669</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY MVCH HONOVRED PATRON ENDYMION PORTER Esquire, and one of his Maiesties Bed-chamber, salvation, long life &amp; happinesse in the Lord Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Widdowes, Giles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lawlesse kneelesse schismaticall Puritan. Or A confutation of the author of an appendix, concerning bowing at the name of Iesus. Written by Giles Widdowes rector of St Martins Church in Oxford, and late fellow of Oriell Colledge</title>
                 <author>Widdowes, Giles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>Widdowes, Giles</distributor>
                            <distributor>Widdowes, Giles</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 79, 79-90, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO MY MVCH HONOVRED PATRON ENDYMION PORTER Esquire, and one of his</hi> Maiesties Bed-chamber, salvation, long life &amp; happinesse in the Lord Iesus.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR noble intents, and ancient Reall fauours towards me, ought to be honoured with millions of thanks. And so thankfull I am, as tis possible for me, so farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath your worth in termes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall. I here present you with the first fruits of my Autumne-vintage, with the best grape, that ever was pressed into wine. The vine, wheron it grows, is the true vine: and the cup of saluation is the benefit, which it
<pb facs="3"/> brings to the worthy receauer. This makes glad the heart of man, it cheares vp the drooping soule, recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ats the spirits, quickeneth the senses, and raiseth vp the whole man to the highest pitch of happines. And now giue me leaue, plainely to commend vnto you the subiect it selfe, or rather the Lord, and Master of my ensuing labours, which is this vine, this grape, and this wine, soprecious, so excellent, so everlastingly sauing. Tis Iesus the Author of saluation, that's his name aboue all names: at the mention whereof S. Bernard in his 15. sermon on the Canticles was rapt into admiration, <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      </hi> Hierome, and other of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ancient Christians of the Primitiue Church into amazement, and adoration. And well they might, for there is none other meanes vnder heauen to attaine to salvation: this saues from the strength of death, from the pit of hell, from the tyranny of the Devill. But being dishonoured by a disgracefull pen, I am not asham'd to confesse, that <hi>Iesus</hi> is the <hi>Lord</hi> in the despight of his enemies, with heart, and knee, and pen: and am like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise bold to commend this Apologetique, or schole-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of mine to your courteous acceptance, in token of my oblig'd thankfullnes. And thus, till God shall adde a greater blessing to my studies, now, and ever I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours at my hearty praiers, <hi>GILES WIDDOWES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>