<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Hayward, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120160_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68903</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25731</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120160</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hayward, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The actions of the Lowe Countries. Written by Sr. Roger Williams Knight</title>
                 <author>Williams, Roger, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 133, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit in all Histories three things
are especially required, Order,
Poyse and Truth: yet for diuers
causes it hapneth that in many,
one of these doth faile.</p>
   <p>For some haue written of
times so anciently past, that no
means are extant, either to <hi>direct</hi>
or to <hi>correct</hi> them. Many of these liuing in Artlesse
ages, haue stuffed their Stories with most senselesse fictions;
nothing better then country womens tales. Of this sort was
<hi>Hunibaldus,</hi> who fableth that the French tooke their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
from <hi>Francio</hi> a Troian: and is followed in his sotteries
by <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Tours, Rheginus, Sigebert,</hi> and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of the same suite. After this example <hi>Geoffry</hi> of
<hi>Munmouth</hi> about 400 yeares since, did first (as some af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme)
draw the originall of the <hi>Britans</hi> from <hi>Brutus</hi> the
<hi>Troian:</hi> forging such races, names, reignes and passages of
affaires, as may more easily be conuinced to be false, then sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
with any certaine truth. Of the same streine is <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikind;</hi>
who by his counterfeit <hi>Saxo,</hi> hath drawen the <hi>Saxons</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
and first Inhabitants of <hi>Germanie,</hi> from the olde Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian
Souldiers of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great. So the <hi>Scots</hi> set
vp <hi>Scota</hi> daughter to <hi>Pharao</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> for foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse
of their Nation. Likewise the <hi>Irish</hi> hatched their
<hi>Hiberus,</hi> the <hi>Danes</hi> their <hi>Danus,</hi> the <hi>Brabants</hi> their <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi>
the <hi>Gothes</hi> their <hi>Gothus,</hi> as founders both of their
Nation and name: a subiect wherein forgeries may range
at large; because the first times of Nations for the most part
are, as very small, so altogether obscure. Of this sort among
the ancients were <hi>Herodotus, Diodorus Siculus,</hi> and
<hi>Theopompus:</hi> in whose Bookes <hi>Cicero</hi> saith, many idle
vntruthes are found; euen so farre as the vaine veine of
the <hi>Graecians</hi> durst aduenture to aduowe for truthes. In
how many places (saith <hi>Iosephus</hi>) is <hi>Hellanicus</hi> charged
with falsities by <hi>Agesilaus,</hi> and by <hi>Ephorus?</hi> they by <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus?
Timaeus</hi> by many who followed? <hi>Herodotus</hi>
by all?</p>
   <p>Others haue written of Countries farre distant, either al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
vnknowen, or by them neuer seene: who writing
vpon vulgar reports, things either imagined, or erroneously
obserued, are easily entangled with vntruthes. Of this fault
<hi>Era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>osthenes, Possidonius</hi> and <hi>Patrocles</hi> the Geographer
are branded by <hi>Strabo.</hi> Hence also did rise the fables of the
<hi>Arimaspes, Gryphons, Troglodites, Amazons, Satyrs,
Pigmies,</hi> and of their cruell warres with Cranes: of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of men with dogs heads, with horse feete, without heads,
without mouthes, with one foote wherewith they couer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
against Sun and raine, and of diuers other monstrous
kinds of men, beasts &amp; fowles, which now are discouered for
vtopicall Aperies. With these may <hi>Stephanus</hi> &amp; <hi>Arianus</hi> be
ioyned; of whom the one writeth, that the French are a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of <hi>Italie;</hi> the other placeth the <hi>Germanes</hi> neere to the
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Ionick</hi> sea. So <hi>Strabo</hi> choppeth, that the riuer <hi>Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>et</hi>
or <hi>Danowe,</hi> hath his spring neere to the <hi>Adriaticke</hi>
sea: and that the riuers <hi>Lapus</hi> and <hi>Vezer,</hi> discharge
themselues into the riuer <hi>Enis;</hi> whereas the one runneth
into the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the other into the <hi>Ocean.</hi> So are <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus,
Marcellus, Orosius, Blondus,</hi> in diuers places of
<hi>Germanie</hi> much mistaken. And so <hi>Sabellicus, Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrane,</hi>
and <hi>Conrade,</hi> doe much confound the <hi>Alans</hi>
and <hi>Almans;</hi> the <hi>Hungarians</hi> and <hi>Hunnes;</hi> the
<hi>Danes</hi> and the <hi>Dace; Austerane,</hi> and <hi>Austrich;</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
the mount Saint <hi>Ottoly</hi> in <hi>Bauaria,</hi> and the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaean</hi>
mountaines in <hi>Polonia,</hi> or <hi>Muscouia.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Others haue written of their owne countries and
times: but these againe are of diuers sorts. For some
busie themselues much in those things which the popular
multitude doe applaud: making <hi>wordie</hi> (I cannot say
<hi>worthy</hi>) reports of Beare baitings, lanching of shippes,
fleas, mice, owles, maskes, mayings, &amp;c. And if they
speake of any publicke affaires, they discerne nothing but
the out-side: not vnlike to beggars, who trauerse ouer
many Countries, from dore to dore, and touch as many
faire buildings; but obserue nothing either of the persons,
or furniture, or order within. Such Historians doe daily
and duely attend certaine Kings in <hi>India:</hi> And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
they doe, whether eate, drinke, sleepe, disport,
ease nature, retyre to any woman; In a word, <hi>All,</hi> they
barely wright downe, and nothing else.</p>
   <p>Some others better furnished with iudgement, doe
strongly biasse in their affections: and that chiesty by two
meanes, <hi>leuitie</hi> and <hi>partiality.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Of the first sort are they who affecting to write ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="5"/>
pleasingly then truely, doe enterlace many ieasts,
conceits, tales, and other pleasing passages; either omitting
or defacing the solide truth. Of this fault <hi>Trebellius</hi> is
reprooued by <hi>Laberian</hi> and <hi>Vopiscus, Tacitus</hi> by <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>
and <hi>Orosius, Orosius</hi> by <hi>Blondus.</hi> To these al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
wee may adioyne <hi>Danudes, Philostratus, Guidius,
C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esias, Heca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aeus,</hi> and diuers others; who haue trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
the truth of many things into fabulous inuentions
of their owne.</p>
   <p>Of the second sort are they who vpon hate, feare, or
fauour, either to some persons, or to their natiue countrey,
or to the religion which they professe, or for some other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
respect, doe write Panegyrickes or Inuectiues, rather
then Histories. So <hi>Salust</hi> writeth, that the acts of the
<hi>Graecians</hi> are much admired: not because they exceede
the Atchieuements of other men, but because their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
hauing wit at will, did much enlarge them aboue the
truth. Of this fault <hi>Blondus</hi> and <hi>Sabellicus</hi> are noted
in their Histories of <hi>Venice: Paulus Aemilius</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine</hi>
in their Histories of <hi>France:</hi> and most others
in the Histories of their owne Countries. Who extoll,
depresse, depraue immoderately; making things seeme
not as they are, but as they would haue them; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
almost then Comedies and Tragedies are fashioned by
their Authours.</p>
   <p>Amongst those fewe who haue written with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
iudgement, and sincerity, the Authour of this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie
is worthy to be ranged: who doubtlesse was of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
industry; alwaies in action, either with his sword,
or with his penne. He was well knowen to be a man, who
both knew and durst: his courage no lesse free from indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
<pb facs="5"/>
then from feare. Yet hath hee wrote so modest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of himselfe, that some may happelie esteeme him ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
a looker on, then a medler, in the hot medlies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
he doth write: but his attributing so little to himselfe,
will make others attribute the more vnto him. In wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of others hee expresseth a most generous disposition;
neither forbearing the errours of his friends, nor forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
the vigilancy and valoure of his enemies; but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying
himselfe with an euen hand betweene them.</p>
   <p>Touching the Historie it selfe, it is faithfull and
free; wherein are found sieges, assaults, surprizes, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bushes,
skirmishes, battailes, liuely described. Great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie
both of persons and of actions; much mutability
of fortune, many changes in affaires. Admirable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices,
vnexpected euents, ponderous iudgements; a
phraze in a Souldiers stile, sinowie and sweet; full both
of perspicuitie and grace. In a word, I esteeme it a
compleate Historie, if it were compleate. I meane, if it
extended to all the actions wherein the Authour did
serue. But whether the residue was neuer written,
or whether it bee perished, or whether it resteth in
any other hand, I remaine doubtfull. This piece
beeing shewed to mee, by a person, of whose ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
I had rather speake nothing, then not enough,
I did much esteeme; for that it comprizeth some
actions of the time wherein I haue liued: Of
which time I endeauour to leaue a large memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
to posteritie. But comming to mee in a rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
hand, much maimed, both in sense, and in phrase:
<pb facs="6"/>
I haue restored it so neere as I could, both to the
stile and meaning of the Authour. This is all the
paines that I haue taken. This is all the thankes
which I doe either challenge or deserue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Io: HAYVVARDE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>