<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120251_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15695</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25971</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120251</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A childes patrimony laid out upon the good culture or tilling over his whole man : The first part, respecting a childe in his first and second age</title>
                 <author>Woodward, Ezekias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meredith, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stephens, Philemon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 47, 9, 182, 16, 14, 6, 207, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Treatise</hi> tendeth to the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of faire <hi>Edifices</hi> to the Lord, which are the children of <hi>children of men.</hi> The <hi>Author</hi> sheweth himself herein, a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full builder: in that he first lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a sure, solid foundation, and then reareth thereupon his goodly edifice. This the Lord Himselfe noted to be the part of a prudent builder (<hi>Luk. 6. vers.</hi> 48.) He wisely sheweth, when, and by whom especially, this foundation is to be laid, even by Parents so soone as their children attaine any competent capacitie. Young and tender yeares are flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and may easily be bowed this way, or that way. They are like <note n="a" place="margin">—Argillâ quidvis imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris udâ. <hi>Hor.</hi>
      </note> the <hi>moist potters clay,</hi> which <hi>may readily be fashioned into any shape:</hi> and like soft waxe, which soone receives any print; Nor so only, but also long retains what it first receiveth:
<pb facs="9"/> like <note n="b" place="margin">Quo semel est imbuta recens servabit odorem Testa diu▪ Idem.</note>
      <hi>a vessell, which long holds the savour which it first tooke while it was new.</hi> Old men are said to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>in their elder</hi> yeares, what they learned in their <hi>younger.</hi> I shall not need to presse this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it being so plentifully and pithily pressed by the <hi>Author</hi> himself, who layes his foundation ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deep, even in the mothers wombe: and goeth along from <hi>infancy</hi> to <hi>childhood,</hi> thence to <hi>youth,</hi> and so on, till he bring his childe to a <hi>growne,</hi> yea, an <hi>old man,</hi> full of dayes, <hi>going to the grave in a full age; like as a sheafe of corne cometh in, in his season</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Job 9. 26.</note>.</p>
   <p>In every estate and degree of these <hi>Ages,</hi> even from the wombe to the grave, he prescribeth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent and profitable directions, not to children only, but also to <hi>Parents, Guardians, Schoole-masters, Tutors, Governours</hi> of all sorts of Societies, yea, and to <hi>Ministers</hi> too, whom he fitly styleth, <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s of Instructors.</hi> So full he is, as he hath passed nothing over in this long journey without a due observation, whether it concerns the mothers care of the childe in her <hi>wombe,</hi> or after in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,</hi> or both Parents care about a <hi>new birth,</hi> or ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating it in pietie, good manners, good literature at <hi>home,</hi> at <hi>schoole,</hi> at <hi>Vniversity,</hi> or any other good <hi>Seminary;</hi> Yea also about <hi>calling, marriage, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi> to Parents, to their superiours, equalls, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, in all ages, times, and places. This is that faire <hi>Edifice,</hi> whereof intimation was made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: fairer then the Edifices which have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been erected by <hi>Xenophon</hi> in his <note n="d" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Institution of Cyrus;</hi> by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Treatise <note n="e" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>of training up
<pb facs="9"/> children;</hi> by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his <note n="f" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of children;</hi> by <hi>Hierome,</hi> in his Epistle to <hi>Laeta</hi> concerning the <note n="g" place="margin">De institutune fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iae.</note>
      <hi>educating of her daughter;</hi> by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasmus,</hi> in his Discourse <note n="h" place="margin">De pueris sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim &amp; libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aliter instituendis.</note> of <hi>timely</hi> and <hi>liberall training up of children,</hi> or by others in like Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises.</p>
   <p>This Author hath more punctually and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, handled all kinde of duties from ones first entrance into this world, to his going out thereof, then any of the fore-named Authors, or any other that have written of the like subject. Such varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of matter is here couched, as it will prove use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all of all sorts, that will reade and heed it. The Lord give a blessing to this and all other like labours of his faithfull servants.</p>
   <closer>Amen.
<signed>William Gouge.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>