<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Praeface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120773_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13174</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23469</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120773</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Praeface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The subuersion of Robert Parsons his confused and worthlesse worke, entituled, A treatise of three conuersions of England from paganisme to Christian religion</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 48, 57-144, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Praeface to the Christian</hi> Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an old trick of heretikes, Christian Reader, to grace their leud opinions with faire titles. <hi>Sub falso praetextu &amp; spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie pietatis,</hi> saith <hi>Constantine</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Euseb. de vit. Constant. lib. 3. ca. 62.</note> speaking to heretikes, <hi>semper delinquentes, omnia contagione vestra contaminatis.</hi> So <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> albeit he talketh of popish religion, which is nothing else but a mixture of <hi>Iudaisme, Paganisme,</hi> and Heresie; yet doth he giue out, that he contendeth for Christian religion. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine albeit the Masse, wherein the whole seruice of God (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinion of Papists) consisteth, be but a late pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, and their popish opinions meere nouelties, and strange fancies; yet would he make men beleeue, that the Masse was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted by <hi>Christ,</hi> and that these new doctrines were taught by <hi>Peter</hi> and the rest of the Apostles of our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Christ Iesus.</hi> In his Epistle Dedicatory he calleth the English Papists <hi>the off-spring, and children of the first professors of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie</hi> in this Iland. And yet no children could further degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from their ancestors, then the moderne Papists from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Christians, as by many particulars may be demonstrated. Their faith concerning the foundations of Christian religion, concerning Christs office, and humane nature, concerning the Church and Sacraments, concerning the ministery and policy of the Church, nay cōcerning the Law and the Gospell, is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether different from that faith which the first Christians of this Iland professed. And were not the difference so great as we find it, yet what needed this babling fellow to search antiquitie for proofe of his three imagined conuersions of the ancient inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of our countrey to Christian religion? Let him shew, that the doctrine of popery which we refuse, is Christian religion, and that it was first taught by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in Britany, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and that will suffice without more adoe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
But herein the poore fellow faileth most grossely. Nay where he needed not, blindly he plungeth himselfe into diuers diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, offering to prooue, that the ancient inhabitants of this land were conuerted vnto Christian religion by <hi>S. Peter, Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius,</hi> and the Monke <hi>Austin:</hi> matters farre beyond the reach of his abilitie, and impertinent. For neither doth he prooue, that the <hi>Britaines</hi> were thrise by them conuerted, nor would it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage his cause being prooued, seeing the decretaline and wicked doctrine of Popes, which all true Christians refuse, is of a late and different note from that faith, which those three taught and professed, and which was of ancient time planted in this Iland.</p>
   <p>The which, that it may euidently appeare, I haue for thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter satisfaction thought good to examine this whole treatise <hi>of three Conuersions,</hi> in volume big, in value small, in discourse idle, in proofes weake and simple, and altogether vnworthy any long answere, were it not that some men suppose, that he hath sayd somewhat, where God wot his whole treatise is nothing but vaine talking, and tedious discoursing to no purpose. <hi>Eadem at{que} eadem saepe dicit</hi> sayth <hi>Augustine epist.</hi> 86. of such an idle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>aliud non inueniendo quod dicat, nisi quod inaniter, &amp; ad rem non pertinens dicit.</hi> But with better reason may this be sayd of this pratling <hi>Iebusite,</hi> which repeating the same things often, yet findeth nothing to serue his purpose, but that which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the purpose of the author.</p>
   <p>In his Epistle Dedicatory he giueth the title of <hi>Catholikes</hi> to <hi>English</hi> Masse-priests and their consorts. But that is the point in question. He calleth them also <hi>the worthy children</hi> of the first professors of the Christian faith in this land. But the testimonie of a bastard shall neuer make bastard professors true <hi>Christians.</hi> Further it is not like, but his prouision will faile him before the end of his iourney, that beginneth so impudently to beg at his first setting forth, and so presumptuously to take for granted matters in controuersie. <hi>Finally,</hi> vnder the name of the <hi>Christian catholike faith,</hi> he goeth about to commend the corruptions and trash of the Romish church, as the <hi>Macedonian</hi> heretikes did their hereticall poyson. <hi>Venenum melle illitum, nempe catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co
<pb facs="5"/>
nomine superinducto propinabatur</hi> sayth <hi>Athanasius ad Serap.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He sheweth reasons of his dedication, but all false. For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall he euer prooue, that <hi>Papists</hi> professe the Christian ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith first planted in <hi>England,</hi> nor deriue their pedegree from the first Christian <hi>Britains,</hi> or <hi>Saxons.</hi> His best reason is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgotten or ouerslipped, <hi>viz.</hi> that such patcheries are most properly due to such patrons.</p>
   <p>Against true Christians he inueigheth with open mouth, as if they were <hi>heretikes,</hi> and <hi>intruders on the right of the catholike church.</hi> But that is a common practise of men of his sort, to fall to rayling and lying, when by truth they cannot stand. <hi>Hierome in his 2. apology</hi> against <hi>Russine,</hi> speaking of Heretikes, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicti de perfidia</hi> sayth he <hi>ad maledicta se conferunt.</hi> And <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Euseb. de vit. Constant. lib. 3. ca 63.</note> directing his words to heretikes, chargeth them with vaine lyes. <hi>Cognoscite</hi> sayth he, <hi>quibus mendacijs vestrae doctrinae inanit as implicata teneatur.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In fauour of the <hi>Papists</hi> he braggeth, that he hath <hi>produced the sentences and arrests of all Christian Parliaments of the world, to wit, the determination of all the highest ecctesiasticall tribunals.</hi> But if by Parliaments he meane generall Councels, he abuseth his clients, and all the world. For it were great simplicitie, if vpon his word they should suppose, either that Popery is au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by ancient generall Councels, or that the late conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Laterane, Constance, Florence</hi> and <hi>Trent</hi> ordered by the Popes directiō were lawfull Coūcels. He doth also erre grossely, if he affirme it. Finally he contradicteth his owne holy fathers pleasure, if he affirme the Councell to be aboue the Pope, and the highest tribunall on earth.</p>
   <p>The words of the Apostle, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. he applieth to such Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists as haue bene of late time called in question for treason and felony, as if they did not only <hi>beleeue in Christ, but also suffer for him.</hi> Whereof the second is euidently false, as publike records testifie; the first is doubtfull, seeing heretikes cannot be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted true beleeuers.</p>
   <p>Likewise he abuseth other scriptures 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1. <hi>Thess.</hi> 1. and <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. like the <hi>Valentinians,</hi> endeuouring to wrest the sacred word of God to his owne fancies, and fabulous discourses. <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare
<pb facs="6"/>
volunt</hi> sayth <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>aduers. haeres. ca.</hi> 1. <hi>fabulis suis elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quia Dei. Saint Paule</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and 1. <hi>Thess.</hi> 1. speaketh of true Christians, that followed <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> and his Apostles: this <hi>Iebusite</hi> talketh of such, as follow <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and hearken to the Ieud perswasions of the false Apostles of <hi>Satan.</hi> That which the Prophet <hi>Isay, chap.</hi> 1. speaketh of purging the Church of God, the same he applieth to the rusty followers of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> whom he seeketh to continue in their disorders, and errors.</p>
   <p>Neither could he conceale the stirres that haue bene in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> betweene the secular priests, and the Iebusites, although good it were for him, that they were neuer remembred, he being conuinced by the testimonie of his owne followers in diuers discourses written of this argument, to be a <hi>Machiauelian,</hi> 2 <hi>traytor, and a diuell.</hi> Here also he applieth the words meant of our Sauiour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. to <hi>Antichrist</hi> the destroyer, as if he <hi>rising vp could cōmand winds &amp; seas, and cause calmes;</hi> who indeede ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther causeth stormes, then calmes; warres, then peace; and is the firebrand of troubles throughout all Christendome. Further he entitleth him <hi>Christes substitute.</hi> But his outragious persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods saints, shew him to be <hi>Christes</hi> aduersary, rather then substitute. Commission or act of substitution he sheweth none. But of the other we find diuers argumēts <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. and 11. 2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2. <hi>Apocalyp.</hi> 13. and 17. which in my bookes <hi>de pontif. Rom.</hi> are at large declared.</p>
   <p>In an addition to his epistle he triumpheth ouer Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of pious memory, and raileth at her, as <hi>a persecutor,</hi> whose clemencie her greatest enemies cannot chuse but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge: and he among the rest, if he were not vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But herein the heathen Philosophers do accuse him. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, sayth <hi>Homer odyss.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And another, <hi>de mortuis nil nisi bonum.</hi> Herein therefore the prouerbe is verified, that <hi>Hares insult ouer dead Lyons.</hi> If he had not bene a renegate Christian, and fugitiue traytor, he would neuer haue compared her to <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>apostate,</hi> or to <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesian</hi> that persecuting tyrant. Neither if he had bene wise, would he haue mentioned these two examples, himselfe in apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacie being like the one, and the Pope in crueltie and pride
<pb facs="6"/>
farre surpassing the other.</p>
   <p>From railing he falleth into a veine of flattering the King, whom he cōpareth vnto <hi>Constantine.</hi> And yet not many yeares since, in his most trayterous booke of titles he sought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue this <hi>Constantine</hi> of the crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and to conuey the same to the Infanta of Spaine, who now condemneth the glosing companions flattery. And very lately the gunpowder Papists by his direction attempted to destroy him, and his whole house. Thus with the time this <hi>Iebusite</hi> can change his note, singing that only which maketh for his profit. <hi>Modo palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus, modo togatus.</hi> Now he playeth <hi>Dolman,</hi> now <hi>N. D.</hi> But as <hi>Ambrose</hi> sayth writing against <hi>Auxentius, vnum portentum est, duo nomina,</hi> that is, one monster, two titles. Yet such is the folly of this parasite, that thinking to praise the King, he doth greatly dishonor him, comparing his royall Maiesty to diuers not yet conuerted to Christianitie, and implying, that the King is no Christian.</p>
   <p>He talketh of the Kings preseruation; yet may we probably suppose, that he had a finger both in <hi>Percies</hi> treason discouered in Nouember last, and in <hi>Clerks and Watsons</hi> practise executed at <hi>Winchester</hi> not long since, for intending the destructiō of the kings Maiesty, and the subuersion of the realme, as appeareth by a publike edict against them.</p>
   <p>In commending the Kings booke, he condemneth his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: as if any could be more dishonored, then by imputation of want of religion. Againe he contradicteth himselfe, cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the king <hi>for feruent and extraordinary affection of piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and godlinesse:</hi> and yet presently after taxeth him as being addicted <hi>to vanity, and inanity of sects and heresies, where no ground, no head, no certaine principle, no sure rule or methode to try the truth can be found.</hi> Which his vaine and idle sconce shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer either iustly impute to that religion, which his Maiesty professeth, or cleanly auoyd in that sect, which he followeth, being a pack of impieties, blasphemies, heresies, nouelties, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certeinties, contradictions, absurdities and fooleries. The <hi>first</hi> we verifie by diuers treatises written in defence of our religion, wherein we declare, that the same is not only built vpon the
<pb facs="7"/>
immoueable rocke <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> the writings of the Prophets and Apostles bearing witnesse vnto it, and full of sincere wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but also approoued by Councels, Fathers, consent of nations, miracles, yea and by the bishops of <hi>Rome</hi> for many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The second is euidēt by the schoole doctrine of the Masse, of the Sacraments, of the Pope, of Purgatory, Indulgences, works of supererogation, and such like. For what more impious, then to say, that Christes body may be really eaten of dogs or hogs eating the Eucharist? What more blasphemous, then to giue Gods honor to stocks, stones, and to Antichrist? What more hereticall then to destroy <hi>Christes</hi> humane nature, and office, and to worship Angels, Saints and Images? What more new then the doctrine of <hi>Constance, Florence, Trent,</hi> concerning the massing sacrifice, the communion vnder one kind, the subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting of accidents without substance, indulgences and such like? What more vncertaine, then popish religion, that dependeth vpon the Popes determination, a man oftentimes blind, vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and variable? What more contradictory then that Christes body should be both visible and inuisible, aboue and below, dead and aliue at one time? What more absurd then to limite the catholike church within the diocese of Rome, or to say with the <hi>Donatists,</hi> that it is perished out of the whole world, saue in one corner of the Romish church? <hi>Finally</hi> what more foolish, then the apish toyes of Masse-priests at the altar, of massing Bishops in consecrating Churches, and such like super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious ceremonies?</p>
   <p>In his Preface he endeuoreth to prooue, <hi>that man is mutable,</hi> by his owne example, that hath so often altered his intention in his treatise of three Conuersions. But that is little for his credit, or the credit of his cause. For what if he turne like a weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke, and renounce religion? would he haue all his countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to prooue apostates like himselfe? Truth also is constant, and alwayes like it selfe. But falsehood varieth, and false tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers differ in the defence of falsehood. <hi>Noua ipsa rursum inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uata emendatione scindis, emendata autem iterum emendando condemnas,</hi> sayth Hilary to <hi>Constantius.</hi> The like we may say to this motley and changeable Iebusite, who being vncertaine in
<pb facs="7"/>
his resolution, and leauing matters formerly purposed, brought forth matters neuer designed, for a calfe presenting his readers with a hedgehog. Afterward he exhorteth men by the example of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> to the search of Catholike Religion, &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the sluggishnes of them, that are carelesse in this behalfe. But his words are contrary to the Romish practise, that forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the reading of Scriptures in vulgar tongues without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and maketh it mortall sinne for a lay man to dispute of religion. Much, certes, it were to be wished, that men would do as he sayth, for then should Christians easily espy the iugling of <hi>Papists,</hi> and see, that popery is not Catholike, as it differeth from the faith professed in the church of England. <hi>Dagon</hi> cannot stand before Gods Arke, nor darkenes continue, when light appeareth.</p>
   <p>To preuent perillous courses, and to giue light, where cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinty of religion lyeth, he sayth he hath framed his treatise <hi>of Three Conuersions.</hi> But alas, the poore ideot is so farre from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the certeinty of his religion, as the East is from the West. For what assurance can he haue of religion, who doth beleeue neither Propheticall, nor Apostolical writings, nor other article of faith without the Popes resolution, and for his proofes alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Simeon Metaphrastes, Surius, Baronius,</hi> and other fabulous writers, and vaine and vncertaine traditions, of which he hath no certeinty? Againe his pamphlet of <hi>Three Conuersions</hi> doth principally handle matter of history, and not matter of faith or doctrine. Lastly, he doth rather seeke to draw men into danger both of soule and body, by seeking to bring Gods people back to the thraldome of <hi>Babylon,</hi> then to keepe them from any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Neither doth he handle in his treatise any point here by him promised. In this preface, I confesse, he compareth the Church to a mansion house, and seuerall points of doctrine to parcels of land belonging to the same, promising that he will make proofe, that the right of the Church belongeth to the <hi>Romanists,</hi> as true owners of the mansion house built in the clouds by <hi>Parsons,</hi> and <hi>that we are but vagrant and contemptible persons.</hi> But first there is great difference betweene the Church, and a mansion house: the Church being a mysticall body, and
<pb facs="8"/>
being scattered here and there, and not being appropriated to any family, city, or nation: and a mansion house being a ciuill and artificiall building situate in one place, and belonging to one family or sort of people. <hi>Secondly</hi> seuerall points of doctrine are rudely compared to seuerall parcels ofland, which are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall, and may be translated from one to another, whereas points of Christian doctrine are matters spiritual, and cannot be held &amp; truly professed, but by the members of the true Church. In like sort the <hi>Arians by their grosse similitudes depraued such matters, as were well spoken,</hi> as sayth <hi>Athanasius orat. 4. contr. Arian. Incorporalia</hi> sayth he, <hi>corporaliter excipientes, quae probè dicta erant, deprauarunt.</hi> Thirdly neither shall he euer prooue, that the right of the Church belongeth to the Pope and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, nor shall he exclude vs from the precincts of the true Church, howsoeuer in his Luciferian pride he do here despise and scorne vs. His marks of Antiquitie and Succession are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the proper notes of the Church, nor were they so to be taken, can he, if by succession he meane discent of true doctrine, either take them from vs, or giue them to the Popes adherents, who rather belong to the synagogue of <hi>Sathan,</hi> then to the Church of God.</p>
   <p>In the latter end of his Praeface he taketh vpon him the person of a Doctor, and layeth downe <hi>foure points of consideration about matters of faith. The first is, that our articles of faith are aboue mans reason. The second, that they haue sufficient arguments of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility. The third is, that it behooueth vs to haue a pious affection. The fourth is, that some articles of our faith may be demonstrated and knowne by force of humane reason.</hi> But first, he sheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a vaine and arrogant companion, that in matters where he is party, taketh on him to be a Doctor, not distinguishing betwixt a barre, &amp; a Doctors chaire. Secondly, all thèse schoole-points are matters far distant from the argument of <hi>Three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersions,</hi> which he vndertaketh to handle. For I hope he will not affirme, that his Three Conuersions be matters of faith. Thirdly, his first and last point contradict one another. For if all the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our faith are aboue mans reason, as he sayth, handling the first point, then are not some articles of faith demonstrable by force of reason: which is also the doctrine of the Apostle,
<pb facs="8"/>
who sheweth vs, <hi>that the naturall man vnderstandeth not the things of the spirit of God.</hi> Fourthly, by <hi>pious affection</hi> he absurdly vnderstandeth a good opinion of the Pope and his slaues the <hi>Iebusites,</hi> and Masse-priests. But how can <hi>Christians</hi> haue a good opinion of them, whom holy Scriptures declare to be false tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and vpholders of the kingdome of Antichrist, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience declareth to be professed enemies of piety and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? Fiftly he concludeth very absurdly, <hi>because some matters of faith are demonstrable by reason, that he hath so discussed matters in his treatise of Three Conuersions, as that all matters thereby may be cleared.</hi> For neither doth his treatise properly concerne matter of faith, nor hath he done such glorious acts, as he braggeth of. Finally these points do little relieue <hi>Parsons.</hi> For if we are to talke of matters of religion with great reuerēce and submission, then are the writings of the Schoolemen scādalous, that dispute <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>contra</hi> in all matters of religion. <hi>Parsons</hi> also dealeth very lewdly, who attributeth more to Philosophical demōstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then to arguments inducing vs to beleeue matters of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Next if there be matters sufficient in religion to induce vs to beleeue, then are not the articles of Popery to be beleeued, we hauing more inducements to reiect them, then to beleeue them. <hi>Thirdly</hi> if matters are to be scanned before they be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as <hi>Parsons</hi> inferreth; then most blind are the Papists, that beleeuing the Pope and his adherents to be the Church, drinke vp all the abhominations, which the whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> doth present vnto them, without all examination, whether they be consonant to holy Scriptures &amp; the faith of the ancient Fathers, or not. <hi>Fourthly</hi> if matters are to be examined with serenitie of mind, why are Papists forbidden to reade our bookes, to heare our reasons, nay without licence to reade the Scriptures? Why do they condemne them, whose cause they refuse to heare or know? Lastly this his treatise of Three Conuersions is not such a braue peece of worke, as he imagineth, nor shall he gaine any one iote ofhis cause thereby. For first; it is either false that the ancient <hi>Britains</hi> were conuerted by <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> or else very doubtfull. Likewise it is a matter questionable, whether <hi>Austin</hi> the Monke, or some other did first conuert the <hi>Saxons</hi> to the <hi>Christian</hi> faith.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Secondly,</hi> admit the ancient <hi>Britans</hi> had bin conuerted by <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and by <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> and the <hi>Saxons</hi> by <hi>Austin</hi> the Monke; yet this maketh nothing for Pope <hi>Clement the 8.</hi> or <hi>Paule the fift,</hi> that is, no more like to <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> then a Cheshire cheese to the bright Sunne. <hi>Peter</hi> was a holy Apostle, and fed <hi>Christes</hi> sheepe, <hi>Eleutherius</hi> was a godly Bishop, and preached the Gospell, which <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Paule the fift</hi> doth not. Againe <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Paule the fift</hi> challenge two swords, and haue a temporall Kingdome, which those two neuer had, nor challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. This <hi>Clement</hi> and Pope <hi>Paule</hi> mainteine many hereticall doctrines established in the Popes Decretals, and late Popish conuenticles, which neither <hi>S. Peter,</hi> nor <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> nor <hi>Austin</hi> euer heard of. Finally neither are the <hi>Romans</hi> subiect to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> although the Gospell first came to them from thence, nor owe we ought to <hi>Rome,</hi> albeit those that first conuerted the <hi>Britains</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> had come from thence. To those that first taught vs we are obliged to render thanks. But <hi>Parsons</hi> like a foolish logician would thereof inferre, that we are now to yeeld obedience to the Pope, because <hi>Peter</hi> preached first in <hi>Britaine.</hi> He might as well inferre, that the <hi>Romans</hi> are to be subiect to the <hi>Turke</hi> that sitteth at <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> for that the Gospell came first to them from thence.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly</hi> those exceptions which he taketh to vs and our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are most vaine and friuolous, as the discourse ensuing shall declare. Wherefore, as we haue already ripped vp his rude and ragged epistle, aduertisement, and preface; so now, Godwilling, I purpose to discouer the vnsufficiencie and foolery of the rest of his frapling discourse. I do not thinke thou shalt finde a booke of that bulke so void of all proofe, or good matter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse it be some that proceedeth from the same author.</p>
   <p>Reade therefore I beseech thee both our writings with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, and iudge according to equity, and so shalt thou hereafter be made more wary in esteeming such huge volumes fraught with nothing but idle tales, grosse lyes, loose collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to say all in one word, <hi>Iebusiticall</hi> and Popish vanity and foolery, and learne to discerne shadowes from substance, and errors from truth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>