<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND DEVOVT seruant of Iesus Christ.
SISTER CATHARINE FRANCIS, Abbess of the English Monas∣terie of S. Francis third Rule. in Bruxelles.
Euerlasting health.</title>
           <author>Bell, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120727_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08886</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19167</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120727</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND DEVOVT seruant of Iesus Christ.
SISTER CATHARINE FRANCIS, Abbess of the English Monas∣terie of S. Francis third Rule. in Bruxelles.
Euerlasting health.</title>
                 <author>Bell, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short relation, of the life, virtues, and miracles, of S. Elizabeth called the peacemaker. Queen of Portugall : Of the third rule of S. Francis. Canonised by Pope Vrban the VIII. the 25. of May. Anno 1625. Translated out of Dutch; by Sister Catharine Francis, Abbess of the English Monasterie of S. Francis third rule in Bruxelles</title>
                 <author>Paludanus, François</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pepermans, Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Brussels</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 66, 2 pages, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE REVEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND DEVOVT seruant of Iesus Christ.
SISTER CATHARINE FRANCIS, Abbess of the English Monas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of S. Francis third Rule. in Bruxelles.
Euerlasting health.</head>
   <p>REVEREND MOTHER. Having seen in English the little booke of the life of S. ELISABETH Queen of Portugall: vvhich F. Paludan. abbridged, and gaue out to all the people in Spanish, French, and Dutch, in the solemnitie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de at the publishing of her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonisation, in Bruxelles: I knew it to be your Reuerences hand wrighting, and being farder cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb facs="3"/>
that it was your ovvne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and that you had your selfe translated it out of the dutch. Esteeming it so much the more, I conferred it with the originall; and finding it in all things to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and to be à mirrour, not only for Religious, but also for Princes, I had scruple to hide vvhat vvas so behouefull for the commun good; therfore witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing heer the truth of the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I demāded of our superiour his approbation that it might be printed, vvhich had, I dedicate your worck to your ovvne selfe, vvilling you to go forvvard in so good exercise, for nothing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth more to perfection then the examples of those saintes that vvere in all respectes of the same profession that our selves are: nor contrarievvise can any thing more hinder it, then to be bound to one profession, and
<pb facs="3"/>
in affection to follovv another. Verely, to your serious looking into theyr liues (next vnto your dayly, and nightly exercise of quire and meditation) I must at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that principall spirit of gouernement, to vvhich in short time you haue attained by the assistance of him who needeth no long times in teaching, Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, who euer bless your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and bring vs all to see his face, in heaven. Pray for your pore Chaplain.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>BR. FRANCIS BEL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>