<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER, whom I desire to be as Courteous as Conceited.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120514_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03559</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1368</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER, whom I desire to be as Courteous as Conceited.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A banquet of ieasts. Or Change of cheare : Being a collection of moderne jests. Witty ieeres. Pleasant taunts. Merry tales</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 192 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER, whom I desire to be as <hi>Courteous</hi> as <hi>Conceited.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you (of all sorts) that shall vouchsafe the perusall of these few sheetes stitcht vp in a small fardell, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare you to expect no more in this collection of Iests, then the Title page promiseth, wherein is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing earnest, sauing a
<pb facs="3"/> pledge of my good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towards you. If you looke that I should feast you senses, or banquet your particular Pallates, these Papers will much deceiue you: For in the stead of dainties you shall finde <hi>Dicteria:</hi> for Iunkets, <hi>Ioci:</hi> and for curious Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, <hi>Sales.</hi> Onely they are passages of myrth, fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine time, and imploy leasured houres, when they cannot bee more seriously and profitably imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So milde and gentle they are in their condition,
<pb facs="3"/> that as they barke at none, so they bite not any: and therefore you may sport with them freely, and safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Now if some out of their curiositie shall despise them for their common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; I must then retire my selfe to the refuge of that old Adage, <hi>Bona quo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munia eo meliora:</hi> If they prooue good, they cannot be too common. Againe, if any shall obiect and say, that I know that, and this I haue heard related; Those I thus answer. If many haue heard some of them, but
<pb facs="4"/> few or none (I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume) all. Besides I doe not challenge them for mine owne, but gathered from the mouthes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and what is stale to mee, may bee to thee new. Accept them then as cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously as they are offered to thy perusall willingly, to make them familiar vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to such to whom they are meerly forraigne, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect the memories of those to whom they have beene knowne, but since forgotten. I must ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously confesse vnto you,
<pb facs="4"/> that had not the Licence curbed my libertie, the leaves of this booke had beene more in tale, and the Ieasts (for I know not how more properly to style them) greater in number: But as they are (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise now they cannot be) if they bee well accepted, I acknowledge thē too few, but if not well receiued, by many, too many.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Anonimos.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>