<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120982_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17369</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4202</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120982</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and notable sermon vpon the text Vos autem non sic. But you not so : Lately preached vpon speciall occasion, by M. Butler of Owndell, in S. Maries Church in the Vniuersity of Cambridge: and succinctly debating the chiefe matters, which are now in question in the Church of England. Verie profitable for the further resoluing of them, who being brought into suspence by the contradiction of ministers, are content to lend an indifferent eare vnto the truth</title>
                 <author>Butler, of Oundle</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 23, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He necessitie of these our times requiring the helpe of all hands, to the quenching of that fire, vvhich hath of late bene kindled in our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish church, by certaine factious and sedicious firebrandes: I could not (gentle Reader) but impart vnto thee, the frutefull labors of the Author hereof, a diligent labourer and assistant in that businesse, and that not vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some scorching of those flames vvhich he sought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish. And though that dangerous fire (God be praised) be novv so vvell allayed, through the prouident circumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of some vvorthie personages, and no lesse vvorthy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of diuerse learned men, vvho lately haue layed their hands vnto this vvorke, that all danger of further procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is cleane taken avvay: yet this helpe also, shall come (I hope) not out of season, if but to the quenching of that smoke vvherevvith that smothered fire still offendeth the eyes of the better sort. The copie of this Sermon comming to my handes, not by the Author selfe vvho first made it, and then vvrit it: but by an auditor that heard it vvhen it vvas preached, I thought good to permit it to the censure of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate friend, before I vvould commit it to the presse. VVho vpon the first sight of it, euen before he had perused it, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing also bene a hearer) gaue this good testimonie of it, that it neede not feare the censure of any priuate man, vvhich had passed alreadie the censure of a vvhole Vniuersitie, and
<pb facs="3"/> that vvith the general approbation of the common suffrage: excepting onely a fevv odde and singular fellovves, vvho being forestalled vvith a left hand persvvasion of the cause it selfe, cannot brooke the impeachment of their strong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion: and therefore vse of custome to runne against the common streame of all other men. This then, vvas his first opinion of it. But hauing perused it, he further added, that of manie bookes vvhich of late haue bene published in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, not manie haue contriued in so short a a compasse, so manie great matters of question and controuersie: it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the grounds of all the chiefe questions, vvhich at this day do exercise the Church of England. All vvhich he hath not only vvith singular dexteritie and art, and yet very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, raised out of his short Text, but also layed open and dilated so fully as the quicknesse of so learned an auditory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and a great deale more fully, than in that shortnesse of time could be expected. This iudgement being deliuered to me of this Sermon, I could not vvith equitie but send it vnto thee, vvith the same commendation, vvith vvhich it came commended vnto me, both by the first and second cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of a learned man, I being content to haue vsed another mans better eyes, vvhere the vveake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of mine ovvne, vvould not suffer my selfe so vvell to iudge.</p>
   <trailer>Fare-vvell.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>