<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Kings most ex∣cellent Maiestie.</title>
           <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120023_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25672</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120023</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Kings most ex∣cellent Maiestie.</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An antilogie or counterplea to An apologicall (he should haue said) apologeticall epistle published by a fauorite of the Romane separation, and (as is supposed) one of the Ignatian faction : wherein two hundred vntruths and slaunders are discouered, and many politicke obiections of the Romaines answered. Dedicated to the Kings most excellent Maiestie by Andrevv Willet, Professor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 269, that is 279, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_to_King">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Kings most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>AINT <hi>Paule</hi> that diuine Apostle (most gracious and dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) thus concludeth his second Epistle to the Corinthians:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.1.</note>
      <hi>This is the third time that I come vnto you. In the mouth of two or three witnesses shall euery word stand.</hi> As he by his preaching and writing thrise presented himselfe to the Corinthians to testifie his loue: so I haue bene bold now thrise to exhibite my simple la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to your Highnesse; which as three witnesses may, I trust, sufficiētly expresse my ioy for your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties peaceable entrance, and professe my seruice and dutie in prayer for your prosperous cōtinuance.</p>
   <p>Two yeares since I sent a booke to your Highnes into Scotland by your Maiesties Printer, then set foorth vnder Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> name; since, I was bold at your happie arriuall into this land, to present the same vnder your Highnesse owne name: the first a new worke, but not yours; the second yours, but not new: this third is both, which in some sort may supply the foresaid wants in the others.</p>
   <p>The first miscaried, being not at all deliuered. The second was deliuered, but not in season. And now I haue sent this after the other,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.20</note> as <hi>Ionathan</hi> shot three arrowes one to find another; and as the hewer hauing lost his axe in the water,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.6.</note> sent the helue after
<pb facs="5"/>
the head, and found both: so I hope this simple pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent added to the former, may make a way for me vnto your Maiestie, not to speake for my selfe, but in the behalfe of the Church of Christ.</p>
   <p>Now because I know not, whether in this kind I may euer hereafter haue occasion to speake to your Maiestie, let me be bold in the feare of God to vtter my mind to your Highnesse, not onely with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as to a King; but plainely in singlenesse of hart, as to a Christian, a good man, and louer of Gods Church.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Hierome</hi> of Sicile was wont to say, <hi>That none that spake freely to him, did importune him or was vnseasonable</hi>: much more to your Christian Maiestie free and plaine speech deliuered in dutie (I trust) shall not be vnpleasing.</p>
   <p>First then, as we all do praise God for your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie succession in the kingdome, by whom we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly perswaded religion and peace shall be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and maintained; that we haue all cause to say with Israell,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 126.3.</note>
      <hi>The Lord hath done great things for vs, whereof we reioyce</hi>: the times fall out much better, and the change more happie then was of some fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, of others expected. It hath not happened vnto vs, as aged <hi>Leontines</hi> foretold to the Antiochians, who pointing to his gray and white haires, said: <hi>When this snow is melted,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>Hac niue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quefacta mul tū erit luti. <hi>Sozomen.</hi> 3.19▪ <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</p>
         <p>Numantinus ad Scipionē.</p>
      </note>
      <hi>much mire will follow</hi>: that is, sedition and trouble. But after the dissolution of the white snowie haires of our last aged Soueraigne, no such trouble (God be thanked) hath followed: the Lord hath not left vs as sheepe without a shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: <hi>We are the same sheepe to be led foorth still to the waters of life, though another sheepheard.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>As the Church of England acknowledgeth Gods great goodnesse herein: so your Christian Maiestie shall do wel to recogitate with your selfe (as you do) the Lords great mercies toward you; who in your infancie from many perils most prouidently preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you, and in your former raigne from many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers miraculously deliuered you, and now to a most flourishing kingdome most honourably aduaunced you. I doubt not, but as your Highnesse hath the like occasion, so with the Prophet you will vtter the same affection: <hi>My soule praise thou the Lord, and forget not all his benefites</hi>;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.2.</note> as well appeareth to the great comfort of vs all, by that religious weekely ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted exercise in your Highnesse Court. Your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie well remembreth <hi>Moses</hi> counsell to the king:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.20.</note>
      <hi>that he should reade in the law of God all the dayes of his life, that his heart be not lifted vp aboue his brethren.</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are set in slipperie places: if God stay them not, abundance of honor, pleasure, wealth may soone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle thē. This appeared in <hi>Salomon,</hi> who strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell and declined from his integritie. <hi>Alexanders</hi> example in forraine stories is notable, who in iustice, temperance, chastitie was a mirror to all Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he tasted of the pleasures of Asia.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Dionysius</hi> for a while delighted in <hi>Plato,</hi> and seemed to be studious of Philosophie, but he quickely fell away; therein well resembled to a booke, wherein that which was before written, was soone blotted out. But in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, the mutabilitie of nature is corrected by the stabilitie of grace; and God <hi>with whom there is no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riablenesse, nor shadowing by turning,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.7.</note> shall so streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then your royall heart, as that it be neither ouer-cast
<pb facs="6"/>
with shadow, nor turned by change.</p>
   <p>There are two enemies to Christian constancie enuie and flatterie: the one practiseth, the other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swadeth; that pulleth backe, this letteth to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; the last is the worst, the first least to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Enuie followeth vertue, flatterie nourisheth vice: the first <hi>Themistocles</hi> well perceiued, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet young,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> said <hi>he had done no excellent thing, because he was not enuied</hi>: the other <hi>Phocion</hi> was not ignorant of, to whom when the people gaue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause for his oration: <hi>What</hi> (saith he to his friends) <hi>haue I spoken any thing amisse vnawares?</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> shewing that popular applause and flatterie doth often worke vpō some infirmitie. Many haue preuented trecherie, that could not take heed of flatterie. <hi>Dauid</hi> whom neither <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amasaes</hi> valour,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.3. 2. <hi>Sam</hi> 11.</note> nor <hi>Achitophels</hi> wit could subdue, <hi>Ziba</hi> his false tale seduced, and smiling ease and prosperitie corrupted. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> could wel beware of <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Nehe.</hi> 6.10.14.</note> that were threatning aduersaries, but he was most in daunger by <hi>Shemaiah</hi> and <hi>Noadiah</hi> dissembling Prophets. The way for Princes to auoide such flatterers, is to haue faithfull seruants and followers, as <hi>Dauid</hi> saith: <hi>The faithfull in the land shall dwell with me, the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart shall serue me.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 101.6.</note>
      <hi>Lysippus</hi> the Caruer did worthily reproue <hi>Apelles</hi> the Painter, because he had made <hi>Alexanders</hi> picture with a thunderbolt in his hand as a God; the other with a speare, honouring him as a valiant Prince. I doubt not but they are more pleasing to your Highnesse, that giue you that is due, then which ascribe that you will not take. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst enuie and trechery your Maiestie must oppose
<pb facs="6"/>
your Christian innocencie and carefull circumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: against flatterie, your Princely humilitie.<note place="margin">
         <p>Obliuiscitur se regē esse, vbi Deū om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium regem pertimescit: mira res, dū abiicit pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puram, &amp; se regem homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num esse non meminit, rex esse incipit iustitiae, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giosus Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, nō per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit imperiū sed mutauit. <hi>Sam.</hi> 40. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. <hi>v.</hi> 23 24.</p>
         <p>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</p>
      </note> As <hi>Ambrose</hi> well describeth the penitent king of Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie that humbled himselfe in sackcloth: <hi>He forgetteth himselfe to be a king, while he feareth God the king of al: a straunge thing, while he casteth away his purple robes, and remembreth not that he is a king, he beginneth to be a king of Iustice, he did not lose his kingdome, but chaunged it to the better.</hi> God graunt that to your Princely humilitie and Christian pietie may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded diuine constancie, that although archers shoot at you, some with darts of enuy &amp; trechery, some with the bolts of flatterie; yet with <hi>Ioseph your bow may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide strong, and the hands of your armes strengthened to the end. Agesilaus</hi> well said: <hi>I do so vse my selfe, that in no chaunge I be chaunged.</hi> We all trust that this speech will be more truly verified in your Christian Maiestie then in that heathen Prince: which your firme, and (we hope) vnchaungeable constancie hath manifested it selfe in your stedfast resolution for the continuance of religion in sinceritie without mixture. Some haue preas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed alreadie, if not presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to make request for toleration of their Masse, or rather Misse-seruice, for all is amisse in it: but they might know that the Arke and Dagon cannot dwell together: that <hi>Hezechiah</hi> will not suffer the brasen serpent to stand, nor <hi>Iosias</hi> permit the Chemarims to execute their idolatrous seruice. They wold seeme to condition with your Maiestie, whose lands and persons are at your courtesie; much like the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who being forced to giue vp their citie to the Spartans, desired that Samos might be left: to whom
<pb facs="7"/>
one wittily answered:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>When you are not your owne, you would haue others to be yours.</hi> Whereupon grew this Prouerbe: <hi>He that hath not himselfe, would haue Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos.</hi> We haue an English by-word, Beggers must be no choosers, so neither must petitioners be prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Your Maiestie can answer such importunate &amp; vnreasonable suiters, as <hi>Zerubabel</hi> answered the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries of <hi>Iudah,</hi> that offered their seruice craftily to build the temple: <hi>It is not for you, but for vs to build the house vnto our God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4.3.</note> And as <hi>Valentinian</hi> made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the Romaine Embassadors that made peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the restoring of the idoll temples: <hi>That which my brother</hi> (Gratian) <hi>taketh away,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Quod pius frater cripuit, quomodo putatis à me reddendum, cûm in eo &amp; religio &amp; fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter laedatur? <hi>in obit. Valen.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>how can you thinke I should restore? In so doing I should both hurt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and do my brother wrong.</hi> Postulet parens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, alia quaecunque desideret: <hi>Let our mother citie Rome aske any thing else which she desireth.</hi> This good Emperour <hi>Valentinian</hi> being yet but young, was so resolute to continue the puritie of religion, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the instance of the Romaine Orators, and the counsell of all his Senatours that approued their petition, he would not graunt any libertie to Romaine idolatrie. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> answer was very fit to one that perswaded, that the gouernement might be committed to the people:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Do thou first make triall in thy house, giuing thy seruants the rule:</hi> So these that would haue diuerse religions in the Cōmon-weale, yet mislike that there should be any but their owne profession in their houses and families, their children and seruants being for the most part, if they may haue their desires, like affected to themselues. We thanke God for your Maiesties firmenesse and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie
<pb facs="7"/>
herein; praying heartily for the encrease of Christian zeale, strength and corage in your prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heart.</p>
   <p>But as your excellent resolution is to haue the state of the Church and Commonwealth no worse: so we reioyce to heare of your princely consultation to make them both better. Alwaies the noble Princes Reformers haue added somewhat to their predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors worke; and where the other left, they began: <hi>Dauid</hi> brought the Priests and Leuits to order:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 14.3. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 17.6. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 18.4. 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 35.18.</note>
      <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> built the Temple: <hi>Asa</hi> tooke away Idolatrie: <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hosaphat</hi> remoued the high places: <hi>Hezekiah</hi> brake downe the brasen Serpent: <hi>Iosias</hi> restored the feast of the Passeouer to his first integritie: vnder <hi>Nehemiah</hi> the feast of Tabernacles was reuiued:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Neh.</hi> 18.5.</note> So in England <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight expelled the Pope, and abolished I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie: King <hi>Edward</hi> proceeded, and abrogated the Masse: Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> wēt yet further, took or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for recusants, seminary seducing Priests, &amp; Iuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sits: and somewhat it may be is yet remaining, either to be amended or added by your Maiestie; for we doubt not, but that you haue set your heart to seeke the Lord; and with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 20.3.</note>
      <hi>to do that which is good in his sight.</hi> That saying of <hi>Alexander</hi> doth well fit a Christian Prince: <hi>It profiteth not to possesse all things,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>and to do nothing.</hi> As we ioy to see you a possessor of the Crowne,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> so we desire to behold you an agent in Christs Church: we ioy from our hearts to see what reformation your M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>estie hath begun in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, in staying of monopolies, redressing of oppression and extortion by officers, restraining vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games vpon the Lords day. We do also as
<pb facs="8"/>
much reioyce to thinke of your princely resolution for matters Ecclesiasticall, <hi>In restoring the reuenues of the Church, and misliking the law of Annexation, in maintaining the three estates of Parliament,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. 43. l. 1. p. 43. l. 10. vide l. 23.</note>
      <hi>in see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all Churches in your dominions be planted with good Pastors.</hi> And that euery Church may be thus planted with a good Pastor, one should no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be suffered to haue many; nor he that is no good Pastor nor able to teach, any: and if the Pastor must be planted in his Church, then to be plucked and pulled from thence by long absence, is not fit. Thus so many hundred Churches that want teachers shall be supplied; and diuers hundred Preachers not yet called abroade, shall be employed. But seeing a great cause of an vnlearned Ministery is want of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we thanke God for your Highnesse Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an care also herein,<note place="margin">p. 44. l. 1.</note>
      <hi>that sufficient prouision be made for the sustentation of Ministers:</hi> which may be fitly done, if patrons were vrged to bestow their liuings freely, and better order were taken for impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that such as are of the Churches fee, be demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for the old rent to the incumbent Preacher; such as belong to others, be charged with some conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent portion to issue forth for the maintenance of the Pastor. But I presume not to prescribe a course, but onely to giue my simple aduice. To our great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort also your Maiestie hath declared your princely care and desire,<note place="margin">p. 43. l. 26.</note>
      <hi>that the doctrine and discipline be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued according to Gods word:</hi> whereas the first hath bin in this Church by some with vnsound teaching corrupted, as I haue partly shewed in the Preface fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; the other by some much neglected, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="8"/>
not vsed well. There are bookes abroade main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining offensiue doctrine, too much declining to poperie, which haue done great hurt: it might please your Maiestie that such dangerous bookes might be inhibited; and because they are dispersed into many hands, that they receiue some answer by publike al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, or sufficient satisfaction from the authors, lest the infection spread further.</p>
   <p>We also with thāks to God take knowledge of your Highnesse Christian disposition to peace,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s. p.</hi> 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 16</note> that no cōtention shold be in the Church about ceremonies in your princely iudgement, indifferent; whereabout the Church of England hath bene much distracted. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> is said, to auoide drunkennesse to haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the vse of vines. Your Highnesse in good time may more easily remoue the iust occasions of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: or so indifferently moderate them, that they breede no strife. God giue your Maiestie strength in due time to reforme both those, and what other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses are in Church or Commonwealth. Some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps would haue your Maiestie to minister no phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke at all, as though the Church ayled nothing: which were nothing else, but (with <hi>Herodotus Selym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brianus</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi>) to make a long and lingring sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; who falling into an incurable disease,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Plato</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> deuised how to prolong death where he could not preuent it. Some would haue <hi>Heraclitus</hi> phisicke vsed to do nothing but purge; who being sicke of a dropsie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired the Phisitian to purge him throughly, <hi>to turne the abundance of showers into drought:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> so they would haue all purged, not the superfluous humors onely, but some profitable parts; as the very calling it selfe
<pb facs="9"/>
of reuerend Pastors and Bishops: who while they attend the sincere preaching of the word, and the vncorrupt administration of discipline, may (no doubt) do the Church much good. But the better sort desire neither with <hi>Heroditus</hi> nothing to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, nor with <hi>Heraclitus</hi> all things to be euacuated and purged; but rather approue <hi>Hippocrates</hi> method, that, what is euill may be purged, the rest to be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted &amp; strengthened. This was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> course, <hi>to purge out the old leauen, that there might be a new lumpe.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> We would not the leauen, lumpe of dough, and all to be cast out; but the lumpe to be renewed, the old sower leauen to be reiected. Thus shall your Maiestie shew your selfe as <hi>Hierome</hi> saith of one, to be <hi>Hippocrates Christianorum, A right Hippocrates of Christians indeed</hi>; that you may say with the kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 75.3.</note>
      <hi>The earth and the inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are dissolued, but I will establish the pillars of it.</hi> Your Maiestie as another <hi>Moses,</hi> can onely appease the strife betweene the Hebrewes; and as another <hi>Constantine,</hi> to reconcile the Church-ministers, who wrote thus vnto them: <hi>Let me enioy good daies and quiet nights without care;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Date mihi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es tranquillos &amp; noctes cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra expertes: quod si mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, necessum est ingemis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. <hi>Socr.</hi> 1.4</note>
      <hi>if not, my griefe will be the more.</hi> When your Highnes hath wrought this cure, you shal be no more troubled with petitions by day, nor careful meditations by night. <hi>Aristippus</hi> and <hi>Aes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines</hi> being fallen out, one asked the first, what was now become of their friendship; he answered: <hi>It was asleepe, but he would awake it.</hi> When your Highnesse hath awaked the peace of the Church,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> you shal sleep more quietly your selfe, and not be troubled any more with <hi>Constantines</hi> carefull nights. You are our
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Salomon</hi> to iudge betweene vs: they that loue diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and to contend causlesse, let them haue the least part. <hi>Theodosius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Socrat.</hi> 5.10.</note> when Catholikes and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes put vp their libels to him, prayed God to direct him: so your Maiestie well knoweth that your dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction herein must come from God. Diuerse com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints as lots, are cast into your Princely lap, <hi>but the disposition thereof is of the Lord.</hi> God (we trust,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 16.33.</note> and for the same pray) will so dispose your royall heart, that the best cause may haue the first lot, the most honest suite the happiest issue, and the iustest quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell the fairest triall. Faile not their godly desire here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (most gracious Prince) that neuer would haue fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you: who were resolued (I speake herein of mine owne knowledge) to haue aduentured their liues and states for your Maiesties iust title: who waited for <hi>you, as for the raine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 29.23.</note> and for the consolation of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. Faile not then (O noble King) the hope of Christs Church, yea the expectation of Angels, yea the trust that Christ hath committed vnto you, to be a <hi>faithful seruant,</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> in his house: so, as one saith, <hi>The eyes of men are not only cast vpon you,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2. In te vnū puta cunctorū ocu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>los conuersos, &amp; ad specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culū vitae totā consedisse An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliam: Deus ipse cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Angelorū militia certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tuum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectat. Hier. ad Demetr. August. conf. lib. 3. ca. 12.</note>
      <hi>and the whole land setled to behold your life; but God and Angels expect your faithfull seruice.</hi> God, we verily trust will not faile you with his spirit: but as the Prophet saith, <hi>Whosoeuer calleth vpon the name of the Lord, shal be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi>: so your prayers and teares which you poure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, shall both saue you and your people; as one said to <hi>Augustines</hi> mother, <hi>Non potest perire tantarum lachrymarum filius: the child of such prayers and teares cannot possibly perish or fall away.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now as to our great comfort we enioy your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,
<pb facs="10"/>
a norishing father of Christs Church at home; so your Highnesse is expected to be a succour and comfort to other afflicted Churches abroad: though you are not as a head to direct them, yet you may be as a hand to helpe them; though not a roote to giue them life and sap,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.22.</note> yet as a <hi>wall for the small branches to runne vpon, to stay them vp:</hi> as it is said of <hi>Ioseph.</hi> It was <hi>Iosua</hi> his honour, to ayde the Gibeonites their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iosua.</hi> 10.5.</note> against the combined Kings of Canaan. <hi>Dauid</hi> was a captaine to all that were distressed and afflicted.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22:2:</note>
      <hi>Hercules</hi> is honoured in heathen stories, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he trauelled through the world to remoue cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell gouernours.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Noble <hi>Alexander</hi> is famous for the same, who conquered a great part of the world, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing rude and barbarous people to ciuill life: who charged all to esteeme the <hi>whole world as their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Fox pag.</hi> 228. <hi>col.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>good men, as their countrymen; the bad, as aliens and strangers.</hi> Our English Chronicles do blame <hi>Henry</hi> the second for refusing to take the protection, and defence of the distressed Christians in Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, offered vnto him by <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Patriarke; the troubles that befell him at home are ascribed to that cause. But Ecclesiasticall stories make honourable mention of the Emperour <hi>Theodosius</hi> the younger,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Socrat.</hi> 7.23.</note> whose loue was such to the afflicted people of God, that being present to behold certaine publicke sights and shewes, and there hearing of the death of one <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes,</hi> a cruell rebell and tyrant, presently left the playes, and went to the Church to giue thankes to God. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was a foster mother to all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed Christians; and I doubt not, but all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants in the world shall receiue comfort (in the cause
<pb facs="10"/>
of Religion) from your Maiesties fauour, in being a mediator for their peace, or succour for their reliefe.</p>
   <p>But of all other, we the poore companie of schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and students, haue greatest cause to reioyce in your Maiestie, whom now we haue obtained a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and iudiciall patron of our labours and writings: whereas before, no gift or present was held to be more base, nor lesse regarded of all hands. Schollers bookes, the trauaile of the soule, the weakning of the bodie, the care of the day, and studie of the night, were not not so welcome to the most, as a Lawyers fee from the client, or a tenants new-yeares gift to his Land-lord. I your Maiesties poore subiect could speake herein by experience, what small hartening I haue had in the world for my poore trauels in the Church: but I will be sparing in mine owne cause. And yet I speake not this as though we expected our reward from men (though we be men, and had need of terrene encouragement:) but I am bold, a poore writer of this Church of England, to poure forth the common griefe and complaint of students in this behalfe, into your princely bosome. Bookes were growne into such small request, that many would scarce vouchsafe the reading of them; but few beare in mind who presented them: they were layed aside by the walles, or set vp onely to make a shew, as one saith:<note place="margin">Senec. lib. 1. de tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vitae.</note>
      <hi>Sacrorum opera ingeniorum in speciem &amp; cultum parietum comparantur; The labours of sacred wits were vsed onely to beautifie the walles.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But now we trust, as <hi>Homers</hi> Iliads were accepted of <hi>Alexander,</hi> which he made <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, the furniture of his iourney; <hi>Terence</hi> workes of <hi>Scipio;
<pb facs="11"/>
Origens</hi> bookes of <hi>Ambrosius,</hi> whom he called <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, because hee continually prouoked him to write; and as <hi>Hieromes</hi> writings were esteemed of <hi>Damasus</hi>: so I doubt not, but scholers labours shall be as welcome to your Maiestie, as any other subiects presents. And in this confidence I haue bene bold againe to offer my seruice to your Maiestie. For as he that made that harpe wherewith <hi>Thales</hi> appeased the tumult of the Lacedaemonians; and he that built the ship wherewith <hi>Themistocles</hi> did defend Greece, had cause more to reioice therein, then in any worke beside: so to none else we more willingly present our labours, then to your sacred Maiestie, a generall procurer of our peace, and defender of Church and countrey; whose vigilant heart careth for all, whose diligent eye seeth for all, whose liberal hand reacheth vnto all. And not onely at this present, but while I liue, haue I purposed to consecrate my pen to the honor of your Maiestie (if God will &amp; you please:) And I say with <hi>Hierome:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prefat. in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nielem.</note>
      <hi>Quamdiu in hoc corpusculo sum, scribam aliquid gratum vobis, vtile Ecclesiae, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num posteris.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But here one thing I cannot pretermit, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the great ioy of your Maiesties subiects for your princely acceptance of poore mens complaints, and the readie accesse to your royall person. It hath pleased your Maiesty to signifie herein, that it is your gracious pleasure and minde <hi>in giuing accesse to be so open and affable to euery ranke of honest persons,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. 46. l. 12.</note>
      <hi>as that they may make their owne sutes to you them selues, and not to employ others to be their intercessors.</hi> Therfore the King is said to go out and in before the people,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 3.7.</note> that
<pb facs="11"/>
they may haue free accesse vnto him in time &amp; place conuenient: that though it be not for the safetie of the Prince to be so open as the Romane Tribunes, whose doores night and day were open to all suters; nor yet fit to be <hi>locked vp and retired as the Persian kings</hi>; or as <hi>Clearchus</hi> of Pontus,<note place="margin">Plutarc. quaest. <hi>Rom.</hi> 81. p. 12. l. 19.</note> that did hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and sleepe in a chest; or <hi>Aristodemus</hi> king of the Argiues, that did clime vp into his hanging bed by a ladder, that no man should come vnto him: yet is it honorable (as your Maiestie well knoweth, and we hope will practise) for the Prince often to shew himselfe to his people, that they may flocke vnto him <hi>tanquam ad salutare sydus;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Seneca. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>as to a comfortable starre,</hi> as one saith; and to be free for all to come vnto, <hi>as the altar.</hi> We shall not neede then (especially the Ministers of the Gospell) to complaine with <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose,</hi> who suing to the Emperour for one <hi>Higmus</hi> an ancient Bishop adiudged to exile,<note place="margin">Epist. 27.</note>
      <hi>ne sine veste &amp; plumario pateretur extrudi, extrusus est ipse: that he should not be thrust out without his bed and clothes, was thrust out himselfe.</hi> But we praise God for your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, as the same father doth for the good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Gratian,</hi> of whom he saith:<note place="margin">Epist. 126.</note>
      <hi>Scripsisti tua totam Epistolam manu, You wrote an Epistle with your owne hand</hi>: whom he compareth to <hi>Abraham</hi> which kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a calfe with his owne hands to entertaine the Angels: <hi>Nec in ministerio religioso aliorum adiumenta quaesiuit; And in a religious worke sought not anothers helpe.</hi> For the like mercifull disposition in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, in vouchsafing your selfe to attend the causes of your subiects, we say with S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Onesiphorus:</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18.</note>
      <hi>The Lord grant that you may find mercie with the Lord
<pb facs="12"/>
in that day.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now lastly I craue pardon for my boldnesse and plainenesse of speech, not doubting but that your Maiestie approueth that saying of <hi>Ambrose</hi> vttered of noble <hi>Theodosius:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist. 29·</note>
      <hi>Neque imperiale est, libertatem dicendi negare; neque sacerdotale, quod sentit non dicere: It is nether princelike, to denie liberty of speech; nor mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterlike, not to speake what he thinketh.</hi> And we are not ignorant of your royall disposition herein, to <hi>loue those best that are plainest with you</hi>:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. p. 71. l. 3.</note> which emboldneth me to say with <hi>Hierome, Mallem apud te verecundia parumper, quàm causa periclitari; I had rather hazard my credite then the cause</hi>: but I trust I shall hazard nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by any thing which out of a single heart, and loyall affection I haue vttered. I haue deliuered my conscience, discharged my dutie, and (I hope) not written otherwise then became me. I leaue the rest to your princely consideration, according to that saying in the Prouerbes:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.9.</note>
      <hi>Da sapienti occasionem, &amp; sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piet amplius.</hi> Thus I end with heartie prayer vnto God, so to strengthen your Maiestie with his grace, that you may be constant in all goodnesse to the end, zealous of his glorie to amend what is amisse, to supply what is wanting, to cherish the good, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the euill, relieue the oppressed: so shall your Highnesse do that which shall be acceptable vnto God, honourable to your selfe, profitable to his Church, comfortable and ioyous to your owne soule in the end. Go forward then, noble King, in your wel-begun course; follow your owne Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an iudgement, to practise as you haue prescribed, to performe as you haue purposed; consider that all
<pb facs="12"/>
the people of this land are your sheepe: the Lord hath made you the chiefe ouerseer and Steward, according to your princely name, both of Church and Common-wealth. Of this Stewardship you must one day render account vnto God: prouide then, O Christian Prince, that you may do it with ioy. The Persian Kings alwayes appointed one in the morning to call vnto them; <hi>Arise, O King,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>and take care of these things which</hi> Oromasdes <hi>bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee be carefull of.</hi> But your Maiesties owne thankfull remembrance of Gods mercies, will suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice within to put you in mind, and sing as it were in your eares, what God requireth and you haue promised: and to thinke of <hi>Mordecay</hi> his speech to Queene <hi>Esther, Who knoweth whether thou art come to the Kingdome for such a time?</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Esther</hi> 4.14.</note> As for vs, we trust by Gods grace to see so happie a chaunge by this chaunge, that whereas we had thought our selues vndone, we may truly say as <hi>Themistocles</hi> did, who being exiled his countrey was better entertained in the Persian court,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>We had perished, if we had not perished.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>God graunt to your Maiestie a long and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous raigne; to your noble Queene happie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance with you; and length of dayes to your honourable sonne, Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> encrease of all princely graces with growth of yeares; and to your royall posteritie to raigne ouer this land, if it be Gods will, vnto the worlds end: and vnto you all an endlesse reward in heauen, for your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full seruice to Christ here on earth. And so I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with <hi>Ambrose: Ipse me citiùs quàm vos ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuiscar;
<pb facs="13"/>
&amp; si vnquam sermo tacebit, loquetur affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus</hi> (Iacobe <hi>&amp;</hi> Henrice) <hi>in vestris nominibus adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere iuuat,</hi>
      <note place="margin">(Gratiane, Valentiniane) apud Ambr.</note>
      <hi>&amp; delectat in vestri commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione requiescere.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble subiect, <hi>Andrew Willet.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>