<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE OPINION OF George Cassander, A LEARNED PAPIST, AND GRAVE DIVINE; That by two seuerall Emperors, FERDINAND, and MAXIMILIAN, was set on worke to compose these quarrels of the CHVRCH. In his consultation, pag. 56. &amp; 57.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr37_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE OPINION OF George Cassander, A LEARNED PAPIST, AND GRAVE DIVINE; That by two seuerall Emperors, FERDINAND, and MAXIMILIAN, was set on worke to compose these quarrels of the CHVRCH. In his consultation, pag. 56. &amp; 57.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="text">
   <pb n="631" facs="332"/>
   <head>THE OPINION OF George Cassander, A LEARNED PAPIST, AND GRAVE DIVINE; That by two seuerall Emperors, FERDINAND, and MAXIMILIAN, was set on worke to compose these quarrels of the CHVRCH. In his consultation, pag. 56. &amp; 57.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et J cannot denie, but that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, many out of a godly zeale and care, were driuen to a sharpe and seuere reproofe of certaine manifest abuses; and that the principall cause of this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie, and distraction of the Church, is to bee laid vpon those, which being puffed vp with a vaine insolent conceit of their Ecclesiasticall power, proudly and scornefully contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reiected them, which did rightly, and modestly, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish their reformation: Wherefore my opinion is, that the Church can neuer hope for any firme Peace, vnlesse they make the beginning, which haue giuen the cause of the distraction:
<pb n="632" facs="333"/> that is, vnlesse those which are in place of Ecclesiasticall Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will bee content to remit something of their too much rigor, and yeeld somewhat to the Peace of the Church; and hearkening vnto the earnest Prayers and Admonitions of many godly men, will set themselues to correct manifest abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, according to the rule of Diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and of the ancient Church from which they haue swarued.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>