<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Baddeley, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120841_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68096</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1185</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120841</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Baddeley, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The boy of Bilson: or, A trve discovery of the late notoriovs impostvres of certaine Romish priests in their pretended exorcisme, or expulsion of the Diuell out of a young boy, named William Perry, sonne of Thomas Perry of Bilson, in the county of Stafford, yeoman : Vpon which occasion, hereunto is premitted a briefe theologicall discourse, by way of caution, for the more easie discerning of such Romish spirits; and iudging of their false pretences, both in this and the like practices</title>
                 <author>R. B. (Richard Baddeley)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 47, 1, 45-75, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing acquainted with the mind and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the <hi>Author</hi> of this ensuing <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise,</hi> and hauing thereunto added those other Pieces (vnto which I am no stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,) to make the <hi>Narration</hi> complete, as concerning <hi>the Boy of Bilson:</hi> I thought it my duty, after much sollicitation, to communicate the whole in print; and so to make it <hi>iuris publici.</hi> And this (as I thought) these very times did exact. For now the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Priests haue so cauterized their consciences, and rub'd their foreheads, as that they take delight, and blush not, daily to forge and coyne most monstrous<note n="*" place="margin">Witnes (among many others) their fresh <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-lye,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the supposed <hi>Apostasie</hi> of the late <hi>L. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
      </note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths; all to support their drooping and dropping Cause. Since therefore their appetites are so well <hi>whetted</hi> and set on edge (by what<note n="*" place="margin">Perhaps the same that one of them hanged about the Boyes necke. <hi>vid.</hi> pag. <hi>63.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Stone</hi> we may easily ghesse, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their due reward,) as that they make no bones of whatsoeuer is set before them; to stay their stomacks a while, let them be chewing this bit, (which otherwise they shall not now eschue,) <hi>Vt quam falsa dicendo</hi> &amp; scrthendo <hi>voluptatem ceperint, eandem vera</hi> legendo &amp; <hi>audiendo amittant.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Here then (good Reader) in the first place thou hast a <hi>Treatise</hi> professedly written for a <hi>Discouery</hi> of, and a <hi>Caution</hi> against the enueagling proiects of Romish <hi>Priests,</hi> chiefly in that one particular, <hi>viz.</hi> their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Priestly <hi>Exorcizing</hi> and expolling <hi>of Diuels</hi> out of bodies possessed. By which thou maist iudge, whether these <hi>Mirabularies</hi> deserue not the reputation of the
<pb facs="3"/>varest <hi>Mountebanks</hi> of these times. Next followes, <hi>A faithfull Relation</hi> (for so they name it) made by these <hi>Priests, touching</hi> their <hi>proceedings with the Boy:</hi> which they did purposely write and disperse,<note place="margin">Vide pag. <hi>45.</hi>
      </note>
      <q>
         <hi>To the end</hi> (as they professe) <hi>that all indifferent mindes may magnifie and praise Almighty God, that hath left such power to men, &amp;c.</hi>
      </q> such (for sooth) as they had, in <hi>Exorcizing</hi> and coniuring the <hi>Diuell</hi> within that <hi>Boy,</hi> being their supposed desperate <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack.</hi> Which glorious worke of theirs when these <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Aruspices</hi> shall, at their next enteruiew, recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize,<note place="margin">cie.</note>
      <hi>Mirabor si non riserint.</hi> And that so much the rather, after they haue perused the Remaine of this Booke, in which the Euent and successe of the whole busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is truly related; and their formidable <hi>Mormo</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no other then an Apish <hi>Cobalus.</hi> Whereby it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so come to passe that these <hi>Catholike Gentlemen</hi> (for so they stile thēselues, albeit by their<note n="*" place="margin">See their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions in this Booke. pag. <hi>63.64.</hi> &amp;c.</note> outward garbe one would rather suspect thē for Serning-men &amp; attendants on such persons, <hi>nè quid grauius</hi>) shall be so cleerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced of palpable Quacksaluing, as that a very meane Herald, knowing the house they come of, may blazon their Armes; and so expose thē vnto shame and laughter.</p>
   <p>But I will not intertaine thee (gentle Reader) with any longer parle in the entrance, after that I shall put thee in mind of that sound aduise, which an Heathen Philosopher long since prescribed (but neuer so necessary as now, when Popish impostures are so rife,) <hi>viz.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Ipicharmus.</note> Which may be thus englished; <hi>Bee wise, and bee not hasty to beleeue.</hi> which precious <hi>Amulet</hi> I commend vnto thee, and All of vs to the rich mercy of our most gracious God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ryc. Baddeley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>