<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>G., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120800_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02239</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12374</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120800</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>G., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A generall historie of the Netherlands : VVith the genealogie and memorable acts of the Earls of Holland, Zeeland, and west-Friseland, from Thierry of Aquitaine the first Earle, successiuely vnto Philip the third King of Spaine: continued vnto this present yeare of our Lord 1608, out of the best authors that haue written of that subiect: by Ed. Grimeston</title>
                 <author>Le Petit, Jean François</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 299, 310-646, 4, 647-1415, that is 1413, 21 pages, illustrations (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, it is now almost two yeares since I published to your view the Inuentorie of the French Historie: I must confesse, it had beene more safe to haue made that worke the period of my labours, and not to haue vndergone a new taske of greater difficulty. But by the intreaty of some (whom I much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect) and mine owne desire to giue my countrie-men some more contentment, and to acquaint them (that haue not read it in the French) with the whole hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie of the Netherland warres, as wel as with the estate of France, I haue thus venturously once againe put forth from a safe port, into an ocean of dangers, and vndertaken the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation of this historie of the Netherlands. Whereunto I was the more incouraged, by the gratious recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my noble patrons, and the kind testimonies of approbation of many courteous and well minded gentlemen, who haue bin content to wincke at my weakenesse and defects in that worke, and to allowe of mine indeauours: yet will I not arrogate any thing that was praise worthie in that storie vnto my selfe, nor attribute the worthinesse of those authors to mine owne merit, who could both grace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in writing French, and me in teaching them to speake English. I doubt not but some will thinke it a great indiscretion to meddle with this subiect, whereas the soueraigntie and prerogatiue of a mightie monarch in those vnited prouinces is called in question. I confesse it were so, if it were origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally done by me; but beeing written in the French, Italian, Latine, and Dutch, I thought I might without any imputation impart it to our owne nation, which hath had so great a share in those warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s. I assure my selfe it will be diuersly censured, as men stand affected to the cause; some (I doubt not) will read it, to be satisfied of the true causes and proceedings of this long and bloodie warre; some I presume, will curiously search out but for matter of exception, and not instruction; and I feare some will be so transported with passion, and out of charitie, as whereas before they would haue exchanged a friendly good morrow with me, they will now shunne my company, and take me for a capitall enemie to their cause. But good God, how are they abused in their conceptions? I would intreat those men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that I neither take vpon me to be an aduocate to plead the cause, nor a champion, to defend it by armes; but am onely a bare translator, who am tied to my teacher, and cannot exceed the limits pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed me by mine author. There is nothing of mine owne in this worke; neither haue I added nor kept backe anything that was materiall for the subiect: and I may lawfully protest, that I haue beene free from passion, without aggrauation or detraction, hauing vsed all the moderation I could in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of any thing, where there might appeare either spleene or affection. As for the truth of the historie, and the integritie of mine author, I must referre you to <hi>Iohn Francis Petit,</hi> who must plead for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: and therefore I haue planted his owne preface or apologie in the front of this booke; where you may both see his reasons for the course of the historie, beginning with the earles of Holland and Zee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and read his protestations for his sinceritie, in the faithfull relating of all things that haue passed during the warres. If this may not suffice for his iustification, he himselfe is yet liuing here in London, and ready to satisfie any doubt that may arise. I must aduertise the reader, that to make this historie more perfect, and to continue it vnto these times, I haue beene forced to vse some other helpes, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially of <hi>Emanuel Demetrius,</hi> who hath beene very carefull and industrious to congest all things which concerne this subiect; for the effecting whereof, hee hath had very good and great intelligence. I haue also beene beholding to monsieur <hi>Hottoman,</hi> a french gentleman, who at my late beeing in
<pb facs="6"/>
France, did furnish me with sundrie excellent discourses, concerning this hystorie: And I haue had some obseruations in written hand, by the meanes of that worthy knight, sir <hi>Peter Manwood,</hi> the which were gathered by sir <hi>Roger Williams,</hi> when he first bore armes vnder <hi>Iulian Romero,</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard in the great Commanders time: all which I haue presumed to insert, knowing they wil be a grace and beautie to the storie, and a benefit to the reader: And therefore I hope I shall bee excused, if I haue borrowed a little of the laws of translation, seeing it belongs vnto the subiect, and is but a supply of that which my author wanted. My designe was, to make it a particular Hystorie of the Netherlands, wherein I haue not willingly inserted any thing, which doth not directly concerne the prince or the prouinces. If you shall find any thing related here, which you haue formerly read in the French Inuentorie, as the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Netherlands to the Infanta, the death of the king of Spaine, the combat of <hi>Briaute,</hi> &amp;c. I pray you consider, that they do chiefly belong vnto this subiect, and were drawne out of this originall.</p>
   <p>But leauing the subiect and the author, I must be a sutor vnto you for my selfe and the Printers: my first suit shall be, That in reading of this historie, you will not expect the succinct stile of <hi>Iohn de Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> nor the fluent discourses of <hi>Peter Mathew,</hi> but (being written by a soldier, and, as he himself con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth, in harsh vnpolished Wallon French) you will accept thereof in this course English habit, beeing bare, and without ornaments of Rhetorick; my chiefest care and studie hauing alwayes beene, to inrich it with good matter, for their better instruction which are desirous to learne. I must confesse my stile is harsh and plaine, for so is my authors: Besides, I haue beene forced to vse the helpe of a harsh translator, for some things, out of the Dutch tongue, the which (being surprised with the shortnesse of time) I haue been constrained to insert, being not so exactly reformed as I could haue wisht. Which defects of mine, with all others committed at the presse (the which must needs be many in so great a volume) I must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to supply with your iudicious reading, &amp; to censure fauorably. I must also craue your patience for a misprision in the Titles: for being my selfe at court, and absent from the presse, the Printer hath continued the earl of Leicesters name in the Title, long after his death; and hath forgotten to set prince <hi>Maurice</hi> his picture in his due place: the which is but an offence to the eye, but no alteration in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. My last suit vnto you is, in respect of the verses vnder euerie picture, I must confesse, they were out of my element, neither was I willing to trouble my selfe therewith, being opprest with the shortnesse of time, and the greatnesse of this worke: I referred them to the Printers care, who (being no good po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets themselues) haue employed one, which hath scarce made good rime of many of them. Our ioynt suit is, That if the rime please you not, you would be satisfied with the reason: or at the least (being not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the matter) passe them ouer as blanks. And so, wishing you as much content in the reading, as I haue had care to giue you contentment in the writing, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer,
E. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>