<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, containing the Scope of all the Sixe Treatises, and certaine generall things, which by way of Introduction belong vnto them all.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120511_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17397</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4222</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120511</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, containing the Scope of all the Sixe Treatises, and certaine generall things, which by way of Introduction belong vnto them all.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The marrovv of the oracles of God. Or, diuers treatises : containing directions about sixe of the waightiest things can concerne a Christian in this life. by N. Bifield, late preacher of Gods Word at Isleworth in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meredith, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stephens, Philemon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 101+ pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="12"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, containing the Scope of all the Sixe Treatises, and certaine generall things, which by way of Introduction belong <hi>vnto them all.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orthy sake <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> I haue beene willing to prepare for the Presse, Sixe little Treatises: Which may informe thee of six things, of the greatest consequence, that I know can concerne thee in this life. And though I haue reason to abase my selfe in the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mine owne frailtie and
<pb n="2" facs="13"/>
insufficiency for these things, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> thou hast cause to awaken to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> consideration of the matter which so neerly concerneth thee vsing the helpe of this labour, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> God affoord thee better helpe from more able instruments. The matter in all of them is so neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, that I know not which of them thou mayest safely neglect</p>
   <p>The first thing which any man <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note> disposing himselfe for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, will and ought to inquire after, is, <hi>What he should doe to be rid of those so many sinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> he hath beene and is guilty of?</hi> Rid (I say) from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> guilt and danger of them, and from the power and dominion of them. For the satisfaction of thy conscience in this most needfull question, I haue in this first Treatise gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee, out of the whole Bible, a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of those sinnes, which in our repentance God will haue with speciall notice to be confessed and auoided. And
<pb n="3" facs="13"/>
these sinnes I haue set downe, as neere as I could, in the <hi>expresse words of the text,</hi> that thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test see the Lord himselfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing thy offences: and so mightest haue no excuse or doubt, to imagine that it was but the iudgement of some men, that made such things to bee thought to bee sinnes. By this course of surueying the whole Scriptures, I haue both found out diuers particular offences plainely <hi>proued</hi> to be so, which I could not obserue to be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in any exposition of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements which I had, and also diuers things proued cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be sinnes, which were one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly barely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ffirmed to bee so in other writers. I haue likewise plainely shewed thee by <hi>expresse Scripture,</hi> what course thou maiest distinctly take to be rid of thy sinnes: a course that cannot faile thee, being grounded on the most euident directions,
<pb n="4" facs="14"/>
which God himselfe hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed vnto thee, if thy owne slothfulnesse &amp; proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>astination, or wilfull peruersenesse binder thee not: And I doubt not but by experience thou wilt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, the course is comfortable &amp; easie, considering the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and rest thou mayest bring to thy conscience thereby.</p>
   <p>The second thing a man would <note place="margin">2. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the second booke.</note> desire to bee satisfied in, (that hath beene entred into the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of Repentance) is, <hi>How hee might come to bee infallibly assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, concerning Gods fauour, and his owne saluation;</hi> and for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer hereunto, I haue in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. Treatise gathered out of the Scriptures, <hi>signes</hi> of Gods owne making, by which men may try their estate, &amp; these <hi>such, as</hi> both <hi>describe wicked men,</hi> not yet in Christ, <hi>and such,</hi> as describe <hi>godly men</hi> that shall certainly bee saued. And withall, I haue now added directions, how by the
<pb n="5" facs="14"/>
helpe of those signes men may settle their <hi>assurance,</hi> and how such as yet want those signes, may attaine them.</p>
   <p>The third thing euery Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ought to seeke satisfaction in, <note place="margin">3. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the third booke.</note> is this, <hi>How a man that hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto the assurance of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when hee dies, may comfort and establish his heart against all the miseries and distresses, which may, and will befall him in this life before his death.</hi> And to this end I haue gathered out of the whole <hi>Scriptures</hi> those admirable <hi>conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> which may bee abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sufficient to vphold him with much ioy in the worst estate that can befall him. And this is done in the Treatise which I call the <hi>Promises.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The fourth question, a carefull Christian, that hath thus found <note place="margin">4. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the fourth booke.</note> out the gaine of godlines, would aske, is this, <hi>what he should doe in the whole course of his life to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God,</hi> who hath thus loued
<pb n="6" facs="15"/>
him, and giuen his Sonne to dye for him, and purchased such a glorious inheritance for him. And for answer hereunto, I haue likewise out of the Scripture ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <hi>the rule of Life,</hi> which will shew him distinctly, how he should carrie himselfe <hi>towards God,</hi> and <hi>towards men</hi> in all parts of his life; how hee should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himselfe <hi>at home</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,</hi> in <hi>company,</hi> and <hi>out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> &amp;c. and all this shewed him by the <hi>expresse words</hi> of the Scriptures.</p>
   <p>In the fifth place, if a man aske himselfe what yet he wants that <note place="margin">5 The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the fift booke.</note> is necessarie for his state, he may and ought to bethinke himselfe of this question; <hi>What are those necessarie truths, which God hath absolutely tied him to know and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, without which he cannot bee saued, and which are fundamental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needfull for him?</hi> To this end I haue collected a fift Treatise, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <note n="*" place="margin">Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of the Principles, reade the Aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the end of the Rules of Life, pag 640.</note>
      <hi>Principles:</hi> which are
<pb n="7" facs="15"/>
an extract out of all the Doctrine of religion: of such truths in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of religion, as a man is bound of necessitie to know. And this I haue not onely <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> by Scripture, but shewed what <hi>vses</hi> hee may put such knowledge to, all the dayes of his life.</p>
   <p>The sixt and last thing which <note place="margin">6 The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the last booke.</note> ought to bee enquired after, is, how a man thus fitted to liue the life of God, may also <hi>bee cured of the feare of death;</hi> and to this end I haue published that Treatise of the Cure of the feare of Death, which shewes plaine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable wayes, how any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian may deliuer his heart from <note place="margin">Whom these Treatises concerne.</note> those feares.</p>
   <p>I suppose that no man that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this, will conceiue, that any of these is needlesse. And as I would aduise such Christians as abound with abilitie and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, to furnish themselues with the labours of such worthy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ines,
<pb n="8" facs="16"/>
as haue written of any of those subiects: so vnto such Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians as haue not that abilitie or leysure I commend these Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises, both for their breuity, and the distinct digesting of the things he would seek after; there being nothing of mine in these, but the labour of disposing them, the maine substance of them being Gods owne Word, and things deuised and inuented by God himselfe. I may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend the care and study of these things vnto thee, and that with so much authority from the Lord, as to tell thee, that thou maiest not safely bee negligent in any of these, if thou consider the worth of them, or thy owne n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed.</p>
   <p>If thou say, that here is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed a hard tas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, and so many <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>y of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>se <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> things are to bee done, as may make any man afraid to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ddle with directions of such variety, and number;</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="9" facs="16"/>
I answer; that in many of these Treatises the way is not made harder then is required; or in the doctrine of the Church mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested: but rather things are made more plaine, and so more easie. Besides, thou knowest already, that the <hi>way</hi> to heauen <hi>is a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and straight way, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>w find it.</hi> But especially thou shouldest weigh with thy selfe the great encouragements and motines to abide the hardship and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of any godly and necessary course. Though the way to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> (with the <hi>Israelites)</hi> were through a solitary wildernesse, yet it should comfort thee, that it is but <hi>a way of three dayes,</hi> as they say, being about to get out of Egypt, God will keepe thee at worke but a little time, and therefore thou shouldst not thinke much of thy paines. And further thinke of it, that this is a course of wonderful comfort and safety: when a Christian followes
<pb n="10" facs="17"/>
the euident directions of Gods Word in these most weighty things, he walks safely: He is in the <hi>good way, the way of life,</hi> the <hi>way of peace;</hi> he is sure to <hi>see the saluation of God.</hi> To follow those directions soundly, is to keepe our soules. All <hi>Gods waies</hi> will be <hi>mercy and truth</hi> to vs. God will cause vs <hi>to heare his louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in the morning.</hi> Our way will be full of refreshing: Gods waies are <hi>wayes of pleasure,</hi> and if any man set himselfe exactly to take notice of Gods will in these things, and will be at paines to store his heart distinctly in such solid truths: it is certaine, the Lord will recompence his way vpon him, <hi>God will not cast away the exact man, till he fill his mouth with laughter,</hi> as it is said, <hi>Iob</hi> 8. 20, 21. Sure it is, that in the study of these things lyeth the way of eternity, and though thou thinke the way to be hard and narrow, yet this may somewhat case thee;
<pb n="11" facs="17"/>
it is a <hi>plaine way:</hi> For the <hi>simple</hi> may profit by it, as is auouched to bee true of all the courses which God by his Word so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly required, <hi>Psal. 119. Isaiah</hi> 26. 7. &amp; 52. 16. <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides thou hast many helpes; the word of God will not only shew thee what to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, but it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in thee a secret power to doe it; God will <hi>teach thee to profit,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit of God will helpe thy infirmitie:</hi> and God will <hi>send his Angels to guide thee</hi> in thy way: <hi>Christ will be the Way and the Life to thee.</hi> And thou hast good company; for this is the <hi>old way,</hi> the way of all Gods ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in the substance of the course.</p>
   <p>Onely before thou set vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Generall directions by way of preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> of these directions, let mee giue this generall aduice, to looke to these few things.</p>
   <p>First, thou must giue ouer, and forsake vngodly company; for else it is in vaine to meddle with
<pb n="12" facs="18"/>
any religious course, as these pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will shew thee, Psal. 1. 1, 2. Prou. 4. 14, 15. &amp; 9. 6. &amp; 23. 19, 20, &amp; 29 27. Psal. 26. 2 Cor. 6.</p>
   <p>Secondly, thou must <hi>get thee into the way of good men,</hi> prouide <note place="margin">2</note> for thy self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> (if it be possible) the fellowship and societie of godly persons, Prou. 2. 20. Isai. 19. 23, 24, 25. For this fellowship will take away the tediousnesse of the way, and much preserue thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst giuing ouer; and their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples will bee as patternes for thee, and by acquaintance with them, thou wilt be brought into acquaintance with God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, Isaiah 16. 23, 24. 2 Cor. 6. 16, 17, 18. Prou. 2. 20.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, thou must remember <hi>to pray vnto God</hi> by all meanes <hi>to</hi>
      <note place="margin">3</note>
      <hi>direct thee, and shew thee the way</hi> in all these things, thou must <hi>beg a way of God,</hi> and beseech him to <hi>remoue from thee all lying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull wayes,</hi> Ezra 8. 21. Psal, 119. 26. Ier. 2. 33.
<pb n="23" facs="18"/>
Fourthly, thou must, when thou comest to Gods directions, <hi>lift</hi>
      <note place="margin">4.</note>
      <hi>vp thy soule,</hi> and giue not way to thine owne <hi>carnall reason,</hi> and the sluggishnesse of thy owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the deceitfulnesse of thy owne heart: but let the Lord see thou art willing to doe any thing thou canst, Psal. 143. 8. Bring a <note place="margin">Note.</note> mind desirous to <hi>obey in all things.</hi> By any meanes take heed, thou be not like those complained of, Isaiah 58. 2. that haue a great mind to know Gods wayes, and to read all sorts of directions, as if they sought righteousnesse in a speciall manner of care, and yet do not follow any of the courses they so much desire to kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>w, &amp; seeme to commend and like. If euer thou wouldest haue thy soule to dwell at ease, choose out for thy selfe those wayes which God doth teach thee, Psalme 25. 12, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>. Let the Lord know, that if hee will be pleased to teach thee a sure way, thou wilt
<pb n="14" facs="19"/>
walke in his paths; and to that end, beforehand beseech him <hi>to vnite thy heart to his feare, Psal.</hi> 86. 11. Thou shouldest bee of <hi>Dauids</hi> mind, to say, <hi>O that my way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s were directed to keepe Gods statutes,</hi> and then thou wouldst resolue to keepe them, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 5, 8.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>