<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE To the right welbeloued Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>W., Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120274_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15731</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26000</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120274</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE To the right welbeloued Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>W., Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An anker of Christian doctrine : Whearein the most principal pointes of Catholique religion are proued by the only written word of God. Not abandoning diuine, nor apostolical traditions, authentical councels, popes decrees, auncient fathers, nor other ordinary proofes: bu abstracting from them in this encounter: for better satisfaction of those, who wil admitte none other tryal of true religion, but Scriptures only. Permissu superiorum</title>
                 <author>Worthington, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai ; Great Britain--England--East Ham ; Great Britain--England--Lancashire</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Birchley Hall Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kellam, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>332, 233-236, 335-496 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="1"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE To the right welbeloued Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>AL that beare the name of Christians, &amp; seme<note place="margin">Man was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated apt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal glory.</note> to haue any Religion at al▪ doe agree in these three general pointes. First that God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">Gen. 1. v. 26. 1. Tim. 2. v. 4. Math. 7. v. 13. 14.</note> man <hi>to his owne image &amp; liknes,</hi> a reasonable cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, thereby made him apt to participate eternal glory. Secondly, that notwithstanding mans creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Moe are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then saued.</note> in so perfect estate, the greater part of mankinde falleth into eternal perdition. Because (as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour testifieth) <hi>Brode is the gate, and large is the way that leadeth to perdition, and many there be that enter by it. And narrow is the gate, &amp; strait is the way, that leadeth to life, &amp; few there are that finde it.</hi> And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the only way to saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> that true faith and Religion, is the onely way to<note place="margin">Heb. 11. v. 6.</note> life euerlasting. For <hi>without faith, it is impossible to please god.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>2 But the maine controuersy is, whether the Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane<note place="margin">Al Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly professing one Religion, Luther prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> Religion, commonly called Catholique, or rather some other, be the right way to saluation? Which question one Martin Luther, about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred<note place="margin">1517. See Art. 41.</note> yeares agoe, raised amongst Christians. For when he first began to preach his new doctrine, there was no publique pretence of any other Religion in the Christian world, but of that only which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome beleued and professed. Neither was<note place="margin">Which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer approued in England.</note> Luthers doctrine at any time approued in England, nor elswhere, saue only in a smale part of Germ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. And amongst many others, King Henry the 8. cōfuted him in a learned booke. For which, his great<note place="margin" type="runSum">1522.</note> zeale, he receaued of Pope Leo the Tenth, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed title (which his successors stil enioy) to be
<pb n="4" facs="2"/> called, <hi>Defender of the faith.</hi> But shortly after, when<note place="margin">The first bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach in England was King Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lus making him self head of the Church.</note> the same King Henry could not obtaine the Popes cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to put his wife Queene Catherin from him, and to marry an other, he, with aduise of certaine of his owne subiectes, Cranmer, Cromwel, &amp; some others, abandoning the Popes authoritie, made him self su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme<note place="margin" type="runSum">1533.</note> head of the Church of England, and Ireland, in al spiritual causes, mantayning stil in most other<note place="margin">After which, came in Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianisme in the time of King Edward.</note> pointes, the Romane Religion. Yet after his death, the Gouerners of his yong sonne, King Edward the Sixt, brought in the doctrine of Zuinglius; denying<note place="margin" type="runSum">1548.</note> the Real presence of Christ in the Sacrament (which Luther acknowledged) and diuers other new opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with a new forme of publique prayer. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, they laid also the Primacie of the Church, vpon the King a childe, scarse tenne yeares of age. Al which<note place="margin" type="runSum">1553.</note>
      <note place="margin">Queene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry restored Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Q. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated it againe.</note> Queene Marie reforming, restored the Catholique Religion. And shortly againe, Queene Elizabeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assuming<note place="margin" type="runSum">1559.</note> to her self, the spiritual supremacy (which noe others in the world graunt to Lay-men, much lesse to children, or women) abrogated the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Rites: and in place thereof, renewed the forme of common prayer, which is now in practise, much like to the former, but not in al pointes the same, which was in King Edwardes time.</p>
   <p>3 This being done by force &amp; power of the Queene,<note place="margin">Al the Bishops, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, M. Iuel chalenged to try true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not onlie by the holie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, but also by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers.</note>
      <note place="margin">Act. of Par. An. 1. Eliz.</note> and of such as consented thereto in Parlament: al the Bishoppes of the Realme, expresly disclaming frō it, not only al the same Bishoppes, but also many others, aswel of the Clergie, as Laitie, both in worde and fact, pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uering in the Catholique faith: one M. Iohn Iuel, preaching at S. Paules Crosse in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, with strange audacitie, challenged al Romane Catholiques in the world, to trie with him, by way of learning, the truth of Religion, now called into
<pb n="5" facs="2"/> controuersie: solemnly promising, that if anie of his aduersaries, should produce, any one sentence, or any one word, either of holie Scripture, or of authentical Councel, or Auncient Father, within the first sixe hundred yeares of Christ, geuing euident testimonie, for any one of sundry Articles of the Romane Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, there by him recited, that then he would recant his denial thereof, and subscribe to the Romane doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
   <p>4 Hereupon diuers learned Catholiques with great<note place="margin">He was so cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Harding, &amp; others, that his felowes say: his chalenge was too large.</note> speede, some in brefer, some in larger Treatises, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially Doctor Thomas Harding, in an ample work clearly proued the same Articles, by abundance of such irrefragable testimonies of holy Script. approued Councels, and auncient Fathers, as the chalenger had demanded: And therefore required him, according to his so publique promise, for his own soules health and others by him deluded, to recant his errors, &amp; to submit himself to the Catholique Church. But he Persisting wilful (though, manie of his folowers, by<note place="margin">The Lord Copley; Doctor Richard Steuens; M. Williā Reynolds. And others innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> Gods grace, vpon this occasion, became firme Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques) replied against Doctor Harding, and the rest, vsing such poore shiftes, fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olous euasions, and false sleightes, that his owne complices, namely Doctor Laurence Humfrey, in his Booke, <hi>de praxi Romanae Curiae,</hi> plainly confessed, that his Chalenge was incō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderate, ouer large, and could not be mantayned. And therefore our aduersaries euer since, generally<note place="margin">Generally our aduersaries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse al other tryal, but by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures only.</note> refuse to trie this cause by any other authorities, then by the only holie Scriptures. Neither wil they sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte them selues, to the Explications of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, nor yet stand to the expositions of their felow Protestantes, further then euery ones owne spirit liketh. For when they are pressed with any such, either they appeale to some other of their owne Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="6" facs="3"/> on whom they more relye, or if them selues pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to be learned, and be vrged with the Doctrine of others, they wil not stick to say, that whosoeuer doe teach otherwise then them selues, whether they be auncient, or late writers, doe mistake the holy Scriptures. Yea, if they be further charged, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, or those others doe erre, because they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch contrary doctrine, they say plainly, that al doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine which is contrary to theirs, is contrary to the holy Scriptures. And thē forsoth, doe they most friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously<note place="margin">The true ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is who best vnderstand the holy Script.</note> pretende, that we must beleue, the diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, before al humane iudgments: as though any Christian euer doubted therof, whereas the true que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is, not betwene the diuine Scriptures, and mens writinges, but which men doe best vnderstand &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the holy Scriptures? And in very deede, this is<note place="margin">Protestantes rely only, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally vpō ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</note> the proper difference betwixt our aduersaries and vs, touching this point, that they by the holy Scriptures <hi>only,</hi> we by the same <hi>principally,</hi> professe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed.</p>
   <p>5 Rightly then obseruing wherin the question con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth;<note place="margin">We agree to try Religion with our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, onely.</note> whosoeuer willearne the true sense of holy Scriptures, and therby know the true Religion, must resolue whether he wil vnderstand them as the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers did whom al later Catholique Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors doe follow; or as some new Doctors expound them. And then which new Doctors he wil preferr, Protestants, or Puritanes, or what others. Or els, (which is an other new way) without binding him self to one sort or other, he wil be his owne chooser, following which sense him self shal iudge best. To which newest maner of vnderstading gods word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause many in these daies, are so addicted, that they wil not yeld to any other, we condescend to ioyne this issue with them, to trye the true Religion, by the
<pb n="7" facs="3"/> only writen word of god, as each mans owne iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the grace which god wil geue him, shalbe able to discusse and vnderstand it.</p>
   <p>6 And this we doe, as willing to vse al possible means<note place="margin">Hoping that our endeuour wil be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to many; being necessary for the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for the more manifes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of truth.</note> to satisfie al: trusting, that as our endeuour semeth necessary for those which wil admitte none other kind of trial, and for their better information, which think that we preferre any other authoritie before the holy Scriptures: so it may be also profitable to many, as being expedient for the more manifestation of truth (which can neuer be too much knowen) &amp; must nedes be wel accepted of our aduersaries, who so continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prouoke vs to this onely trial; bearing the world in hand, that therein they haue great aduauntage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs. Here therfore, beloued aduersaries, to the more honour of god, and benefite of soules, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, that you and we may be the sooner accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to our mutual comforth, &amp; for the necessarie reduction vnto truth, of whosoeuer are presently in errour, we doe agree to encounter you, not onely <hi>principally,</hi> as we haue continually done, but also with the <hi>onely</hi> short and sharpe weapon of the sacred Textes<note place="margin">We require reasonable conditions.</note> of gods word, writen in the holy Bible of the old &amp; new Testament. Alwaies presupposing, that reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable conditions may be obserued on both parties, without preiudice to either of both.<note place="margin">First to be stil remēbred, that we do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, but abs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract frō other proofes. And therfore if our aduersaries wil vse others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs, they must admit the like against them selues.</note>
   </p>
   <p>7 As first of al, it is stil to be remembred, that albeit we thus condescend to encounter you, by only holy Scriptures; yet we doe not therby graunt your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of other proofes to be iust or lawful. For we doe hold it certaine, that al Christian Doctrine, can not be expresly, and withal immediatly proued by holy Scriptures only; &amp; that other proofes are both necessary, &amp; authentical, as we doe vndertake (in due<note place="margin">Article 3. 41. 42.</note> places of this work) to proue, by the expresse written
<pb n="8" facs="4"/> word of God. But we are content to abstract from them, with this prouiso for your good, that if your selues, vpon tryal of this proposed combate, shal find it necessary to vse other meanes, for proofe of some doctrine which you hold, and can not shew immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly by the holy Scriptures; or, if at least you shal think it needeful to repair to the aunciēt Expositors, for better vnderstanding the true sense of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; we wil be no lesse readie, to returne thereunto with you, then we are in the meane time content for your sakes to abstaine from them. And therefore we wil in this case agree, that you may if you can, either produce approued Traditions, Definitions of authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Councels, Popes Decrees, Vniforme consent of the auncient Fathers and Doctors, General practise of the visible knowen Church, or any other substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial proofe, &amp; that you may alledge the cleare iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Ecclesiastical Interpreters, of any holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture against vs; so that you wil allow vs to vse the same meanes, that each of vs may indifferently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our selues, and assault the others, with the same kindes of defensiue, and offensiue, armour and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</p>
   <p>8 In the meane while, so long as you wil needes try<note place="margin">2. Whiles our aduersaries wil admit noe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofe but onlie holie Scriptures; they must also be limited ther vnto.</note> this cause by the only holy Scriptures, we must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire this second condition, that seeing we refraine for your contentment, from other proofes; you must also be bound and limited to the same. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, it is vnreasonable, &amp; ouer partial dealing, that whatsoeuer you find in any authentical Councel, Popes decree, auncient Father, or Catholique Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, which may seeme to make for you, or against vs; should by and by, be taken for a wounding blow ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs, and neither the same, when it is rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed, nor the like, must touch you at al. Whiles
<pb n="9" facs="4"/> therefore you debarre vs from al other kindes of proofe, you must also containe your selues within the same listes of holie Scriptures onlie.</p>
   <p>9 Neuerthelesse, the third condition may be, if you<note place="margin">3. That it may in this combate suffice to either partie to proue the thing it self, though the word be not expressed in the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> please (for it wil be as needeful to you as to vs) that it may suffice in some special pointes of Christian Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, to proue the thinges them selues which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, by necessarie conclusions deduced from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Scriptures, though the verie wordes or termes be not there expressed: as the wordes <hi>Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> in the sense wherein we vse them, in professing our beleefe of three diuine persons in god. Also the consubstantialitie of the same persons. The perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Virginitie of the most B. Virgin Marie, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God. The name of Sacrament. And the like.<note place="margin">4. That the more obscure textes may be expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the more cleate.</note>
   </p>
   <p>10 The Fourth condition may likewise be, whereto we suppose you wil also accord, that producing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular textes, for proofe of particular pointes, sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the proper and vsual signification of the sacred wordes, weying the circumstances of persons, times, and places, with the occasion, intention, &amp; drift of the Author: we may so reguard gods holie worde, conferring text with text, that we admitte that to be the true doctrine, which shal be proued by the more euident wordes or sentences. For that in al reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable pleas, especially in religious causes, the more cleare textes, ought to illustrate the more obscure.</p>
   <p>In case also that anie wordes or passages, may seme cleare to one partie, and obscure to the other, then doth reason dictate, to reasonable persons, to the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of truth, and studious of concord, that the moe<note place="margin">Or the fewer, by the more in number, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that al are true.</note> places in number, being, or seming, of like perspicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, of obscuritie, may iustlie preuaile to expl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ate the fewer: Stil considering, that al and euerie parcel of holy Scripture, is absolutlie true, whether we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
<pb n="10" facs="5"/> it or no; al being indited by the holie Ghost, the Spirit of truth.</p>
   <p>11 Behold these are the conditions, which seme both<note place="margin">The holy Bible is set forth in English, and this booke is also written, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare which Religion is best grounded in holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> reasonable and requisite in this kinde of trial, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken for their contentment, that desire to be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, who amongst diuers pretenders of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are best groūded in the holie Scriptures. For whose sakes also, &amp; for this verie purpose, the whole sacred Bible faithfully translated into english, is late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set forth, with annotations, gathered especially out of the commentaries, and other writinges of the auncient Fathers, and Doctors of the Church.</p>
   <p>And now this work is compiled more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the diuine textes; agreable indeede, to the same holie Fathers sense and beleefe: but so connecting manie concordant places, pertayning to the same pointes of doctrine, though not al that might be brought (for that would be too immense) yet so much as may abundantly suffice, aswel for decision of the cheifest controuersies, of these times, as also for confirmation of most other principal articles, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine mist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ries of faith and Religion.<note place="margin">The Summe of al Christian doctrine is here proued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause manie pointes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Articles.</note>
   </p>
   <p>12 Our reasons, why in this maner, we proue the whole Catholique doctrine, not onlie in matters at this time in controuersie, but also in such others as haue bene in former ages, or may be in future, drawne into question, are especially these three. First because there is such connexion amongst manie partes of faith and Religion, that diuers which are or haue bene, called into controuersie, can not be sully declared, without presupposed knowledg of other groundes, whereon they depend. For example, it behoueth al men, first to beleue, that God is one in substance, and three in persons, before they can be wel instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that according to the Catholique faith, al the
<pb n="11" facs="5"/> three diuine persons, are consubstantial, and coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal. Likewise except we first confesse, that God is omnipotent, it wil be hard or impossible to beleue miracles. So we must beleue that there is a Church, els we can not know what proprieties, priuiledges, and power it haith. And so in many other contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies, it auaileth much, to see the proofes of that which is confessed, because by the same oftentimes, that which is denied, may either wholly, or in some part be proued, and explaned.</p>
   <p>13 Secondly we consider, that as we are presently<note place="margin">Secondlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause new er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors are stil deuised.</note> encombred with the controuersies raised by Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Zninglius, Cranmer, Caluin, Knox, Cartwright, and daily by new, and newer sectaries: so we may hereafter (we know not how soone) be put to proue, any other part of Christian Religion, not as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied. And therefore it shal be good, to see some groundes in the holy Scriptures, of al the principal pointes of our faith.</p>
   <p>14 Thirdly by this general proofe, of al Christian<note place="margin">Thirdly to shew that old heresies had as great pretence of holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as anie new doctrine now haith.</note> doctrine, the diligent Reader may see, that manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greatest misteries, which our present aduersaries acknowledg to be true and certaine, are as hard to be proued by expresse canonical Scripture, as any of those which they deny. Yea I dare auouch, that the holie Scriptures, doe more clearly shew, in plaine termes, the cheifest pointes of the Romane doctrine, denyed by Protestantes and Puritanes, then anie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse wordes doe declare, the true Catholique be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe against the Arians, Eunomians, Nouatians, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians, and the like. As therefore diuers auncient Fathers and Doctors, haue, not onlie confuted the aduersaries of truth, liuing in their owne time, and passed before them, but likewise haue taught, and explicated the residue of Christian Religion: so we,
<pb n="12" facs="6"/> according to our smalest talent, by gods gracious helpe, intende to make this summarie proofe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion, &amp; that by the only writen word of God, as a most firme and sacred Anker of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrine, against al impugners thereof, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing other Proofes, yet acknowledg the eminent authority of the holy Scriptures.</p>
   <p>15 For better ordering the whole work, we deuide<note place="margin">We folow the method of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techismus ad Parachos. Diuiding the whole worke into four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and euerie part into spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Articles.</note> it into four partes, and euerie part, into manie parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Articles: after the method of the most authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Catechisme, directed to al Pastors of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world, by the special ordinance of the late holy Councel of Trent.</p>
   <p>In the first part, are contayned manie special Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith, which are breefly comprised in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Crede. In the second are proued, and explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the seauen holie Sacraments; with the dread Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Catholique Church, instituted by Christ. In the third are declared, the ten Commaundements of God. And in the fourth part is shewed, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie and efficacie of praier, especially of our Lords praier, called the <hi>Pater noster.</hi> And also of praiers publique and priuate.</p>
   <p>16 And so to end this Preface as I began, I heartely<note place="margin">Two verie necessarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations.</note> wish al you that desire to be more confirmed in the way of saluation: and againe I besech you for gods more glory, &amp; your owne soules health, wel to pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theese two pointes. First, that our immortal<note place="margin">Al of mankind must either be saued, or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eternally.</note>
      <note place="margin">Math. 25. v. 32. Rom. 14. v. 10.</note> soules, after our temporal death, and our bodies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, at the general Resurrection, must either be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally glorified with al the blessed Angels and other Sainctes in vnspeakable ioyes in the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: or els eternally damned with the deuils, and al the reprobate in vtter darknesse, and inexplicable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orments. Secondly, that as the way to this intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable<note place="margin">The entrance,</note>
      <pb n="13" facs="6"/> euerlasting miserie, is large, the gate is<note place="margin">Math. 7. v. 13. 14. Luc. 13. v. 23. 24.</note>
      <note place="margin">progresse, and arriual to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, is only by true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> wyde, and manie doe enter into it: and the way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal felicitie, is narrow, the gate is straite, and few doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inde it: Euen so, the entrance into the right way is by true faith and Religion: the progresse therein, is by such meanes as true Religion teacheth vs; and the arriual vnto eternal life, is by perseuering to the end in that due seruice of god, which true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion<note place="margin">Which of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> treasures, is most precious.</note> requireth. This true religion, is the hidden<note place="margin">Math 13. v. 44. 45. Is. 64. v. 4. 1. Cor. 2. v, 9. Math. 10. v. 37. Luc. 14. v. 33. Deut. 32. v. 18. Prou. 5. v. 9. Rom. 8. v. 17.</note> treasure which, when you finde, you wil be glad. This is the precious Margarite to be desired of al mē. This wil bring vs to those celestial ioyes, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mortal eye haith seene, nor eare haith heard, nor heart of man can conceiue. For true Religion therfore, we must principallie imploy our selues, our most diligent studies, our best laboures, and al that we haue. And euer be readie in preparation of mind, rather to lose temporal goodes, landes, libertie, and life, then to leau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the right way of eternal life. That being made to the image of god, we be not iniurious to our Maker, nor cruel to our owne soules: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, procede, and perseuer, to serue God rightly. So shal we be heyres of God, and felow-heyres of Christ in his Kingdome which haith none end▪ To him be al glorie for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer in Christ our Lord, Th. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>