<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ANSWER TO THE ADVERTISEMENT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr40_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ANSWER TO THE ADVERTISEMENT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="response">
   <pb n="716" facs="375"/>
   <head>THE ANSWER TO THE ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE man begins with a threat; I may not but tremble; Hee frights me with an vniuersall Detection of my errors. It is almost as easie to finde faults, as to make them. Perhaps the Time had been as well spent in tossing of his Beads: How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie a man am I that shall see all my ouer-sights? My com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that if my Tree were fruitlesse, there would bee no stone throwne at it. In the meane while, how well doth the title of a Detector become him that hides himselfe? If hee be not afraid or ashamed of his cause, let his name bee knowne, that his victories may be recorded. It is an iniurious and base aduantage to strike and hide; and after a pitcht Duell to gall a fixed Aduersarie out of loope-holes. If his person be vpon some treasonable act obnoxious, it is hard if some of his names be not free: But if I must needs be matcht with the shadow of a Libeller, I wil so take him, as he deciphers himselfe: <hi>C. E. Cauillator Egregius;</hi> and vnder this true stile of his, am ready to encounter him, and doe here bid Defiance to an insolent, and vniust aduersarie: And first, let me tell my Cauiller, this order is preposterous. If all my er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors be at the mouth of the Presse, how is it that two or three of them are thus suffered to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne their fellowes? Was his malice so bigge with these, that it could not stay the time of the common deliuerie? Needs must they be notorious falshoods, that are thus singled out from the rest. Let them appeare in their owne shapes, vgly, (doubtlesse) and prodigious. The first is,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ex Decad. Ep.</hi> 3. <hi>Epist</hi> 5. Reckoned out of <hi>Pappus</hi> his Enumeration; My peace of <hi>Rome</hi> makes vp 103.</note>
      <hi>That most shamelesse assertion that</hi> Bellarmine <hi>vnder his owne hand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, 237. Contrarieties of Doctrine amongst his Catholikes.</hi> Could the man but haue patience, he should finde aboue three hundred: What sayes my Detector to this? He hath not seene the seuerals, yet (like a braue man at Armes) he professes to kill his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ere he can appeare; and tels vs those <hi>237</hi> Contrarieties, are nothing but <hi>237</hi> lyes in one assertion. That there are in them so many vntruths I easily grant; for in Contradictions one part must needs be false; And Truth is but single: They are vntruths then, (lyes are too broad a word) but their owne. My assertion shall onely iustifie that they are told; let him take care for the rest:<label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
      </label>
      <hi>But they are not in points belonging to Faith and Religion, only in matters vndecided, and disputable:</hi> The sequell shall try that shift; Why doe wee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stall our Reader?<note place="margin">Sol.</note> Who knowes not that there cannot be so many points fundamentall? Let him take them as they are, I aggrauate nothing; It is but onely in such light chaffe, as this; In the number and extent of Bookes Canonicall, wherein <hi>Driedo, Erasmus, Genebrard, Caietan, Sixtus Senensis,</hi> are acknowledged to oppose the rest; In the Popes infallibilitie of iudgement, wherein <hi>Gerson, Almayne,</hi> Pope <hi>Adrian, Eckius, Hosius, Pichius, Waldensis,</hi> are at quarrell; In the reach and originall of spirituall iurisdiction, wherein <hi>Abulensis, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recremata, Fran. à Victoria, Alphonsus de Castro, &amp;c.</hi> proclaime to differ: what should I instance in more? It is but in the Popes power in Temporalities, in the inerrablenesse of Councels, whether particular, confirmed by the Pope, or Generall; in the authoritie of Councels aboue Popes, in the force of Vowes, in the worship due to Images, and the like.
<pb n="717" facs="375"/> These and such other are the slight Trifles (since all cannot be weightie) impertinent to faith, wherein the Romish Doctors varie.</p>
   <p>Neither doth my assertion of their discord gall him more, then of our Vnity: O the forehead of Heretikes! I said that we in our Church differ onely in Ceremonies, they in substance. Let him giue leaue to the <hi>contra-diuision</hi> of these two, and I will take leaue to maintaine the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuision</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the dogmaticall points of Faith.</p>
   <p>This boldnesse, together with my eminent ignorance, makes him admire the scarcitie of learned men in our Countrey, that could finde no better Doctors to send to <hi>Dort</hi>-Conference then Master <hi>HALL.</hi> To your griefe, Sir, it was a Synode, and that noble and celebrious; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it out of want that your silly Aduersarie was sent thither. This happy Iland (which hath no blemish but that it yeelds such Vipers as your selfe) abounds (as you too well know) with store of incomparable Diuines; such as may set your <hi>Rome</hi> to schoole. So as the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger of <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> long since called your <hi>Italy,</hi> a Countrey of Kings,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and <hi>Egypt</hi> was wont to be called the Countrey of Physicians: so may this blessed Iland of ours iustly merit the title of <hi>The Region of DIVINES.</hi> For me, I can bee content to bee base enough in mine owne eyes, but if my disparagement shall redound to my betters, I dare tell him it is my comfort, that I was sent thither by a iudgement no lesse infallible, then of <hi>Paul</hi> the Fift. Let himselfe or any of his Eaues-dropping companions (to whom that place stood open) say wherein I shamed those that sent me. It was my iust griefe that the necessitie of my health,<note place="margin">Necessitate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellente proditie est ea tacere quae quis flu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>e perfecerit. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sost. in ill.: vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam toter assetis, &amp;c.</note> yea of my life, called me off immaturely: but since either death or departure must be yeelded to, others shall iudge whether I went away more laden with infirmitie, then (how-euer vnworthy) with approbation.</p>
   <p>But that second lye of mine is so loud, that all my Brethren of <hi>Dort</hi> must heare it, and they which were lately the Witnesses of my sinceritie (gracing mee with the deare Testimonie of their approofe) are now made the Iudges of my impudencie. What monster of falshood will come forth? <hi>In my censure of Trauell, glancing at the Iesuiticall bragge of their Indian Miracles</hi> (whereat their very friends make sport) <hi>I charge Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine <hi>for an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoucher of these Cozenages, who dares auerre that his fellow</hi> Xauier, <hi>not onely healed the Deafe, Dumbe, and Blinde, but raised the Dead, to which I adde (whiles his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Acosta, <hi>after many yeares spent in those parts, can pull him by the sleeue, and tell him in his eare, so loud that all the World may heare,</hi> Prodigia nulla producimus.) This is my Indictment; Let me come to my Tryall: Cast me, if ye can, ye reuerend heads; I craue no fauour. Where lyes this so lewd lye, and malicious abuse? That <hi>Bellarmine</hi> sayes thus of the Iesuite <hi>Xauier,</hi> is not denyed; That <hi>Acosta</hi> sayes thus of himselfe, and his fellow Iesuites, is granted; The first lye yet is, <hi>Acosta</hi> was neuer in the <hi>East-Indies</hi> at all, nor <hi>Xauier</hi> in the <hi>West;</hi> and how then could <hi>Acosta</hi> spend many yeares in those parts? A perilous Plea! Who euer, I beseech you, mentioned either <hi>East</hi> or <hi>West?</hi> I spake of the <hi>Indies</hi> in common;<note place="margin">Bell de notis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> so did his <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> from whom I cited this, <hi>Claruit etiam in Indiis omni genere miraculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp;c.</hi> Here is not one of the <hi>Indies</hi> mentioned, but both or either; If both liued in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> though not in one Towne, in one Country, in one <hi>Indie;</hi> wherein haue I offended; whiles speaking of the <hi>Indies</hi> in generall, I said that <hi>Xauier</hi> and <hi>Acosta</hi> liued there? Yet this is one lye (he saith) and that so long a one, as that it reacheth as farre as it is from the <hi>East</hi> to the <hi>West,</hi> from the <hi>Artick</hi> to the <hi>Antarctick Pole;</hi> wherein I doubt not but your reuerences wil easily marke the skill of this learned Cosmographer. Some parts of those instanced <hi>Indies</hi> differ not so farre; not to speake of the small strait of <hi>Anian;</hi> the mentioned Region of <hi>Mexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi> is not aboue fourescore degrees from <hi>Iapan:</hi> Either your construction must fauour him, or else this must goe into the Booke of ouer-sights.</p>
   <p>The second lye is, that <hi>Acosta</hi> pulled <hi>Bellarmine</hi> by the sleeue in this assertion, as if hee denyed those <hi>Easterne</hi> Miracles, which he elsewhere confesseth. Indeed, this sawcinesse were dangerous: The red Hat (you say) is fellow to a Crowne. But shall I confesse where I erred? My dull head could not conceiue that God should be the God of the Mountains, and not of the Valleys; Of the <hi>East Indies,</hi> not of the <hi>West;</hi> and yet be the Iesuites God in both: Especially, since the reason that <hi>Ioseph Acosta</hi> fetches from the persons (which should be the subiect of those Wonders) holds as equally for both <hi>Indies,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ios. Acosta l <hi>2.</hi> de s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l. Ind. c. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note> as an Almanack made for the Meridian of one Citie, serueth the Neighbours.</p>
   <pb n="718" facs="376"/>
   <p>Hitherto then the Prologue of my infamous falshoods, such, as if all my Writings could haue afforded any equally hainous, these had neuer beene chosen out to grace the front of his Detection; There must needs be much terrour in the sequel.</p>
   <p>The rest of this storme fals vpon our learned Professor, <hi>D. Collins;</hi> one of the prime or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of our <hi>Cambridge;</hi> the partnership of whose vniust disgrace doth not a little hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten my vnworthinesse. The world knowes the eminency of that mans Learning, Wit, Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Eloquence; His workes praise him enough in the Gate; Yet this Malapert Corner-creeper doth so basely vilifie him, for ignorance, fillinesse, pratling, rusticitie, lying, as if in these onely he were matchlesse. Indeed whom doth the aspersion of that foule hand forbeare? <hi>Vilium est hominum alios viles facere?</hi> I appeale to all the Tribunals of Learning tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the World, whether all <hi>Doway</hi> haue yeelded ought comparable to that mans Pen: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he haue not so<note n="*" place="margin">This Booke of Doctor <hi>Coll. C. E</hi> falsly insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth to haue bin suppressed. All Stationers shops can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince him of a lye: Nothing euer fell from that learned hand, without applause.</note> coniured downe his <hi>Caco-Daemon Ioannes,</hi> that he neuer dares to look backe into the light againe; whether his <hi>Ephatha</hi> be not so powerfull, that if his Aduersarie were any otherwise deafe then the blocke which hee worships, it might open his eare to the Truth. It angers <hi>C.E.</hi> to heare that Kings should not dye, or perhaps, that they whose heads are anointed, should dye by any other then anointed fingers; The sentence of his Cardinall and Iesuites both <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>de jure,</hi> of deposing and murdering Kings, is now beside our way; Onely we may reade afarre off in capitall Letters, <hi>Arise,</hi> Peter, <hi>kill and eate:</hi> Hee knowes the word, with shame enough. I will not so much wrong that worthy Prouost, as to anticipate his quarrell; rather I leaue the superfluitie of this malice to the scourge of that abler hand; from whom I doubt not but <hi>C. E.</hi> shall smart and bleed so well, that he may spare the labour of making himselfe his owne Whipping-stocke on Good-Friday.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>