<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Honorable Syr Henry Sidney, Lorde President of her Maiesties Counsel in the Marches of VVales, Knight of the moste noble order of the Garter, and of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell: VV. H. wisheth plentie of those blessings which haue promises of this life and the life to come.</title>
           <author>Hopkinson, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120355_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03645</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13774</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120355</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Honorable Syr Henry Sidney, Lorde President of her Maiesties Counsel in the Marches of VVales, Knight of the moste noble order of the Garter, and of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell: VV. H. wisheth plentie of those blessings which haue promises of this life and the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Hopkinson, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preparation into the waye of lyfe : vvith a direction into the right vse of the Lords Supper: gathered by VVilliam Hopkinson, preacher of the worde of God</title>
                 <author>Hopkinson, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <distributor>Harrison, John 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ <hi>To the right Honorable</hi> Syr Henry Sidney, Lorde President of <hi>her Maiesties Counsel in the Marches</hi> of VVales, Knight of the moste noble order of the Garter, and of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell: VV. H. wisheth plentie of those blessings which haue promises of this life and the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that it is the duetie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery true Christian (Righte Honorable) from the highest to the lowest, according to the measure of the grace that he hath receyued of the Lord, to reache out him selfe vvith continuall attendance to profite euery his felowe neighbour, especially in the charge ouer vvhiche the Lorde hath set him for the tyme, so labouring in him selfe to exceede the measure of the moste, vvho make muche of lyfe vvithout consideration vvherefore they liue: I haue held my selfe boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb facs="3"/>by all meanes that I might, to endeuour the regarde of those ouer vvhom the Lorde by your Honour hath set me. And seeing that not onely the iudgement of reason, but continuall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth teache vs, that to make a scholler lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the tongues, the readyest vvay is, to begin vvith the letters, or vvell profited in any Science, to set first a sure foundation in the principles of the same, I haue helde it the moste ready en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce to make the Lordes trueth familiar to his people, especially them of vvhom I haue speciall knowledge, and ouer vvhom peculiar charge, to laye the groundworke as sure as I might, namely in leading them in the light of the Lords vvorde, to the true sight of them selues in two respectes, that is, vvhat they are by nature, and vvhat by grace, vvherof if eyther be vvanting in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Christians, the Lorde looseth (in respect of him) his due glory, and the people their sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. As if the first be not knowen, men receiue the Lordes promises in securitie, as vvhich num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at this day seemeth to be great, and if the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond be not had, mens hearts are surprised in the vvaye of death. And as he that buyldeth without a foundation layde, shall buylde in the ayrc, so this steddie groundworke surely founded, &amp; vvell beat vpon, shall giue an easie entraunce to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buylding by the vvord of doctrine and faith, that the Lordes Saintes by this meanes maye through his grace not onely be gathered, as the Apostle sayth, but that through the vvorke of the ministery they may be built vp into him vvhich
<pb facs="3"/>is the head, euen Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>And for this cause I haue, as I might, gathered these directions by the Lords vvorde, for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall testimony to remayne vvith thē, a consent to suche as turne to the Lorde, and for a vvitnesse to the rest. But especially (next vnto this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation layde) haue I laboured to leade them into the right vse of the Lords Supper, a speciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Gods promises in Christ to our cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, a matter also miserably neglected and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accounted of, to the lamentable ruine and downefall of many thousande soules, for the Lordes iudgementes stande inuiolably: vvhose vvorkes doth testifie that they are iustly in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his endles indignation, vvho prophane his misteries in vnworthines, of vvhat condition or sort soeuer they be, for vvith him is no respect of persons. In both vvhich I haue ioyned the desire of mine owne discharge, vvith the peoples safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and gathered the summe of both into suche a forme, as may best agree vvith their experience: not as refusing or lightly accouting of the labors of such godly brethren as haue much profited the Lords people in the lyke vvay, but as casting in two mytes vvith the poore VVidow to the Lotds vvorke, vvhich as it vvas specially ment for mine owne charge, so haue I yeelded to the perswasion of certayne godly friendes, to communicate the same vvith the Church of God by suffering it to be published in print, both for the comfort of the godly, the Lorde blessing it: and testifie to the Papistes the Lordes enimies, that though the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of speach be diuers, yet that vvee holde
<pb facs="4"/>firmely one and the selfe same grounde and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of trueth, and that there is not amongst vs at all any oddes or varietie of doctrine, vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they and their lyke, shame not vniustly to say agaynst vs.</p>
   <p>But in this case considering that it must vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe the viewe aswell of foes as fauourers, &amp; that as I am assured of fauourable acceptation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the godly, yet as the sunne neuer vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth light, the fyre heate, or the srostie vvynter coldnes: so haue there euer bene, and vvyll be, plentie of such vvho in steade of vvell deseruing, do please them selues vvith vniust reproching of others labours. In this respect, as that I might content my selfe, in accepting gladly any iust oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to leaue some testimonie of a right thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart for your Honours fauours many wayes vouchsafed me, vvhereby I holde my selfe in the Lorde continually bounde to your Honorable house in all that I maye, and in consideration vvherof, vvhen other meanes be vvanting wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to testifie the same, I shall not cease (I truste) right humbly to commende your estate vnto the Lorde, vvho hath promised to heare the iuste prayers of his seruauntes for the vvorthines of his Christ: So haue I bene bolde to present the same vnto your Honour, such as it is, the rather hauing iust cause to perswade my selfe of your honorable acceptation and protection of vvhatsoeuer may profite the Church of God, I haue also together deliuered to the print, for the care I haue of my brethrens health, a most notable and christian cōfortable letter, vvritten by that notable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="4"/>of the Church of God in his time, M. Edward Dering, to a godly christiā gētlewomā, by which through the Lordes blessing I must needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to haue gayned muche comfort, as also mine hartie desire and hope is that others shall. So that vvhile the vncleane and impure Atheistes, frozen harted Papistes, temporisers, carnall Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, and infidels, shall suppe out the measure of Gods iudgementes to the bottome, vve, vvell vvarranted in our Christian estate, soundly dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the right vse of the Lordes mysteries, by the vvorde preserued in the extremities of sinne, and in all, lightned to the right application of the grace of Christ, shall vvith inuincible constancie runne out the course that is set before vs, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently vvayte for our deliueraunce, euen the comming of our Lorde Iesus Christ, of vvhom it is vvritten that he shall appeare the seconde time vvithout sinne to saluation, to them that vvayte for him. VVhich that vve maye conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually do, our good God and Father graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by the speciall direction of his holy spirite of sanctification and grace, and powre plentifully vpon your Honour those blessings vvhich speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye concerne the aduauncement of his glory, your Honours safetie both in body and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the peace of his Church, in and for his sonne our Lorde Iesus. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most humbly to be alwayes vsed in the Lorde Christe, VVILLIAM HOPKINSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>