<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Barlow, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120873_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04269</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1439.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120873</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Barlow, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A seasonable discourse of spirituall stedfastnesse : wherein, 1. it, and a relapse, with the heads, members, and degrees of both, are exactly defined. 2. The subiects, causes, and symptomes of the fearfull sinne of apostasie cleerely expressed. As also directions, incentiues, to recouer, re-inkindle the old-cold-declining zelot. Together with arguments, motiues, that the young, or strong standing convert may be in grace firmely established. By I.B. preacher of the word</title>
                 <author>Barlow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 265, that is 266, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Prediction,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1. &amp;c.</note>) <hi>we live</hi> in perillous times; <hi>the last, and worst age of the world. For are not men</hi> Lovers of themselves? Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteous? Boasters? Proud? And what not? <hi>Who can number the</hi> dust <hi>of</hi> Atheists? Papists? He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks? Hipocrits? <hi>Or measure the</hi> spatious Gloabe of meere For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malists? Selfe-condemned Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stats? <hi>Have we not a</hi> Viperous generation <hi>among vs, who professe themselves to be of the</hi> damned Crew? <hi>Will sweare</hi> for a wager? <hi>Drinke health's</hi> to the Devill? <hi>And account it their</hi> Grace, <hi>to be</hi> reputed gracelesse? <hi>Crying, in the</hi> Epicure an language, <hi>Let vs</hi> eate,
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>and</hi> drinke:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.32.</note> for to morrow we shall dye? <hi>And is not the heavie hand of our</hi> God, <hi>gone</hi> out against vs? <hi>How many</hi> worthy men (<hi>some whereof our</hi> English forrest <hi>brought foorth) in</hi> Germanie, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, <hi>And the</hi> Palatinate, <hi>are fallen vpon the</hi> sword? <hi>And have spilt their</hi> bloud, <hi>like water,</hi> on the ground? <hi>Who can</hi> tyth <hi>the</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, <hi>or</hi> tell <hi>the tenth part of</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlesse children, <hi>that fold their</hi> armes, <hi>wring their</hi> hands, <hi>And shed</hi> teares, <hi>because the</hi> Enemie hath possessed the Land? <hi>Is not their</hi> fathers house, <hi>at</hi> Prage, Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg,<note place="margin">Math. 21.13.</note>
      <hi>And</hi> Bre-da, made a denne of Theeves? <hi>Hath not that</hi> noble Prince, <hi>And</hi> right noble Princesse Palatine, <hi>bin pursued as</hi> David <hi>before</hi> Saul, <hi>of the</hi> vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised Philistines? <hi>Carried their lives in their</hi> hands, <hi>And many a time constrained, to refresh their fainting</hi> spirits, <hi>to put their</hi> royall feet, <hi>vnder the Table of some</hi> Churlish Naball? <hi>And (ah
<pb facs="7"/> my brethren!) is there yet a</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet gone out, <hi>to declare</hi> when these things shall have an end? <hi>But because this dolefull</hi> obiect <hi>is more remote; therefore (though it should not) the lesse lamented, Let vs draw neerer home. And take a view of our owne</hi> Nation. <hi>Hath not</hi> Death cruell death, <hi>haunted the</hi> Court, Citie, Countrey? <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our</hi> King? <hi>Slaine our</hi> Nobles? <hi>And turned into small dust, sixtie-six-thausand of the</hi> common sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects? <hi>Call for the</hi> aged, <hi>and let them (if they can) tell when so many in so short a revolution of time, haue</hi> vealed the head, <hi>And</hi> given vp the Ghost? <hi>But what effect hath followed this</hi> dreadfull mortalitie? <hi>Is not</hi> England (London especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,) <hi>as</hi> proud, covetous, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaine, <hi>And</hi> secure as ever? <hi>I doubt not but that some have laid these iudgements to heart, brought</hi> foorth fruite, worthie amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life:<note place="margin">Math 3.8</note>
      <hi>But as the</hi> Disciples <hi>sayd of the</hi> five loaves <hi>and</hi> two
<pb facs="8"/> fishes, what are they amonge so many? <hi>Alas! Alas! The</hi> dead carkesses <hi>of</hi> neighbours, kindred, friends, <hi>like rotten</hi> dung <hi>spread on the earth, have caused the</hi> seeds of wickednesse, <hi>in the lives of a huge multitude, but to</hi> shoot vp, <hi>&amp;</hi> grow the faster. <hi>What then shall we, can we expect (without a change)</hi> to be the end? <hi>For will not</hi> God take vengeance on such a people as this.<note place="margin">Zeph. 2.2.</note>
      <hi>You therefore</hi> (before the decree come foorth,) <hi>Who make profession, like</hi> Moses <hi>stand in the gappe, pitition the</hi> Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, <hi>And the</hi> God of all consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>not to enter</hi> into iudgement, with this sinfull generation: <hi>but to put the</hi> evill day farre from vs. Pray <hi>for the</hi> life <hi>of our</hi> King, <hi>the</hi> peace of our Land; <hi>And the</hi> continuance of the Gospell, to <hi>vs</hi> and <hi>our posteritie</hi> from <hi>generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation. Cry in the eares of</hi> the Lord of hoasts, <hi>to powre downe the</hi> Spirit of wisdome <hi>and</hi> resolution vpon his own annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>that he may</hi> guide the great people <hi>committed to his charge,</hi> in the way of truth; <hi>be the</hi> ioy of all his chosen, <hi>and</hi> a terror to all his enemies. <hi>That the</hi> Sun <hi>of that morning may</hi> never rise, <hi>or that</hi> day <hi>numbred to the</hi> Monthes of the yeere, <hi>when it shall be sayd, the</hi> Adversary <hi>hath</hi> invaded the land; <hi>the</hi> Arke of God is gone <hi>from our</hi> English Israel. <hi>If we sit secure, take heede of</hi> a Spanish whip, a Catholike scourge <hi>For what pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge have we,</hi> Iudah, Ierusalem; <hi>And our</hi> Neighbour kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s <hi>have not inioyed? Why then may we not feare the</hi> like correction? <hi>Chiefly, if we lye in the</hi> same sinnes? <hi>Now that you may be</hi> prevented of <hi>or</hi> prepared <hi>for the</hi> invasion of <hi>Foes,</hi> fiering of Beacons, roaring of Cannons, sacking of Cities, ravishing of wives, deflouring of virgins, tossing infants on Pikes, rending of members a sunder, <hi>and</hi> resisting vnto bloud,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.37</note>
      <hi>Consider what</hi> I have sayd, <hi>And</hi> write in
<pb facs="9"/> this short succeeding Tractat.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.37</note>
      <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Counsell to vndergoe the</hi> harsh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est torments to flesh and bloud, <hi>than I have in these few lines,</hi> I cannot give thee. <hi>Read them</hi> for thy selfe, <hi>Pray</hi> for me. <hi>And the rather, in that thou little knowest,</hi> how short a time thou hast.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus: <hi>Iohn Barlow.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>February</hi> 23. 1626.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>