<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very deare friends Sir LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall in the County of Norfolke Knight Baronet, and Lady FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT his most louing Bed-fellow, HENRY GREENVVOOD Wisheth all increase of Grace in this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.</title>
           <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120478_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02192</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120478</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very deare friends Sir LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall in the County of Norfolke Knight Baronet, and Lady FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT his most louing Bed-fellow, HENRY GREENVVOOD Wisheth all increase of Grace in this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tormenting Tophet: or A terrible description of Hel : able to breake the hardest heart, and cause it quake and tremble. Preached at Paules Crosse the 14. of Iune 1614. By Henry Greenvvood, Master of Arts, and preacher of the word of God</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bell, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 82, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very deare friends Sir LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall in the County of <hi>Norfolke</hi> Knight Baronet, <hi>and Lady</hi> FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT <hi>his most louing Bed</hi>-fellow, HENRY GREENVVOOD Wisheth all increase of Grace in <hi>this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is, and hath beene long since (Right Worshipful) the custome of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to publike view (therein ayming at cōmon good) their Christian paines and diuine indeuours,
<pb facs="3"/>
(knowing that the truth hath, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had many oppositions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions) to present them to men of high place, and well affected in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that so their works might passe with lesse feare, and danger of disgrace and opprobrie: I (though vnlearned) making bold to imitate their Christian policy herein, haue presumed to present that doctrine to your <hi>Worships</hi> eies, that lately in publike place was sounded in your eares, both of which senses are great Instruments in the furtherance of our soules in the way of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for as the eare conueieth grace to the affections of the soule, so the eye bringeth much matter to the vnderstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the mind; nay, the eare cannot so often be an Auditor, as the eye an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour to the conscience.</p>
   <p>For which cause (your Worships no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more affecting than growth in Grace and Religion) I haue attempted to commend to your often considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Tormenting Tophet,</hi> for as nothing allureth the heart to grace, more than Gods mercies, so nothing more preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="3"/>
against sinne, than his fearefull and terrible iudgements.</p>
   <p>If therfore your gracious Worships shall vouchsafe to accept of these my poore presented paines, it will giue content to mine own heart, and (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les) answerable comfort to your owne soules.</p>
   <p>And to conclude, as the Lord hath abundantly blessed your <hi>Worships</hi> with graces internall, and blessings external; So (to vse the words of the Apostle) <hi>the very God of peace sanctifie you still through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and I pray God that your whole spirits, and soules and bodies, may be kept blameles to the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. From Hempsted in Essex, Aprill,</hi> 3. 1615.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships alwayes ready to bee commaunded in the Lord, HEN. GREENVVOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>