<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults escaped.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120442_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16567</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3473</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120442</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults escaped.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of that most ancient and sacred ordinance of Gods, the Sabbath day : Consequently, and together with it. 2. A defence of the iiijth commandement. 3. A defence of the integrity and perfection of the Decalogue, morall law, or X. commandements. 4. A defence also of the whole and intire worship of God, in all the partes thereof, as it is prescribed, in the first table of the Decalogue. 5. A discouery of the superstition, impurity and corruption of Gods worship; yea, and idolatry, committed by multitudes, in sanctifying the Lords day, for a Sabbath day, by the iiijth commandement. Vndertaken against all anti-Sabbatharians, both of Protestants, Papists, Antinomians, and Anabaptists; and by name and especially against the X ministers, ... by Theophilus Brabourne</title>
                 <author>Brabourne, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 633, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="335"/>
   <head>Faults escaped.</head>
   <p>In pag. 51. lin. 9. <hi>for</hi> reuerence, <hi>read</hi> reference. pag. 103. lin. 2. <hi>for</hi> preformed, <hi>read</hi> reformed. pag. 165. lin. 5. <hi>for</hi> denegerated, <hi>read</hi> degenerated. pag. 331. lin. 6. <hi>for</hi> contraicted, <hi>read</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted. pag. 421. lin. 22. <hi>for</hi> eparate, <hi>read</hi> separate. pag. 475. lin. 2. the text Rom. 15.1. there cited, with ij lines before it, I iudge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soundly applied. pag. 582. lin. 36. <hi>for</hi> subiect and Magistrate, <hi>read</hi> seruant and Master. As for other faults, as mise-pointing of senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and mis-placing, lacke or superfluity of a letter here and there, the intelligent Reader may easily correct them.</p>
   <pb facs="335"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>