<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A. D. §. 1.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120318_Bo1_1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15739</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26009</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120318</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A. D. §. 1.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trial of the Romish clergies title to the Church : by way of answer to a popish pamphlet written by one A.D. and entituled A treatise of faith, wherein is briefly and plainly shewed a direct way, by which euery man may resolue and settle his mind in all doubts, question and controuersies, concerning matters of faith. By Antonie Wotton. In the end you haue three tables: one of the texts of Scripture expounded or alledged in this booke: another of the testimonies of ancient and later writers, with a chronologie of the times in which they liued: a third of the chief matters contained in the treatise and answer</title>
                 <author>Wotton, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Burby, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tymme (Timme), William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 420, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="quoted_front_matter">
   <div n="§ 1" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 1.</head>
      <p>A TREATISE OF FAITH, WHEREIN IS BRIEFLY AND <hi>PLAINLY SHEWED, A DIRECT WAY, by which euery man may resolue, &amp; settle his mind, in all doubts, questions, or controuersies, concerning matters of Faith.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Title is like the Apothecaries boxes &amp; pots; which promise goodly matters by the inscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but within haue either nothing, or some ordinarie drugs. <hi>A treatise of faith, shewing a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect way, by which euery man may resolue, and settle his mind, in all doubts, questions, or controuersies, concerning mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith:</hi> makes shew of instructing him, that shall reade it, what faith is, what kinds of faith there are; and (aboue all) what a iustifying faith is; how to be attained vnto; how vsed, to the obtaining of euerlasting life. These principally, and many more like these are required in a Treatise of faith; of neuer a one whereof there is any one Chapter, or peece of a Chapter, in this whole Discourse.</p>
      <p>Neither hath he done that litle he hath done, either briefly; as the heaping vp of vnnecessarie testimonies, in matters not doubtfull, in the verie first Chapter, euidently proues; or plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; because, though in his Preface he sets down what he meanes to proue, yet it is verie hard for a man to apply his seuerall Chapters to the generall matter propounded by him, as the handling of them will shew.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 2" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 2.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>A Table or briefe summary of the whole treatise.</hi>
      </p>
      <list>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 1.</label>
            <hi>That faith is absolutely necessary to saluation.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 2.</label>
            <hi>That this faith is but one.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 3.</label>
            <hi>That this one faith must be infallible.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 4.</label>
            <hi>That this one infallible faith must be entire.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 5.</label>
            <hi>That Almighty God hath prouided some sufficient meanes</hi>
            <pb n="2" facs="5"/>
            <hi>whereby all sorts of men, may at all times, learne this one infallible, and entire faith.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 6.</label>
            <hi>What conditions or properties are requisite, in this rule or meanes, prouided by Almighty God.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 7.</label>
            <hi>That Scripture alone, cannot be this rule or meanes.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 8.</label>
            <hi>That no naturall wit of man, or humane learning, either by interpreting Scripture or otherwise, can be this rule of faith.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 9.</label>
            <hi>That priuate spirit cannot be this rule.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 10.</label>
            <hi>That the doctrine or teaching of the true Church of Christ, is the rule or meanes, wherby all men must learne the true faith.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 11.</label>
            <hi>That this true Church of Christ, of which we must learne the true faith, is alwayes to continue, without interruption, vntill the worlds end.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 12.</label>
            <hi>That this same Church must alwayes be visible.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 13.</label>
            <hi>How we should discerne or know, which company of men is this true visible Church, of which we must learne true faith.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 14.</label>
            <hi>That those Notes or markes which heretikes assigne: to wit, true doctrine of faith, and right vse of Sacraments, be not sufficient.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 15.</label>
            <hi>That these foure,</hi> Vna, Sancta, Catholica, Apostolica, One, Holy, Catholique, Apostolique, <hi>be good markes, whereby men may discerne, which is the true Church.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 16.</label>
            <hi>That these foure markes, agree onely to the Romane Church. That is to say, to that company of men, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth in profession of faith, with the Church of Rome.</hi>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>§. 1.</label>
                  <hi>That the Romane Church onely is</hi> One.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>§. 2.</label>
                  <hi>That the Romane Church onely is</hi> Holy.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>§. 3.</label>
                  <hi>That the Romane Church is onely</hi> Catholique.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>§. 4.</label>
                  <hi>That the Romane Church is onely</hi> Apostolique.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
         <item>
            <label>Chap. 17.</label>
            <hi>The conclusion of the whole discourse:</hi> viz. <hi>That the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church is the onely true Church of Christ, of which, all men must learne, the one, infallible, entire faith, which is necessary to saluation. And that the</hi> Protestants <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations cannot be this true Church.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
      <p>
         <pb n="3" facs="5"/>
THE PREFACE.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>BEing moued by some friends, to conferre with one of indifferent good iudgement, and of no ill disposition of nature; though verie earnest in thaet religion which he did professe: I was desirous to do my best endeuors, to let him plainely see, that the Catholique Romane faith was the onely right.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>Being requested by some friends to maintaine the truth of Christian religion professed amongst vs, against the antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian cauils of this popish proctor; I thought it my best course, first to answer in generall to the whole substance of his booke; and then to examine euerie particular Chapter. In the former, I first consider his drift and scope: then how he proues that which he intends. His drift is to shew, <hi>That the Catholique Romane faith is the onely right:</hi> wherein he craftily begs that which is in question; <hi>That the Romane faith is the Catholique faith;</hi> &amp; which himselfe propounds, as the second thing to be proued by him: <hi>That those onely which professe the Romane faith, are the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church.</hi> Neither can it be auouched by the authority of anie ancient writer, or by any good reason, that it is lawfull or fit to ioyne the terme Catholique (as Papists take it) to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church whatsoeuer. There was great strife about the Catholike Church vpon earth in Austins time, which the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natists <note n="*" place="margin">
            <hi>August. ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nif. Epist.</hi> 50. <hi>ad Honor. Ep.</hi> 161. <hi>de Agone Christian. c.</hi> 29.</note> would haue confined to Affrica: but the true Christians freed it from that bondage, and bounded it with no other limits then the compasse of the whole world. Let the Papists shew, if they can, that in this whole cōtrouersie, the Catholique Church was euer restrained or coupled to anie one Citie, Dioces, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, or Nation, as it is now by them to Rome. If they cannot, let them acknowledge, and renounce this their noueltie.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 3" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 3.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>For which purpose, I did chuse to let passe disputes about parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular points, and in generall to shew; First, that it is necessary to admit an infallible authoritie in the true Cathòlique Church: by reason whereof, euery one is to learne of it onely, which is the true faith of Christ. Secondly, that those onely which professe the Románe faith, are the true Catholique Church. The which hauing proued, I did consequently conclude; that the faith and beliefe which the authority of the Romane Church doth cōmend vnto vs, ought, without doubt,</hi>
         <pb n="4" facs="6"/>
         <hi>to be holden for the true faith.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>Indeed the best, and onely way to auow the doctrine of the Romish Church, is to leade men hoodwinckt in ignorance of the particular points it holds, many whereof are so palpably false, that he that knowes them, will easily be perswaded to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them. But let vs see what you shew in generall.</p>
      <p>Thus you dispute: <note place="margin">The generall syllogisme.</note>
         <list>
            <item>The faith, which the authoritie of the true Catholique Church commends vnto vs, ought, without doubt, to be holden for the true faith.</item>
            <item>But the faith, which the authoritie of the Church of Rome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends vnto vs, is the faith which the authoritie of the true Catholique Church commends vnto vs.</item>
            <item>Therfore the faith, which the authoritie of the Church of Rome commends vnto vs, ought, without doubt, to be holden for the true faith.</item>
         </list>
The conclusion of this syllogisme is set downe by you in plaine words, there; <hi>The which hauing proued, I did consequently cōclude, that the faith, &amp;c.</hi> The proposition, or major is not exprest; no more is the assumption or minor; but instead of them you haue deliuered the proofes of them, thus to be concluded. First for the proposition; at those words: <hi>That it is necessary to admit an infallible, &amp;c.</hi>
         <note place="margin">Proofe of the proposition.</note>
         <list>
            <item>If it be necessary to admit an infallible authoritie in the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, by reason whereof euery one is to learne of it onely, which is the true faith of Christ: then the faith, which the authoritie of the true Catholique Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends vnto vs, ought, without doubt, to be holden for the true faith.</item>
            <item>But it is necessarie to admit such an authoritie in the true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church.</item>
            <item>Therefore the faith, which the authoritie of the true Catholike Church commends vnto vs, ought, without doubt, to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for the true faith.</item>
         </list>
Onely the assumption of this syllogisme is propounded, the rest omitted. The proofe of your principall assumption is at those words: <hi>That those only which professe the Romane, &amp;c.</hi> And (as in
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>
the former syllogisme) the assumption onely is exprest, the rest vnderstood. Thus: <note place="margin">Proofe of the Assumption.</note>
         <list>
            <item>If those onely which professe the Romane faith, are the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, then the faith which the authoritie of the Church of Rome commends vnto vs, is the faith which the authoritie of the true Catholike Church commends vnto vs.</item>
            <item>But those onely which professe the Romane faith, are the true Catholique Church.</item>
            <item>Therefore the faith which the authoritie of the Church of Rome commends vnto vs, is the faith, which the authoritie of the true Catholique Church commends vnto vs.</item>
         </list>
We see now what his drift is; how he proues that he intends: and by what reason he confirmes his proofe. It remaines that we consider in general, to what part of his proofe, or confirmation thereof, euery Chapter in his Discourse appertaineth.</p>
      <p>In the 4. first Chapters he layeth certaine grounds concerning faith: in the 13. following he disputeth the matter propounded.</p>
      <p>First he shewes the necessitie of faith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. then he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth three properties required to true faith. <hi>That it is one, Ch.</hi> 2. <hi>That it is infallible, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>That it is entire, Chap.</hi> 4. In his dispute, the twelue former Chapters, from the beginning of the fifth to the end of the sixteenth, containe the antecedent, or first part of his reason, and the proofes thereof. The seuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth addeth and enforceth the maine conclusion.</p>
      <p>The assumption of the second syllogisme: <hi>That it is necessary to admit, &amp;c.</hi> is handled from the fourth Chapter to the tenth.</p>
      <p>The proposition of the first syllogisme: <hi>That the faith which the authoritie of the true Catholique Church commendeth to vs, ought, without doubt, to be holden for the true faith:</hi> is proued by another reason, from the ninth Chapter to the thirteenth.</p>
      <p>The assumption of the third syllogisme: <hi>That those onely which professe the Romane faith; are the true Catholique Church:</hi> is debated from the twelfth Chapter to the seuenteenth.</p>
      <p>This is the generall frame of the whole Treatise, as farre as I am able to conceiue of it. Now let vs examine the truth therof. Wherein that I may proceed the more orderly and plainely, I wil first speake a word or 2. of some matters that seeme fit to be
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
vnderstood, ere I answer particularly to the seueral propositiōs.</p>
      <p>What the diuerse significations of this word <hi>faith</hi> are, and how many sorts of <hi>faith</hi> there be, I will inquire (as farre as it is needfull for this Treatise) in my answer to the first Chapter: onely we are now to know, that by <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>beliefe,</hi> this Papist vnderstands the <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>doctrine</hi> which is to be beleeued. This appeares in the rest of this Preface, and namely at these words: <hi>Fourthly because these few plaine points, &amp;c,</hi> as also euery where in his Treatise; though sometimes (as I will shew in due place) he take it otherwise. The like I say of the word <hi>Church:</hi> which being diuersly taken in Scripture, is here to be restrained to <hi>a certaine cōpany of men vpon earth,</hi> as this Author himself shewes in this Preface, at the place aforenamed.</p>
      <p>Now then to answer directly to his principall syllogisme; I deny the whole antecedent therof. Because it takes some things <note place="margin">To the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme.</note> for a knowne truth, which are either false, or, at least, full of doubt. As for example, that <hi>the true Catholique Church is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men vpon earth:</hi> whereas who knowes not, that the saints, that haue bene, are, and shalbe in all ages, are members of the true Catholique Church, which consists of them all ioyntly? That <hi>all the seuerall congregations, which hold the true doctrine of the Gospell, are one and the same Church.</hi> A doctrine (in his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) without anie warrant of Scripture, as it shall be shewed hereafter. That <hi>there is authoritie in a certaine company of men vpō earth, to require, that whatsoeuer they deliuer, be held for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, vnder paine of damnation to all that wil not so beleeue them:</hi> whereas God vseth not <hi>the authoritie</hi> of men, but <hi>their ministerie,</hi> to the begetting of faith in them that shall be saued.</p>
      <p>In particular I denie the proposition; because all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <note place="margin">To the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position.</note> in the world may erre, either in some one point not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall; or some in one, some in another. And therefore some things may be propounded by the true Church of Christ, which notwithstanding are not, vpon any authoritie of theirs, to be held for true.</p>
      <p>To the proofe of the proposition set downe in the second syllogisme I answer, by denying the assumption: <hi>That it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary</hi>
         <note place="margin">To the proof of the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition.</note>
         <hi>to admit such authoritie in the Church.</hi> The reasons of my
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
deniall are: 1: That God hath giuen no such authoritie to anie companie of men, since the Apostles, or besides them; who had it seuerally, euery one in his owne person. 2. That there is no necessitie of anie such authoritie, for the saluation of the elect, or damnation of the reprobate. 3. That the Scriptures are left vnto vs for an absolute rule, whereby all things that are to be beleeued must be tried.</p>
      <p>I denie also the assumption of the first principall syllogisme; <note place="margin">To the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, and the proofe thereof.</note> and to the proofe of it, contained in the third syllogisme, I say further, that they which professe the doctrine that the Church of Rome now teacheth in many points, are members of the Church of Antichrist, vnder the Pope the head thereof. But if, as you say, <hi>Those that professe the Romane faith, are the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church,</hi> how ignorantly and absurdly do your Monkes <note place="margin">
            <hi>In fidei profess. anno</hi> 1585. <hi>art.</hi> 60.</note> of Bourdeaux write, in their solemne profession of religion; where they say, that <hi>the holy, visible, catholique, and Apostolike Church dispersed ouer the whole world, hath communion in faith &amp; manners with the Church of Rome?</hi> If the Catholique Church haue communion with the Church of Rome, sure the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church and the Church of Rome are not all one.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 4" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 4.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Ʋpon which points, when he had heard my discourse, he desired me, for his better remembrance, to set downe in writing, what I had said. The which I had first thought to haue done briefly, and to haue imparted it onely to him: but by some other friends it was wished, that I should handle the matter more at large; they intending (as it seemed) that it might not only do good to him, but to others also, that should haue need of it, as well as he. Of which sort of men standing in this need, as I could not (considering their miserable case) but take great pitie: so I was easily moued, especially at my friends request, to be willing to do my endeuour, which might be for their reliefe and succour: and to take any course which might turne to their helpe and profite.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>The title of your booke professeth breuitie; here you say, that <hi>you had thought to set downe your discourse briefly, but haue handled the matter more at large.</hi> Either your <hi>Title</hi> or your <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> is to blame. Your Title is iustified afterward, where you say, that <hi>your course of writing is very briefe and compendious.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <pb n="8" facs="8"/>
Papists talke of pitie, who, without mercie or conscience wold haue murdred so many thousāds by treason, &amp; (as they thought) haue sent them almost quicke to hell, soules and bodies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? It is not anie pitie of vs, but your slauery to the Pope, and proud conceit of (I know not what) merite, with hope of making your part strong for rebellion or massacre, that drawe from you these goodly treatises.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 5" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 5.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Now of all other courses, which haue bene, and might be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; that, which in my speech I did chuse as most expedient for him with whom I did conferre, seemed best also for me to prosequute in this my writing, for the benefite of him and others, and this for foure reasons.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>I know not what he was, with whom (as you say) you did conferre, but I am sure his iudgement was (at the most) but <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different good,</hi> if such a course as begs the question, would be any way liked of him. You vndertake to shew, That <hi>it is necessary to admit an infallible authority in the true Catholique Church:</hi> which you expound to be, <hi>A companie of men vpon earth.</hi> VVhat Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant is there of any knowledge, but vnderstands, that by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church</hi> we meane ordinarily, not any companie in this world, but the whole societie of the faithful, from time to time? But these gay shewes of <hi>Catholike Church, Ʋniuersalitie, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, vnitie, succession,</hi> and such like, are fit to deceiue the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; for which purpose your discourses are written, &amp; with whō they preuaile, by the iust iudgement of God, <hi>who sends them</hi>
         <note place="margin">2. Thes. 2. 9. 10</note>
         <hi>strong delusions, that they may beleeue lyes, because they haue not embraced the loue of the truth, that they might be saued.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 6" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 6.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>First, because it is very briefe, and compendious; and consequently such, as euery one might haue leysure, and should not be much weary to reade it.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>You deale in your corrupt writings, as leud men do in slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous reports: who speake anie thing, at aduenture, though neuer so vntrue, or vnlikely. It is hard but some men will either beleeue, or make doubt of it, at the least. So all men reade your writings, you care not. Though they, that are of knowledge, and iudgement, discerne your falshood: yet it is twentie to one, but some ignorant fellow will light on them, that may be sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.
<pb n="9" facs="8"/>
And this practise you follow the rather, because you are, for the most part, out of feare of being shamed by confutation; for that you are vnknowne, and know well inough, that our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers to you, are commonly, and many times must be so large, that one amongst manie can hardly find leisure to reade them. Whereas if the authors of your treatises were knowne amongst vs, and our answers applied shortly, and plainely to the verie point of the argument, that being disrobed of the idle orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you cloath it withall, and laid naked to the view of true reason, we should haue as few of your discourses, as we haue now of your replies, to our refutations of your treatises; which are so few, that, in many yeares, it is rare to haue anie second charge by you; vnlesse it be in such a fight, as requires no more but a <hi>brauado,</hi> without coming to handie blowes.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 7" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 7.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Secondly, because, it, standing onely vpon few, but most certaine conclusions, and grounds; is free from many cauils of the captious, which more ample discourses are subiect vnto.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>To speake truly, and properly, there is but one conclusion in your whole Treatise, as I haue shewed out of this your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. Against which we also oppose one as briefe, and more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine then yours. Your conclusion is, That <hi>the faith, and beliefe, which the authority of the Romane Church doth commend vnto vs, ought, without doubt, to be holden for the true faith.</hi> Ours, That <hi>the faith which the Scripture teacheth vs, is the onely true faith.</hi> If you speake of the seuerall cōclusions belonging to the proofe of the generall, there are (at the least) as many as there are Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But if you meane the three grounds, which you signifie before, and repeate afterwards, they are so farre from being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that there is neuer a one of them true, as you vnderstand them.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 8" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 8.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Thirdly, because, the matter handled in it, is not very high nor hard, but common, easie, and plaine: and such, as may be vnderstood of any, who, hauing but a reasonable wit, or vnderstanding, wil care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully read it (as the importance of the matter requireth) with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deliberation, and (which is chiefe) with prayer to God, and a resolute good will to follow that, which he shall find to be right.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>The matter is as hard, by your handling of it, as sophistrie 
<pb n="10" facs="9"/>
can well make it; as high, as the deepe foundation of religion. Yet I denie not, but it may be vnderstood by a man of such parts, and paines, as you require: and adde farther, that the like may be auowed of the true grounds of religion, as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scripture: to the reading, and meditation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lord himself hath promised such a blessing, as your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises, <note place="margin">Psal. 1. 1. 2. Ioan. 5. 39.</note> if they were neuer so true, could not looke for. Is not the fountaine better then the chanell?</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 9" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 9.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Fourthly, because, these fewe plaine points, which are here set downe, include all other: and whosoeuer shall, by the helpe of Gods grace, and the force of these, or other reasons, yeeld assent to the points proued in this discourse: must by consequence, without further dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting or difficultie, yeeld to all particular points, which the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Church commendeth for points of faith, and will be moued to settle himselfe in the stedfast beliefe of all. For if he once admit, that there is a Church, or company of men, on earth, infallibly taught by the holy Ghost, what is the true faith in all points: and that this Church is, by Gods appointment, to teach all men in all matters of faith, which is the infallible truth: and further, that this Church, which is thus taught, and must teach vs, is no other but that visible company, which professeth the</hi> Romane faith: <hi>then he shall not need to straine his wits in studying, or to wast words in wrangling, about particular points of controuersies, or to vse any such troublesome and vncertaine meanes to find out the truth: but may easily, and most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be instructed in all, by onely enquiring and finding out (which all sorts of men may easily do) what is generally holdē by the Church, for truth, in all particular points, whereof they doubt.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>If these few points be so conuenient, because in thē all other are included; why should not our doctrine of the Scripture be as conuenient, by the same reason? Let vs compare our assertions together. The first of yours is, That <hi>a man must admit, that there is a company of men on earth, infallibly taught by the holy Ghost, what is the true faith, in all points.</hi> The first of ours, That <hi>a man must beleeue, that there is a written word of God, wherein the holy Ghost hath certainely taught, whatsoeuer is needfull to be knowne to saluation.</hi> Your second is: That <hi>this company of men is, by Gods appointment to teach all men, in all matters of faith, which is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi>
         <pb n="11" facs="9"/>
         <hi>truth.</hi> Our second: That <hi>this written word of God is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by him to teach all men in all matters of faith, what is true, what false.</hi> Your third: That <hi>this company of men is no other, but the visible company, which professeth the Romane faith.</hi> Our third: That <hi>this written word is no other, but the bookes of the old and new Testament.</hi> The proofe of your positions, and the exceptions, you take against ours, shalbe handled (if it please God) in their due places; in the meane time, if any mā be troubled with those ordinarie doubts, which you haue buzzed into the common peoples eares, concerning <hi>the vncertainty and hardnesse of the Scriptures,</hi> let me intreat him to stay himselfe a while vpon these considerations. First that <hi>the bookes of the old and new Testament acknowledged by vs, are also confessed by you to be the verie word of God; in the penning whereof</hi>
         <note n="*" place="margin">
            <hi>Bellar. de Concil. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. §. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>the penners were so directed by the holy Ghost, that they could not erre.</hi> Therefore whatsoeuer the meanes be, whereby we come to assurance, that these bookes are the word of God, let it suffice all men, that both we, and you agree, they are so. But I pray tell me: Are the determinations of the Church any more certaine? What ground haue I, but the word of some men, that the Church hath so determined? It is not a matter so agreed vpon betwixt vs, as the bookes of Scripture are. Out of question the ods is on our side. It is doubtfull, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you Romanistes are the Church or no: it is out of doubt, these bookes are the infallible word of God. But you will say, the Scriptures are hard to be vnderstood; as well because they are written in Hebrew, and Greeke, as also for the kind of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Are not all the Decrees of your Councels, and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your Popes Consistorie, written either in Greeke, or Latin, or in the Italian language; in none of which one man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ten thousand hath any skill? And is there not as great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to thinke, the Scriptures are rightly translated, as your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, Decretals, and Determinations? Especially when as we (commonly) alledge the interpretations of the ancient Fathers, and learned Papists for the auowing of our translations. But the Scriptures are hard to be vnderstood, though a man be skilfull in the tongues. And are the Decrees of your Councels so easie, that euery man may vnderstād them, who knowes the language
<pb n="12" facs="10"/>
they are written in? Doth not <note n="a" place="margin">
            <hi>Bellar. tom.</hi> 3 <hi>de Sacram. passim: &amp; vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</hi>
         </note> Bellarmine condemne, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute our writers, Caluin, Chemnitius, and other, for not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Decrees of your Councell of Trent written in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; which language they were as skilfull in, as himselfe? If they be so easie, how chance <note n="b" place="margin">
            <hi>Dominic. Sotus in Apol. contra Cathar. cap.</hi> 2.</note> Bishop Catharin and Frier Soto, that were both present at the Councell, and heard the debating of matters, can not agree about the doctrine of it, concerning <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of saluation?</hi> which (as <note n="c" place="margin">Vbi supra.</note> Soto affirmes) <hi>was the longest and most troublesome disputation of all in the Councell:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore should haue bene best vnderstood, and plainliest deliuered. Yet is it so propounded by the holy fathers, the authors of it, that <note n="d" place="margin">Vbi supra.</note> Catharin saith boldly, <note n="e" place="margin">
            <hi>Ambros. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharin. tract.</hi> 1. <hi>Verba decreti aliter pleros{que} accepturos, quā fuerat mens sancte Synodi.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>he foresaw, that most men would vnderstand the words of the Decree otherwise then the holy Synod meant them.</hi> Was there not great contention within these very few yeares, betwixt <note n="f" place="margin">Christophor. de Cap sont, archiepisc. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sariens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> de ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessat. correct. theologie scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>last.</note> Archbishop Christophor. <hi>de Capite fontium</hi> and many other Diuines, about the meanes of transsubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the bread, though in his iudgement the Councel of Trent makes manifestly for him? I forbeare to say, that some points seeme to haue bene craftily set downe of purpose, like the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Apollo, that which way soeuer they be taken, the Church may not seeme to haue erred. Neither will I adde, that <note n="g" place="margin">
            <hi>Bellar. de Concil. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. §. <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>diuerse matters are deliuered by Councels, not as points of faith, but as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable coniectures:</hi> which yet may be, and are taken by some of your owne <note n="h" place="margin">Clement. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. de summa Trinit. &amp; fide catholica.</note> learned writers, as if they were resolutely determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for certaine truth. These things considered, I see no suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reason, why it should not be as fit, and safe to learne of the Scripture, <note n="i" place="margin">
            <hi>Canus loc. com. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> which is the infallible truth, as of any companie of men whatsoeuer.</p>
      <p>But you labour to commend to vs this resting on the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Romish Church by some especiall commodities, that shall ensue thereupon. The first wherof is <hi>ease:</hi> the 2. <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of knowledge. He shall not need</hi> (say you) <hi>to straine his wits in studying &amp;c.</hi> If ease were not too much delighted in by men of your profession, there would not be such swarms of idle Monks, Fryers, Nuns, nonresident Bishops and Priests amongst you. But true Christians vnderstand, that it was not Gods purpose to prouide so much for their ease, by giuing them leaue to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="13" facs="10"/>
at aduenture, hand ouer head, whatsoeuer it should please men to enioyne thē; but that it is his good pleasure, that <note n="k" place="margin">
            <hi>Psal.</hi> 1. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> 119. <hi>per tot.</hi>
         </note> all men should carefully and painfully exercise themselues, night and day, in reading and meditating of the Scriptures. He is too nice and dainty a professor of religion, that is loth to straine his wits to the vttermost, in the study of any thing reuealed by God in Scripture. What shall I say of him, that cals conference and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputation about, euen the greatest points of faith and iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>wasting of words in wrangling:</hi>
         <note n="l" place="margin">
            <hi>Ouid. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. lib.</hi> 13.</note>
         <hi>Nec se magnanimo maledicere sentit Achilli?</hi> It is strange you should not haue the wit to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that, by this censure, you condemne <hi>Lombard, Thomas,</hi> and all your schoole men: yea the Pope, and generall councels, <note n="m" place="margin">
            <hi>Bellar de pontif. Rom. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ad obiect.</hi> 2.</note> who are bound to vse such meanes, for the finding out of the truth: and (as <note n="n" place="margin">
            <hi>Sotus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. contra. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar. cap.</hi> 2.</note>
         <hi>Sotus</hi> saith) <hi>did vse them in a long and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some disputation,</hi> yet forsooth neither the one, nor the other, at <note n="o" place="margin">
            <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>sect</hi> 1. <hi>post. med.</hi>
         </note> least both together cannot erre. No man then ought to refuse study, or disputation of controuersies in diuinitie, because they are troublesome. Therefore, to mend the matter, you adde that they are also <hi>vncertaine:</hi> what can be certain, but only reuelation, if the true vse of reason can breed nothing but vncertainty? How idly and vainly did your schoolemen imploy themselues: if all their study and labour must end in vncertainty? What vse is there of Councels for finding out of the truth, since the helpe to be had of them, is debating of matters by reasoning? Do we not find in daily experience, that as flint and steele stric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together bring forth fire: so truth is, as it were, beaten out by disputation? It is reported you make great shewes of desiring a disputation. I maruaile to what end: If, when all comes to all, your auditors shall still remaine vncertaine what is true. Shall I go yet farther? You tell vs <hi>the Church cannot erre;</hi> we beleeue you not: you alledge some places of Scripture to proue it to vs: we say they proue no such matter: what course will you take? It is in vaine to dispute of it: that is, (as you say) <hi>to wast words in wrangling about it.</hi>
         <note n="p" place="margin">See 12. Art. part. 1. art. 5.</note>
         <hi>For that is but an vncertaine meanes to find<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the truth.</hi> Haue you not brought matters to a good passe, thinke you, when you professe that there is no meanes to discern certainlie whether the Church can erre or no, but onely to take
<pb n="14" facs="11"/>
her own word for it? Yea no meanes left to know that she is the Church. For if you will againe fly to the Scriptures; you run into the former difficulties, and end as before in vncertainty. Who would haue to do with such vnreasonable men?</p>
      <p>But that you may not seeme to leaue vs in vncertainty; you tel vs, that <hi>we may most certainly be instructed in all particular points of controuersies, by onely enquiring and finding out what is holden ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally by the Church for truth, &amp;c.</hi> You send vs to the faith of the Church, and namely of the Church of Rome. Which (say we) is onely so farre forth to be yeelded vnto, as it is agreeable to the Scriptures. Neither do we say so onely, but <note n="a" place="margin">
            <hi>Ambros. in Lucam. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note>
         <hi>Ambrose,</hi> long before our time, hath said the like. <hi>We are commanded</hi> (saith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose) to enquire after the faith of the Church, and that</hi>
         <note n="b" place="margin">In primis quaerenda.</note>
         <hi>especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: in which Church if Christ be a dweller,</hi>
         <note n="c" place="margin">Haud dubiè legenda.</note>
         <hi>it is doubtlesse to be made choise of. But if the people be vnfaithful, if an heretical teacher deforme the dwelling; the communion of heretickes is to be auoided, the congregation must be shunned.</hi> And a little after: <hi>If there be any Church that refuseth the faith, and</hi>
         <note n="d" place="margin">Possideat.</note>
         <hi>holds not the foundation of the Apostles preaching, it is to be left, lest it taint vs with some spot of</hi>
         <note n="e" place="margin">Perfidiae.</note>
         <hi>vnbeliefe, or vnfaithfulnesse.</hi> Neither will it serue the turne; that you referre vs to that which is generally holden by the Church: for both the generall faith depends vpon the particular beliefe of the Church, or Pope of Rome; and is not to be taken for truth, because it is generally receiued, but because it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with the Romane faith; as we learned before of your <note n="f" place="margin">
            <hi>Profess fidei art.</hi> 60.</note> Monkes of Bourdeaux, who make the Catholique Church to haue communion with the Church of Rome, as the fountaine of truth; and of greater authoritie, in their iudgement, then the Catholicke Church. But let vs admit that you desire, of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing whatsoeuer is generally holden by the Church: I am half a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, this conceit, be it neuer so strong, wil not procure the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes you promise vs. The causes of my feare are these two. First, I may doubt of such a point, as is not yet determined by the Church; for example, I make question of the Popes authority aboue Councels, or theirs aboue him. How shall I most certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be instructed in the truth of this question? <hi>Enquire</hi> (say you) <hi>and find what is generally holden by the Church.</hi> What if the
<pb n="15" facs="11"/>
Doctors of your Church cannot agree about this point? That they cannot, it appeares by your owne doubting; <note n="g" place="margin">Chap. 16. Sect. 1.</note> where you make it questionable, whether the Pope alone or the Pope with a general Councell be free from error. And <note n="h" place="margin">
            <hi>Bellar. de Concil. autor. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. 14. 15 16. 17.</note> Bellarmine is faine to take a great deale of paines, in answering the arguments of diuers Papists, <note n="i" place="margin">
            <hi>Nicol. Cusan. Concor. cathol. li</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. 12. <hi>Panorm. in c. significasti. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. de electio.</hi>
         </note> some of them equall to himselfe for learning, iudgement, and authoritie, who make the Pope subiect to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels. But of this in due place. Say it were generally agreed on: Could I thereby be most certainly instructed what is truth in this point? May not all saue the Pope be deceiued? and perhaps he to; without the aduice and assent of a general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: at least, if he haue not in his consistory, vpon good delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Abulens. in Math.</hi> 18. <hi>q.</hi> 108 <hi>&amp; alij apud Bellar. vbi supra. Christop. de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite fontium de necessar. correct theol. schol. fol.</hi> 53. <hi>b.</hi>
         </note> resolued of the matter? What shall it auaile me then to know, that (generally) it is thought the Pope is aboue any Councell? Supposing this point were generally held to be true, though indeed, as I said before, it is denyed both by priuate men &amp; by 2. councels; that of <note n="k" place="margin">
            <hi>Concil. Basil. sess</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi>
         </note> Basil, &amp; the other of <note n="l" place="margin">
            <hi>Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. sess.</hi> 4.</note> Constance which deposed two Popes, Iohn the three and twentieth and Benedict the thirteenth. And <note n="m" place="margin">
            <hi>Bellar. de Concil. autor. l.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 13. §. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde.</hi>
         </note> Bellarmine saith, that to this day it remaines in question, euen among the Catholikes. Well, put case all men thought, as Bellarmine, and all such Popish pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasites would haue it, what were I the nearer, as long as there can be no certainty of truth, (in your opinion) where nothing is iudicially determined by a Pope, &amp; Coūcell? The second resō of my doubt is, that I know not how to find out, either <hi>easily,</hi> as you say euery man may, or <hi>certainly,</hi> though with some paines, what is generally holdē by the Church for truth, in al particular points, wherof I doubt. Shall I looke into the confessions of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Churches? Where are they to be found? Shall I trauail in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery particular country, to learne what they hold of this, or that poynt? What assurance can I get hereby, but from some speciall men? And it is a venture, but they will not all agree in euery point. What remaines? Forsooth that which is all in all; I must beleeue, <hi>Watsō,</hi> or <hi>Clarke,</hi> or <hi>Blackwel the archpriest,</hi> or if al these will not content me, <hi>Gerrard, Tesmond, Hall,</hi> or, without all doubting, <hi>Garnet</hi> the superior of the Iesuites, who questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onlesse is as void of error, as the Pope himselfe. Haue I not,
<pb n="16" facs="12"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="17" facs="12"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="18" facs="13"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="19" facs="13"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="14" facs="14"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="15" facs="14"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="16" facs="15"/>
trow you, a sound foundation, to build my faith vpon, when I haue the word of these equiuocating traitours, Priests and Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its? And yet this is the most I can haue in this case, if I be a man vnlearned, especially vnable to reade. Is it possible, any man should be so senslesse as to hazzard his euerlasting saluation, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such an vncertainty, to beleeue he knowes not what, because a Priest, or a Iesuit tels him, that the Church generally doth so beleeue? But what if it fall out, as it may do, that the <hi>Priests</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade him the Church holds one thing; and <hi>the Iesuites</hi> affirme it maintaines the contrary; how shall a poore soule either settle his iudgement, or quiet his conscience? <hi>Quid sequar, aut quem?</hi> Were it not a directer, and certainer course, to hold nothing for truth in religion, but that which is proued to vs by plaine testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Scripture, or certaine consequence of reason, drawne from principles euidently exprest, or apparētly contained in the knowne word of God? The difficulties of translation and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation shal be handled in their places; <note n="n" place="margin">See 12. Art. part. 1. Art. 3. &amp; 5.</note> which also, as I shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ere while, accompany al your writings of priuate men, Popes or Councels. Now then if their be many particular points of cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies, whereof I may doubt, which are not resolued of by any iudgement of the Church, nor agreed vpon by the learned of your owne side; if I cannot certainly know what is generally held for truth, by the Church, but as I giue credit to the report of a Priest, or Iesuit, whom I know to be partiall in the matter, because he is one of the Popes vassals; subiect to erre, because he is a priuate man; likely enough to lye because he maintaines equiuocation; what madnesse were it for me to forbeare search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and studying of the Scriptures, where I am sure the truth of God is to be found, and to lose my time, and labour in seeking what the Church generally holds, and that of those men who perhaps vnderstand not what is held, but as they haue bene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by others, who may themselues haue mistaken the true meaning <hi>of the Church in that it holds?</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 10" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 10.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>Of which points also, (If they be desirous) they may haue suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent authority and reason yeelded, by the learned of the same Church; though they should not so desire reason to be yeelded, that without reason be giuen, they would not beleeue at all, or as grounding their</hi>
         <pb n="17" facs="15"/>
         <hi>faith vpon the reason giuen: sith Christian beliefe ought onely to be grounded, vpon the authoritie of God, speaking by the mouth of the Church, who ought to be beleeued in all matters, without giuing any reason.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>There is no sufficient authoritie for a man to ground his faith vpon, but the truth of God reuealed. <note n="a" place="margin">
            <hi>Hieron. ad Math. cap.</hi> 23.</note>
         <hi>Whatsoeuer is taught with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that authoritie, is as easily contēned as alleadged.</hi> Therfore <note n="b" place="margin">
            <hi>Iustin. contra Trypho. p.</hi> 207.</note> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine wils him, that would be setled in the truth, <hi>to flie to the Scriptures.</hi> And <note n="c" place="margin">
            <hi>Tertullian de carne Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti. cap.</hi> 7.</note> Tertullian reiects that which is brought, <hi>if it be not in the Scriptures.</hi>
         <note n="d" place="margin">
            <hi>Origen in Cantic. hom.</hi> 3.</note> Origen saith, <hi>Christ is no where to be sought, but in the mountaines of the law and the Prophets.</hi> Yea <note n="e" place="margin">
            <hi>Hieron. in Mich. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome <hi>makes the Scriptures the bounds of the church beyond which she may not go.</hi> Are you able to shew this authority in all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler points of Controuersie, whereof a man may doubt? Are you not faine in many particulars, to deny the sufficiency of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and to run a madding after traditions? What talke you then of shewing sufficient authority? The bestauthority you can alleadge for many matters, is the Popes will, who cannot erre, as you ridiculously imagine. And this authoritie is all the reason you haue in diuers points; except such stuffe as <note n="f" place="margin">Durandus in Ration. Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. officior. passim.</note> Durād brings in his Rationale diuinorum officiorum; wherof many of your own men are ashamed.</p>
      <p>I had thought your Friers vow of obedience to their superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, or, at least, the <note n="g" place="margin">
            <hi>Constitut. Iesuit. par.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Maffae. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Iesuit. Catech. lib.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> Iesuits special vow of blind fold obedience, head bene the height of all perfection in this life: but I perceiue now, that there is a greater opinion of holinesse in these vowes, then there is cause why. For you tye the obedience of euery Christian in such sort to the authoritie of the Church, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, of his particular pastor, yea of euery Priest, or Iesuite, that comes licenced by <hi>Blackwell,</hi> or some <hi>new Garnet,</hi> that be must beleeue, without enquiring any reasō, whatsoeuer such a fellow shall deliuer to him for truth. This is the obedience, one of your Cardinals speakes of. <hi>Obedience without reason</hi> (saith <note n="h" place="margin">
            <hi>Nicol. Cusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. excitat. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>vbi ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia.</hi>
         </note> Cusan) <hi>is full and perfit obedience, namely when a man yeelds obedience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out requiring any reason; as</hi>
         <note n="i" place="margin">Iumentum.</note>
         <hi>a beast</hi> (horse or other) <hi>obeies his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi> So doth your Popish Clergie vse the people, as men do their Asses; make them beare, and do what they list, yea euen to
<pb n="18" facs="16"/>
the attempting of most horrible and incredible treasons against their Soueraigne and countrey. I will not now dispute what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement there is betwixt faith and reason; nor whether of them is the former; nor, in what case, a man may require reason; onely that no man may conceiue amisse of our doctrine, concerning our demanding of proofe for that we are enioyned to beleeue; he is to vnderstand, that we aske no farther proofe, but to be perswaded that the point deliuered to vs, is warranted by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Let it be neuer so much in (seeming) contrary to reason, if it be agreeable to Scripture, we hold our selues bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to take it for truth, though we be no way able to answer such reasons, as we know are brought against it. Neither yet do we rest satisfied, as soone as some place of Scripture is alledged in a doubtfull matter; but, here indeed we hearken after reason. Yet not to prooue that true, which we find affirmed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but to make vs perceiue, that such, and such is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Scripture. Whatsoeuer the Scripture saith, we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be absolutely true, so farre as it is deliuered for true by the holy Ghost. But what the sense of the Scripture is, we thinke it must be prooued by the true vse of reason, according to the certain principles of diuinitie, and such helps, as obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of circūstances, vnderstanding of the tongs, conference of like places, &amp; logical discourse, with such other helps, reasonably affoord vs. But why should you find fault with demanding rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or not be most willing &amp; ready to ioyne it to your authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, since (as <note n="k" place="margin">
            <hi>Nicol. Cusan. Excitat. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Serm. perfectus omnis eris.</hi>
         </note> Cusan saith) <hi>faith is not abased by reason, but exalted: euen as water in a vessell supports and lifts vp oyle.</hi> As for your proofe, that therfore we may not demand a reason, nor so much as enquire, whether the points that are taught vs, be sutable to the Scripture or no, because <hi>Christian beliefe must onely be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the authority of God speaking by the mouth of the Church:</hi> we say that you auouch that which is not true. For Christian faith must be grounded vpon the authoritie of God, speaking by the pens of his Apostles, and Prophets in the Scripture; not vpon the authoritie of any company of men liuing, from time to time, in the world. The Church you dreame of, will, I doubt not, in another part of my answer be shewed to be nothing, but
<pb n="19" facs="16"/>
a fancy, and a gay word to deceiue the simple; when as by it you meane no more, but your clergie, or perhaps your Bb. onely assembled in a Councell, or the Pope himselfe alone, who can with no more reason be called the Church, then <note n="l" place="margin">See 12. Art. part. 1. art. 5. pag. 63.</note> the head may be tearmed the body, or the whole man, if I should grant you, that he is the head, which is both <note n="m" place="margin">Reynald. confer. with Hart. <hi>Clamierus de Oecumen. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>arg.</hi> 1.</note> false and absurd. The Lord vseth not the authoritie of men, to enioyne what they list for a matter of faith, but their ministery, to beget faith (by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what he hath reuealed in the Scripture) through euidence of truth, and power of exhortation, testified and made effectuall by the mightie grace of the holy Ghost in the hearts of them that shall be saued.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="§ 11" type="extract">
      <head>A. D. §. 11</head>
      <p>
         <hi>The which briefe and compendious resolution of faith, whosoeuer will (as euery one may securely, and (as in the discourse following shall be declared) must necessarily embrace: beside the ease, he shall also reape this commoditie, that, cutting off all occasions of needlesse and fruitlesse doubts, questions and disputes, concerning matters of faith: wherin vnsettled minds spend their time and spirit, he shall haue good leisure, and better liking, then ordinarily such vnquiet mindes can haue, to employ his endeuours more fruitfully otherwayes; to wit, in building vpon the firme foundation of stedfast faith, the gold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious stones, of Gods loue, and other vertues, in practise whereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth that good life, which maketh a man become the liuing temple of almightie God: the which temple, Gods spirit will not onely visite, with holy inspirations and blessings oftentimes, in this life, but he wil also inhabite and dwell continually in it, both by grace, here, and by glory, in the other most happy, and euerlasting life.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="commentary">
      <head>A. W.</head>
      <p>The securitie, that ariseth from resting vpon the authoritie of the Church, is freenesse, not from danger, but frō care. This latter, I confesse, will easily be wrought by this perswasion in the heart of a carelesse worldling, or a man superstitiously ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, if he can be senslesly obstinate inough, in keeping his eyes and eares from seeing and hearing the truth of God, in the Scripture: for to such men <note n="n" place="margin">2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2. 9. 10.</note>
         <hi>God sends strong delusions to beleeue lyes, that they may be damned which haue not receiued the loue of the truth, that they might be saued.</hi> But alas! what shall this ease aduantage them, but onely that they may <note n="o" place="margin">
            <hi>Prou.</hi> 7. 22.</note> go laughing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction,
<pb n="20" facs="17"/>
as a foole doth to the stocks and whip? What necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can there then be, of embracing such a dāgerous resolution?</p>
      <p>Besides the ease, you tell vs now of another commodity, that may be reapt by embracing that <hi>compendious resolution of faith.</hi> Which before I examine, let me here againe put you in minde, that you condemne the greatest part of all your Schoolemens writings, as needlesse and fruitlesse doubts, questions and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes; and call them <hi>vnsetled minds, that spend their time, and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in such matters.</hi> And surely such were many of the points they handled, hauing nothing in them but vanitie and vexation of spirit: as may appeare (to name one for all) by their articles and questions vpon <note n="*" place="margin">
            <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>senten. dist.</hi> 8.</note> Lombard and <note n="a" place="margin">
            <hi>In</hi> 3. <hi>Thom. q.</hi> 73. <hi>&amp;c. Vide Christop. de cap fontium vbi supra.</hi>
         </note> Thomas, about the Masse. But is anie man to be found so shamelesse, as that he dare call it a needlesse and fruitlesse labour, <note n="b" place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5. 39.</note> to search the Scripture, for the finding out of the truth, in such matters as are necessarily to be beleeued for the attaining to saluation? Doth the neglect of this dutie bring a man good leisure and liking, to build himselfe vp in the loue of God? What loue of God can there be, where there is no delight in his word? <note n="c" place="margin">
            <hi>Psal.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119. 103. 127.</note> Dauid makes it his meditation day and night: and preferres the sweetnesse he finds in it, and the account he makes of it, before <hi>honie and the honie combe, fine gold and all maner of riches.</hi> But what should I heape vp vnneces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie testimonies, in a case not doubtfull? Is it possible they should be Christians, that make so small reckoning of the testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Iesus Christ? Can he be said truly to loue his father, that neuer cares to see what his fathers loue to him is; but contents himselfe with so much knowledge of it, as men list to impart to him; yea that knowes not whether he had such a father or no, but onely, as other men haue told him? We say not, that euery man is bound vpon hazzard of his saluation, to know euery point of difference betwixt you and vs, or to vnderstand the sense of euery place of Scripture; but that all true Christians must labour for as much knowledge, as, by diligent hearing, reading and meditating of the Scirptures, they can attaine to. Neither shall they, by this study and endeuour, either abate their loue to God, or depriue themselues of the sense of his loue to them. Nay rather both the one and the other shalbe increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="21" facs="17"/>
when a man shall feele the work of Gods spirit in his heart, kindling in him a desire to vnderstand the mystery of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by Iesus Christ, to comprehend the infinitenesse of the loue of God the Father, and enlightning him to conceiue that, which, by his owne skill, he neuer were able to discerne. But they that follow your resolution, neuer come rightly to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstant what the loue of God to them is: but if they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider things aduisedly, must needes thinke God hath dealt hardly with them, as with seruants, not with sonnes; whom he shuts out from the knowledge of his will, and view of his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; maiestie, manifested in the writings of the old and new Testament; affoording them no more of that heauenly Manna, but such chippings and parings, as their idle and prowd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates will vouchsafe to cast them. He, that finds the loue of God toward him, in opening to him the true sense of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in matters concerning his euerlasting saluation, doth beare more true loue to God for it, then any Papist can do, that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth in his blind obedience to men, &amp; maketh the end of his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God the deseruing of euerlasting life, by his ignorance of the Scriptures. As for true holinesse of life, whence doth it arise, but from the feeling of Gods loue to vs; whereby the spirit of God which dwels in vs, inflames our hearts with the affections of kind children to so louing a father? Can you imagine, that he, who hath at most, but a kind of perswasion, of I know not what holy inspirations &amp; blessings of Gods spirit, vpon some Priests or Iesuits word, can loue God as truely, and feruently, as he, that knowes by the truth of God in the Scripture, <note n="d" place="margin">
            <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>Gal</hi> 4. 6.</note> that the spirit of God dwels in all Gods children, <note n="e" place="margin">
            <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 16.</note> one of whom the same spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit assures him he is? Your Papist must liue holily, that he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the temple of God; a true Christian knowes he cannot liue holily, but by the holy Ghosts dwelling in him, and making him the temple of God. And can it be a question, whether of these two loueth God more deatly? But I haue bene too long in your Preface. Now to the Treatise it selfe.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>