<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The summe of the Sermons.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120117_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15576</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25843</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120117</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The summe of the Sermons.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The best merchandise or, A cleare discovery of the evident difference, and admirable advantage, betweene our traffike with God, for the true treasure; and with men, for temporall commodity : VVherein is shevved that our spirituall trading is both free from all the evill, full of all the good, which is incident to civill commerce; yea, that it overfloweth with divers excellent prerogatives, which the affayres of the earth cannot yeelde. Preached at Middleburgh in Zeelandt, immediately before the remoovall, of the famous fellowship of Merchant Adventurers of England from thence, vnto Delft, in Hollandt. And now published, and dedicated, to the honour and vse, of that whole society, there, or other where, residing. By Iohn VVing, a true harted wellwiller, to their temporall, and eternall good, with God and men</title>
                 <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nolck (Nolick), Marten Abrahamsz van der</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Flushing</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 138, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The summe of the Sermons.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>God who compare's his kingdome to your trade.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>VVould have you (Merchants) like his kingdome made.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>VVhereto, sincerely if you doe endeavour,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Both rich, and blessed, shall you be for ever.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For why? all things most sweetely doe combyne</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To rayse rare proffit by Commerce divine.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Jt standeth wholy of advantages.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>There is no feare of losse, or damages.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Adventures, Sales, Exchanges, Bartars, Debts</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>All are secure, all gainfull nothing lett's.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Th' Adventure's nothing, it's by th' almighty borne.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Who for your safety, by himself hath sworne.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>That maugre, sin, and all the devills in hell</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Your soules estate, for ever shalbe well.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Your Sales are happy; of your sin that's naught.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Bartar, for the grace, Christ bought.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And soe you make most rich Returnes, and</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To giue the best, for worst, God doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> place;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The Exchange, is gainfull, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lesse bringeth more, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The more (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> occasion) we deliver.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The more we doe receive, from this free giver.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Noe desperate Debts, or Bankrupts in this trade.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>God is the Credditour; Christ Surety made.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And both, have bound themselues to pay to us.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The principall, with gracious over plus</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Nor neede you doubt Bad Servants should deceive</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>You lay out all your self, and all receive</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>There is no trusting other agents here.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Each man, his owne eternall state shall beare</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And if to th' reckoning day we wisely looke</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>When our great Master will peruse his booke.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Th' account will rise most happy to our share</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>That sweetest voyce, with gladsome harts we heare</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Come faithfull servant, take your masters ioy</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Posesse eternall blisse, without anoy</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> here, is heaven for earth, for, trash, true tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>sure</hi>
      </l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <l>
         <hi>For some few cares and paynes, ioy without measure</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Glory for greife, eternity for ages,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For litle worke, immortall, endles wages.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>My soule doth wish you were such Merchants all.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>That he who to himself, his owne will call,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>May take you all, vnto that blisse aboue you</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Next unto Him, (and his Vice-roy) J loue you.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>