<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE Right Worshipfull, &amp; my worthy freinds Master EDVVARD BENNET, Deputy, the Assistance and Generality of the famous Fel∣lowship of Merchant Adventurers of England, resident at Delft in Hollandt.</title>
           <author>Wing, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120117_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15576</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25843</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120117</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE Right Worshipfull, &amp; my worthy freinds Master EDVVARD BENNET, Deputy, the Assistance and Generality of the famous Fel∣lowship of Merchant Adventurers of England, resident at Delft in Hollandt.</title>
                 <author>Wing, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The best merchandise or, A cleare discovery of the evident difference, and admirable advantage, betweene our traffike with God, for the true treasure; and with men, for temporall commodity : VVherein is shevved that our spirituall trading is both free from all the evill, full of all the good, which is incident to civill commerce; yea, that it overfloweth with divers excellent prerogatives, which the affayres of the earth cannot yeelde. Preached at Middleburgh in Zeelandt, immediately before the remoovall, of the famous fellowship of Merchant Adventurers of England from thence, vnto Delft, in Hollandt. And now published, and dedicated, to the honour and vse, of that whole society, there, or other where, residing. By Iohn VVing, a true harted wellwiller, to their temporall, and eternall good, with God and men</title>
                 <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nolck (Nolick), Marten Abrahamsz van der</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Flushing</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 138, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE <hi>Right Worshipfull, &amp; my worthy freinds Master EDVVARD BENNET,</hi> Deputy, <hi>the Assistance and Generality of the famous Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship of</hi> Merchant Adventurers <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>resident at</hi> Delft <hi>in</hi> Hollandt.</head>
   <head type="sub">IOHN WING, wisheth all <hi>Temporall, Spirituall,</hi> and <hi>Eternall</hi> happines, here, and in heaven.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am bolde, (beloved, and much respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Lord) to send this demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my dearest affection after you; not, that that I account it any <hi>competent recompence,</hi> but that you will (as I hope) receive it as some <hi>greatfull remembrance</hi> of those your greater favours, which you have soe kindely communicated vnto me. Some <hi>taste hereof,</hi> you had while I was soe happy as to speake (now and then) in your hearing, and because that was <hi>but a taste,</hi> (yet well savoured of such as heard the same) I could not deny, or discourage, the Christian desire of any, who were affected to feede more fully <hi>therevpon,</hi> It was the <hi>last message</hi> that I delivered among you from God; and therefore, inasmuch as you were vpon your <hi>jmmediate</hi> remoovall, to attayne a more happy cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of commerce with men, I thought it my part and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (therein) to doe my <hi>best,</hi> for the furtherance of your most happy traffike with the Lord; that you
<pb facs="3"/>might (if by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>possibility,</hi> I might helpe) be prosperous both in heaven and earth at once, and grow abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rich, in body <hi>temporally,</hi> and in soule, and body, <hi>eternally</hi> together. And God, who is Lord over all, and <hi>rich</hi> vnto all, grant, that you may enjoy this <hi>double blessednes,</hi> to the greatest prayse of his most glorious name, and the everlasting peace, and welfare, of your owne harts, and states, <hi>for ever</hi> before him. To his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and loue, I commend you <hi>all</hi> for ever; and to you <hi>all,</hi> (and to your loue,) I commend this my poore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour; nothing doubting, (yet earnestly desiring,) your kinde acceptance of the same, from <hi>him,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solveth ever to remayne.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, in all vnfayned affection for good. IOHN WING.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my house in</hi> Flushing. <date>
            <hi>March.</hi> 26. 1622.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>