<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Jn this Prologue, the Aucthour speaketh parti∣cularlye of the booke, called Marcus Aurelius, which he translated and dedicated to the Empe∣rour Charles the fyfte.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120709_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02296</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12428</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120709</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Jn this Prologue, the Aucthour speaketh parti∣cularlye of the booke, called Marcus Aurelius, which he translated and dedicated to the Empe∣rour Charles the fyfte.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dial of princes, compiled by the reuerend father in God, Don Antony of Gueuara, Byshop of Guadix, preacher, and chronicler to Charles the fifte, late of that name Emperour. Englished out of the Frenche by T. North, sonne of Sir Edvvard North knight, L. North of Kyrtheling</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 165, 1, 101, 103-173, 24 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_prologue">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>Jn this Prologue, the Aucthour speaketh <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularlye of the booke, called Marcus Aurelius,</hi> which he translated and dedicated to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Charles <hi>the fyfte.</hi>
      </hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He greatest vanitye that I find in the world is, that vayne men are not only contēt to be vaine in their life: but also procure to leue a memory of their vanity after their death. For it is so thought good vnto vaine and light men, whyche serue the worlde in vaine workes: that at the houre of death, when they perceyue they can do no more, &amp; that they can no lenger preuaile, they offer them selues vnto death, which now they see approche vpon them Manye of the world are so fleshed in the world, that although it forsaketh them in déedes: yet they wyl not forsake it in theyr desires. And I durst sweare, that if the world could graunt them perpetual life they woulde promyse it alwayes to remaine in their customable follye. O what a nomber of vaine men are aliue, whiche haue neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of god to serue him, nor of his glorye to obey him, nor of their conscience to make it cleane: but like brute beasts folow and ronne after their voluptuous plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours The brute beast is angrye if a man kepe him to much in awe: if he be wery he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his rest, he slepeth when he lysteth, he eateth and drinketh when he commeth vnto it, and vnles he be compelled he doth nothing, he taketh no care for the common welth, for he neither knoweth how to folow reason, nor yet how to resist sensualitie. Therfore if a man at al times should eate when he desireth, reuenge himselfe when he is moued, commit adultrie when he is tempted, drinke when he is thristie, and slepe when he is drousey, we might more properly cal such a one a beaste nourished in the mountaines: than a man brought vp in the common wealth. For him properly we maye cal a man, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> gouerneth him self like a man, that is to say, conformable vnto such things as reason willeth, and not wher sensuality leadeth. Let vs leaue these vaine men whyche are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, and talke of them that be dead, against whom we dare say, that whyles they were in the world they folowed the world, &amp; liued according to the same. It is not to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled at that sins they were lyuing in the worlde, they were noted of some worldlye point. But seing their vnhappy and wicked life is ended: why wil they then smel of the vanities of the world in their graues? It is a great shame and dishonor for men of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; stout harts, to se in one minut thend of our life, and neuer to see the end of our fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. We neither read, heare, nor se any thing more common, then suche men as be most vnprofitable in the comon wealth, and of life most reprobate, to take vpon them most honour whiles they liue, and to leaue behind them the greatest memorye at their death. What vanity can be greater in the world, then to esteme the world whych estemeth no man, and to make no compt of god who so greatly regardeth al men? what a greater fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can ther be in man, then by muche trauaile to encrease his goodes, and with vaine pleasours to lose his soule? It is an olde plague in mannes nature, that many (or the most parte of menne) leaue the amendment of their life farre behind: to set their honor the more before. <hi>Suetonius Tranquillus</hi> in the first booke of the Emperours sayth, that <hi>Iulius Cesar</hi> (no further thenne in Spaine, in the Citye of <hi>Cales</hi> nowe called <hi>Calis</hi>) sawe in the temple the triumphes of Alexander the great paynted, the whyche when he hadde wel vewed, he sighed marueilous soore, and beinge asked why he dyd so, he aunswered: What a wofull case am I in, that am now of thage of .30. yeres, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> at the same yeres had subdued the whole worlde, and rested him in Babilon. And I (being as I am) a Romaine, neuer dyd yet thyng woorthy of prayse in my lyfe, nor shal leaue any renoume of me after my death. <hi>Dion</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> in the second boke <hi>de Audacia</hi> saythe, that the noble <hi>Drusius,</hi> the Almayne, vsed to visite the graues and
<pb facs="11"/>
tombes of the famous and renowmed which were buried in Italy, and did this alwaies, especially at his going to warfare, and it was asked him why he did so, he aunswered. I vysite the sepulchers of <hi>Scipio,</hi> and of diuers others which are dead, before whom al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth trembled when they were alyue: For in beholdyng their prosperous successe, I dyd recouer both strength, and stoutnes. He sayth furthermore, that it encourageth a man to fight against hys enemies, remembring he shal leaue of him a memory in time to come. <hi>Cicero</hi> sayth in his Rhethorike, and also <hi>Plynie</hi> maketh mencion of the same in an epistle: that there came from <hi>Thebes</hi> (in <hi>Egipt</hi>) a knight to Rome, for no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, but onelye to see whether it were true or no, that was reported of the notable thinges of Rome. Whom <hi>Mecenas</hi> demaunded, what he perceyued of the Romaynes, and what he thought of Rome. He aunswered: the memorye of the absente dooth more content me, then the glory of the present doth satisfye me. And the reason of this is. The desire which men haue to extol the lyuing, and to be equal vnto the dead: maketh thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges so straunge in their lyfe, that they deserue immortal fame after their death. The Romaynes reioysed not a litle, to heare such wordes of a straungers mouth, wherby he praysed them whych were departed, and exalted them that yet lyued. O what a thing it is to consider the auncient heathens, whych neyther feared hel not hoped for heauen, &amp; yet by remembraunce of weakenes, they toke vnto them strength▪ by cowardnes, they were boldened: through feare, they became hardy: of daungers they toke encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: of enemies they made frendes: of pouertye they toke pacience: of malyce they learned experience: finally I say, they denied their owne willes, &amp; folowed thopinions of others, only to leaue behind them a memory with the dead, and to haue a lytle honor with the lyuing O how many are they that trust the vnconstauntnes of fortune, only to leaue some notable memorye behind them. Let vs cal to mynd some worthy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, wherby they may se that to be true, which I haue spoken. What made king <hi>Ninus</hi> to inuent such warres? Quene <hi>Semiramis</hi> to make such buildings? <hi>Vlisses</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> to sulke so many seas? king Alexander to conquere so many landes? <hi>Hercules</hi> the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bane</hi> to set vp his pillers where he did? <hi>Caius Cesar</hi> the Romayne to giue .52. battailes at his pleasure? <hi>Cirus</hi> king of <hi>Persia</hi> to ouercome both the Asiaes? <hi>Hannibal</hi> the <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gian,</hi> to make so cruel warres against the Romaines? <hi>Pirrhus</hi> king of <hi>Epirotes</hi> to come downe into Italy? <hi>Atila</hi> king of the <hi>Huns</hi> to defye al <hi>Europe?</hi> truly they woulde not haue taken vppon them such daungerous enterprises, only vppon the words of theym whych were in those dayes present: but because we should so esteme them that should come after. Seing then that we be men, and the chyldren of men, it is not a lytle to bee marueiled at, to see the diuersity betwene the one and the other, and what cowardnes ther is in the harts of some, and contrarywise what courage in the stomakes of others. For we se commonly now a daies, that if there be, 10. of stout courages, whych are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous with honour to dye: there are 10. thousand cowards, whiche throughe shamefull pleasurs seke to prolong their life. The man that is ambitious, thinketh him most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, who with much estimacion can kepe his renowme, and with litle care regarde his lyfe. And on the other side, he that wil set by his lyfe, shal haue but in small estimacion his renowme. The <hi>Sirians,</hi> the <hi>Assirians,</hi> the <hi>Thebanes,</hi> the <hi>Caldes,</hi> the <hi>Grekes,</hi> the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians,</hi> the <hi>Rodians,</hi> the <hi>Romaines,</hi> the <hi>Huns,</hi> the <hi>Germaines,</hi> and the Frenchmen, if such noble men (as among these were most famous) had not aduentured their lyues by such daūgerous enterprises, they had neuer got such immortal fame as they had don to leaue to their prosperity. <hi>Sextus Cheronensis</hi> in his third boke of the valiaunt deedes of the Romaines saith, that the famous captaine <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> (which was the first of al men that sawe the backe of <hi>Hannibal</hi> in the fielde) was demaunded of one how he durst enter into battaile, with such a renoumed captaine as <hi>Hannibal</hi> was? to whom he aunswered: frend, I am a Romaine borne, &amp; a captaine of Rome, and I must daylye put my lyfe in hazard for my countries sake, for so I shal make perpetual my renoume. He was demaunded againe why he stroke his enemyes with such fiersenes, &amp; why he did so pitefully lament those which were ouercome, after the vyctory gotten in battaile? he aunswered: the captaine which is a Romaine, and is not iudged to be a tiraunt, ought
<pb facs="11"/>
with his owne hand to shed the bloud of his enemyes, and also to shed the teares of his eyes. A captayne Romaine ought more to aduaunce him of his clemencie, then of hys bluddie victory. And <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> sayth further, when a Romaine captaine shal be in the field, he hath an eye to his enemyes with hope to vanquishe them, but afterl they be vanquisshed, he ought to remember they are men, and that he might haue bene ouercome. For fortune shewith herselfe in nothinge so common, as in the successes of warre. Certes these were words wel beseming such a man, and surely we may boldlye say, that al those which shal heare or read such thinges, wil commend the words which that Romaine spake: but few are they that in dede would haue done the feates that he did. For there be many that are ready to praise in their words that which is good: but ther are few that in their workes desire to folow the same. Such harts are vnquiet, &amp; much altered by sight and enuie that they bare towards their auncients which through manfulnes atayned vnto great tryumphes, and glory) let them remember, what daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and trauailes they passed through, before they came thereto. For there was neuer Captaine that euer triumphed in Rome, vnlesse he had first aduentured his life a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand times in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> feld I thinke I am not deceyued, in this that I wil say. That is to wete, al are desirous to tast of the marye of fame presente: but none wil breake the bone for feare of peril ensuing Yf honour cold be bought with desire onely, I dare boldly say, it would be more estemed in these dayes of the poore page: then it was in times past of the valyaunt Romaine <hi>Scipio.</hi> For ther is not at this day so poore a man, but would desire honour aboue al thinges. What a doleful case is this to se, many gentlemen and yong knights, becom euyl disposed vacabondes, and loyterers: the whych hearyng tel of any famous battaile fought, and that many of their estate and profession haue done va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaunt feates in the same: immediately therwith be stirred and set on fire through en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies heate, so that in the same furye, they chaunge their robes into armour: and wyth al spede prepare them selues to warre, to exercyse the feates of armes. And finally (like yong men without experience) make importunate sute, and obtaine licence, and money of their frends to go vnto the warres. But after they are ons out of their countrey, and see them selues in a straunge place, their dayes euyl, and their nightes worse, at one tyme they are commaunded to skirmish, and at an other time to watch, when they haue vittailes, they want lodging, &amp; when the pay day cometh, that pay &amp; the next also is eatē and spent. With these &amp; other like troubles &amp; discommodityes, the poore yong men are so astonyed: especially when they cal to mind the goodly wide haules, so wel hanged &amp; trymmed wherin they greatly delighted to passe the time in sommer season. When they remember their greate chimneis at home, whereby they comforted their olde limmes, and how they vsed to sit quietly vpon the sonny bankes in winter. For the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrauncr of the pleasour past, greatly augmenteth the paines present. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing their parents and frends, had admonished them hereof before: And now being beaten with their owne folye, &amp; feling these discommodities which they thought not of before: they determyne to forsake the warres, &amp; eche one to retourne home to his owne againe. But wher as they asked licence but ons to go forth, now they were enforced to aske it .10. times before they could come home. And the worst is, they went forth loden with money, and retourne home loden with vyces. But the end why these thinges are spoken is, that sage and vertuous men shold marke, by what trade the euil disposed seke to gaine: which is not gotten by gasing at the windowes, but by keping the frountiers against their enemies: not with playeng at tables in the tauernes, but w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> fighting in the fields: not trimmed with cloth of gold or silkes, but loden with armoure &amp; weapons: not praunsing their palfreis, but discouering the ambushmentes: not sleaping vntill none, but watching al night: not by auauncing him of his apparaile and handsomnes, but for his stout couragiousnes: not banketing his frends, but assaulting his enemies: though a knight do these things, yet he ought to consider that it is vanitye and folish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But seing the world hath placed honour in such a vaine thyng, &amp; that they can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto it by none other way, the yong aduenturous gentlmen ought to employe therunto their strength, with stout courage, to atchieue to some great actes worthy of
<pb facs="12"/>
renowne For in the end when the warre is iustly begonne, and that in defence of their countrey: they ought to reioyce more of him that dieth in the hands of his enemies: thē of him which liueth accompanied with vices. It is a great shame and dishonour to men of armes, &amp; yong gentlemen being at home, to heare the prayse of them whych be in the warres, for the yong gentlemen ought not to thinke it honour for hym to heare or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the newes of others? but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> others shuld declare the vertuous dedes of him. O how many are they in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world this day puffed vp with pride, &amp; not very wise) which stil prate of great renowne, &amp; yet passe their life w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> smal honesty. For our predecessours foughte in the field with their launces, but yong men now a dayes fight at the table with their tongues. Admit that al vaine men desire, &amp; procure to leaue a memory of their vanity: yet they ought to enterpryse such thyngs in their life, wherby they might winne a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous renowne (&amp; not a perpetual shame) after their death. For ther are many departed, which haue left such memory of their works as moueth vs rather to pitie their folye, than to enuy their vertue. I aske those that read or heare this thynge, if they wil be in loue wyth <hi>Nembroth</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first tiraunt: with <hi>Semiramis,</hi> which sinned with her owne son: with <hi>Antenor,</hi> that betrayed <hi>Troy</hi> his countrey: with <hi>Medea,</hi> that slew her children: w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Tarquine</hi> that enforced <hi>Lucretia:</hi> with <hi>Brutus,</hi> that slew <hi>Cesar:</hi> wyth <hi>Silla,</hi> that shed so much bloud: with <hi>Catilina,</hi> that played the tiraunt in his countrey: with <hi>Iugurtha,</hi> that strangled his bretherne: with <hi>Caligula</hi> that comitted incest with his sisters: with <hi>Nero</hi> that killed his mother: wyth <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> that robbed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> temples: with <hi>Domitian,</hi> that in nothing delighted so much, as by straunge hands to put men to death, and to dryue away flies wyth his owne hands Smal is the nomber of those that I haue spoken, in respect of those which I could recite: of whom I dare say &amp; affirme, that if I had bene as they, I cannot tel what I would haue done, or what I should haue desired: but this I know, it would haue bene more paynes to me, to haue wonne y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> infamy that they haue wonne, then to haue lost the lyfe that they haue lost, It profyteth hym lytle, to haue his ponds ful of fish, &amp; his parkes ful of deere, whych knoweth neyther how to hunte, nor how to fysh. I meane to shew by this, that it profiteth a man lytle to be in great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, if he be not estemed, nor honored in the same. For to attayne to honour, wysedome is requisite: &amp; to kepe it, pacience is necessarye. Wyth great consyderacions wyse men ought to enterpryse daungerous thyngs. For I assure them they shal neuer winne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but wher they vse to recouer slaunder. Returnyng therfore to our matter (Pui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt prynce) I sweare &amp; durst vndertake, that you rather desyre perpetual renowne through death: then any idell rest in this life. And hereof I do not merueile, for ther are some that shal alwayes declare the prowesses of good prynces, &amp; others which wyl not spare to open the vyces of euyl tiraunts. For although your imperial estate is much, &amp; your catholike person deserueth more, yet I beleue wyth my hart, &amp; se with these eyes, that your thoughts are so highly bent vnto aduenturous dedes, &amp; your hart so coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to set vpon them, that your maiestie litle estemeth the inheritaunce of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessours, in respect of that you hope to gaine, to leaue to your successours. A captaine asked <hi>Iulius Cesar</hi> (as he declareth in his commentaries) why he trauailed in the winter in so hard frost, &amp; in the sommer in such extreme heate, He aunswered: I wyl do what lyeth in me to do, and afterward let the fatal destinies do what they can. For the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt knyght that gyueth in battayle thonset, ought more to be estemed: then fickle fortune, wherby the victory is obtayned, sins fortune gyueth the one, &amp; aduenture gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the other. These words are spoken like a stout &amp; valyaunt captayne of Rome. Of how many prynces do we read, whom trulye I muche lament to see, what flatteries they haue herd wyth their eares being aliue: and to redde what slaunders they haue susteyned after their death. Prynces and great lords shold haue more regard to that, whych is spoken in their absence: then vnto that which is done in their presence. Not to that whych they heare, but to that whych they would not heare: not to that whiche they tel them but to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which they would not be told of: not to that is wryten vnto them being aliue, but to that which is wryten of them after their death: not to those that tell them lyes, but to those whych (if they durst) would tel them trouth. For men manye
<pb facs="12"/>
times refrayne not their tongues, for that subiects be not credited: but because y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prince in his auctority is suspected. The noble &amp; vertuous prince, shold not flit from the trouth wherof he is certified: neyther with flateryes &amp; lyes should he suffer himselfe to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but to examine himselfe, &amp; se whether they serue him with trouth, or deceiue hym with lyes. For ther is no better witnes &amp; iudge, of truth, &amp; lyes: then is a mans owne conscience. I haue spoken al this, to thintent your maiesty myght know, that I wil not serue you, wyth that you should not be serued. That is, to shew my selfe in my wryting a flaterer. For it wer neither mete nor honest, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> flateries into the eares of such a noble prynce shold enter: neither y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> out of my mouth (which teach the deuine truth) such vaine tales should issue. I say, I had rather be dispraysed for trew speaking, then to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for flatery &amp; lieng. For of truth, in your highnes it shold be much lightnes to heare them, &amp; in my basenes great wickednes to inuent them. Now againe folowing our pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pose I say, the historyes greatly commend <hi>Licurgus,</hi> that gaue lawes to the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians. Numa Pompilius,</hi> that honoured and adourned the churches. <hi>Marcus Marcellus,</hi> that had pitye on those whych were ouercome. <hi>Iulius Cesar,</hi> that forgaue his enemyes. <hi>Octauius,</hi> that was so welbeloued of the people. <hi>Alexander,</hi> that gaue rewards and gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to al men. <hi>Hector</hi> the <hi>Troyane,</hi> because he was so valiaunt in warres. <hi>Hercules</hi> the <hi>Thebane,</hi> because he emploied his strength so wel. <hi>Vlisses</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Grecian,</hi> because he aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured himselfe in so many daungers. <hi>Pirrhus</hi> king of <hi>Epirotes,</hi> because he inuented so many engins <hi>Catullus Regulus,</hi> because he suffered so many torments. <hi>Titus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, because he was father to the <hi>Orphanes. Traianus,</hi> because he edified sumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; goodly buildings. The good <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> because he knew more thē al they. I do not say that it is requisyte for one prynce in these dayes, to haue in him all those qualyties: but I dare be bold to affirme this, that euen as it is vnpossible for one prince to folow al: so likewise it is a great slaunder for him to folow none. We do not require princes to do al that they can, but to apply themselues to do some thing that they ought And I speake not without a cause, that whych I haue sayd before, For if princes did oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy themselues, as they ought to do: they shoulde haue no tyme to be vycious, <hi>Plynie</hi> saith in an epistle, that the great <hi>Cato,</hi> called <hi>Censor,</hi> did were a ring vpon his fynger, wherin was wryten these wordes, <hi>Esto amicus vnius, &amp; inimicus nullius,</hi> which is, be frend to one, &amp; enemy to none. He that would depely consider these few words, shal find therin many graue sentences. And to apply this to my purpose, I saye, the prince that would wel gouerne his common weal: shew to al equal iustyce: desire to possesse a quiet lyfe: to get among al a good fame: &amp; that coueteth to leaue of hymselfe a perpetual me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory: ought to embrace the vertues of one, and to reiect the vices of al. I alow it verye wel that princes should be equal, yea &amp; surmount many: but yet I aduise theym, not to employ their force, but to folow one. For oftētimes it chaunseth, that many, which sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselues in their life to excel al, when they are dead are scarcely found equal to any. Though man hath done much, &amp; blased what he can: yet in the ende he is but one, one mind, one power, one byrth, one life, and one death. Then sithen he is but one, let no man presume to know more then one. Of al these good princes which I haue named in the rowle of iustice, the last was <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> to thintent that he should weaue his webbe. For suppose we read of many prynces that haue compyled notable things, the whych are to be redde and knowen: but al that <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> sayd, or dyd is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be knowen, &amp; necessary to be folowed. I do not meane this prynce in his heathen law, but in hys vertuous dedes. Let vs not staye at hys belyef: but let vs embrace the good that he did For compare many chrystians wyth some of the heathen, &amp; loke howe farre we leaue them behynd in faith: so farre they excel vs in vertuous works. Al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> old prynces in times past, had som phylosophers to their familiars, as <hi>Alexander, Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi> King <hi>Darius, Herodotus. Augustus, Pisto. Pompeius, Plauto. Titus, Plinie. Adrian, Secundus. Traian, Plutarchus. Anthonius, Apolonius. Theodotius, Claudius. Seuerus, Fabatus.</hi> Fynally I say, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> philosophers then had such authority in princes palaces: that children acknowledged them for fathers and fathers reuerenced them as maysters. These sage mē wer aliue in the cōpany of princes: but the good <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> (whose
<pb facs="13"/>
doctrine is before your maiestie) is not aliue, but dead. Yet therfore that is no cause why his doctrine shold not be admitted. For it may be (paraduenture) that this shal profit vs more, which he wrate with his hands, then that which others spake with their tongues. <hi>Plutarche</hi> sayth, in the time of Alexander the great, <hi>Aristotle</hi> was aliue, and <hi>Homere</hi> was dead. But let vs see how he loued the one, &amp; reuerenced the other: for of truth hee slept alway with <hi>Homers</hi> booke in his hands, &amp; waking he red the same with hys eyes, &amp; alwayes kept the doctrine therof in his memory, &amp; layed (when he rested) the booke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der his head. The which priuiledge <hi>Aristotle</hi> had not, who at al times cold not be heard, &amp; much lesse at al seasons be beleued: so that <hi>Alexander</hi> had <hi>Homere</hi> for his frend, and <hi>Aristotle</hi> for a maister. Other of these phylosophers wer but simple men: but our <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius,</hi> was both a wyse phylosopher, and a valiaunt prynce: and therfore reason would he should be credited before others. For as a prince he wyl declare the troubles, &amp; as a phylosopher he wil redresse them. Take you therefore (Puisaunt Prince) this wise phylosopher and noble emperour, for a teacher in your youth, for a father in your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, for a captayne general in your warres, for a guide in your iourneys, for a frend in your affayres, for an example in your vertues, for a maister in your sciences for a pure whyte in your desyres, and for equal matche in your deedes.</p>
   <p>I wil declare vnto you the lyfe of an other beinge a heathen, and not the lyfe of an other being a chrystian. For how much glory this heathen prince had in this world, being good and vertuous: so much paynes your maiestie shal haue in the other, if you shalbe wicked and vycious. Behold, behold noble prince, the lyfe of this Emperour, &amp; you shal se how clere he was in his iudgement, how vpright in hys iustyce, howe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspect in hys life, how louing to his frends, how pacient in his troubles, how he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled with hys enemies, how seuere agaynst Tyraunts, how quyet among y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> quiet, how great a frend to the sage, and louer of the simple, how aduenturous in his warres, and amyable in peace, and aboue al thinges, how high in words, and profound in sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. Many tymes I haue bene in doubt with my selfe whether the Eternal maiesty (which gyueth vnto you princes the temporal maiestie, to rule aboue al other in power and authorytie) did exempt you that are princes, more from humaine frayltye: then he did vs that be but subiects: and at the last I knew he did not. For I see euen as you are chyldren of the world, so you do lyue according to the world. I see euen as you trauaile in the world: so you can know nothing but things of the world. I se because you liue in the fleshe, that you are subiect to the myseryes of the fleshe. I see though for a tyme you prolong your lyfe: yet at the last you are brought to your graue. I see your trauaile is great, and that within your gates there dwelleth no rest. I se you are cold in the wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and hote in the sommer. I se that hunger feeleth you, and thirst troubleth you, I se your frendes forsake you, and your ennemyes assault you. I se that you are sadde, and lacke ioy. I se you are sicke, and be not wel serued. I see you haue muche and yet that which you lacke is more. What wil ye se more, seyng that prince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> die? O noble princes &amp; great Lordes, syns you must die, and become wormes meat, why do you not in your lyfe tyme serche for good counsayle? If the prynces and noble men commit an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rroure no man dare chastice them, wherfore they stand in greater nede of aduyse &amp; counsaile. For the trauailer who is out of his waye, the more he goeth foreward, the more he er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe. If the people do amisse, they ought to be punyshed: but if the prince erre, hee shoulde bee admonished, And as the Prynce wyl the people shoulde at his handes haue punyshment: so it is reason that he at their hands should receyue counsayle.</p>
   <p>For as the wealthe of the one dependeth on the wealthe of the other: soo trulye if the prince bee vycious, the people can not be vertuous. If youre maiestie wyl pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshe your people with words, commaund them to prynt this present worke in their harts. And if your people would serue your hyghnes with their aduise: let them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse beseche you to reade ouer this booke. For therin the subiectes shal fynd how they may amende, and you Lordes shal se al that you ought to do, wdether this presente worke be profytable, or noo, I wyll not that my penne shal declare: but they whyche reede it shall iudge.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>For we aucthours take paines to make and translate, &amp; others for vs vse to giue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and sentence, From my tender yeres vntil this present, I haue liued in the world, occupieng my selfe, in reading and studieng humaine &amp; deuyne bookes, and although I confesse my debilitie to be such, that I haue not reade so much as I might, nor studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed so much as I ought: yet not withstandinge al that I haue red, hath not caused me to muse so muche, as the doctrine of <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> hath, sith that in the mouth of an heathen, god hath put such a great treasor. The greatest part of al his workes were in Greke: yet he wrote also many in latin. I haue drawen this out of greke throughe the helpe of my frends, &amp; afterwards out of latin into our vulgare tongue by the trauaile of my hands. Let al men iudge what I haue suffred in drawing it out of Greke into la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, out of the latin into the vulgar, and out of a plaine vulgar, into a swete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt style. For that banket is not counted sumptuous, vnlesse ther be both pleasaunt meates, and sauory sauces. To cal sentences to mynd, to place the wordes, to examine languages, to correct sillables: what swette I haue suffred in the hote sommer, what bytter cold in the sharpe wynter, what abstinence from meates when I desired to eate, what watching in the night whan I would haue slept, what cares I haue suffred in steed of rest that I might haue enioyed: let other proue, if me they wyl not credite. The intencion of my painful trauailes, I offer to the deuine maiestie vpon my knees, &amp; to youre highnesse (noble prince) I presente thys my worke, and humbly beseche god, that the doctrine of this booke may be as profitable vnto you, and the common wealth in your lyfe: as it hath ben to me tedious, &amp; hinderaunce to my health. I haue thought it good to offer to your maiestye the effect of my laboures, thoughe you peraduenture wyl lytle regard my paines: for the requyting of my trauayle, and reward of my good wyl, I requyre nought els of your highnes, but that the rudenesse of my vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the basenes of my stile, the smalnes of my eloquence, the euil order of my senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the vanitie of my words, be no occasion, why so excellent and goodly a worke shold be lytle regarded. For it is not reason, that a good horse should be the lesse este<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for that the ryder knoweth not how to make hym ronne hys carrier. I haue done what I could doe, doe you now that you ought to doe, in gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge to this present worke grauytye, and to me the interpretor thereof aucthority. I saye no more, but humbly besech god to mayntayne your estimacion and power in earth: and that you maye afterwarde enioye the fruicion of hys deuyne presence in heauen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>