<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull Sir Iohn Shurley Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of peace for the County of Sussex; and to the Lady Dorothy his wife: together with the Right Worshipfull Sir Giles Ouersberry Knight, and to the Lady Anne his wife: I. G. wisheth increase of sauing knowledge in this life, and the frui∣tion and enioyment of Eternall glory in the life to come for euer heereafter.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120492_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11498</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120492</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull Sir Iohn Shurley Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of peace for the County of Sussex; and to the Lady Dorothy his wife: together with the Right Worshipfull Sir Giles Ouersberry Knight, and to the Lady Anne his wife: I. G. wisheth increase of sauing knowledge in this life, and the frui∣tion and enioyment of Eternall glory in the life to come for euer heereafter.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians profession, or A treatise of the grounds and principles of diuinity : by way of question and answer. In which all the chiefe grounds of religion are so plainely proued and explained by the Word of God, as that the meanest capacitie may by reading vnderstand the same</title>
                 <author>I. G.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Dever (Dewer), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 97, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Sir <hi>Iohn Shurley</hi> Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of peace for the County of <hi>Sussex;</hi> and to the Lady <hi>Dorothy</hi> his wife: together with the Right Worshipfull Sir <hi>Giles Ouersberry</hi> Knight, and to the Lady <hi>Anne</hi> his wife: <hi>I. G.</hi> wisheth increase of sauing knowledge in this life, and the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and enioyment of Eternall <hi>glory in the life to come for euer heereafter.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfuls, it behooueth all people of what calling, state, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition soeuer, to giue all diligence to acquaint themselues with the will of God reuealed in his Word; and as with the VVord of God in generall, so to know God and our selues in particular, (according to the word of God.) The want of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which, is the cause of all errors, both in iudgement and practise: neither is it suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that we endeauour our selues to attaine to the knowledge of the same in some measure, but
<pb facs="3"/>also that we indeauour to instruct others in the knowledge of the same, especially those whom God hath committed to our charge. Wherfore since it hath pleased the Lord in some measure to acquaint mee with his will reuealed in his word; and to call me to haue charge of those few of mine owne family, I indeauoured to instruct them in the word of God, according to the measure of knowledge which the Lord hath giuen me. And obseruing by experience, that a set forme of Catechising vpon the grounds of Religion was most profitable and lesse labour, I resolued with my selfe, to write downe at such times as I had best oportunity, in regard of other imployments, the chiefe heads and grounds of Diuinity in the plainest manner and method that possibly I could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise: not that I did either despise or disregard those Catechismes which are already printed &amp; set forth by many reuerend and learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, in vsing of which I might haue saued that labour: but because I desired to haue all the grounds of Diuinity, not onely deliuered as neere as possibly may be, in the very words and phrases of the Scripture, and the quotations of the Scriptures for euery ground: but also that the words of euery Scripture should be written downe, which are pertinent to the prouing of euery grownd, with the explication of such
<pb facs="3"/>things as might seeme to be darke and obscure to the vnderstanding of the meanest capacity: the which order I could not finde in any printed Catechisme; the consideration of which, moued me the rather to put my resolution into practise; the which I began long since, not hauing the least thought that euer it should haue come to the presse, as the Lord who is the searcher of all hearts knoweth. But when I had finished the same, it grew to a farre greater volume then I expected. Afterwards some of my friends that were conuersant at my house desired cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of the same in writing, the which I knew by experience, would bee both troublesome and tedious; yet being desirous to pleasure my friends in what I might, preferring a publike good before a priuate, I asked a Printer who was a friend of mine, whether hee thought he could haue the same authorized to be printed shewing him the coppie; he was desirous both to get it authorized, and to haue the printing of it. Whereupon I tooke aduice of some of my friends, whose iudgements I preferred before mine owne, shewing them the coppie, who gaue me incouragement concerning the same: then I gaue it into the Printers hand to get it authorized if Authority should thinke it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, although I confesse I did not expect that it would haue beene authorized: but how euer,
<pb facs="4"/>it was authorized contrary to my expectation: and therefore I was willing to admit the same vnto the presse, although I confesse that there are many printed Catechismes se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> forth by many reuerend learned men to whom I am farre infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, and whose workes are more learned and eminent: yet considering of the great vse that now at this present there is of Catechismes in regard of the order of Catechising inioyned by publique Authority ouer all England: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that diners people are of diuers minds and opinions, some liking and approuing of one Catechisme, and some of another: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering withall, that all people generally are affected with new bookes, I aduentured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the same to publike view, hoping that it will be profitable vnto some, and then I know, I shall not lose my labour. Howsoeuer, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that the ignorant may bee instructed thereby: and that all in generall which reade the same, may be furthered, built vp, strengthened &amp; confirmed in the truth, and armed against all errors and false doctrine; the which my poore labours, I make bold to dedicate vnto your Worships: And although I confesse it may seeme strange vnto your Worships, that I should presume to present to you a Treatise of the first principles of religion; whom God hath indued with so great learning and wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="4"/>yet I was theereby the more encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged thereunto, both because that I conceiue that you are thereby the better able to iudge and discerne of the matter contained in the same: and also because it is the glory of a wise man to passe by infirmities, as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith; and I was the rather moued thereunto because I desired to giue this testimonie of my true thankefulnesse for those testimonies of loue which I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from you, and especially vnto you right worshipfull in the first place vnto whom I am ingaged in a double respect; first, in regard of your ancient and long continued loue vnto my Parents; Secondly, in regard of the continuance of the same vnto their children, and vnto my selfe in particular. And especially for that first testimony of your loue, when you promised in my stead, that I should professe the Faith of Christ crucified; the which profession of my faith, I publikely declare in this treatise follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto all in generall, and vnto your selfe in particular. Secondly, as a testimony of that vnfained loue I beare vnto you all, and that not onely in regard of those outward bonds and ties of those many fauours receiued from you, and that naturall affection which I beare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, in that I was of a child brought vp among you, but principally in regard of your pious zeale and forwardnesse in Religion which
<pb facs="5"/>I haue obseru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> to both in you and your vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ladyes. thirdly, because I am perswaded by obser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing your worships care in your fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that you will make some good vse of the same. Lastly, I presumed to dedicate the same vnto your worships, and your Ladyes ioyntly together, both because of that neere relation that is betweene you, and also because of my selfe being so much obliged vnto you, humbly crauing pardon for this my boldnesse; and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly suing that these my poore labours may find acceptance: I commit both you and all of yours vnto the blessing and protection of Almighty God, vnto whom my prayers shall euer bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected for your continuall ioy and comfort in the inioyment of all out ward mercies, so farre as in mercy hee shall see best for you; and for your continuall growth and increase in the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and assurance of his free grace and fauour here, and the inioyment of euer lasting glory for euer hereafter; and so I reft</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to command in what I may, <hi>I. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>