<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE LORD DENNY, BARON OF WALTHAM, MY SINGVLAR GOOD PATRON; All Grace and Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr44_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE LORD DENNY, BARON OF WALTHAM, MY SINGVLAR GOOD PATRON; All Grace and Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="437"/>
   <pb n="841" facs="437"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE LORD <hi>DENNY,</hi> BARON OF <hi>WALTHAM,</hi> MY SINGVLAR GOOD PATRON; <hi>All Grace and Happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIght Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know, and in all humility confesse, how weake my Discourse is, and how vnworthy of this diuine subiect, which J haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; which if an Angell from Heauen should say hee could sufficiently comment vpon, J should distrust him: Yet this let me say (without any vaine boasting) that these thoughts (such as they are) through the blessing of <hi>GOD,</hi> J haue wouen out of my selfe, as holding it (after our Sauiours rule) better to giue, than to receiue. It is easier to heape together large volumes of others labours, then to worke out lesser of our owne: and the suggestion of one new thought, is better then many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated.</p>
   <p>This part (which together with the Author is yours) shall present to your Lordship, the busiest of all the Patriarks, together
<pb n="842" facs="438"/> with his tryalls, and successe: wherein you shall see <hi>Esau</hi> stripped by fraud, of that which he willingly sold, <hi>Iacobs</hi> hard aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for the blessing, and no lesse hard seruices for his wiues and substance, his dangerous encounters ending ioyfully, the ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of his onely daughter, seconded with the trecherous murder of his sonnes, <hi>Iudahs</hi> wrong to <hi>Thamar</hi> repayed by his owne vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: <hi>Iosephs</hi> sale, imprisonment, honour, pietie; The sinne of his brethren well bestowed, well answered. J so touch at the vses of all these, as one that knowes, it is easie to say more, and impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to say enough. <hi>GOD</hi> giue a blessing to my endeuours, and a pardon to my weakenesse, to your Lordship an encrease of his graces, and perfection of all happinesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships humbly and</hi> officiously deuoted in all dutie, <hi>IOS. HALL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>