<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ERRATA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120599_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02484</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12611</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ERRATA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie of the povver and prouidence of God in the gouernment of the world. Or An examination and censure of the common errour touching natures perpetuall and vniuersall decay : diuided into foure bookes: whereof the first treates of this pretended decay in generall, together with some preparatiues thereunto. The second of the pretended decay of the heauens and elements, together with that of the elementary bodies, man only excepted. The third of the pretended decay of mankinde in regard of age and duration, of strength and stature, of arts and wits. The fourt of this pretended decay in matter of manners, together with a large proofe of the future consummation of the world from the testimony of the gentiles, and the vses which we are to draw from the consideration thereof. By G.H. D.D</title>
                 <author>Hakewill, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 392, 395-473, 5 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>ERRATA.</head>
   <p>Pag. 5. lin. 13. read <hi>Psammeticus,</hi> p. 18. l. 16. r. thought. p. 26. l. 27. r. <hi>miror.</hi> p. 27. l. 3. r. words. p 31. l. 5. r. in antiquitie. p. 45. l. 13. r. almost halfe a pound. p. 62. l 40. r. are. p. 73. l. 17. r. commenteth. p. 80. l. 42. r. <hi>mentitus.</hi> p. 81. l. 17. r. be diminished. p. 84. l. 15. r <hi>aestate</hi> p. 90. l. 41. r. speakes p. 95. l. 2. r. about. p. 100. l. 34. r. religion. p. 101. l. 31. r. <hi>incommoda.</hi> p. 104. l. 5. r. <hi>Ex. ibid.</hi> l. 12. r. milke. p. 112. l. 10. r. drought. p. 118. l. 40. r. better. p. 124. l. 7. r. <hi>naturalis.</hi> p. 129. l. 27. r. <hi>Blancanus.</hi> p. 133. l. 37. r. <hi>Sylvine.</hi> p. 136. l. 19. r. better cheape. with. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. vlt. r. his. p. 144. l. 26. r. touching. p. 145 l. 4. r. reason. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 26. r. mortall, that if hee sinned not, hee could not. p. 153. l. 4. r. <hi>Archepius.</hi> p, 163. l. vlt. r. nineteene. p. 1. 7. l. 42. r. namely. p. 176. l.. 10. r. the. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 11. r, that. p. 191. l. 21. r. <hi>regum.</hi> p. 210. l. 12. r. <hi>Yol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> p. 234. l. 41. r. <hi>Fuchsius.</hi> p. 241. l. 44. r. <hi>Polyaenus.</hi> p. 269. l. 24. r. <hi>innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiles.</hi> p. 277. l. 37. r. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 285. l. 8. r. lawmaker. p. 338. l. 10. in marg. r. <hi>c.</hi> 22. p. 385. l. 19. r. <hi>immundis.</hi> p. 403. l. 47. r. daughter. p. 413. l. 4. r. <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</hi> p. 415. l. 16. r. venturous. p. 418. l, penult. r. by the Romans. p. 419. l. 21: r: except: p: 443: l: 31: r: <hi>terras: ibid</hi> l: 39: r: nought: p: 448: l: 35: r: infinitely in their: p: 401: l: 29: r: of.</p>
   <p>These are the greatest I haue met with, not doubting but some of consequence haue escaped me, and for those of lesser note I haue passed them ouer, desiring the reader if he will not take the paines to amend al, yet he would be pleased to set these foure or fiue right: p: 45: lin: 13: p: 104: l: 12: p: 136: l: 19: p: 145: l: 26: p: 163: l: vlt:</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>