<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, ADAM Lord Vicount LOFTVS of Elie, Lord Chancellour of Ireland, and one of his Maiesties Iustices for the gouernment of this Kingdome.</title>
           <author>Olmstead, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120808_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08488</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18811</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, ADAM Lord Vicount LOFTVS of Elie, Lord Chancellour of Ireland, and one of his Maiesties Iustices for the gouernment of this Kingdome.</title>
                 <author>Olmstead, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sions teares leading to ioy: or The vvaters of Marah sweetned : First preached at Clonenagh in the Queenes County in seuerall sermons, and now published for the benefite of the Church. By Ri: Olmstead, minister of Gods word, and Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Olmstead, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 245, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE</hi> RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, <hi>ADAM</hi> Lord Vicount <hi>LOFTVS</hi> of <hi>Elie,</hi> Lord Chancellour of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>one of his Maiesties Iustices</hi> for the gouernment <hi>of this Kingdome.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Humbly beseech You to accept this poore model of my labours, as did <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> a cup of cold water at the hands of silly <hi>Synaetus,</hi> euen from me, the meanest of <hi>Leuie</hi> his sonnes: It shall bee much honoured if it please your Lordship to pardon my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption,
<pb facs="3"/>and to afford your patronage thereunto.</p>
   <p>The subiect is worthy your Lordships consideration in it selfe, if the euill cooking of it by my vnskilfulnesse, detract not from the lustre thereof; but if I had inioyed either that <hi>Academick</hi> leisure,
<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of some <hi>Amaraean</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, or conference with men of excellent both parts &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I might haue produced a more cōpleat <hi>Minerua;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pressed with the care of a large family depēding (though not vpō tent-making, as <hi>Paul</hi>) yet vpon my industrie, now these seuen yeares, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny annuall revenue from the Church, besides my weekely labours in preaching too, and catechizing my people, denyes me to furnish it as I would. If I bee asked, why I publish a
<pb facs="3"/>Treatise of this subiect:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.18.</note> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere with S. <hi>Iohn, these are the last times,</hi> wherein our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our sayth,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12.</note>
      <hi>Because iniquity shall abound, the loue of many shall waxe cold.
<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> Aristippus</hi> and <hi>Aes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinus</hi> being fallen out, one asked the other, <hi>what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of their friendship,</hi> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer was, <hi>it was asleepe, but hee would awake it.</hi> Now Right Honourable, seeing the most lye like the people of <hi>Laish,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iudg.</hi> 18.7.</note> wretchlesly and securely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their lees, that neither our owne sinnes, the sinnes of the times, afflictions of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God abroad, nor the consideration of the signes and symptomes of Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, dependant or powred out vpon vs (especially spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall vengeance at home) can awaken, I thinke it my duty, to make an experiment by this
<pb facs="4"/>poore Worke to stir vp and prouoke this frozen age to humble thēselues before God in the sense both of their own &amp; the sins of others.</p>
   <p>This point (my much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lord (though sacred, yet a paradoxe and <hi>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aigma</hi> to nature, and the world, <hi>the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man not perceiuing the things that bee of God, because they are spiritually discerned.</hi> I may truely apply that saying of <hi>Themistocles</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> who beiog exiled his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Country, &amp; being better intertained in the <hi>Persian</hi> Court, said; <hi>I had perished, if I had not perished:</hi> that whereas this simple World are opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, that to mourne vnder the sense of sin, is most vncō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, &amp; the way to depriue thēselues of all solace &amp; joy, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery true Christian is assured,
<pb facs="4"/>and may say, <hi>perijssem si non pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijssem,</hi> that if he had not sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, he had forfeited his joy and his soule also.</p>
   <p>Right Honourable, In your absence &amp; affliction, this Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth &amp; Church of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> doubting of the successe &amp; issue, &amp; experimentally sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the want of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships indefatigable labours in the execution of justice impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially to al, many of her faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful children were not wanting in their daily supplications to God, waiting your Lordships happy return, as for the
<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Iob</hi> 29.23.</note> raine, gaue me assur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ce of Gods spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall blessing to honour your Lordship; as <hi>Ambrose</hi> said to <hi>Moni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a</hi> the mother of <hi>August:
<note place="margin">Non potest peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum filius</note> the child of so many prayers and teares cannot possibly perish;</hi> the most High hath pleased to heare their prayers (blessed be
<pb facs="5"/>his most sacred name) in your Honours safe returne, with a largesse of honour. Faile not then (my deare Lord) the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the spouse of <hi>Christ,</hi> and that trust which the most High and his Majesty hath cōmitted to you to be a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full seruant,
<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2.</note> as <hi>Moses</hi> in the house of God, for the eyes of men are not onely cast vpon you (my noble Lord) and the <hi>whole land intent to be hold your life,</hi>
      <note place="margin">In re vnum cunctorum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos &amp;c. Hier. ad de.</note> but God &amp; Angels expect your faithful seruice, to which end my daily praiers shalbe to the most omnipotent, that hee wil not faile you with his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; being assured that your Lordsh:
<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> intēds to imitate that saying of <hi>Alexāder, It profiteth not to possesse all things, &amp; to do nothing,</hi> as appeares by your Lordships painefull industrie (in the judgement of all that behold your insupportable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs
<pb facs="5"/>beyond humane strēgth, I am bold to exhort your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in the words of an <hi>Apostle, (not to be weary of wel doing, for in the end you shall receiue the crown, if you faint not:</hi> assuring my selfe that that Proverbe so oft inculcated by <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Cicile</hi> wil for euer be your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position:
<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>That none who spake freely to him, did importune him, or was vnseasonable.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus crauing pardon of my boldnes in dedicating this tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise to your Lo: to which my affection are loue and duty to your Ho: the zeal of the glory of God, &amp; the care of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity of this church &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōwealth, with the particular comfort of hūbled &amp; afflicted consciences, hath transported me: I hūbly beseech your Lo: &amp; this whole church, to accept this poore mite at my handes, most hūbly &amp; heartily intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="6"/>the most high to water it with the dew of his blessing, who only can make the labor both of minister and people fruitful: <hi>Rebeeca</hi> may cook the venison, but <hi>Isaak</hi> must giue the blessing: wee, nay <hi>Paul</hi> can but speake to the eare, it is the Almighty that must speake to the heart &amp; conscience by his Spirit, and <hi>perswade Iapheth to dwel in the tents of Shem.</hi> Thus wishing my much esteemed Lod, to your selfe, your noble Lady, &amp; posterity, not onely with the Philosophers <hi>prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, physitiās lēgth of daies with health, the cōmon people ioy, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mās safty,</hi> &amp; increase of honor, but with that blessed <hi>Apo. Paul, the peace of God which passeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstāding,</hi> with eternall glory in the highest heauēs, I remain</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships in all humble seruice</hi>
RI: OLMSTEAD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>