<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MVCH HONORED LADIES, the Ladie ANNE CLEERE, and the Ladie ANNE PINCH, and the Ladie IONE HERICKE: N. Bifield wisheth all increase of the true grace of Christ, and the blessed fruition of the glory of God in heauen.</title>
           <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120511_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17397</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4222</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120511</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MVCH HONORED LADIES, the Ladie ANNE CLEERE, and the Ladie ANNE PINCH, and the Ladie IONE HERICKE: N. Bifield wisheth all increase of the true grace of Christ, and the blessed fruition of the glory of God in heauen.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The marrovv of the oracles of God. Or, diuers treatises : containing directions about sixe of the waightiest things can concerne a Christian in this life. by N. Bifield, late preacher of Gods Word at Isleworth in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meredith, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stephens, Philemon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 101+ pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE MVCH HONORED LADIES, the Ladie ANNE CLEERE, and the Ladie ANNE PINCH, and the Ladie IONE HERICKE: <hi>N. Bifield wisheth all increase of the true grace of Christ, and the blessed fruition of the glory of God in heauen.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worthie Ladies,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Amentable are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he ruines, into which the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of men are generally fallen by their sinnes: which appeares especially by the waies men take in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse of their soule. The most men are cleane out of the way to heauen, and walke in by wayes
<pb facs="6"/>
of their owne, which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Scripture, The <hi>waies of the wicked;</hi> The <hi>waies of their owne hearts; Peruerse waies; Darke and slipperie wayes; The way of iniquity.</hi> All mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in that <hi>broad way that leadeth to destruction,</hi> being wholly ignorant of the <hi>way of life</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> yea, the most of them <hi>speake euill of the good way of God,</hi> and persecute it. Some there are, that are so farre enlightned, as not to like the common roade way of the multitude; and after some enquirie haue found them out <hi>wayes that seeme good in their owne eyes;</hi> and they are wonderfully well pleased with their course, but <hi>the issues of these wayes are death</hi> too, as well as the former. And the more is this
<pb facs="6"/>
danger increased vpon men, because the <hi>way of life is</hi> but <hi>one,</hi> and it is a <hi>narrow way,</hi> and hard to find, and may be <hi>sought</hi> by many, and yet <hi>not found.</hi> Yet this hope is left vnto forlorn men, that there is a way to heauen and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines: A <hi>way of righteousnesse</hi> and peace, a <hi>way of mercy and truth,</hi> a <hi>way of wisedome:</hi> A way that men may <hi>securely</hi> and safely walke in; a way, in which Christ will <hi>guide thē,</hi> God the Father will <hi>keepe them,</hi> and the holy Ghost <hi>leade them</hi> by the hand, and direct them in all the passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges thereof. Onely it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs <hi>to aske the way,</hi> with all importunitie, of God, and to attend vnto the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Word of God, &amp; apply our hearts, and suffer
<pb facs="7"/>
our selues to bee disposed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, that our eyes may see the saluation of God. And in particular wee must looke to three things: First, that if the Lord shew vs that mercy, to direct vs in the way, we must take heede that wee neglect not, or despise notthe care of walking in the way. Second ly, that with all diligence we auoide <hi>going about,</hi> and make <hi>straight stops to our feet.</hi> And thirdly, with all feare watch our selues, that we <hi>fal not</hi> off with <hi>the errors of the wicked,</hi> from the good way of God, and so our latter end be worse then our beginning.</p>
   <p>I haue vndertaken by the assistance of God, and the direction of this, blessed word, to single out the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest things I could finde in
<pb facs="7"/>
the Scriptures, concerning <hi>the entrance</hi> into the way of God, and those first <hi>path: which are called Holy.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> substance of these directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I haue digested into the Treatise following: which I dedicate vnto your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, as a testimonie of my thankfulnesse, for the respect you haue shewed vnto my Ministerie, both in your constant resort vnto it in the weeke dayes, while you li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in a neighbour Parish; and in that two of you are pleased to come to liue amongst vs, and so are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a part of my charge. As also to manifest to the world my obseruance of your Ladiships, for the good report you haue amongst the godly for the grace of
<pb facs="8"/>
Iesus Christ, and your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned loue of the truth. Beseeching your <hi>Acceptation, Perusall,</hi> and <hi>Patronage</hi> of these, I take my leaue, and commend your Ladiships to the <hi>God of Mercie</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> who guide, comfort, deliuer, sanctifie, and preserue you all vnto the day of Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships to be commanded in Iesus Christ,
N. BIFIELD.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <date>Febr. 12. 1619.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>