<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           <author>H., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120493_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11539</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 <author>H., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An abridgement of Christian perfection : Conteining many excellent precepts, &amp; aduertisments, touching the holy, and sacred mysticall diuinity. Written in Italian, by Fa. Achilles Galliardi of the Society of Iesus, &amp;translated into English, A.H. of the same society</title>
                 <author>Galliardi, Achilles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>216 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <p>
      <gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="2 pages">
         <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="16" facs="8"/>many aduises in the booke, (especially in the Chapters
of the second &amp; third Estate) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ere i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ught that the sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le must be content
to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rgo first all actiue
operat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on, and practise euen of
vertues themselues, and lastly to be depriued euen of the pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tue also so farr as it may seeme
sensible vnto the soule that it is her own work. And this to the end that
Gods will may be the pure, and only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of her will and workes
whatsoeuer; thou must beware in these, &amp; the like sentences, of two
seuerall doctrines or errors, wholy contrary to that which is beere intended.
The one, least thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that a soule being come to that estate, doth
not indeed work with her owne will, but that God then worketh all in her, so
that those workes be not really the act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ons of the soule, but of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe; which thing is both
false and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd The other error is, that a soule in this state of
Perfection should not doe any thing, but as seeing her self to be 
<pb n="17" facs="8"/>cleerly moued therunto by the will of God, and in a manner
compelled by the same to doe all her actions, so that she in the meane tyme
should be idle, vntill the feele this impulsion from God. This doctrine would
nourish slouth in the sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, yea and breed, if not bring forth, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy
also against the freedome of our wil, and against the necessitie of our
concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the grace of God: all which are not different only, but
contrary to the intentiō of the Author, as (besides the authority of the
<hi>Parisian</hi> Doctours who approued this booke, when it was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated
out of Italian, and set forth in their owne language) the diligent &amp;
impartiall Reader may also by himself easily discerne, if he mark wel
the whole discourse. For he shall find it here requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that one omit no
practise, or proofe of likely meanes, either in rooting out of euill, or in
planting of good habits. Also that all the rules, &amp; aduises of this
boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, are to be applied to euery mans estate <pb n="18" facs="9"/>and that he
omitting no part of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, doe practise the same, togeather with the
actions which his estate and institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te require. Lastly that this
<hi>Subtractiō</hi> of actiue and pass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue Will, touching the acts of vertue, is the worke only of God in
the soule, with which (when the soule doth perceaue it to be so) it must
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre as with the will of God, to will the same thing, as our dutie doth
bind vs. And this is no other thing then we find in daily practise, though
all doe not feele it a like, nor all follow this rule, as they should, when
they feele it. Ye happeneth vnto vs more or lesse whensoeuer any
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation by Gods appointment doth fall vpon vs, for in that case we
finde our sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues lesse apt then before to will, or worke any good, yea,
or to suffer the proceeding of that good (which before we desired) with any
contentment: and this desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may so increase, that it shall seeme
to vs, our desire carrieth vs wholy to the contrary of that we had
resolued. But all <pb n="19" facs="9"/>this is only in the inferiour part of
ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> soule to wit in our naturall
inclination, which for the time is left to it self, by <hi>Subtraction</hi>
of that effect, and fruit of grace by which it was before comforted,
strengthened, and enabled to performe good actions, and concurre to
supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues, with desire and delight: which to be the effectes
and fruits of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the Apostle teacheth, <hi>Galat. 5.22.</hi> when he
saith: <hi>Fructus autem spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus est charitas, gaudium, pax, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia
&amp;c.</hi> So that all this while gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is not diminished in the superiour
part of the soule, nor the vertues lesse perfect which are placed therin,
but only there-doundance, fruit, and effect of that grace is stopped, and
subtracted for the time, from the inferiour part, to increase the batta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le which the soule is to bane, and
the victory which it is to obtaine, by constantly conforming, and vniting her
will to Gods, notwithstanding that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased difficultie; yea by
renouncing <pb n="20" facs="10"/>her owne naturall will and inclination,
transforming the same into the will of God, and so saying with our
Sauiour Christ in the like case: <hi>Non mea, sed tua voluntas
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Pater:</hi> not my will, o Father, but thine be done. In whose
example we may see, that the practise of this point may stand with all
Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which could not be wanting in his actions. So that the scope of
this doctrine is not to make vs idle or remisse in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, nor to expect
that God should doe all in vs, and that our will should haue no part in the
action: but it requireth, that we doe coopera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e with Gods grace, and labour with all diligence, whilest we can.
And when by Gods ordinance we feele that our sensible forces do faile vs,
and that we are not now able to creep, who before were able to runne in the
wayes of God (as the Prophet saith, <hi>Psal. 118.32.</hi>) <hi>cùm
dilatater cor nostrum,</hi> whilest he dilated our hart with ioy and
comfort; we must then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <pb n="21" facs="10"/>our will to God, yea, and
be glad to transforme our weake will into his strength of goodnes, to vnite
our drop of water to his sea of graces, and to say with our actiue will
(though our incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations striue against it) that his will shall be ours, and
therfore that we desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re his will may be done with vs in all thinges,
howsoeuer our in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>our part doe, according to nature,
desire the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
   <p>This is the Perfection vnto which this Booke leadeth: the
practise wherof we may see both vsed, and declared by God to his beloued
Apostle, as may be gathered out of the first Chapter of the <hi>2. Epist. ad
Cor.</hi> and it is the highest which the soule can arriue vnto in this life.
For as the will of God is infinitly good, and euen goodnes it self, so the
nearer we come vnto it, the more we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to a good and perfect estate.
Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can there be, euen by imagination conceaued, a higher Perfection, or
grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="22" facs="11"/>happines, either in this world or the next, then
to be vnited vnto God, the fountaine of all goodnes. In this life it is to be
done by grace, and in the next by glorie. This
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>le Booke, gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le Reader, will lead thee to the one,
and thy dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent practise of what it teacheth, will bring thee to the
other.</p>
   <p>Christ IESVS gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt vs
grace to seeke this treasure with true desire, &amp; finding it, to vse
it to our best commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. We shall doe it the better, if we pray hartily for
one another, which I purpose to doe for all, that will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to
practise this Booke, &amp; do craue the like of them for my greater needs.
Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>