<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND truly Religious, PHILIP HERBERT, Earle of Montgomery, Baron of Sherland, and Knight of the most Honourable Order of the Garter; and to the most Vertuous and Zealously Religious Lady, the La. SVSAN, his most deere and louing Wife; and to those fiue blessed branches, their most sweet, gracious, and hopefull children, the Lord Charles Herbert, the Lady Anna-Sophia Herbert. Mr. Philip Herbert, Mr. William Herbert, and Mr. Iames Herbert; all grace and happinesse in this life, and eternall blessed∣nesse in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120026_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15447</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25719</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND truly Religious, PHILIP HERBERT, Earle of Montgomery, Baron of Sherland, and Knight of the most Honourable Order of the Garter; and to the most Vertuous and Zealously Religious Lady, the La. SVSAN, his most deere and louing Wife; and to those fiue blessed branches, their most sweet, gracious, and hopefull children, the Lord Charles Herbert, the Lady Anna-Sophia Herbert. Mr. Philip Herbert, Mr. William Herbert, and Mr. Iames Herbert; all grace and happinesse in this life, and eternall blessed∣nesse in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seuen goulden candlestickes houlding the seauen greatest lights of Christian religion : shewing vnto all men what they should beleeue, &amp; how they ought to walke in this life, that they may attayne vnto eternall life by Gr: Williams Doctor of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gryffith</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 468, 471-617, pages 596, pages 609, 618-744, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND truly Religious, PHILIP HERBERT, Earle of <hi>Montgomery,</hi> Baron of <hi>Sherland,</hi> and Knight of the most Honourable Order of the Garter; and to the most Vertuous and Zealously Religious Lady, the La. SVSAN, his most deere and louing Wife; and to those fiue blessed branches, their most sweet, gracious, and hopefull children, the Lord <hi>Charles Herbert,</hi> the Lady <hi>Anna-Sophia Herbert.</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Philip Herbert,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>William Herbert,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Iames Herbert;</hi> all grace and happinesse in this life, and eternall blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you seauen, I dedicate these seauen <hi>Golden Candlestickes;</hi> and to whom should I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the same, but to you? for in your house, and by your light I haue composed them; and God hath blessed you, not onely in making you great through the fauour of Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, but especially in making you good through the
<pb facs="5"/> im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mutable grace and fauour of himselfe which changeth not, and which hath planted his feare in your hearts, and diffused those graces into your soules, that doe infalliby accompany saluation, and make you to shine as you doe, for the sincerity of your profession in the truth of the Gospell, and the vprightnesse of your hearts, which haue bin euer seene void of all double courtly dealing, amongst a crooked and peruerse generation, whereof I had almost said, the greatest part is either basely filled with hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall flattery, or most pittifully blinded with idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latricall impiety; and as a sure pledge of his pure loue vnto your Honours, he hath giuen vnto you such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable gift, so many, so sweet, and so gracefull children, which for all good parts and endowments of nature, and for infallible signes of grace, I dare boldly say it, (and I may the rather say it, because, rather then any other, I doe more experimentally know it) God hath annointed aboue their fellowes,<note n="*" place="margin">Especially that worthily beloued child, my LORD <hi>CHARLES HERBERT;</hi> of whom for h s admired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, I could truly say, more then any that know him not, would ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily beleeue.</note> that neither you nor all yours can be sufficiently thankefull vnto God for them; so great a blessing it is, to haue so many, so many such Oliue-bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches round about your Table. And therfore as God hath blessed your Honors, and made you great lights to shine for godly zeale in this wicked declining world, and to be patternes of true piety vnto others round about you; So I doe assure my selfe, you will not disdaine to accept and peruse these my labours, which as a small expression of my vnfained thankefulnesse for those manifold testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of your loue and fauours vnto me, farre I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse beyond my deserts, I doe most syncerely dedicate vnto your Honours, for whose compleate happinesse my witnesse is in Heauen, that since first I belonged vnto you, I haue daily prayed vpon my bended knees; and I doe vnfainedly acknowledge that you deserue more from me, then I can performe, and haue performed more
<pb facs="5"/> vnto me, then I can any wayes deserue from you: And therefore I presumed to dedicate these Treatises vnto your Honours, not to shelter them from any stormes of maleuolent tongues, but to publish that thankefulnesse vnto the world, which my heart euer acknowledgeth to be due vnto you: For I know it is fit that whosoeuer publisheth any thing vnfit, should beare the whole bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of his owne fault, and whosoeuer ventureth to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in print, must expect the common lot of all Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to be variously censured of various dispositions; Some as <hi>Nebuzaradan</hi> burnt the Temple,<note place="margin">Greg. Cur. past. <hi>3.</hi> p. c. <hi>20.</hi> Nazian. in pacif. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> but kept the gold, will be content to take the matter, and yet blame the Author; others will reade it, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, not to better themselues, but to censure others; In all these I would neuer desire Patrone to defend mee, nor feare enemy to depraue me; for what is good will defend it selfe, and to flatter those whose pennes are silent, and their tongues alwayes babling, to condemne others in what they cannot mend themselues, were impiety, and to feare them imbecility; for to please all is vnpossible, and to indeauour it is folly: And therefore I hope you will receiue them as I tender them. They be not vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeming to be knowne by the greatest Monarches, for they containe not the smoaking fume of humane reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, nor the meandrian windings of Controuersiall subtilties, but the purest lights of all Christian Religion; for I saw that as the <hi>Athenians</hi> were euer desirous of nouelties, so to satisfie this Criticke age, affecting nothing so well as quiddities, too many men haue addrest their mindes to disputable Controuersies; and I found, though with griefe, that the Aduersaries on either side, and especially the Pontificials, as if there were not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies enough in Religion, doe often forge tenents out of their owne braynes, and impute them each one
<pb facs="6"/> against the other; and so each Aduersary striues to make the other say what indeed he abhorres to thinke; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it happeneth that a great part of disputations, being about imaginarie Controuersies, is but like a skirmishing in the ayre, which seemeth furious, but striketh no man; and is vainely spent to no purpose, but to increase Schisme, and to inuolue themselues within the thickets of inextricable labyrinths; because iarring and iangling about errours, they let passe the maine grounds of truth, and striuing to finde out new wayes, they doe quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the old way, which is the good way, and are become almost ignorant of the first and chiefest Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Such is the pollicie of Satan, to busie their heads about the lesse needfull Controuersies, thereby to make them the lesse diligent to inquire after the most necessary counsels of their saluation. And therefore considering with my selfe what the Apostle saith, that hee desired to know nothing but <hi>Iesus Christ, and him crucified;</hi> I haue applyed my selfe to treate of these ensuing Theames: I confesse my manner of handling them is like my selfe, plaine and homely, without any gorgeous garments of Rhetorical ornaments; because I euer desired to speak ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the edification of my hearers, then for the often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of my selfe; but I assure you the matter is like them from whom I receiued it, sound and good; fit to feede all those Christians that desire rather to haue their hungry soules fedde with the sincere milke of Gods Word, then their itching eares tickled with the inticing speech of mans wisedome: for they doe containe the knowledge of our selues, how poore and miserable we are become by sinne, the knowledge of the true and eternall God, and the knowledge of Iesus Christ, God and Man, then whom there is no greater, no better; which few lessons are alone able to make vs happy. I neede speake
<pb facs="6"/> no more of the worke, let it speake for me: I referre all to God, who esteemeth of our indeauours, not by their euent, but by our intent; but remembring that presenting your Honours with a Booke, I must not make a Booke of an Epistle, I onely desire you to accept these notes of a Schollers obseruation, who desires not so much to make himselfe knowne, as to acknowledge his duty to God, and his desire to doe him seruice, to extoll his name in Heauen, and not to gaine himselfe a name on Earth, and to haue all his thoughts and workes to honour Christ, or to be dishonoured himselfe for no Christian. So with my daily prayers for you and all yours, I humbly take my leaue and rest;</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours true seruant and most humble Chaplaine, in all Christian seruice, euer to be commanded, <hi>GR. WILLIAMS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>