<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Jntroduction to the whole BOOKE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120026_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15447</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25719</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Jntroduction to the whole BOOKE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seuen goulden candlestickes houlding the seauen greatest lights of Christian religion : shewing vnto all men what they should beleeue, &amp; how they ought to walke in this life, that they may attayne vnto eternall life by Gr: Williams Doctor of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gryffith</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 468, 471-617, pages 596, pages 609, 618-744, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>An Jntroduction to the whole <hi>BOOKE.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Almighty God had <hi>decreed</hi> from all eternity, to make certaine creatures partakers of his felicity, he did in that very period of the decreed time by his eternall Councell, <hi>create</hi> of nothing, all the things that are subsistent, and thereby he shewed himselfe to be, as all <hi>Gentiles</hi> confest it, <hi>optimus maximus,</hi> the very <hi>best</hi> of all that is good, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>greatest</hi> of all that is great: and, as <hi>Pliny</hi> saith well, especially hauing but the light of nature to enlighten him,<note place="margin">Plutarch, in Panegyrico Trai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n. dict.</note> he did herein shew himselfe to be <hi>prius optimus quam maximus;</hi> because hee which was so <hi>eminently</hi> good, that he could not be <hi>bettered,</hi> did all this for them that were iust nothing: but alas, behold a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapsed</hi> creature, from his most <hi>indulgent</hi> Creator, and see how this <hi>goodnesse</hi> of God, <hi>abused</hi> by the creature, became through the iust iudgement of GOD, an euitable <hi>cause</hi> of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series vpon all transgressors; for wee not <hi>contented</hi> with that blessed state wherein wee were established, did spurne against our God by a most <hi>ambitious</hi> vsurpation of his very Deity, and so aspiring vnto a <hi>blessed</hi> life as we thought, we brought vpon our selues a most <hi>accursed</hi> death, as we all finde: yet God still desiring to shew himselfe <hi>a God of mercy,</hi> he promised to send a Sauiour to <hi>redeem</hi> vs,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> by taking our <hi>nature</hi> vpon him, and <hi>suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> in our <hi>flesh,</hi> whatsoeuer we deserued for our <hi>sinnes;</hi> and to this end <hi>when the fulnesse of time came, God sent his Sonne, made of a woman, made vnder the Law,</hi> subiect to the <hi>curse</hi> of the Law,
<pb facs="18"/> which was <hi>death</hi> of body, <hi>buriall</hi> in the graue, and <hi>discention</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, that he might <hi>free</hi> vs from eternall death, and then to <hi>rise againe</hi> the third day, to ascend into heauen, and to send his holy Spirit into our hearts, to worke in vs <hi>faith</hi> to apply all this vnto our selues, and <hi>all</hi> other graces whatsoeuer, that might fit vs and bring vs vnto euerlasting life.</p>
   <p>And this is the summe of all that is contained in this booke, to know our <hi>selues,</hi> to know <hi>God,</hi> to know <hi>Iesus Christ, borne, dead, raised, ascended,</hi> and now <hi>raigning</hi> in eternall glory, to guide his <hi>Church,</hi> and to confound his <hi>foes</hi> for euermore.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this worke may seeme as the water boughs of a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse tree, a <hi>superfluous</hi> branch vnto the Church of God; I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly submit it to the iudgement of Gods children: they must all confesse it is the last houre of the worlds age, wherein ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is <hi>increased,</hi> impiety is <hi>enlarged,</hi> and all charity is almost <hi>abandoned,</hi> all things growing worse and worse by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; <hi>Et satanas tanto feruentior ad sauitiam, quanto se sentit vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorem ad paenam:</hi> and Satan hauing the greater rage to driue vs to transgression by how much the neerer he perceiues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to destruction; And therefore let men say what they will, yet seeing we may truly demaund of them, <hi>Quid audiam ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, cum vidiam contraria facta?</hi> What booteth all our <hi>knowledge,</hi> seeing we <hi>doe</hi> nothing that we know, nor <hi>know</hi> nothing indeed as we <hi>ought</hi> to know? I say that it cannot be amisse to do what wee can to expresse those things that may best make for our happinesse; and I know these points are <hi>necessary</hi> to be <hi>knowne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aetas parentum peior auis tulit, nos nequiores, mox daturos progienem visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem Horat. car. <hi>3.6.</hi> Greg, Moral l. <hi>34.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> and most <hi>profitable</hi> to be <hi>practised</hi> by all Christians. Reade them then, and I will pray to God that he will giue thee grace, <hi>Faeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer currere &amp; faelicius in Christi pietate cursam tuum consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare;</hi> to vnderstand what thou readest, to beleeue what thou vnderstandest, and to practise what thou beleeuest, that so thou mayest attaine vnto euerlasting life, through Iesus Christ our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>