<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRIS∣TIAN REA∣DER,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120491_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21065</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7433</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120491</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRIS∣TIAN REA∣DER,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian schoole-maister, or A dialogve betweene the maister and the scholler. By G.E. minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>G. E., minister of Gods word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Barrenger (Barringer), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 45, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER,</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the office and duetie of euery good childe, that carefullie and studiouslie laboureth to obey &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Fathers precepts and cōmandements, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally before all things, to endeuour to know per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the nature and condition of his Fathers will, whereof (if he be ignorant) many times in the same things hee iudgeth best and most pleasing, hee most offendeth, and incurreth greatest displeasure. Euen so, wee that be Subiects and Children to the great GOD, and Almighty Creator of all that heauen and Earth containeth, can doe nothing gratefull and acceptable vnto his Maiestie, except we
<pb facs="3"/> first know his good will &amp; pleasure towards vs, concerning our duties in beliefe, life and conuersation: In the knowledge whereof, that we might haue a setled foundation, and familiar education, this ensuing <hi>Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me.</hi> is collected and gathered from the Sacred Worde and will of Almightie God, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Olde and Newe Testament.</p>
   <p>The commandement of God, to teach and instruct children in religion is general, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to all men of euery age &amp; time: and therefore as well vnto vs as to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> it is saide, <hi>Teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> like of them when thou art in thine house, &amp; as thou walkest by the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, when thou li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st downe, &amp; when thou risest vp; Deut.</hi> 11. 19. Wherevpon <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Paule</hi> saith, <hi>And you Fathers prouoke not your Children to wrath, but bring them vp in Instruction, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the Lorde. Ephes.</hi> 6. 4.</p>
   <p>There is but one and the same corruption of nature, and our Children are as well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued &amp; borne in sinne, as the childrē of our forefathers, which corruption must be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by carefull and diligent instruction, and long custome, euen from tender yeares; and this especially is required in the children of the Faithfull and beleeuers: who seeing they belong to Gods Church, and our Sauiour Christ commanded them to be brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="3"/> him; It were a most heynous fault, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious shame, if they should bee found vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught, &amp; ignorant of the doctrine of Christ and his Church.</p>
   <p>Therfore <hi>Salomon</hi> most wisely counselleth in the 12. of his Prouerbs, <hi>Instruct a Child in the trade of his way, and when hee is olde he shall not depart from it:</hi> That is, If you would haue him leade his life godlie, iustly, honestlie, and vertuously, you must instruct him when he is young, in all those things which belong to the seruice of God, to the societie of men, and to all speciall duties.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Consecrate vnto mee</hi> (saith the Lorde) <hi>euery one that first openeth the Wombe amongst the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Israell: Exod. 13.</hi> By which Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, God did not onely call to their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the benefit long before shewed their Fathers in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> &amp; thereby confirme them in the Faith of <hi>Redemption</hi> that was to come; but also put them in minde of their dutie, that they ought to cōsecrate vnto him what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer was most pretious, &amp; euen their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren especially; For though all were not admitted to the Priest-hoode, yet all were to bee instructed in the knowledge of God, and though the outward Ceremonie therof, together with the rest be abolished in Christ, yet the commandement remaineth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="4"/> wee are euen at this day bounde to the like holie presentation of their soules.</p>
   <p>For the performance of this, did the mother of <hi>Samuel</hi> voluntarilie binde her selfe vnto God, saying: <hi>If thou wilt giue vnto thy Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide a man childe, then will I giue him vnto the Lorde all the dayes of his life. 1. Sam.</hi> 1. 11. This did <hi>Ioseph</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> diligently obserue towards <hi>CHRIST</hi> whome both according as it is written in the Law of the Lorde, they brought him to <hi>Ierusalem</hi> to present, and when hee was come to the Age of twelue yeaes, they caried him thither for the seruice of God.</p>
   <p>The better part of man is the soule, which cannot bee redeemed with the substance of the whole worlde; Are not they then most foolish and very indiscreete in their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, who straine themselu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> to prouide for their children things pertaining to the body, and the honours of this worlde, in the meane time beeing vtterly carelesse whether they haue anie true knowledge of God, whether they bee ioyned to him by Faith, whether they know wherein consisteth the saluation of their soules, and the euerlasting happines of man.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Abraham</hi> and the rest of the holie Fathers were farre wiser then these men, whose spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb facs="4"/> care was this, to haue their Children instructed in the knowledge and feare of God, for they knewe that godlines was the greatest gaine of all.</p>
   <p>For these causes then the necessitie of godlie Instruction doeth appeare; and to that ende this ensuing Treatise is collected, wherein is layde open and expounded the Morall Lawe, and the vse thereof, out of which a man may knowe his owne wretched estate, and his debt, wherein hee standeth bounde vnto God, that so hee may truely humble himselfe before him, and earnestly bethinke himselfe how he may be deliuered from sinne, and the punishment thereof, and from the wrath of God, and from the curse.</p>
   <p>In the nexte place is Expounded the <hi>Creede,</hi> (that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>,) the doctrine of mans deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from miserie by <hi>CHRIST;</hi> of the person and Office of Christ; of Iustification by Faith; of the Sacraments; of the Keyes of the Church, and vse of them; of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; of good work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, and the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of them, for the true seruice of God; Of the thankfulnes wee owe vnto God; Of the insufficiencie of man in this life, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the Lawe of God.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>Last of all, the sense and meaning of the Lordes Prayer; This for the glorie, praise, and honour of the diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and the benefite, profite, happines, and saluation of thy Soule.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell, In Christ Iesus.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>