<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Indifferent Reader.</title>
           <author>Meredyth, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120673_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17831</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120673</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Indifferent Reader.</title>
                 <author>Meredyth, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sinne of blasphemie against the Holy Ghost, scholastically examined : the reasons of the absolute irremissibility thereof displayed; an admonition to all reuolting apostataes [sic] annexed. By Iohn Meredyth, sub-deane of Chichester</title>
                 <author>Meredith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 70, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Indifferent Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, as wee are obliged by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian modesty to Beleeue the principles of Faith, before wee presume to discusse them by reason; So I hold it Negligence, if after our confirmation in the Faith, we study not to vnderstand the reason of that we beleeue. In which consideration, I (though the weakest among thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands) am excited, to wade into these depthes, where (as <note n="*" place="margin">Ad Leandr, de Expositione libri Job.</note>
      <hi>Gregory</hi> saith) <hi>Agnus peditet, &amp; Elephas natet,</hi> the simple may finde what to learne, and the learned what to admire as In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omprehensible.</p>
   <p>Wherein, if (by Gods assistance) I doe happily finde ought, whereof before I was ignorant, I doe willingly impart the same vnto others; <hi>Apertae Musarū Ianuae.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The vnstable dissolutenesse of sundry deboshed Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, in this decrepit Age of the world wherein wee liue, who halting betweene two opinions, spare not to belch forth blasphemies against the Truth, whereof they are as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, hath mooued mee to search into that fearefull <hi>Sinne</hi> of <hi>Apostacy,</hi> that those who repute it a small matter, to depart from the Truth of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> to the Tents of <hi>Antechrist,</hi> may consider the danger, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, before they fall into that <hi>Sinne</hi> against the <hi>Holy Ghost, which is Irrecouerable.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Againe the tender Consciences of other, who capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated with a conceit of this Sinne, haue beene swallowed vp in Despaire. How necessary the Subject is, I referre to thy Iudgement; In the meane time I feare, that least as Painters, who limbe a satre creature in vgly forme, deserue iust rebuke: So I should drawe on my selfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued reproach, by cloathing so wrothy a matter, in a rude and vnpolished stile.</p>
   <p>Tet this may not with-hold mee; for I binde no man from more curious performance hereof, whom my harsh phrase offendeth: But this I craue; If any suppose that I haue set abroath herein, any thing different from the Truth, let him not presently condemnt me, as a presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous publisher of Nouelties, or a broacher of falshood, vntill he hath first consulted with the Authors herein alledged.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer, if I haue not attained my purpose herein, yet I reioyce in seeking laboriously; though the length and difficulty of the way cause me to faile:</p>
   <p>This I am sure, I may truely say; I haue done my vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most: I haue sought, if not sound; I haue called, if not receaued an answer.</p>
   <p>Take it (gentle Reader) as it is, if it answer my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, it cannot displease thee; Howeuer, I publish it, to Gods glory, and thy good.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesvs, John Meredyth.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>