<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Godly and vvell-affected Reader vvhosoeuer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120444_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16568</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Godly and vvell-affected Reader vvhosoeuer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse vpon the Sabbath day : Wherin are handled these particulares ensuinge. 1. That the Lords day is not Sabbath day, by divine iustification. 2. An exposition of the 4. commandement, so farr fort has may give light vnto the ensueinge discourse: and particularly, here it is showne, at what time the Sabbath day should begine and end; for the satisfaction of those who are doubtfull in this point. 3. That the seaventh day Sabbath is not abolished. 4. That the seaventh day Sabbath is now still in force. 5. The authors exhortation and reasones, that neverthelesse there be no rente from our Church as touching practise. Written by Theophilus Brabourne</title>
                 <author>Brabourne, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 238, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Godly and vvell-affected Reader vvhosoeuer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>NOWEING (dearly beloued and Christian Reader) by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in my selfe as well as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, that there is a propensity &amp; holy inclination, in all who are truly Gods, to haue a respect vnto all Gods Commandements, without exceptions or reseruations, I iudged this discourse of the Sabbath day, which is one branch of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Law, could not be vnwelcome to thee: Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leing to minde also, the parable of our Saviour, how seuerly He will deale with that seruant, to whom he deliuered but one single Talent, for his hideing it, so as no profit came on it. Math. 25-24. remembring also, that Christ made it an essentiall marke of Peters loue vnto him, To fecd his Lambes: Ioh. 21.15. And, that it is giuen in charge to all, to exhorte one another, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish one another, &amp; to edifie one another 1. Th. 5.11.14. I durst not for feare, nor could I for
<pb facs="3"/>loue, but make knovvn my minde in this pointe: To see the Church and Spouse of Christ, to lye in the weekly breach of the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. Commandement, by violating and prophaning of the Lords sacred tyme and Sabbath (a sine of ignorance hether to I confesse) and in meane tyme superstitiously sanctifying a day, the first day of the weeke for a Sabbath, which God, nor Christ, nor any of his Apostles euer commanded or appointed: how could my spirit but be stirred within mee, to shew vnto hir this errour, and to declare vnto hir, which day is that righte and true day, which God requireth of hir: and the Rather, since God hath put it into hir hart, wilingly to giue God a day: for, this last and honourable Parliament (blessed be God for their zeale and Godly care) hath enacted a Law for the better keeping holy of the Lords day. I know, for my good will &amp; loue, I shall reape euill vvill and hatred; and for this paynes I shall vndergoe most harsh &amp; bitter censures, but blessed are ye (said Christ) when men speak euill of you falsely for my sake. They will say as some allreedy doe say, tis pride and singularity that setes me on vvorke; To vvhom I ansvvere in Pauls vvords 1. Cor. 4. I knovv no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by my selfe, yet am I not thereby iustified; but if it be, I beseech God pardone the syne, but blesse this work. Others, and that more charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, obiect the vnseasonablenesse of this motion,
<pb facs="3"/>because the Church of God is now vnder mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould afflictions, and liable to subuersion by hir enemies: where vnto I say, the more neede shee shold dravv neere to hir God, sticking closse to his Lawes, the breach whereof he hath threatned with subversions and desolations, Deut. 28. and, Gods truthes may not waite attendance, till men be at leisure to receiue them. Others, may thinke and say, there are men more fit then, I am for a matter of this weight &amp;c. To whom I answere, by a free acknowledgement of this truth; what multitudes are there in our Church, euery ech one wherof farr surpasse mee, for partes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and for learning, and for outward digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, titles, &amp; preferrments, all which might well countenance and helpe forwards such a cause as this, and were much to be desired, I confesse: Neither can I think, but some of those haue long agone foreseene this truth, either perfectly, or at least a farr off, as my selfe at first sawe it in my studies, like as the blind man in the Gospell, at first sawe men like trees; but whats the cause, why they did not prosecute the matter, till it came to perfection, till they sawe men like men clearly? was it not a slothfull feare to leese their labour, and catch a shadow for a Substance, as painfull Studentes must doe somtymes? or, for feare of the greatnesse of the labour: or, for feare of the losse of reputation, dignities, preferments, liueings,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>