<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR Thomas Edmonds KNIGHT, TREASVRER OF HIS MAIESTIES HOVSHOLD, AND OF HIS MOST Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr57_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR Thomas Edmonds KNIGHT, TREASVRER OF HIS MAIESTIES HOVSHOLD, AND OF HIS MOST Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="553"/>
   <pb facs="553"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR Thomas Edmonds KNIGHT, TREASVRER OF HIS MAIESTIES HOVSHOLD, AND OF HIS MOST <hi>Honourable Priuy</hi> Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter your long and happy acquaintance with other Courts and Kingdomes, may it please you to compare with them the estate of old Jsrael; You shall find the same hand swaying all Scepters, and you shall meet with such a proportion of dispositions, and occurrences, that you will say, men are still the same, if their names and faces differ: You shall find Enuy and Mutability ancient Courtiers: and shall confesse the Vices of men still aliue, if themselues die; You shall see God still honouring those that honour him, and both rescuing Jnnocence, and crowning it. Jt is not for me to anticipate your deeper and
<pb facs="554"/> more iudicious Obseruations J am bold to dedicate this piece of my Labour to your Honour, in a thankefull acknowledgement of those Noble Respects, J haue found from you, both in France, and at home. Jn lieu of all which, J can but pray for your happinesse, and vow my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all humble obseruance, IOS: HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>