<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120145_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10018</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20270</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120145</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons preached before his Maiestie; and vpon other speciall occasions : viz. 1 The pillar and ground of truth. 2 The new life. 3 A sensible demonstration of the Deity. 4 Exact walking. 5 Samuels support of sorrowfull sinners. By the late faithfull and worthy minister of Iesus Christ, Iohn Preston Dr. in Diuinity, chaplaine in ordinary to his Maiesty, master of Emmanuel College in Cambridge, and sometimes preacher of Lincolnes Inne</title>
                 <author>Preston, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Greene, Leonard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Boler (Bowler), James 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 92, 73-134 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>AVTHOR</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, being hindred by death, from digesting his thoughts into Tractates more accommodate for all mens vse, presaged notwithstanding, a little before his death, that they would be pressed into publike view by one or other, which might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps bee lesse carefull; who that he might preuent, hee bequeathed the care of those Sermons that were
<pb facs="3"/>
only preached at <hi>Lincolnes Inne,</hi> to those his worthy friends, by whom you see them faithfully set forth, who liuing in the City, were better conuersant with those that tooke them from his mouth: All others whatsoeuer vnto vs, who (though much more vnworthy and vnable) were yet more frequently his Auditors in other places, and had reason fully to know his Doctrine, manner of life, purpose, &amp;c should therefore bee more guilty of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull negligence, if any of those Lamps, into which he emptied the golden oile out of himselfe, should not by vs be lighted vp to serue the Temple, to which vndoubtedly by him they were deuoted. Moued therefore with the necessity of our
<pb facs="3"/>
duty, their former good example, and the successefull entertainment the rest haue found, we doe here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture into light these fiue short Sermons, preached at speciall times, and in Auditories of greatest worth and expectation, and accordingly composed of more exact materials, and closer put together, which in him may well be pardoned, who in all his other works did bow his more sublime and raised parts to lowest apprehensions. Wee haue laboured what we could to discharge the trust by him reposed in vs, and desire that others would be pleased to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the putting forth of any thing of his, without acquainting some of vs therewith, by him deputed for that worke; who as soone as may
<pb facs="4"/>
be will be carefull to present thee with what else soeuer we shall think vsefull: the Lord grant they may doe as much good as the Author of them did intend.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <list>
            <item>T. G.</item>
            <item>T. B.</item>
         </list>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>