<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>B. G. Londrada A Portu Aquita∣nus vnto the gentle Reader, health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120733_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08904</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120733</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>B. G. Londrada A Portu Aquita∣nus vnto the gentle Reader, health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A hundred and foureteene experiments and cures of the famous physitian Philippus Aureolus Theophrastus Paracelsus : translated out of the Germane tongue into the Latin. Whereunto is added certaine excellent and profitable workes by B.G. a Portu Aquitano. Also certaine secrets of Isacke Hollandus concerning the vegetall and animed worke. Also the spagericke antidotarie for gunne-shot of Iosephus Quirsitanus. Collected by Iohn Hester</title>
                 <author>Paracelsus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 55, 58-82 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>B. G. Londrada A Portu Aquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vnto the gentle Reader, health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His treatise of <hi>Paracelsus</hi> (friendly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) came vnto my hands by the gift of a certain nobls Prince of Germanie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is sufficiently euident to be <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celsus</hi> worke, I thought it not good to reserue it to my selfe, but to publish it abroad, seeing there commeth no commoditie or profit of hidden treasure. This therefore such as it is (louing Reader) imbrace: and shortly, God willing, looke for more and greater matters. But this one thing I would haue you vnderstand, that when you do minister those exalted essences of <hi>Paracelsus</hi> and his precious oyles, thinke not that they are to be ministred by themselues, but with some other mixture to cary or leade them: and they must be vsed, the stomack first being pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with some speciall medicine of <hi>Paracelsus:</hi> as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if you will minister oyle of Vitrioll, mingle fiue or sixe droppes with an ounce of conscrue of Roses, so shall you safely giue it; the like you must iudge of other things; vse these happilie.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>