<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDWARD LORD DENNY, BARON OF VValtham, my bountifull, and dearely honoured Patron.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr69_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDWARD LORD DENNY, BARON OF VValtham, my bountifull, and dearely honoured Patron.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="686"/>
   <pb facs="686"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDWARD LORD DENNY, BARON OF VValtham, my bountifull, and dearely honoured Patron.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>One can challenge so much right in these Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, as your Lordship, vnder whose happy shade they receiued their first conception: Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Juniper of yours, haue J (not driuen by force, but drawne by pleasure) slept thus long, sweetly, safely; and haue receiued these Angelicall touches: How iustly may your Lordship claime the fruits of your owne fauours? Your carefull studies in the Booke of God, are fit to bee exemplary; which haue so enriched you, that your Teacher shall gaine. In this reach of diuine thoughts, you shall see <hi>Benhadads</hi> insolence taken downe by <hi>Ahabs</hi> victory, an humble (though Idolatrous) <hi>Israelite</hi> carying it from an insulting Pagan: You shall see in <hi>Ahab</hi> the impotent passions of greatnesse; in <hi>Naboth,</hi> bleeding honestie; in <hi>Iezebel</hi> bloody hypocrisie, cruell craft; plotting from hell, pretending from heauen: You shall see the wofull successe of an vniust mercy; <hi>Ahab</hi> forfaiting what hee gaue, killed by him, whom hee should haue killed: You shall see resolute <hi>Michaiah</hi>
      <pb facs="687"/> opposing the mercenarie Synode of Prophets, a beaten victor, an imprisoned freeman: You shall see <hi>Ahaziah</hi> falling through his grate; <hi>Elijah</hi> climbing vp his Mount, mounting vp to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; fetching fire from Heauen, fetcht by a fiery charet to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>Elisha</hi> the heire of his mantle, of his spirit, no lesse mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous in his beneficences, in his reuenges. What doe J foretell all? Me thinkes J feele my selfe now too like an <hi>Italian</hi> host, thus to meet your Lordship on the way, and to promise before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand your fare, and intertainment: Let it please your Lordship rather to see and allow your cheere: Jndeed the feast is Gods, and not mine, wherein store striues with delicacie: Jf my coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerie hurt it not, it is enough: Through your hands I commend it to the world, as I doe your Lordship, and my honorable good Ladie, to the gracious protection of the Almightie, iustly vowing my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all faithfull obseruance for euer to command, IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>