<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY HO∣NORABLE, SIR IOHN OGLE KNIGHT, COLONELL OF A REGIMENT OF FOOTE, VNDER the Lords the Estates of the vnited Provinces: And Lord Gouernour of the Forces in the Towne of VTRECHT.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120617_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15207</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19512</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120617</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY HO∣NORABLE, SIR IOHN OGLE KNIGHT, COLONELL OF A REGIMENT OF FOOTE, VNDER the Lords the Estates of the vnited Provinces: And Lord Gouernour of the Forces in the Towne of VTRECHT.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most true relation of the affaires of Cleve and Gulick : as also of all what hath passed this last summer, since the most excellent and victorious prince, Maurice of Nassau, tooke the field with his armie, encamping before Rees in Cleueland: and the losse of Wesel, take in by the Marques Spinola: vnto the breaking vp of our armie in the beginning of December last past. 1614. With the articles of the peace, propounded at Santen By Henrie Peacham</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Helme (Helmes), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, SIR IOHN OGLE KNIGHT, COLONELL OF A REGIMENT OF FOOTE, VNDER <hi>the Lords the Estates of the vnited</hi> Provinces: And Lord Gouernour <hi>of the Forces in the Towne of</hi> VTRECHT.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O giue testimonie of my thankefulnesse vnto you, for many fauours, and your honorable respect of me, I present you with this, the fruit of my leisure, for the which also I am beholden vnto you since my returne from the Armie before <hi>Rees;</hi> not that, as some may imagine, I meant to carrie Pearles into <hi>Persia,</hi> or Owles to <hi>Athens,</hi> bring you newes of that you know alreadie, better then my selfe, being interessed in this, as in all other the most important actions that concerne the Field in these vnited Provinces, hauing had your Regiment in the Armie, and these things done in a manner before your dore; but that, whatsoeuer I haue seene with mine owne eyes, or receiued by sound Relation of others, might vnder your name winne a better reputation with the
<pb facs="3"/>World, to whom I doe assure me, for your sake such as it is it will be welcome. The occasion of it was the satisfaction of many honorable and my worthy friends in <hi>England,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired mee at my comming ouer (as it is commonly the parting request of friends) to write such newes as hapned, yea though a priuate iournall of things of small moment seene or done vpon the way, which haue also their delight aswell as the most serious affaires. For their sakes haue I done it, as also for mine owne priuate recreation in the Armie, who haue beene euer a profest Enemie vnto <hi>Idlenesse;</hi> I take my leaue, from <hi>BREDA</hi> in <hi>Brabant.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships truly. HENRIE PEACHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>