<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authours Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120909_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5881</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120909</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authours Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iust and temperate defence of the fiue books of ecclesiastical policie: written by M. Richard Hooker : against an vncharitable letter of certain English Protestants (as they tearme themselues) crauing resolution, in some matters of doctrine, which seeme to ouerthrow the foundation of religion, and the Church amongst vs. Written by William Covel Doctor in Diuinitie, and published by authority. The contents whereof are in the page following</title>
                 <author>Covell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 154, that is 152 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="4"/>
   <head>The Authours Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ittle hath labour done, to make any man excellent, if vertue haue not as much power to make it continue: neither were it anie honour, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue well, if our memories might die with our names <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or our names be buried, as often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s malice, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie doth seeke to hide them. Fewe things are eminently good, which are indured amongst distempered iudgements without bitter reprehension; for where weakenesse hath not strength enough to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and reuerence that vertue which it feareth; it hath violence and malice sufficient to detract from that vertue which it hateth. Amongst euill persons, as there be fewe things that are good, in themselues; so there be not manie things which they are willing should appeare good in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for vertue, where it is not followed, must either be dispraised, or our negligence shall want excuse. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer hath the power to conuince, must suffer reproofe, where the heart of man wanteth humilitie to giue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The worlds greatest errour, is in esteeming, when our corruptions making vs ambitious to seeme, whilest we are carelesse to be, winneth allowance from a fond opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the streame of violent fancies, denieth to rest vpon those that are truly vertuous. Because for anie man to oppose himselfe, against that euill which is growne heady, either by custome, or patience, is to hazard much of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, if he be strong; and in the opinion of many vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly to perish, if he be weake. And therefore as vice hath
<pb n="2" facs="5"/>
euer had mo that did dislike it, then durst dispraise it; so vertue wil euer haue mo that are willing to allow it in their iudgements, then dare aduenture to interpose themselues, for the defence of that which they do allow. <hi>Iealousie</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king those to depraue, euen the very defence of that, which their owne iudgements did thinke worthy, and their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes desired, might be defended. For to do that which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man accounteth his own duty, as it argueth oftentimes more strength then courage; so amongst many, it reapeth little else but an opinion of singularitie. From this corrupt fountaine (a fountaine poisoned by malicious ignorance) haue flowed these bitter, but small streames, which the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of some mens commendations (arising out of a blind loue) haue made for power and greatnesse, like the red sea, to drown (as they say) <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his host. Let them perish in it without helpe, beaten downe with that hand, that striketh from aboue, who seeke to hold <hi>Israel</hi> a seruant in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or captiue in the house of bondage: but let them passe through without harme, who couragiously haue freed the posterity of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and led <hi>Israel</hi> to the land of promise. I doubt not but without a miracle, a man of small stature may goe through these waters and not bee drowned; yet sometimes the most righteous, may say with <hi>Dauid,</hi> the ouerflowing of vngodlinesse made me afraid. Deceit vsually couereth with a mask (better then the face) that euill which it desireth should kill vnseene and vnpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented: but errour cannot more easily fall, then when it is built vpon such a foundation; nor weaker opinions sooner vanish, then when they are bred, nourished, &amp; supported, onely with the strength of fancie. It is of small vse in the church (though a thing practised in al ages) for men ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiously to labour to remoue those staines, which like an impure breath, darken the glasse of steele, whilest it is warme, but slide off through their owne weakenesse, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no power to make any deeper impression, then onely aire. Any cloth in a hand of no skill, or <hi>strength,</hi> is able to wipe off, with ease, those blots, or marks, that are stained
<pb n="3" facs="5"/>
with no greater force, or vertue, but a hote breath. But seeing the reputation that vertue challengeth, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious labour seasoned with discretion doth merit, seeketh rather to gaine an approbation, from the iudgement of the wise, then recompence or reward, from the mightie hand of the rich; men of vertuous desert in all ages (euen from the lowest step of humilitie &amp; obedience) haue with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and truth, taught the world a far better iudgment, by their wise apologies; and haue gained as much honour in remouing euill, as they haue gotten vertue vnto their names, in doing wel. The malice of enuie out of impatient ignorance, doing vertue this benefit, that that which was cleare before, by a few, light, trifling spots, gaineth a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, to make it clearer. <hi>desert</hi> and <hi>goodnesse,</hi> being effects of a first motion; <hi>perfection</hi> and <hi>excellencie</hi> the worke of a second maker. It must needs seeme strange to many, and be vnpleasing to all, that are of any sober, indifferent, or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous disposition, that the iust defence of a present, religious, <hi>Ecclesiasticall policie,</hi> vndertaken without bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of spirit, in a graue moderation to reforme presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and informe ignorance, should so farre taste, of the eagernesse of some vnlearned pennes; that iudgement, should be thought too weake, to answer idle wordes; or vertue not strong enough to withstand malice; or lastly, that he could want a defence, whose endeuour (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe professeth) was not so much to ouerthrow them, with whom he contended, as to yeeld them iust, and reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble causes, of those things, which for want of due consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, heretofore they haue misconceiued; sometimes accusing lawes, for mens ouersights; sometimes imputing euils growne, through personall defects, to that which is not euill; framing to some sores vnwholsome plaisters; and applying remedies sometimes where no sores were. It is much easier to answer those shadowes of reason, wherein these <hi>Admonishers</hi> do please themselues; then by their silence to make them confesse, that they are fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered. For as they know not (for the most part) well how
<pb n="4" facs="6"/>
to speake, sauing only tinkers musick, like sounding brasse, because they want charitie; so do they lesse know how to hold their peace, like clamorous Frogs, because they want humilitie. Holy pretences haue euer beene the strongest motiues that pride hath; and Zeale, how preposterous and ignorant so euer, hath beene deemed reason sufficient to some men, in the opinion of their followers, to warrant &amp; defend whatsoeuer they haue done. Vpon this ground, was published, some few Articles in manner of a letter, in the yeare 1599. requiring resolution in matters of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, concerning some points, which either they miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, or list not to vnderstand, vttered by M. <hi>Hooker,</hi> in those fiue learned, and graue books of <hi>Ecclesiasticall policie</hi>; wherin, it must needs appeare, that their ignorant malice, hath done him great honour; who in an argument so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasted by them, and comming with a proud confidence to reprehend, haue only carped sillily, at some few things, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of moment, nor importance, whereof humilitie, and charitie, would haue craued no answer. But these being willing, and desirous, to find somewhat to oppose, haue onely discouered▪ his great, mature, and graue iudgement, and their owne small, vndigested, and shallow learning. For there is nothing, that can better, both excuse, and commend a workman, thē to see enuie desirous to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, and reprehension to vanish in his owne smoke. For (saith the Wiseman) <note n="*" place="margin">Wisd. 10.8.</note> all such as regarded not wisedome, had not onely this hurt, that they knew not the things that were good, but also left behind them, vnto men a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of their foolishnesse; so that in the things wherein they sinned, they could not lie hid; yet the people see and vnderstand it not, and consider no such things, in their hearts, <note n="*" place="margin">Wis. 4.15.</note> how that grace and mercie is vpon his Saints, and his prouidence ouer the elect. For as he himselfe well no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; as to the best, and wisest (while they liue) the world is continually a froward opposite, a curious obseruer of their defects, and imperfections; so their vertues, it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as much admireth. Those, whom we must make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>
in this cause, are men, not knowne either by name, religion or learning; yet such as would seem, in zeale to the present state, to desire a resolution in some points that might otherwise giue offence. It may be peraduenture the worke of some one, who desirous to gaine an opinion amongst his followers, vndertaketh to speake as from the minds of many, hoping those demaunds (how idle soeuer) will gaine answer, being to satisfie a multitude, which no doubt M. <hi>Hooker</hi> in his wisdome, patience, and grauity, would easily haue contemned, if they had but beene the priuate cauils, and obiections of some one. For there is no man but thinketh, <hi>manie,</hi> how light so euer, in themselues, being vnited, may haue that weight, to chalenge euen by a ciuill right, a direct answer, from one euerie way farre better then had beene fitting, for their modestie, &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to prouoke. Well; whosoeuer they are, as I cannot easily coniecture, so I am not curious to knowe; this age hath affoorded an infinite number, whom superstitious feare, for want of true vnderstanding, and an ignorant zeale, not directed with discretion, haue made violent in matters of Religion, vsing the razor in steed of a knife, and for hatred of tares oftentimes pulling vp good corne. But with these we will deale, with that temperate moderation, as may serue, to giue true worthinesse, a iust defence; and impatient and furious spirits (vnlesse desperately violent) no iust cause to find themselues to be grieued with vs.</p>
   <p>This which wee are to answer, is tearmed by them, <hi>A Christian letter of certaine English Protestants,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The title of the Booke.</note>
      <hi>vnfained fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the present state of religion, authorised, and professed in England; vnto that reuerend, and learned man, M. Richard Hooker.</hi> Thus the humilitie, and mild temper of their super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription, may peraduenture gaine the reading at some mens hands, through an opinion, that <hi>Protestants</hi>; and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi>; and in a <hi>Christian letter</hi>; would hardly be caried with violence so far, to make demaunds, seasoned with so little modestie, learning, or vnderstanding. These men, they may be (as we take the word largely) <hi>Protestants</hi> for anie
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
thing that I know; that is, men outwardly of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion; who liue and professe a doctrine, for the most part opposite to the Church of Rome; but I can hardly be perswaded, that the Letter being wholy an vnciuill Ironie, is either <hi>Christian,</hi> or that themselues, are vnfained fauourers of the present state of religion; or that they thinke <hi>M. Hooker</hi> to be either reuerend, or learned in their opinions. For whatsoeuer they may pretend, in vrging the reuerend <hi>Bishops</hi> of our Church against his assertions; as though they ascribed much vnto them; yet their desire is, to make an opposition appeare, and in that shewe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, to make themselues sport, &amp; in the end proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and maliciously to contemne both. But Saint <hi>Iames</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth these, that <hi>if anie man seeme religious, and refraine not his tongue, but deceiueth his owne heart, this mans religion is vain.</hi> And in this I appeale to the censure of the most modest and discreet amongst themselues, by what shew of reason, they could tearme that Letter to bee Christian, wherein were contained so many vnseasoned and intemperate spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? or that man to be either reuerend, or learned, whom they haue vsed with so little respect, and accused of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie defects? But doubtlesse, as they neuer thought him to be either reuerend, or learned (whom all that knew him, whilest he liued knew to be both) so they little desired, that their Letter should be such a one, as might worthily be accounted <hi>Christian.</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">in the Letter Pag. 1.</note> Else what meane these accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to account his goodly promises, meere formall, and great offers to serue only, to hoodwink such, as mean wel; as though by excellency of words, and intising speeches, of mans wisedome, he ment<note n="a" place="margin">Ibid.</note> as they say to beguile, and bewitch the <hi>Church,</hi> of God. A little after<note n="b" place="margin">pag. 2.</note> they call him a goodly <hi>Champion,</hi> and by the sweet sound, of your melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious stile, almost cast into a dreaming sleepe; which stile notwithstanding afterwards, they account not<note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 45.</note> vsual, but long, and tedious; far differing from the simplicity of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly scripture; and a<note n="d" place="margin">Pag. 3. Lin. 10</note> hard, and harsh stile: for the manner of the stile, we shall make our defence, when we answere
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
that Article. But in that, you scoffingly account him a goodly <hi>Champion,</hi> giue me leaue to tell you, that if our <hi>Church</hi> were throughly furnished with such men, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly function of our calling, had not growne in contempt by ignorant and vnlearned ministers; our peace had not bin troubled with furious and violent spirits: worldly men, had not seazed vpon the <hi>Church,</hi> with such eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, through an opinion of the vnworthines of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: they of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> had not thus long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained obstinate, through the violent proceedings of vndiscreet men, whose remedies were worse then the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease it selfe: nor last of all, the generall amendment of life (the fruite of our preaching) had not bin so small, if these turbulent heads, had not more desired, to make <hi>Hypocrits,</hi> then truely religious. It is much safer to praise the dead, then the liuing, hauing seene the period of their dayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired; <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Quando nec laudantem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet adulatio, nec laudatum tentat elatio.</hi>
      </note> when neither he that is praised, can be puffed vp, nor he that doth praise can be thought to flatter, hee was, as Saint <hi>Austine</hi> sayd of Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Tanti meriti, tanti pectoris, tanti oris, tantae virtutis.</hi>
      </note>, of such desert, of such a courage, of such a grace, of such a vertue, that as <hi>Theodosius</hi> sayd of S. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> I haue known <hi>Ambrose,</hi> who alone is worthy to be called a Bishop▪ of whom I dare giue that iudgement (though he were in true estimation great already) which <hi>Antigoras,</hi> gaue of <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> that he would haue bin a very great man, if he had bin old. Great in his own vertues, of great vse in the <hi>Church,</hi> &amp; in al app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rance, (though these times be vnthankefull) of great authoritie. I let passe those other tearmes, which shew your letter to bee vnchristian, vntill we come to their particular an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers; and thus much for the title.</p>
   <p>It hath bin, no new thing in all ages, that reprehension hath waited vpon those books,<note place="margin">The preface of the letter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweared: when men dreame they are a sleep &amp;c.</note> which zeale▪ from a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minde, hath written to support the truth; for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man is much apter to reproue others, then reforme it selfe; seeing to see faults in others, is an act of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding if they bee; and of a frowardnes of the will if they be not: but to rectifie them in ourselues must be the
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
worke of a cleare vnderstanding and a reformed will; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vsually men practise themselues, what they punish in others; so that no man can directly conclude, <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Vt argumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o non sit propter quod alios accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant has ipsas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disse. Dio. Cass. lib.</hi> 36. <hi>hist.</hi>
      </note> that all men hate what they do accuse. Therefore Saint <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist. ad Asel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam virg. in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log super los.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Hierom,</hi> of whome saith S. <hi>Austin</hi> (no man knew that whereof S. <hi>Hierom</hi> was ignorant) oftentimes complaineth of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions, slaunders, and vntrue accusations of euill men. These, for the most part, are vnstaid, violently caried with the current of the present time, sometimes bitterly either vpon discontentments, or to please others, inueighing against those, whom themselues before out of flattery, not <hi>iudgement,</hi> haue highly praised. Thus <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Nicephor. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixtus lib.</hi> 10. <hi>hist. cap.</hi> 36.</note>
      <hi>Libanius</hi> the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phister, who was eloquent against the <hi>Christians,</hi> to please <hi>Iulian,</hi> was noted with this marke of leuity, for writing Panegyricks, or orations of praise, to commend <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> while he liued, against whome afterward he wrote most bitter inuectiues when he was dead. Thus some small discontentment serued to turne the heart, and open the mouth of <hi>Porphyry</hi> against the <hi>Christians</hi>: what cause of griefe these zealous professours haue I know not, but in my opinion, the whole tenor of that vncharitable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian letter, argueth some inward discontent, either enuious that other men should be excellent, or that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues being excellent, are not more regarded. Wherein though they dislike, the dim eie of gouernment, that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not cleerely into mens vertues, and the niggardly hand, that doth not bountifully reward such, as deserue well; yet they mighte out of patience, and charity, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily haue forborne, to haue inueied against his honour, which consisted in no other wealth, but in his religious contentment, and in that true commendation, which was the due merit of his own vertues. For <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>In obit. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>i. Ber,</hi>
      </note> the world had not much to take from him, because hee had not taken much from the world; for he neuer affected, flatteringly to please her, nor she neuer cared fauninglie to please him. For as <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Nihil ex ea quod meum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceretur praeter cognomen retuli. Val. Max.</hi>
      </note> all that <hi>Scipio</hi> brought▪ from <hi>Africa,</hi> after his danger, and trauell, to be called his, was only a Surname;
<pb n="9" facs="8"/>
so the greatest recompense, that his labours had, was the iust commendation, that he was a very reuerend, learned and graue man. For his iudgement taught him out of a Christian patience, the resolution of <hi>Cato,</hi> if <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Si quid est quo vtar, vt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r; si <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>, ego sum.</hi>
      </note> I haue anie thing to vse, I vse it; if not, I know who I am. And seeking to profit in knowledge, and that this knowledge might profit the <hi>Church</hi>; he shewed that hee was borne for the good of many, and few to bee borne for the good of him. For as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> speaketh of <hi>Nepotian,</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Nepotianus noster aurū cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans schedulas consectatus.</hi>
      </note> despising gold, he followed learning, the greatest riches. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture his learning had puft him vp; and his pride had made his writings, impatient, and full of bitternes; and this moued you, to vndertake, this vncharitable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian letter; for you say if we beleeue them (meaning the Bishops) we must thinke, that Master <hi>Hooker</hi> is verie arrogant,<note place="margin">Pag. 19. lin. 16</note> and presumptuous, to make himselfe the onely <hi>Rabbi.</hi> That you had no cause, to prouoke him, in these tearmes, all men know that do reade his writings; for dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in an argument of that kinde, with aduersaries, of that nature; and in a time growne insolent by suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; hee hath written with that temperat moderation, rather like a graue father to reforme the vnstayed errors, of hot, young, violent spirits, then seuerelie correcting them with the vntemperat bitternes of their owne stile; and sighing at the scurrilous and more then satyricall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modesty of Martinisme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Lege Carol. mag. fol.</hi> 421.</note> he feared with a true sorrow, least that honourable calling of Priesthood, which was ruinated by slaunder amongst ourselues, could not long continue firme in the opinion of others. Well, for all this the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of his passions, was in his owne power, as <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Ira eius in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu eius. Ber.</hi>
      </note>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> speaketh of <hi>Malachie</hi> the Bishop. And he was able to rule them; for he was truly of a milde spirit, and an humble hart, and abounding in all other vertues; yet he specially excelled in the grace of meekenes: for the graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his lookes, as <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Sereneb at vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum suum assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dētium gratia, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ieret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nerosus, sed visum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum si bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colitis non admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit. Ber.</hi>
      </note> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> speaketh of <hi>Humbers,</hi> was cleered by those that did sit, or conuerse with him; least he should be burdensome vnto them; but a ful laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, few euer discerned in him. Some such our <hi>Church</hi>
      <pb n="10" facs="9"/>
hath had in all ages; a few now aliue, which are her orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if shee can vse them well; but moe that are dead, whome she ought to praise. For <note place="margin">Eccl. 44.7 8. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s. 11 12.13.14.15.</note> all those <hi>were honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable men, in their generations,</hi> and were well reported of, in their times; there are of them, that haue left a name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, so that their praise shall be spoken of, for whose posterity, a good inheritance is reserued, and their seede is conteined in the couenant; their bodise are buried in peace, but their name liueth for euermore; the people speake of their wisedome, and the congregation talke of their praise. In this number vertue hath placed him, whom you accuse; and are not afraid, being now awaked out of a dreame, to account a deceiuer. As though in his labours he had meant by intising speech, to deceiue the <hi>Church</hi>; or as though by a colourable defēce of the <hi>Church</hi> discipline, he purposed (as you say) to make questionable,<note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> and to bring in contempt the doctrine, and faith it selfe; beating against the heart of all true Christian doctrine, professed by her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and the whole state of this realme. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you haue made choice of the principall things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in his bookes; wishing him to free himselfe from all suspicion of falshoode and trechery; accounting your selues to rest contented, if he will shew himselfe, either all one in iudgement, with the Church of England, or else freely and ingenuously acknowledge; his vnwilling ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight; or at the least shew plainely by good demonstratiō, that al our reuerend Fathers haue hitherto bin deceiued▪ To this you craue a charitable, direct, plaine, sincere, and speedy answeare; this is the summe of the preface to your Christian letter. It is too true that al ages haue had decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers; and that the most dangerous deceiuers, haue strong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preuailed vnder pretence of Religion; and therefore whereas all bodies are subiect to dissolution, there are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly mo estates ouerthrown, through diseases with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themselues, which familiarly do steale vpon them, then through violence from abroade. Because the maner is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, to cast a doubtfull, and a more suspicious eie, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="11" facs="9"/>
that, ouer which men know they haue least power; &amp; therfore the feare of apparant dangers, causeth their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be more vnited; it is to all sorts a kind of bridle; it maketh vertuous minds watchful; it holdeth contrary dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions in suspence; and imployeth the power of all wits; and the wits of all men, with a greater care. Whereas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits couered with good pretenses, are so willingly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, so little feared, &amp; so long suffered, vntill their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty burst forth, when it is too late, to cure them▪ vice hath not a better meanes to disperse it selfe, nor to gaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tartainment, and fauour, then by borrowing the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit name, and habit, of seeming vertue. <note n="a" place="margin">Iustin. lib. 15. ex Trogo.</note> Thus that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious <hi>Sandracot</hi> vnder pretence of liberty, mooued the Indians, against the officers of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great; which when they had slaine, he that was the author of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, turned that into a more cruell bondage, oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the people whom he had freed from strangers, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cruell tyranny of his owne gouernment. But of all deceits, there is none more dangerous, then when the name of God, or religion is pretended, to countenance out heinous crimes. And howsoeuer euen in this kinde, this age hath not wāted examples, who beeing dangerous vnder holy pretenses, the hand of Iustice hath cut off; yet the imputation of this fault, can in no reason cleaue to him, who hath so far hazarded himselfe, for the iust de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of religion, and Church gouernement. If hee had broched any new fancies, or proudly opposed the wise established discipline; there had bin some reason to haue suspected, that by intising speech he had meant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Church. But seeing hee hath laboured in a waighty cause, with reasons, against those, whom the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrats seuerity could not easily suppresse; seeing he hath vndertaken it by appointment; and performed it with allowance; and seeing he hath made no other shew of sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting popery, but only by resisting Puritans; the slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der must needs be too light, and the accusation without color, to say that he hath beaten against the heart of al true
<pb n="12" facs="10"/>
Christian doctrine, professed by her Maiestie, &amp; the whole state of this Realme: as though (which you desire the world might beleeue) the hart of Christian religion, were only amongst such, whom the affectation of singularity hath tearmed by the name of <hi>Puritans</hi>: And that the rest who are not of that temper, are dangerous, and close he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks. Thus <hi>Appollinarius</hi> the yonger,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sixt Sin. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>bibliothecae.</hi>
      </note> who wrote so much in defence of the Christian faith, that Saint <hi>Basil</hi> said of him, that with his volumes he had filled the whole world; and wrote against rauing and frantick <hi>Porphury,</hi> thirty bookes, more excellent then any other of his workes; was afterward accused that he held the error of the <hi>Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> that into the trinity he had brought, Great, greater, and greatest of all; that he thought not right of the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Christ: but seeing <hi>Theophilus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> who was an enemy vnto him, &amp; diuers other Authors besides, report that he was vehement, to confute the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Eunomians, Origenists,</hi> and many other hereticks, in many volumes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Epiphanius in</hi> 3. <hi>pannarii.</hi>
      </note> it may be thought whatsoeuer his other errors were, the malice of his aduersaries had forged this, to diminish the authority of those bookes, which hee had written against them. So that this practise is no new thing, to diminish the soundnes of their religion, whose iudgements, and reasons we are vnable to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. But I doubt not by that which followeth, but it shall easily bee made to appeare, that he is of the same iudgement with the Church of <hi>England</hi>; that he hath not committed any ouersight; nor that he goeth not about to contradict, the reuerend fathers of our Church; which things (in al likeliehood) are matters by al you much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired; and therefore I hope you will accept (as you desire) this charitable, direct, plaine, and sincere answere; which no doubt of it, from himselfe had bin far more learned and more speedy, if he could either haue resolued to haue don it, or after he had resolued could haue liued, to haue seene it finished. But first of all, he was loth to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with so weake aduersaries; thinking it vnfit (as
<pb n="13" facs="10"/>
himselfe said) that a man that hath a long iourney, should turne backe to beate euerie barking curre; and hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it in hand, his vrgent and greater affaires, together with the want of strength, weakened with much labour, would not giue him time to see it finished. Yet <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Erat animus victor annor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m, &amp; cedere nesci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens infirmitati: Ber. in vita Humberti.</hi>
      </note> his mind was stronger then his yeares, and knew not well how to yeeld to infirmitie. Wherein if hee had, somewhat fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured himselfe, he might peraduenture, haue liued to haue answered you; to the benefite of the Church, and the comfort of a great number. But <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Mors fecit quantum potuit, occidit carnem, &amp; ecce recondita est in corde ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>; separauit à nobis dulcem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum, prudent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Consiliarium, Auxiliarium for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Ber.</hi>
      </note> death hath done what hee could; it hath killed his bodie, and it is laid vp in the heart of the earth; it hath taken from vs, and from the Church of God, a sweete friend, a wise coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour, and a strong Champion: so that I may say, as it was sometimes said of <hi>Demosthenes: Demosthenes</hi> is meete for Athens, <hi>Demades</hi> ouergreat. Others fit enough to liue in the midst of errour, vanitie, vnthankfulnesse, and deceit, but hee too good. For he was as the morning starre, in the middest of a cloud, and as the Moone when it is full; and as the Sunne shining vpon the Temple of the most High, and as the rainebowe that is bright in the faire cloudes; when he put on the garment of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and was clothed with all beautie,<note place="margin">Eccles. 50.6.7.11. Wis. 3.1.2.3.</note> hee went vp to the holy Altar; and made the garment of holinesse ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. But this ought to content vs, that the soules of the righteous, are in the hand of God, and no torment shall touch them: In the sight of the vnwise they appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to die, and their end was thought grieuous, and their departing from vs destruction, but they are in peace.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>