<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE
METAPHRASE
of the first Chapter of the
first Epistle of PETER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120373_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17411</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4234</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE
METAPHRASE
of the first Chapter of the
first Epistle of PETER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon the first chapter of the first epistle generall of Peter : Wherein method, sense, doctrine and vse is with great varietie of matter profitably handled. By Nicholas Byfeild preacher of Gods word at Isleworth in Middlesex. The rest of the epistle may be published in due time, if God will</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 512 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translation">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE
METAPHRASE
of the first Chapter of the
first Epistle of PETER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>ETER</hi> by immediate calling &amp;
commission from <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi>
the Embassador for the Churches
to the dispersed seruants of God,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse 1. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>TER</hi> an Apostle of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sus Christ to the strangers sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d throughout Pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>latia, Capadocia, Asia, and Bith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nia.</note>
strangers and pilgrims in this
world, that dwell here and there in <hi>Pontus, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia,
Cappadocia, Asia,</hi> and <hi>Bithinia.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Who for their spirituall estate were chosen of
God from euerlasting,<note place="margin">
         <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rse</hi> 2. Elect acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to obedience and sprinkling of the blood of Iesus Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Grace vnto you and peace be multiplied.</note> and fore-seene of God with
speciall approbation aboue the rest of mankinde,
and loued with a fatherly loue (as appeares by
the inward sanctification of their hearts, which
can be found in none, but the Elect of God) sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
of God to these ends, namely that both they
might glorifie God by their holy conuersation, and
be glorified of God by the fruition of the benefits
purchased by the blood of <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> and
n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w estated vpon them by the application of the
<pb facs="8"/>
merits of <hi>CHRIST:</hi> The grace of God, euen
his continuall free fauour, and the gifts of his
spirit, and peace, euen tranquillitie of heart and
conscience, and all comfortable and needfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity
be established vpon you, and more and
more increased in you.</p>
   <p>Eternall thankes be giuen vnto God,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 3. Blessed be the God and F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ther of our Lord Iesus Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st which according to his aboundan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> mercy hath begotten vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto a liuety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ope by the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ction of Iesus Christ from the dead.</note> who is the
God of our Lord Iesus Christ in respect of his
humane nature, and his Father in respect of his
diuine nature, for all the consolations, wherein he
hath giuen vs reason of singular reioycing, and
in particular for that he hath regenerated vs and
made vs his children by adoption, when we deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
nothing but his eternall wrath, meerely out
of the abundance of his owne matchles mercies,
and sets vs in such an estate, as whatsoeuer our
trialls and afflictions may be; yet he hath giuen
vs effectuall and assured hope of full happinesse,
the pledge and vndoubted testimonie whereof
we haue, in that Iesus Christ is risen from the
dead, which shewes euidently, that all is dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged:
For else he could not haue come out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>,
till he had paid the vttermost farthing.</p>
   <p>And to shew that he will acknowledge vs for
sonnes,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 4 To an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>itance incorruptible and vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iled, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> not away, reserued in heauen for you.</note> he hath reserued for vs in heauen such
an inheritance, as shall neuer be lost, or taken
from vs, and shall haue no fault nor defect in it,
nor euery decay in the incomparable worth and
glory of it.</p>
   <p>And that wee may be sure of possession,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 5 Who are kept by the power of God through fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h vnto saluation, ready to be reuealed in the last time.</note> his
owne allmighty power will be as a strong garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
about vs to keepe vs; and he hath giuen vs
<pb facs="8"/>
also a liuely faith, that will preserue vs, till we
be possessed of that glorious and full saluation,
which he hath prepared for vs, and is ready to be
reuealed in the full perfection of it, when the
day of death, or iudgement shall come.</p>
   <p>If you obiect,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 6. Wherein yee greatly reioyce, though now for a season (if neede be) you are in heauinesse through manifold tentations.</note> that you cannot take that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
in these Arguments of consolation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
of the many tentations, inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
with which you are daily dishartned: I
answer, that for all your crosses you may haue
exceeding much ioy euen in the midst of your
tribulations; and besides the trouble of your
crosses is but for a little while, they are but short
tryalls, nor are you bound alwaies to be pensiue
for your crosses, but onely when neede requires,
namely when you neede to be humbled for some
corruptions, that get too much head in you, or for
other profitable ends.</p>
   <p>And lastly you loose nothing by your tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">
         <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rse</hi> 7. That the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of your faith being much more precious, then of gold that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, though it be tryed by the fire, might be found vnto praise, and honor, and glory at the appearing of Iesus Christ.</note>
and afflictions. For your faith, which is a
thing more preciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in Gods account, then all
the gold in the world (for that will perish, and
come to be of no vse one day) is hereby tryed;
and what though the fire▪ of the furnace of
affliction be somewhat hot, yet remember what
wonderfull praise, and honor, and glory you shall
haue for the stedfastnes of your faith, when
Iesus Christ shall appeare, and with his owne
mouth commend you, and glorifie you before all
the world.</p>
   <p>If you obiect, that you do not know, whether
the former consolations doe belong vnto you,
<pb facs="9"/>
or no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I will put you in minde of three infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
signes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Whom ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ng not seene yee loue, in whom (thogh now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> see him not) yet beleeuing yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable, and full of glory.</note> that you are converted and shall goe
to heauen. 1. The first is your vnfained affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
to the Lord Iesus Christ, though yee neuer
yet saw him with your bodily eyes. 2. The
second is your continuall faith relying vpon him
alone for your reconciliation and saluation▪
3. And the third is the wonderfull, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>chlesse,
and vnutterable, and celestiall ioy, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> some
times yee feele in the presence of God in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
   <p>And therefore yee neede make no doubt, but
beleeue confidently,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 9 Receiuing the end of your faith, euen the saluation of your soules.</note> that God will reward your
trust in him, by giuing such an end to your
course, as that your soules shall be sure to bee
saued.</p>
   <p>And that you may bee the more abundantly
confirmed in the former consolations,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 10. Of which saluation the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue inquired and searched diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who prophesied of the grace that should come vnto you.</note> thinke of
the testimonie of the Prophets, that were men
extraordinarily raised vp of God, and did
prophesie of this great saluation, which is now
come to passe, and fulfilled in vs Christians;
and being appointed, and inspired of God to
foretell the singular priuiledges of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Churches, they tooke marueilous paines. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
it, inquiring diligently by all the meanes
they could.<note place="margin">Verse 11. Searching what or what manner of time the spirit of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> which was in them did signifie, when it test<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand the suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ings of Christ, and the glory that should follovv.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Studying to finde it out, if it were possible,
what, and what manner of time the Holy Ghost,
which was in them ment, when it made them
foretell both that the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> should suffer
so many things, and withall that after his suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="9"/>
there should be wonderfull glorious times
for the Church.</p>
   <p>Now they were answered by reuelation,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 12. Vnto whom it was reuealed, that not vnto themselues, but vnto vs they did the things, which are now reported vnto you by them, which haue preached the gospell vnto you with the Holy Ghost sent downe from heauen, which things the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels desire to looke into.</note> that
they themselues must neuer see those glorious
daies on earth: but that they were vsed only as
Gods seruants to signifie to the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rch, what
should bee the estate of Christians after the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of Christ; according also to the doctrine
of the Apostles, who haue published the same
things to you in the preaching of the gospell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
men inspired by the Holy Ghost from heauen,
and assisted with the visible-gifts of the Holy
Ghost: and your happinesse is so great, that the
Angells of heauen (like the Cherubins, that
stood looking into the Arke) doe with singular
admiration stand and wonder at, and search
into the manifold wisdome of God in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines,
to which you are brought by Christ. And as
you neede to bee comforted, so haue I thought
it fit to exhort you, and first in things that
are generall to you all, both concerning the
matter of holinesse, and concerning the meanes
of it.</p>
   <p>There are three things you should labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 13. Wherefore girde vp the loynes of your minde: be so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and hope to the end, for the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ace that is to be brought vnto you at the reuelation of Iesus Christ.</note>
1. The first is the restraining and resisting
of all lets of godlinesse, which within from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
of nature are wont like long garments to
hinder you in the labour and race of a holy life.
2. The second is the moderation of your selues,
and that right temper in your hearts and liues,
especially in the vse of the outward things of
this world. 3. The third is, the perfecting of
<pb facs="10"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
the assurance of your hope concerning the glory
of heauen, which God hath giuen of his free
grace, and shall be fully brought vpon you at
the last day, when Christ shall be shewed in his
glory to the world.</p>
   <p>Now there are six reasons, which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
you to the care of a holy conversation
intended in the former duties.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 14. As obedient children, not fashio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your selues ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former lusts in your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> 1. The first
concernes the image of God: yee are the
children of God, and therefore you should liue
so, as becomes Gods children, and expresse in
your cariage the resemblance of the nature of
God, not giuing your selues ouer out of the
liking of sinne to the seruice and obedience
of any of those corruptions, which either
your selues liued in before your calling, or
are vsually found in such onely, as know not
GOD.</p>
   <p>But as God, who by the power of his word
hath converted you,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 15. But as he which hath called you is holy, so be yee holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n all manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation.</note> is holy; so should you
striue with respect of all his co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>andements
to resemble the praises of God in all your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
striuing in euery duty to follow your
patterne.</p>
   <p>And the rather, because this hath been ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
required in the old Testament of Gods people,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 16. Because it is written, Be yee holy, for I am holy▪</note>
to propound vnto themselues the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itation of
Gods holinesse, and to detest sinne, because they
would not be vnlike to God.</p>
   <p>2. A second reason may be taken from the
iudgments of God. For the time must certainly
come, when God, whom we call a father, and call
<pb facs="11"/>
vpon as a father in this life,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 17. And if yee call on the Father, who without respect of persons iudgeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto euery mans worke, passe the time of your soiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning here in feare.</note> will summon
vs before his Tribunall certainly, and speedily,
and then no man shall escape, but shall bee
delt with without partiality, or any corrupt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect,
according as mens workes haue beene
either good or euill, and therefore it beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ues vs,
that are in this world but as s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iourners for a
time, to spend our daies in all carefullnesse, and
godly feare.</p>
   <p>3. A third reason may be taken from the
consideration of our redemption,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 18. Forasmuch as yee know that yee vvere not redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vvith corruptible things, as siluer and gold, from your vaine conuersatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by tradition from your fathers.</note> which hath
many important moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es in it: For it cannot
be, but yee all know, that your misery by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
was so great, that yee could not be ranso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
if all the treasures of gold and siluer in
the world had beene giuen for you; and when
you were redeemed, a cheefe respect was had
to the freeing of you from the viciousnesse of
your conuersation, in which vainely yee spent
your times, and which corruption in many
things yee sucked in from the sinfull examples,
and precepts, and ill education of your Parents,
and ancestors.</p>
   <p>But especially,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 19. But vvith the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb vvithout blemish, and vvithout spot.</note> if yee consider, what a matchles
price was giuen for your ransome, euen the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
blood of Christ, who as a most absolute
sacrifice for our sinnes, was without all fault
of nature, or life, and so the full substance
of all the ceremoniall sacrifices, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
was the true lambe without blemish, or
spot, that makes attonement for the sinnes of the
world.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
And the rather, if yee consider, that from all
eternity God had ordained,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 20. Who verily was fore ordanid before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f the world, but was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> for you.</note> that Christ should
dye for you, and when the fulln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse of time
came, that God was to reueale his Some, as the
Sauiour of the world, he shewed him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the flesh,
and caused him to be preached vnto you, and for
your sakes with farre more euidence and cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
then in former ages.</p>
   <p>To you, and for your sakes I say, that doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly
put your trust in Gods mercy through his
merits:<note place="margin">
         <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rs</hi> 21. Who by bin doe beleiue in God, that raised hivs vp frō the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ad, and gaue him glory, that your faith and hobe might bein God.</note> that God, that to shew he was fully paid
the vttermost f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rthing of our debts, came to
the prison doore, and let him out, which he did,
when he raised him from the dead; and besides
exalted him to wonderfull glory, when he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
vp into heauen, that so for the time
to come you might beleeue and trust vpon Gods
goodnesse and fauour to you without all feare
or doubting.</p>
   <p>4. And the rather in the fourth place should
you bee carefull of the former exhortation,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Vers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> 22. Seeing you h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ue purified your soules in obeying the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uth throu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> loue of the brethsen; see that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with a pure heart feru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nntly.</note> if
you consider your relation to the godly, to whom
yee are brethren: For seeing that by the spirit
of God your soules are purified from the lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
of inward e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ills by the holy course you haue
held in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ensing your hearts of those euills,
which might hinder your internall sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
in that obedience you yeeld to the truth of
God: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nasmuch as the end of all this refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
was, that there might be a holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
and affection without hypocrisie and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling
among such as feare God, who are all
<pb facs="12"/>
the children of one Father: therefore see to it
by any meanes, that yee order your liues and
hearts so, that you may loue one another both
with ardent affection, and pure and sincere
hearts, which you neuer doe, vnlesse you girde
vp the loynes of your mindes, and liue soberly,
and be setled in the assurance, that yee shall alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
one day raigne in heauen.</p>
   <p>5. And fiftly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 23. Being borne againe not of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible seed, but of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, by the word of God, which liueth and abideth for euer.</note> the immortalitie of your soules
should perswade with you: you were made new
men, not as you were made men by a naturall
propagation, but inspired with a life, that should
neuer cease, hauing the seede of this eternall
life cast into your hearts by the word of God,
which in it selfe, and by effect in you, liueth and
abideth for euer.</p>
   <p>6. And lastly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 24. For all flesh is as grasse, and all the glory of man, as the flower of grasse: the grasse withereth, and the flower there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of falleth away.</note> if you consider the mortalitie
of your bodies: All in a mans outward estate is
but vaine and transitory, the bodies of all men
are but as the grasse, which is to day, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
is cut downe, and cast into the ouen: Man
is quickly and suddenly gone, nor is the glory
of mens outward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> better then their bodies.
For all the riches, pleasures, &amp;c, of this life,
in which men glory most, they are but as the
flower of grasse: His body withereth like the
grasse, decaying in a short time, till hee haue
nothing left but the very roote of life; and
as for his riches and pleasures, they like the
flower fall of so, as they are neuer recouered
againe, many times in this life, but alwaies in
death.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>
But on the other side;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse</hi> 25. But the word of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euer; and this is the word, which by the Gospell is preached vnto you.</note> the word of God, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
which men should set their hearts, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
in the efficacie of it, in the sense of it, and
in the fruit of it for euer; and that you may
not be mistaken, this is that word
of God, which is daily prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
vnto you.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>