<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120044_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25712</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120044</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iustification or cleering of the Prince of Orendge agaynst the false sclaunders, wherewith his ilwillers goe about to charge him wrongfully. Translated out of French by Arthur Goldyng</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thynges (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that are cheefly to be cōside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in this Iustification of a moste rightful case and innocēt person, against vniust slaūders and slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers: are the vnmeasurable crueltie and vntolerable trechery of the Papistes. Who to maynteine the wrongfull authoritie of their tyrannous kingdome, agaynst God and his Christ, and agaynst the Maiestie of lawfull Princes, whom God hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced to Souereintie for the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of his trew Religion, and for the welfare of the people committed to theyr charge: do so stoppe the eares and blynd the eyes of Princes with their horrible leazynges (where they take place and beare sway): as they nother can see the wronges done to their subiectes by those ministers of Antichrist, nor herken to
<pb facs="3"/>
their iust complayntes, that they might vnderstand them and redresse them. For whereas they themselues hauyng shaken of al obedience towards God and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, and confounded the generall bonds of naturall and cōmon reason, do both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siste all law and lawfull Magistrates, and also (as much as in them lyeth) inforce men either to most miserable thraldome, (of conscience by forsaking God and all godlynesse, and of body by losse of goodes, landes, libertie, wiues, children, lyfe, and good name) or to some meanes to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand so extreme wretchednesse whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they driue them by streyning them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all abilitie of humane patience: yit most slaunderously they beare the states and potentates of the world on hand, that those most innocent and giltlesse persons, (whiche stand in nothyng but onely that which their Prince hath both graunted and sworne that it should bee lawfull for them to do, and in such wise as he by lyke graunt and othe hath giuē them leaue and commaundement to do, as appeereth most euidently by his solemne Protestation and vowe made at the tyme of his ioyfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb facs="3"/>
when he was first admitted to the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie of those countreyes, at the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest request and intreataunce of the late Emperour Charles his father, who made the lyke solemne othe Protestation and vowe before him and with him:) are the authors, practizers and workers, of all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, confusions, mutinies, vprores, trub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, rebellions, and treazons: only bycause that after suffrance of their excessiue tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts, &amp; the thrustyng of thē out of their natiue countreys: they giue them not leaue to tread thē vtterly vnder foot as myre, or rather to rid thē quite &amp; cleane out of the world, with the Gospell and Religion of Christ. Which thyng they could not doe, if the Princes whō the Romish Antichrist holdeth yit captiue in the prison of super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious ignoraūce, would vout safe but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to stand as indifferent Iudges, and to make that simple account of them, which euen comō reazon would they should, that is to wit, as of their subiectes. For no righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Iudge condemneth without heering the allegatiōs of both parties, nother doth any rightfull Prince permit his subiectes to reuenge their owne wrongs, and much
<pb facs="4"/>
lesse to oppresse, deuour, and eate vp one an other. Therfore when the hartes of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereine liege Lordes are so shet vppe, and their myndes so alienated aforehād, by the sinister perswasions of cankerharted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes and sly Sycophantes, which care not whose house be on fire so they may warme themselues by the coales of it, as no truth can haue enterance into their eares or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse into their presence: needes must the people go to wrecke to the preiudice of the Prince, and the people being so wronged cā not but seeke to iustifie the right and truth of their cace, by all good and reasonable meanes, to the church of God, and vnto all such as are not so wholly caried away with blynd and fantasticall affection, but that they haue some abilitie to discerne right and equitie: as may appeere by the treatise heere insewyng. For heere is nothyng sayd or intended to the defence, maintenance or allowyng of any disobedience, disorder, or vnlawfull behauiour of the subiect towards his Prince: but to shewe most humbly and dewtifully both to Prince and subiect, the intolerable incōueniences that grow by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting the mutuall regard that eche of
<pb facs="4"/>
them ought to haue of other, and by the permittyng of Papistes to intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues into suche state of credite and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, as they may be able to inforce a Gouernement to the vpholdyng of their owne kingdome.</p>
   <p>And forasmuch as in this treatise there is mention made of <hi>a Ioyfull Entrey:</hi> it is necessarie to know what the same was. Therfore it is to be vnderstode, that when soeuer any souereine Lord entered into the possession of dominion ouer the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, whither it were by name of Earle, Duke, or any other title of superioritie: by succession, election, or otherwise: he first tooke a sacred and solemne othe, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne the Lawes, Statutes, Customes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Priuiledges of those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and not to procure, cause, suffer, or permitte the infrindging, breaking, abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating, disanulling, impeaching, or alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them or any of them, or the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in, setting vppe, or stablishing of any new, without the consent, counsell, aduice, and agreement of the states of the same Countrey, to the benefite and commoditie of the people: before the whiche othe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
was in no wise allowed or acknowledged as Lord there. By reason wherof, Charles the Emperour, and his sonne Philippe nowe king of Spayne, to stablishe the continew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of their possession in those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, as their predecessours had alwayes done at their first <hi>Entryes:</hi> did lately make solemne and faithfull promis, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station, vowe, and othe, as well for their heyres and successours as for themselues, that besides their maynteinyng of the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, peace, rest, quietnesse, tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and securitie of those Countreys: they and euery of them should and would keepe, obserue, and performe all the auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, Lawes, Statutes, Liberties, and Priuiledges of the same inuiolable, and not bryng in any new customes or orders, or suffer any to be brought in: nor set any Gouerner, Magistrate or Officer ouer them or in authoritie among them, beyng not the same Countreyman borne and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing landes goodes or possessions there: nor call any assembly of the States, nor cause any leuying of money or men of warre: no nor any coyning of money to bee made there, without the consent and aduice of
<pb facs="5"/>
the States of the same Countrie. And for the more confirmatiō and assurance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: after the rehearsall of the particular poyntes and Articles of the said Entrie, (whiche are many) they added in effecte this conclusion folowing: That if they, their heyres, or successors shall by them selues, or by any other, either wholy or partly, doo, or cause to be done, any thing contrary or preiudiciall to the premisses, after what sort soeuer it be: they consent, agree, and graunt to their Prelates, Barōs, Knights, Townes, Cities, Liberties, and al other their subiectes, that then and from thencefoorth they shall not doo to thē, their heyres or successors any kind of seruis, nor owe them any duetie of allegeāce, nor obey thē in any matters wherein they shal haue neede of them, or which they shall desire or require at their handes, vnlesse that vpon reconciliation, satisfactiō, and attonemēt, they be by the states of the same Countries accepted new againe. And to the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they decreed and ordeyned, that all officers appoynted or placed contrary to the faythful purport and true meanyng of this their sayd Entrie, should be dischargcd &amp;
<pb facs="6"/>
displaced: and likewise that what soeuer thing were or should be done or attempted in preiudice or impeachment of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, should be esteemed as voyde and of none effecte. In witnesse and euerlastyng confirmation whereof, the said Emperour &amp; the Prince his sonne did set their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and seales to the sayd othe in writyng, at Louane the fift day of Iuly. 1549. <hi>And this is it that is called the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful entrie.</hi> Whereby, and by many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidentes of their stories, (whiche make mention how the people of those Countries haue refuzed, renounced, reiected, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and depozed diuers of their Lords &amp; soueraignes for their misgouernment, and for infrindging their sayd othe: and in their places elected, appoynted, set vp, and established others, of whose Iustice they had better opinion aud likelyhood: which thyng notwithstandyng they haue not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to doo, but vpon most vrgent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme necessitie, after long sufferance and seking of redresse by all reasonable meanes with most duetifull iutreatance, submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, supplication, and humilitie:) It may playnly appeare, that the state of the lowe
<pb facs="6"/>
Countreys is not an absolute Monarchie or heritable kingdome, after the maner of this Realme, and of Fraunce, and such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like: but a State with condition, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and not to continue any longer than the Lorde whom they doo so accept, vpon hope of his good gouernment, dooth continue in reignyng and rulyng accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to his oth taken at his entrie. Which if he violate, then are they by the same his othe discharged of their subiection and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to hym, and haue full authoritie and free libertie both to resist hym and his Officers, and also to chooze and take to them any other head or Soueraigne that wyll be more frendly and beneficiall to their Countrey, as appeareth by that so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and autentike deede of Duke Iohn, dated at Louane the fourth of Maye. 1420. and by diuers other Records to the same effecte. Whereupon it foloweth, that this Iustificatiō of the Prince of Orendge, and of suche as take his parte, and of the cace wherein they stande, is most iust and rightfull euen in these respectes, though there were no further proofes, wberof not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandyng there are very many in this
<pb facs="7"/>
treatise folowing. Thus I commyt thee to God, who giue thee the spirite of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to discerne accordyng to truth, that thou be not lead into errour, to allowe the thyng that is euyll, or to condemne the thyng that is good.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>