<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120341_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02984</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13127</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120341</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An aduertisement to the King of Nauarre, to vnite him selfe with the King and the Catholique faithe : Beeing in trueth a very slaunderous, false, and seditious libell, against the said King of Nauarre, and other Christian princes ... Truely translated according to the cop printed in French</title>
                 <author>Maillard, André</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 37, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore thou enter into this discourse (Gentle Reader) I am to admonish thee of certaine speciall poyntes, whereof I would desire thee to haue some regarde. First as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Pamphlet, it is made as an answere to a very modest and dutifull declaration, written by the KING of
<pb facs="3"/>
NAVARRE, to the King his soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, as concerning the slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders published against him &amp;c.</p>
   <p>And heerin, by many needlesse shifts and palpable cauilles, he laboreth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh against the saide King, because of his Christian Religion, and for that he wil not stoup to the man of Roome. In al which windlasses, he dooth but waste time, with high woordes and termes of disgrace, against those who with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, are content to beare the heauie yoke for their maisters sake, which the aduerssenes of the time laieth vppon them, and God hath appointed to make triall of his Children.</p>
   <p>Secondly, for the contempt he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of Religion, and aduauncing of the inuentions and traditions of men, flatly condemning the Christians, who leane only to the woord of God, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the olde and new Testament, and
<pb facs="3"/>
who will beleeue no other doctrine, though an Angell should reueale it from Heauen: I doubt not but his childish, grosse and absurd reasons, will be very easely perceiued, and specially of the lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, who knowe that better wine neuer comes from such vessels, nor greater rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons from such sencelesse cauillers, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rather to be pitied for their folly, then enuied, because we will shewe more Christian charitie.</p>
   <p>Lastly where he inuaieth against our Cuntry of ENGLAND, and entreth into matters aboue my reach: I must leaue them to the Iudgement of such, who are better acquainted with such high poyntes, albeit I beleeue them to be meere false, and vttered vpon a mallici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous stomack. What els is in this lewd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd slaunderous Pamphelet, of bad na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ure (as it is all) or hurtfull to any, as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ould be loth, I leaue it to the good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration
<pb facs="4"/>
of such, who dayly beholde the mallice of Sathan and his ministers, against the godly and well inclined, and therfore to ioyne with me in praier, that God wil either soone amend them, or end them.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>