<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120772_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11247</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120772</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Resurgendum. A notable sermon concerning the resurrection, preached not long since at the court, by L. S</title>
                 <author>L. S.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 31, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Send thee here (gentle Reader) a Sermon, for stile eloquent, for order methodicall, and for substance of matter, right heauenly: heartily praying thee (euen for thine ovvne soules health) to vouchsafe the reading thereof. Taken it vvas not from the Preachers mouth by any fond or nevv found Characterisme (vvhich to the great preiudice of some vvorthie and learned men, hath of late verie piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blemished some part of their labours this vvay, vvith intollerable mutilations): but set dovvne at their desire, vvho might herein command, by the Authors ovvne pen: and indited (as I verily persuade my self) by special instinct of the holy Ghost. And surely the doctrine of this Sermon is such, as I make no doubt at all, but it vvil be held to be most needfull and necessarie, especially for these desperat times of ours: vvherein amongst other most erronious sects vvhich rent in peeces the coate of Christ, and the vnitie of his Church, that one of the Saduces (vvho say there is no resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) is not perhaps of all other the least imbraced. VVith this sort of hel-hounds this godly Sermon (though not of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) doth chiefly encounter, and vvith inuincible argumēts beateth them dovvne flat to the ground: assuring all flesh of that great and generall Resurrection, vvhich euery true Christian is bound both in heart to beleeue, and vvith his mouth to confesse: hovvsoeuer the prophane Atheist in the
<pb facs="3"/>
greatnesse of his vaine and vvicked imaginations may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervvise fancie to himselfe, not vvithout his ovvne reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilesse damnation, vnlesse in time he do repent him of his sinne. And vvould to God many such <hi>alarums</hi> as this, might dayly be rong and sounded into our eares: that (if it vvere possible) euery Christian might haue as deepe an impression, and be no lesse affected vvith the continuall cogitation and remembrance of our <hi>resurrection</hi> at the last day, then that godly father <hi>S. Ierome</hi> seemed to be, vvho sayd, <hi>Whether I eate or drinke, whether I sleepe or wake, or what thing else so euer I do: me thinkes I heare a trumpet alwayes sounding thus in mine eares: Arise you dead, and come vnto iudgement.</hi> And so (gentle Reader) I leaue thee to the grace of God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>