<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right worshipfull, worthie, and
vertuous Gentleman, Sir William Hatton
Knight, all happinesse.</title>
           <author>Ashley, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120864_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68163</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13102</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120864</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right worshipfull, worthie, and
vertuous Gentleman, Sir William Hatton
Knight, all happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Ashley, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comparison of the English and Spanish nation: composed by a French gentleman against those of the League in Fraunce, which went about to perswade the king to breake his alliance with England, and to confirme it with Spaine. By occasion whereof, the nature of both nations is liuely decyphered. Faithfully translated, out of French, by R.A</title>
                 <author>Gentil-homme francois</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 41, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right worshipfull, worthie, and
vertuous Gentleman, Sir William Hatton
Knight, all happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His comparison of <hi>England</hi> with
<hi>Spaine,</hi> framed (as it should seem)
by some learned French gentlemā
experienced in the estate of both
Countries, but iealous (as he saith)
of the honor of his owne; and (as
appeareth) especially desirous of the prosperitie, and
preseruation thereof; may serue vnto vs for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
patterne, and a liuely example howe farre the
loue of truth is to be preferd aboue al other respects:
yea euen aboue the dutie due vnto our countrie,
which ought notwithstanding to be in greater e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimation
amongest vs, then any reuerent respect
of Parentes; or affection towardes friendes, kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes,
or allyes; or whatsoeuer else we holde dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest
vnto vs. Which loue of truth in this author see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
to haue beene ioyned with so zealous a care
of the wel-fare of his Countrie, that like a skilfull
&amp; wise Chirurgian, he choseth rather to rip vp old
sores, which peraduenture may seeme to be healed
outwardly; then to drawe ouer them faire scars, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
them to rankle and fester inwardly. For euen
as a good Phisician carefull to cure his patients ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie,
and desirous of his health &amp; recouerie, doth
<pb facs="3"/>
not minister pleasant potions, if they be vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
to his purpose; but rather holesome restaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues,
though peraduenture somewhat yrkesome:
So the author of this treatise, especially carefull and
desirous of the good and flourishing estate of his
troubled and afflicted Countrie, (which he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly
prooueth to cōsist not wholy, though chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
in her selfe: but to depend much on her ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
with such of her neighbour Nations, as may
most aduantage or endamage her) to effect his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion
for her benefite and preseruation, bringeth
such proofes as (being but such as their owne Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories
afford) may seeme partiall prayses of our
Countrie, and purposed disgraces of his owne.
Which roundnesse, and integritie of his made me
at the request of some friendes, that vnderstood not
well the French to translate it into English: which
I vndertooke so much the rather, because it contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
the memorable, and valiant deedes of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed
Ancestors, in that noble Realme of
France; togither with a rehearsall of the Spanish
braueries: that the viewe of the one, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
of the other, may stirre vp that courage
which ought still to remaine in our English harts;
that we do not degenerate from our noble Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors,
but with an earnest emulation followe
those happie footsteps of our famous forefathers:
<pb facs="3"/>
and learne to despise those magnificent <hi>Dom Diegos</hi>
and <hi>Spanish Caualieros,</hi> whose doughtiest deedes
are bragges and boastinges, and themselues (for
the most part) shadowes without substaunce:
whose affected <hi>Monarchie,</hi> is like to prooue a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded
<hi>Anarchie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This translation (how simple soeuer) I offer to
your courteous acceptaunce, not that any wayes
you neede it, or that in ought it may pleasure you,
or stand you in steede; who by your owne indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious
indeuours, and continued trauailes in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
Countries, haue so aboundantly made you
profite both in the French, and in other languages
and knowledge: but because I willingly embrace
whatsoeuer small oportunitie of expressing my
gratefull affection towardes you, for those mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde
benefites, which, by your good meanes, and
care had heretofore of my well dooing, I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, your benefites, not onely extended
towardes me, but heaped so largely on my name
and neerest friendes, by our Right honorable good
L. and Patrone, may by good right challenge at
our handes whatsoeuer any trauaile, industrie, and
endeuour of ours may bring forth to the extolling
of that honorable name, vnto the which amongst
the rest, I desire to be accounted as one that is most
<pb facs="4"/>
entirely and affectionatly deuoted. Thus crauing
your courteous acceptation, with the continuance
of your fauourable affection; I desire the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
(who hath hitherto so highly fauoured your
forwarde enterprises) continually to prosper your
vertuous proceedinges: both to the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite,
and your particular aduancement.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, humbly affectionate,
<hi>Robert Ashley.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>