<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120872_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06155</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16645.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120872</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The godly garden of Gethsemani : furnished with holsome fruites of meditation and prayer, vpon the blessed passion of Christ our Redeemer</title>
                 <author>Loarte, Gaspar</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Carter, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>288 pages, illustrations, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y chaunce hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peninge vppon this litle Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise written in the Italian by a deuoute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, as it appeareth, and one specially professed by rules of Christian life, to the glorious name of Iesu: for my small vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in that tongue, and further exercise therein, I put on it an English habite of suche course weauing as skil serued me. And finding therein suche swéetenes as is alwayes proper to so good matter, I thought good
<pb facs="3"/>
to bestowe my simple trauayle though with more charges, in presenting onely the same to a speciall good friend or two: as a winter flowre to weare in their bosome, or red Rose nowe at Christmas, by my tenure or ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice due: whiche they might at their pleasure ioyne with other posies of their accustomed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions. If thou, good Reader, chaunce vpon any one booke tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the liberalitie of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or otherwise by more num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber printed then I purposed, I haue therefore to desire thée to accept it with good will, as I know they do to whom of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
<pb facs="3"/>
I vowed my trauels, &amp; also that thou wilt excuse and beare with all the faultes committed by the Printer or me for this time, which are not so great to frustrate thée or me of the fruite of thy exercise or expectation herein, which is encrease of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and deuotion. Of which thou mayst assure thy self to reape as much fruit to thy comfort as is possible of so litle a treatise.</p>
   <p>I haue called it by the name of the garden of <hi>Gethsemani,</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my fansie to the Garden where Christe prayed and shed both water and blood for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: which name for néede
<pb facs="4"/>
may put thée sometime in mind oftner to resorte to this garden of exercise, and to haue Christes wordes to his Disciples there alwayes sounding in thy eares &amp; slumbring minde: <hi>Can ye not watch with me a litle while?</hi> &amp;c. Also our heauēly <hi>Salomon</hi> and Sauiour Christe inuiteth his spouse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church in these words: <hi>Come into my garden my sister and wife:</hi> And she our mother founde no flowre or fruite in this paradise of god more to hir liking, than this trée of life, the blessed crosse of Christ: as may wel appeare by hir own words: <hi>A nosegay of myrrhe is my true
<pb facs="4"/>
loue to me, and within my brest his habitation shal be.</hi> Meaning by the myrrhe, whiche for the bitternesse thereof was geuen Christ to drinke in his extreme thirst, and which for the swéete smell agayne, serued amongest other thinges to annoynt his body in the sepulchre: That she reioyced in nothing more then to gather hir selfe a posie of the bitter paynes and sorowes that Christe suffered for hir and hir faythfull children. Then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to hir example, as children rightly nurtured in hir lappe, let vs not thinke it tedious to followe hir course and steppes,
<pb facs="5"/>
and say with her: <hi>In the sweete sent of thy oyntmentes</hi> (Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord) <hi>I do runne after thee.</hi> And let vs holde alwaies in our breast, and kéepe in memory by continuall meditation, all the grieuous tormentes and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which our sauiour suffered for the redemption of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde, that therby we may learne and knowe the length &amp; the breadth, the height &amp; depth of that moste healthfull trée and Crosse of Christ, which of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy I beséeche him graunt both thée &amp; me good Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>