<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Epistle to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120492_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11498</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120492</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Epistle to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians profession, or A treatise of the grounds and principles of diuinity : by way of question and answer. In which all the chiefe grounds of religion are so plainely proued and explained by the Word of God, as that the meanest capacitie may by reading vnderstand the same</title>
                 <author>I. G.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Dever (Dewer), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 97, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>An Epistle to the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Readers, when I writ this Treatise, I neuer intended the same should come to publike view: I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended the good of my owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Familie, thereby iudging my labours altogether vnworthy of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon view. But afterwards considering that a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good is euer to be preferred before a priuate, and being publisht it might dee more good in the hands of many in one day, then in my owne priuate Family in many yeares: I was moued through the importunity of some friends to present the same, resoluing that it will meet with many exceptions and obiections among many people, as alwaies the workes and labours of others going before haue done.</p>
   <p>Wherefore Christian Reader, I thought good to acquaint you with such reasons as moued me to publish the same, and to remoue such obiections as I conceiue may bee made against the same. The first reason is, because of all these errours and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
<pb facs="6"/>which dee now so much abound, is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the grounds of Religion grounded vpon the Word of God: Yee erre not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Mat. 22.29.</hi> And therefore we haue cause to blesse God for that order of teaching inioyned by publike authority by way of Catechisme, that so people may thereby be the better instructed in the grounds and principles of Diuinity; and that the publike Catechising may bee the more profitable; it is necessary that people doe acquaint themselues in priuate with such Catechismes as do most plainely by the Scriptures set forth the grounds and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion; and among the rest of Catechismes that are published, Christian Reader, you shall not find your labour lost in the reading of this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme, for this I dare presume that those that read the same with vnderstanding, shall bee able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand in some measure any ground of Religion that is taught by the Minister in publicke; which would be to no small profit both to the Minister and people. Secondly, because I haue obserued by experience that the more Ministers contend against those errours which doe now so much abound ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Sermons or writings, the more they spread abroad: because such is the corruption of mans nature through pride, that the more hee is opposed in those errours which he mayntaines the more strongly hee labours to defend them &amp; spread them abroad. Whereby the peace and vnity of the
<pb facs="6"/>Church is much broken and disturbed to the great griefe and wounding of the soules of all Gods people, and therefore I conceiue that the best way both to suppresse heresie, and to maintaine the peace and vnity of the Church, is positiuely to maintaine those grounds of diuinity which are established and inioyned by publike authority, grounded vpon the Word of God; for one contrary will expell another, when light comes, darkenesse is expelled: and so when the light of Gods Word is clearely set forth, and shines in the Church, the darknesse of Popery and all other errours will be dayly expelled: like as it was with the <hi>Philistians Dagon,</hi> when the Arke was set vp <hi>Dagon</hi> fel to the ground of himselfe. So when Christ and his Gospell is set vp and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who is the true Arke, then <hi>Dagon,</hi> all false Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will fall downe to the ground; for nothing so much ouer-throwes Sathan and his Kingdome. For by the preaching of the Gospell Sathan is say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to fall from Heauen like lightning; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee haue great cause to blesse God in that wee haue those grounds of Religion grounded vpon the word established by publike authority, and inioyning all the Ministers of this Land to teach and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the same, the which I could wish were not too much neglected by many. For my owne part that loue that I beare to the truth of Gods Word, and to the peace and vnity of the Church, moued me to cast in my Mite, desiring that it may bee a
<pb facs="7"/>meanes to stirre vp others who are farre more able, to cast in out of their treasures, that so the truth of Gods Word may be more cleared: the doctrine of the Church, the peace and vnity of the same more defended and maintayned; the ignorant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed, and errours suppressed, all of which by this meanes through the blessing of God may be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. I take not vpon me to teach any, but I onely shew my iudgement as an inferiour, not passing for the censure of any. It may be some will be ready to obiect &amp; say that this was agreat deale of need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse labour spent. For we haue no need of new Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chismes now seeing we haue so many Printed alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made by worthy learned men: and seeing that there is publike Catechising in euery Congregation: to which I answer, I confesse that there are many publike Catechismes made by learned men: to whom I iudge my selfe farre inferiour, and yet I say that among all those varieties of printed Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chismes, you shal find this differing from all other in matter, method, or manner, if not in all: for I neuer yet saw two Catechismes that were iust alike in matter, method, and manner, although they were both concerning the same grounds, but how-euer, in this one thing it is different from all the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chismes that euer I yet saw, namely in the manner of prouing the grounds: for in all ordinary Catechismes the places of Scripture are onely quoted to proue the grounds, by reason where of people that are not
<pb facs="7"/>acquainted with the Scriptures, knowes not whether those grounds be agreable to the word of God or no, and to turne to euery proofe is such a labour as that few will vndertake the same. Wherefore to ease the Reader I haue taken the more paynes not onely to quote the proofes of Scripture, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to write them downe, framing euery an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer so neere as I could to the very wordes of my Text alleadged for the prouing of the same, with explication of such thinges as are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure: which labour I shall thinke well bestowed in writing so that it may bee profitable to the Reader. Agayne I conceiue that there is the more need of Printed Catechismes in regard of that publike Catechising inioyned by authority, that by reading in priuate they may bee the better able to vnderstand the Minister in publike, and so shall the Minister profit the people with lesse labour in teaching in regard of often repeating of the same grounds: and indeed to speake truly it is the duty of euery Maister or Gouernour of a Family to teach and instruct their owne Family in the grounds of Religion in their owne priuate Houses, and not leaue all for the Minister to doe in publike: and because all are not able in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of knowledge to instruct their Families of themselues, it is necessary that they get such Catechismes as are printed, in which the grounds of Religion are most plainely preoued and set
<pb facs="8"/>forth. And among many other Chatechismes as I conceiue, you shall find this to bee one, by which you may benefit both your selues and your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; especially if you in reading marke and obserue what dependencie one thing hath vpon another. But it may be some will obiect and say, that this Chatechisine is too large, concerning too many things; for one thing is necessary to be knowne, which is God in Christ; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what neede people trouble their heads to know so many things? To which I answer, That I freely confesse, that according to the words of Christ, <hi>Iohn 17.3.</hi> This is life eternall, to know thee to bee the very God, and whom thou hast sent Iesus Christ: the which are the maine things contained in this Chatechisme, for to know God aright, is to know him in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in his Attributes, in the Trinity of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and in his workes. And to know Christ aright, is to know him in his Person, in his Natures, and in his Offices. And whosoeuer doth not in some measure thus know God and Christ, knowes neither God nor Christ, but meerely a fantacy of their owne braines. Neither could I well tell how to contract those grounds into a shorter volume, for sure I am that the gleanings which are left behind are more then the whole Croppe heere gathered together. Againe, I did so neere as possibly I could make
<pb facs="8"/>Christ the maine subiect of this Treatise: and that those that reade with vnderstanding, may plainely see by the drift and scope of the same; for all those things which go before the couenant of grace, concerning the fall of man, his miserie by reason of sinne, and the puninshment thereof, serues to make man see how miser able he is without Christ. And all those things concerning the law, are to serue vnto Christ, as the ministery of Iohn Baptist going before to make way for Christ, <hi>Mat. 3.3.</hi> and all the rest following, are either concerning the person of Christ, the two natures of Christ, the offices of Christ, or the Kingdome of Christ: so that Christ and his Kingdome are the mayne things contained in this Cathechisme. Wherefore I desire not to write much in commendation of the same, but rather desire that the worke may prayse it selfe, wishing that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may finde as much benefit in reading as I found in writing; howsoeuer, I desire that it may bee accepted as a testimony of my loue vnto the truth, and the Church and people in which I liue; for whose sakes I haue improued that small talent which the Lord hath lent me, desiring that it may be to Gods glory, and his Churches good: which that it may so bee, I commend and commit both you and it vnto the blessing of almighty God, and rest yours in the Lord, <hi>I G.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>