<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE
Christian-Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120028_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15419</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25693</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120028</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE
Christian-Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Loidoromastix: that is, A scourge for a rayler : containing a full and sufficient answer vnto the vnchristian raylings, slaunders, vntruths, and other iniurious imputations, vented of late by one Richard Parkes master of Arts, against the author of Limbomastix. VVherein three hundred raylings, errors, contradictions, falsifications of fathers, corruptions of Scripture, with other grosse ouersights, are obserued out of the said vncharitable discourse, by Andrevv Willet Professor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Bankworth, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 195, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE
Christian-Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Rezin</hi> King of <hi>Aram,</hi> and
<hi>Pekah</hi> King of <hi>Israel</hi> had conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
against <hi>Iudah,</hi> and fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Ierusalem: the Prophet was
sent with this comfortable mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages
<hi>Feare not,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 7. 4.</note>
      <hi>neither be faint
hearted, for the two tayles of those
smoaking firebrands,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Woodward the Iesuite as it is thought, in his Detection.</note>
      <hi>&amp;c.</hi> two such
suming, rather then fiering brands, haue raised of late a
smoake against me:<note place="margin">R. Parkes.</note> some foure yeares since a Popish Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite
and now of late an English Israelite: But as the
flames of the first were soone quenched, so I doubt not
but the irefull heate, and vaine smoake of the other will
quickly be laide. It were somewhat too hard to say of
these two aduersaries, as <hi>Tulke</hi> did of his two enemies
<hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>labella</hi> and <hi>Antonie:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philippi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 11.</note>
      <hi>Duo haec capita nata sunt post ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines
natos tet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rrima <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> quorum alter effecit,
quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pt abat, de altero p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tefactum est, quod cogitaret: these
two heads are sprung vp the worst and most dishonest of all
men aliue; the one whereof hath effected, what he desired.
the other hath discouered what he thought:</hi> for neither will
I thinke so vncharitably of them, though they thinke and
speake most basely and vilely of me: neither hath either of
them had his pleasure of me, but in seeking to disgrace
me, haue defamed themselues: and haue rather bewraied
what they thought, then effected, what they intended.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nisius</hi> when he heard of two young men, that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
vpon him, and perceiued that the one spake in drinke,
but the other seemed to be sober, and yet reuiled: he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missed
<pb facs="10"/>
the one as a drunken and foolish person,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> but puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonists.
The one beeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
Babylons cuppe, and hauing wrung out the very dregges
of Romish superstition, writ his pleasure of me in his madd
and drunken fittes: the other, professing himselfe a sober
Protestant, (but let him take heede, if all be true<note n="*" place="margin">ô si &amp; mihi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret dicere, quae multi cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant, iam &amp; nos intelligeres scire, quae om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes sciunt, &amp; me quoque au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire, quae nullus ignorat Hieron. ad Theoph.</note> I heare,
least that one cuppe of (<hi>nimis</hi>) more, make him not as
drunke as the other) hath in his pretended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
the raging fittes of the other lightbraine. But I passe
very little, neither doe I regard their rayling speech, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting
my selfe with that saying of the Apostle, <hi>If ye be
rayled vpon for the name of Christ, blessed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> ye:</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all
they are,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 14.</note> which are maligned for the defense of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>:
and here I may fitly vse those words of <hi>Augustine: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>go
volo te esse sanum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Serm. 164.</note>
      <hi>quare tu furis in me sicut insanus; I
would haue thee to be found and whole and you rage against
me, as one vnsound or madde.</hi> If they are become mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
for the Gospel and the truths sake, I will therein glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.
The one of them shooteth his darts at me, because I
strike at the very bodie of Poperie: the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arpeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
I prune off one of the branches thereof, that super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious
opinion of <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> as euen now shall be
s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ewed.<note place="margin">Dialog. 1. adv. Pelagian.</note> But I say here with <hi>Hierome, Bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iter respon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eo,
nunquam me haereticis pepero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>sse, &amp; omni eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sse studio, vt
hostes Ecclesiae, mei quoque hostes fiero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>: I answer briefely,
that I neuer spared heretikes; and haue endeauoured with
all my studie, that the enemies of the Church should also be
enemies vnto me.</hi> Let them diuide this sentence betweene
them: let the first take the first part, and the other, that
which remaineth: for this I speake bordly, and confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
that I know no enemies of mine in matter of religion
(some difference in opinion there may be among friends
and wel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>illers, whome yet I count no enemies) but they
are also enemies (I dare say to the Church of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:
that I may here truly v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the Orators words; <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam
<pb facs="10"/>
meo fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> fieri dicam vt nemo his annis viginti Reipu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>hostis
fuerat, quinon bellum eonam tempore, mihi quoque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixerit:
I can not tell by what fatall destinie it happeneth,
that there hath not beene these twentie yeares an enemie to
the Commonwealth</hi> (and so to the Church also) <hi>which hath
not the same time bid battell vnto me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now I come to shew, that this mungrell Protestant,
directly holdeth, that Christ descended in soule to hell, to
deliuer some from thence, that were there, and so conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
maintaineth the Popish opinion of <hi>Limbus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum:</hi>
where they imagined the soules of the Patriarks to
be till the comming of Christ thither.</p>
   <p>1. Place.<note place="margin">P. 9. of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer booke. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. 1. and p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. edit. 2.</note>
      <hi>These are his owne words:</hi> S. Peter mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
sorrowes, which Christ loosed at his resurrection, which
could not be in the sepulchre, where his bodie lay dead, and
senselesse:<note place="margin">P. 12. 1. b. edit. 1. and p. 14. edit. 2. and 2. b. p. 37.</note>
      <hi>and in an other place: he affirmeth they were</hi>
the sorrowes of hell which Christ loosed: <hi>out of which
words this argument is pressed:</hi>
      <q>The sorrowes of hell which Christ loosed, he loosed for
himselfe, or for others ther. deteined: but not for
himselfe: <hi>Ergo</hi> for others.</q>
      <hi>To this he answeareth: 1. in graunting all this to be
true,</hi> and yet it will not follow that the Fathers were deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
out of Lambus:<note place="margin">2. b. p. 37.</note> vnlesse by bell, you vnderstand Limbus
patrum, and the persons there deteined the Patriarks, then
you will fall into the same ditch your selfe, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Contra.</hi> 1. It followeth well, if the conclusion be
graunted, that Christ loosed the sorrowes of bell for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
for either they must be the Fathers which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
out of <hi>Limbus,</hi> which the Papists make a member
of hell: or els he falleth into a worse heresie, that some of
the damned deteined in hell, were thence deliuered. 2. Is
he so blind and absurd, that he seeth not how this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
is enforced against him, and not out of the Replyers
iudgement: doth the opponents conclusion force the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputer,
I pray you, or the answearer: the conclusion is, <hi>Ergo
be deliuered the Fathers out of Limbas:</hi> doth he inferre
<pb facs="11"/>
this to confirme his owne opinion, or to confute yours?
The Replyer therefore will keepe himselfe well enough
out of the ditch, while he himselfe sticketh fast in the
mire.</p>
   <p>Ans. 2. <hi>He denieth the assumption, affirming with</hi>
Augustine,<note place="margin">Epist. 99.</note>
      <hi>that</hi> Christ loosed the sorrowes of hell for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Contra.</hi> 1. In deede one of <hi>Augustines</hi> expositions in
that place is, that Christ may be said to haue loosed the
sorrowes of hell for himselfe, <hi>quemadmodum solvi possunt
laquei venantium, &amp;c. as the snares of hunters may be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
least they should hold, not because they did hold:</hi> but this
exposition can not serue his turne: for he saith, these sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<hi>were loosed at Christs resurrection:</hi> they were not
then loosed before, till then: so it followeth that Christ
was in them: which <hi>Augustine</hi> there denieth; <hi>neque co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat
in eis esse tanquam in vinoulis: he beganne not at all
to be in those sorrowes, as in bandes.</hi> 2. Againe, he saith,
<hi>these sorrowes</hi> were not in the graue, because the bodie
was senslesse, and so felt them not: therefore by the same
reason, those sorrowes were in hell, because Christ soule
was full of sense, and consequently felt them. Thus, will
hee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> hee, either hee must confesse, that some other
were deliuered out of the sorrowes of hell by Christs
descending thither, or that he himselfe felt the sorrowes
of hell.</p>
   <p>2. The second place that encreaseth this suspition is,
because he striueth mightily,<note place="margin">1. b. p. 36. 1. edit.</note> that we must read, 1. Pet.
3. 19. <hi>the spirits, which were in prison,</hi> not <hi>which are:</hi>
whereupon it followeth,<note place="margin">2. b. p. 39.</note> that he thinketh, some were
in the prison of hell, but are not, or els he striueth about
words.</p>
   <p>Ans. It followeth not, because I say it should be translae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
(which were) &amp;c. not, (which are) that they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
were in hell, but are not: no more then it followeth,
the Angels were in heauen at Christs as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ension, but are
not.<note place="margin">2. b. p. 39.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>Contr.</hi> 1. Hee omitteth the other part of the disiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tion,
that either that must follow, or els he striueth about
words. 2. The instance of the Angels therefore is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent:
for the Replyer doth not reason thus; they were in
hell, <hi>Ergo</hi> they are not: but thus, either they were in hell,
and are not, or else he striueth for words. 3. Yet this cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
about the reading of <hi>were</hi> for <hi>are,</hi> giueth strong
suspicion, that hee so thinketh, that some <hi>were</hi> in hell, and
are not; because his great Master; vpon the aduantage of
that word,<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 4. de Christ. anim. cap. 13.</note> inferreth the same conclusion, thus writing: <hi>All
the Latines, &amp; Greekes, whom we haue cited, expound (were)
not (are;) because they will haue them deliuered out of hell
by Christ but it could not bee said truely of those spirits in
the time of Peter, that they were then in the prison.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>3. <hi>The third place is this: In that Christ personally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended
into hell,</hi> it doth more amplifie and set forth his
goodnesse toward mank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>de,<note place="margin">1. b. p. 52. 1. edit. p. 55. 2. edit.</note> &amp;c. for so much, as the more
vile, and loath some the dungeon is, the greater is the loue of
the Prince,<note place="margin">2. b. p. 40.</note> who to enfranchise and set at libertie the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues
there enthralled, dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ineth not to enter into it, in his
owne person.</p>
   <p>Hence it is inferred, that these captiues in hell, which
were enfranchised by Christ descending thither, could be
no other, then the fathers in <hi>Limbo patrum:</hi> for out of the
nethermost hell of the damned, none can be deliuered.</p>
   <p>Ans. 1. <hi>The argument is denied,</hi> Christ went to set
at libertie captiues in hell: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the fathers in Limbo.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Cont.</hi> The argument standeth thus; the captiues in hel
set at liberty, were either in <hi>Limbo,</hi> or in the nethermost
hell.</p>
   <p>But they were not in the nethermost hell, for thence
none can be deliuered.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ergo:</hi> the captiues in hell set at liberty, were those in
<hi>Limbo.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The reason cannot be denied, beeing a true syllogisme:
the Replyer is not then a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in making such reasons:
but the Confuter a brables in denying them.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
Ans. 2. You must first prooue that the Fathers were in
Limbo patrum and that hell, the place of eternall captiuity▪
was all one with it, which yet your selfe affirme, is no part of
hell: and therefore I inferre it is no place of thraldome.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Cont.</hi> 1. Now this ignorant Confuter sheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
a trifler indeed, and a silly Logician, to denie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion,
that the Fathers were not in <hi>Limbe,</hi> which is the
conclusion of the former argument.</p>
   <p>2. How absurd is this fellow, that seeing a manifest
disiunction in the proposition, betweene <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi>
and the nethermost hell; yet saith, it must be prooued that
they are all one.</p>
   <p>3. The Replyer in his owne opinion taketh <hi>Limbus,</hi> to
be neither a part of hell nor any where else; but disputeth
<hi>ex concessis,</hi> according to their conceit, that so imagine.
But this trifling Confuter is caught in his owne wordes;
for in confessing that <hi>Limbus</hi> is no place of thraldome, he
granteth, that such a <hi>Limbus</hi> there is, but not a place of
that qualitie: for according to his owne rule, the forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
must first be granted, (namely, that there is a <hi>Limbus</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
you can dispute of the latter: whether it be a place of
thraldome,<note place="margin">2. b. p. 3.</note> or not; <hi>and thus to giue him his owne words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
you whip your selfe with your owne scourge, whose la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes
if you feel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> not. I say you are very senslesse:</hi> and to vse
<hi>Tullies</hi> words,<note place="margin">Secund. Philip.</note>
      <hi>haec te si vllam partem habes sensus laceret,
haec cruētat oratio: this saying, if you haue any part of sense,
tareth and woundeth you.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Answ. 3. <hi>But the Confuter not insisting vpon any of
these answers, which are very simple; findeth our another:</hi>
that these captiues, enfranchised by Christ, was all mankind,
which by Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s sinne were made guilty of eternall death,
and so made his captiues, that had power ouer death, that is
the diuell, vnder whom wee were held in most slauish thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
&amp;c. vntill such time, as it pleased our most gratious
king to enfranchise vs.<note place="margin">2. b. p. 143.</note> 2. b. p. 143.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Cont.</hi> 1. This answer is not to the purpose, for the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion
out of his former words obiected, is not of captiues
<pb facs="12"/>
to hell and the diuell, but of <hi>captiues in hell.</hi> 2. b. p. 40. and
<hi>there detained. p.</hi> 37. and <hi>enthralled there; to enfranchise
whom our prince descended thither. p.</hi> 40. We were indeede
all captiues by sinne to the diuell, subiect to death, hell, &amp;
damnation, but not captiues and enthralled in hell; this is
but a simple euasion.</p>
   <p>2. Our deliuerance and enfranchising was procured &amp;
purchased by the death of Christ,<note place="margin">The Coufuters inconstancy &amp; vncertaintie.</note> as the Apostle saith, <hi>that
he might destroy through death, him that had power ouer
death, that is the diuell, and that he might deliuer, &amp;c.</hi> for
that ende therefore Christ needed not to descend to
hell.</p>
   <p>3. See how inconstant this new doginatist is: one while
he saith, that Christ descended to hell, <hi>that the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of mankind now performed, might bee manifested euen
vnto the dead.</hi> 2. b. p. 72. sometime, <hi>to denounce retention in
sinne to the obstinate:</hi> and so consequently, in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
death and damnation; for so hee expoundeth
that preaching to the spirits in <hi>Peter:</hi> 2. b. p. 77. And
now it was, as hee saith, to enfranchise, and set at libertie.
And thus hee is one of those, of whome the Apostle spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note place="margin">1. Timoth. 1. 7.</note>
      <hi>They would be Doctors of the Law, and yet vnder stād
not what they speake, nor whereof they affirme.</hi> I may apply
against him the Orators words, <hi>quam miserum est id nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
non posse, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> est conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>: how miserable a
thing is it,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philipp. 2.</note>
      <hi>not to be able to deny that, which it is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>rame to
confesse.</hi> He is ashamed to confesse he holdeth <hi>Limbus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,</hi>
and yet beeing pressed with his owne words, he can not denie it.</p>
   <p>4. Pla. What honour is greater then his, who entreth by
force into his enemies pallace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him of his power,
disfurnisheth him of his treasure;<note place="margin">Lib. 3. p. 5.</note> and returneth victorious,
&amp;c.<note place="margin">In lib. 5. ep. ad. Rom. cap. 6.</note>
      <hi>and what he meaneth by his treasure, hee referreth vs
to a place of</hi> Origen, <hi>where he saith thus;</hi> hic alligato forti,
&amp;c. the strong man beeing here bound vpon the crosse, hee
went forward into his house, into the house of death, into
hell, and tooke thence his goods, that is, the soules, which he
held.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>
5. Pla. Ambrose <hi>is cited in these words,</hi>
      <note place="margin">lib. 3. p. 22.</note> beeing free a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
the dead loosing the power of death, he gaue release to
those which were in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>and what he meaneth hereby,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. de incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Domin. sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. c. 5.</note>
      <hi>the
words following shew, (omitted by him</hi>) hee shed the light
of life vpon those which were placed in hell, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>6. <hi>Pla.</hi>
      <note place="margin">3. b. p. 72.</note> He saith that Christ <hi>euangelized, or deliuered
the glad tidings of the gospel to the dead:</hi> but to whom else
could the preaching of the Gospel be glad tidings, but to
those, which had comfort and deliuerance by it? And so
he must be driuen to say with his great friend,<note place="margin">Bellarm. l. 4. de Christ. anim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13.</note>
      <hi>Pradicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem
Christi, &amp;c. that the preaching of Christ in hell, was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for the annuntiation of that great ioy</hi> (of their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance)
<hi>to the godly soules.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>7. Pl. You must first prooue,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 79.</note> that they erred in holding
that opinion of the deliuery of the Fathers: <hi>but if he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
hold that to bee an error, what needed any further
proofe thereof?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>8. Pl.<note place="margin">3. b. p. 122.</note> Hierom <hi>is cited, who should say,</hi> that Christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended
to hell, vt vinctos de carcere dimitteret: that hee
might <hi>dismisse</hi> them which were bound, out of prison.</p>
   <p>9. <hi>Pl.</hi> Likewise,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 123.</note>
      <hi>Cyril</hi> is brought in, speaking to the
same purpose: <hi>that Christ appeared to the spirits in hell, and
said to those which were in bonds, come forth,</hi> To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
should he alleadge these testimonies, if he consented
not with them herein? for men doe not vse to produce
witnesses against themselues.</p>
   <p>10. <hi>Pl.</hi> He confesseth <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> but denieth it
to be any part of hell: <hi>to let passe (saith hee) your falshood,
(beeing the falsarie himselfe) and absurditie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">3. b. p. 142.</note>
      <hi>in confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
(Limbus patrum) with</hi> locus damnatorum, <hi>the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
no part of hell, as your selfe euery where preach,</hi> But this
is his owne preaching or rather prating▪ for the Replyer in
those places,<note place="margin">Limb. 43. 44.</note> speaketh onely of <hi>Abrahams</hi> bosome not a
word of <hi>Limbus.</hi> If then, in his opinion, there was a <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
patrum,</hi> then either the fathers were deliuered thence,
or else they are in <hi>Limbe</hi> still; for heauen or paradise, I
hope he will not take to be <hi>Limbus,</hi> which the masters of
<pb facs="13"/>
that tearme the Romanists, take for a prison and dungeon
of darknes.</p>
   <p>11. Pl. Cassiodorus <hi>is brought in thus witnessing for
the deliuerie of the Fathers out of hell:</hi>
      <note place="margin">3. b. p. 144.</note> Christ hauing
bound the devill, brought out those prisoners which he held
in captiuitie.</p>
   <p>12. Hierome <hi>againe is thus alleadged:</hi> Christ descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
not into the whale,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 169.</note> but into hell, to the ende, that those
which were in hell, might be loosed from perpetuall bonds.</p>
   <p>13. Augustine <hi>also is brought to the same purpose:</hi> I
see no reason,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 194.</note> why we should beleeue, that our Sauiour came
thither, but to saue some from the sorrowes and paines
thereof.</p>
   <p>14. <hi>So also</hi> Origene <hi>is produced:</hi> the onely begotten
sonne (of God) descended into hell for the saluation of the
world,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 194.</note> and thence brought backe againe the first man A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</p>
   <p>15. For the enfranchising and setting at libertie the
captiues in hell, he alleadgeth <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> referring vs onely
in generall to his exposition of the Creede: in the which
he directly affirmeth in these words, <hi>Redijt victor à mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. b. p. 55. 2. edit.</note>
      <hi>inferni spolia, &amp;c. he returned a conquerour from the
dead, and carying with him the spoile of hell, brought out
those which were held of death.</hi> So it seemeth that therein
he concurreth with <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> for the bringing out of some
out of hell.</p>
   <p>16. Whereas the Article of the descension was thus
set downe in K. <hi>Edwards</hi> time, in the Synode held <hi>ann.
1552. As Christ died for vs, and was buried, so it is to be
beleeued, that he descended into hell: for his bodie lay in the
graue till the Resurrection, his spirit beeing sent forth from
him, was with the spirits which were detained in prison, or in
hell, and preached vnto them, as testifieth Peter:</hi> the last
clause whereof was left out by the Reuerend Fathers of
this Church in their Synode, <hi>ann.</hi> 1562. and so remaineth
still. Now this man commeth, and would expound the
meaning of that clause omitted:<note place="margin">2. b. p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> saying, <hi>that their applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>
of those words of Peter vnto Christs descension into hell,
is no other then all the auncient Fathers haue made on that
place, as may appeare by holy Athanasius, &amp;c. <hi>But</hi> Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasius
<hi>saith,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>he</hi> preached the Gospel or glad tidings to those
which were in hell:<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>al. 4. de sanct. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>it.</note>
      <hi>so he vnderstandeth S. Peters</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.
<hi>So likewise</hi> Iustinus <hi>and</hi> Ireneus <hi>say,</hi> descendit ad eos evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelizare
salutem:<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>alog. cum T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>phon.</note> he descended vnto them to evangelize, or
bring the glad tidings of saluation,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ea. l. 3. c. 23.</note>
      <hi>as they cite the Prophet
Isai: wherefore, if he vnderstand it according to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position,
he must hold, that saluation and deliuerance was
preached by Christ to some in hell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>17. Place. <hi>The harrowing of hell, &amp;c.</hi> if you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
an old ploughman in your haruest,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 110.</note> is no such matter, as
you take it for,<note place="margin">Northbrokes confes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. c. 4. fol. 11.</note> but such as ought to be beleeued of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
as containing a deepe mysterie: <hi>he would father his
conceit vpon an other, that</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">he expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that phrase of the harrowing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ell, of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie obtained by Christs death ouer hell: not of his personall descending thither, as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oth.</note>
      <hi>fauoureth it not: but indeede
he cunningly hereby conueieth his owne opinion, as fit to
be beleeued of all Christians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>18. His opinion is that <hi>Iob</hi> was in hell: for that place,
Iob 17. 13. he readeth thus: <hi>hell shall be my house, and I
shall make my bed in the darke.</hi> And further he addeth: <hi>for
so much as Iob was a perfect figure of Christ, in many
things, the word (bed) taken in the better part, doth very
truely agree vnto him:</hi>
      <note place="margin">3. b. p. 153.</note>
      <hi>because, though</hi> hell <hi>be a place of
restlesse disquiet to the wicked, yet was it to him a place of
quiet rest.</hi> In which words, beside that in right constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the whole sentence runneth vpon <hi>Iob,</hi> he beeing a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
of Christs beeing in hell, as he maketh him, must first
be there himselfe. But to the hell of the damned he will
not thrust him, where els was he then in <hi>Limbo?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>19. <hi>But he doth not more apparantly discouer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
then in these two places following: the first is, 3. b. p.</hi>
170. Vnto these I will also adde a propheticall saying,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0.</note> (as it
seemeth to me) which I finde reported out of two of the most
famous Doctors among the auncient Hebrewes:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Hoc eo dosti. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. R. Simeon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>d Galatinum.</note> (the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Iewes shall kill their Messias, then shall his soule descend
to hell,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. b. 8. c. 21.</note> where it shall abide three daies, that it may bring
<pb facs="14"/>
from thence all the soules of the Fathers, and of the Iust, and
lead them with him into Paradise, and heauenly glorie:)
<hi>If this be a</hi> propheticall saying, <hi>then it must haue his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment;
and so in his iudgement the soules of the
Fathers and the iust men, were brought out of hell by
Christs descending thither.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>20. <hi>The other place is, 3. b. p.</hi> 174. The ende of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming
visitation he maketh to haue beene,<note place="margin">3. b. p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> (the illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of those, which sate in darknes, and in the shadow of
death,) which words S. Damascene and Ruffinus applie to
Christs descension in hell: And in truth the words of (vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siting
and redeeming) doe necessarily implie a freedome to
men in captiuitie, which to denie to haue beene in hell, as you
doe in your second assumption, is to derogate from the blessed
death, and passion of Christ. <hi>Now my second assumption (as
he calleth it) was, But Christ redeemed none in hell. This
assumption, seeing he denieth, what els can be his opinion,
but that Christ redeemed and deliuered some in hell by
his descending thither? and therein agreeth with</hi> Damas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene
<hi>and</hi> Ruffinus.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>I appeale now to all iudicious men and vnderstanding
Readers, whether this counterfeit Confuter, be not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly
conuinced to be an euident maintainer of</hi> Limbus
Patrum: <hi>therefore how voide of all truth and modestie
that speach is,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. b. p. 5.</note>
      <hi>who seeth not?</hi> there is no cause, nor colour
of cause in the world (<hi>saith he</hi>) why you should accuse that
mine answear, as any way enclining to that opinion: for what
one word is there thorough the whole booke, which doth so
much as insinuate any suspition thereof? <hi>But what neede
this circumloquution of words, when the thing it selfe is
apparant: according to that saying,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; when the matter is conspicuous, the
prolixitie of speech is superfluous. <hi>These places obiected
doe giue such euidence of his opinion, that he can not
with modestie denie it:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philippi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>as the Orator saith,</hi> Respondebisne
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d haec, aut omnino hiscere audebis: can you answer any
thing to this, or dare you once open your mouth? <hi>and so I
<pb facs="15"/>
say with</hi> Hierome:<note place="margin">Apolog▪ 3. cont. Ruffin.</note> si non illud scripsisses, vtcun{que} de luto
evaderes, If you had not thus written, &amp;c. you might haue
wrastled out of the mire.</p>
   <p>But in defence of this his opinion, of the deliuering
the Fathers out of <hi>Limbus,</hi> antiquity will bee allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged:
for this goeth for currant among the Fathers:
whereunto I answere; That the auncient writers of the
Church, in some things might bee ouerseene, and that
this error might be both generall, and continue long also:
as the Patriarkes long remained in that error of Bygamie,
and Polygamie, and corrected it not. <hi>Augustine</hi> answered
<hi>Hierome</hi> well, who hauing alleadged diuers places, said,
<hi>Patere me errare cum talibus:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. ep. 19.</note> suffer me to erre with such:
<hi>quis est</hi> (saith he) <hi>qui se velit cum quolibet errare?</hi> who is
there that would willingly erre with any? The Orator
saith well, <hi>quae malum est haec ratio, semper optimis causis
veteranorum nomen opponere,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philip. 10.</note>
      <hi>&amp;c. quos quidem libertatis
adiutores complecti debetis, seruitutis authores sequi non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betis:</hi>
What reason is this, alwaies in good causes to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
the name of the auncients, whom you ought to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
as helpers of your liberty, not to follow, as authors
of your seruitude. The like may be said of the auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
that we ought to follow them, when they stand for
the truth, not to be lead by them, when they incline to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.
And herein the <hi>intent</hi> of the Fathers is rather to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected,
then the <hi>content</hi> of their speech: their meaning
was, that euen the Fathers of the olde Testament, though
beeing at rest in Abrahams bosome, yet had an accession
of ioy, the Redemption of mankind beeing accomplished
by Christ: (like as the Saints now shall haue the like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
of ioy at the resurrection, and consociation of their
bodies with their soules) though they failed in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
apprehension and application of this mysterie. And
so I end this point, with that worthy saying also of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator,<note place="margin">Philip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 9.</note>
      <hi>Non exempla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aierum quarenda sunt, sed consilium
est eorum, à quo exempla nata sunt, explicandum:</hi> The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
of the Elders, are not (so much) to bee sought into,
<pb facs="15"/>
as their intent, and counsell, from the which the examples
are sprung, is to be expounded.</p>
   <p>Thus much for the matter of his booke in generall,
now concerning the manner: First, he faileth in charitie, in
confuting publikely, that which was written first priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
and bringing into open view to the world, that which
was sent in secret to a gentleman: I speake of the originall
occasion of his first booke, wherein, he beeing a Christian,
saw not so much, as <hi>Tullie</hi> perceiued by the light of nature;
who thus reprooueth <hi>Antonie</hi> for the very like, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
his letters publike, which he sent vnto him in priuat:
<hi>Quis vnquam, qui paulum medo bonorum consuetudinem
nosset,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philipp 2.</note>
      <hi>literas ad se ab amico missas, offensione aliquâ interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sita,
in medium protulit? quid hoc est aliud, quam tollere è
vita vitae societatem: quam multa ioca solent esse in Episte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,
quae prolata si sint, inep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a videntur? quam multa seria,
neque tamen divulgenda?</hi> Who euer, that was but euen a
little acquainted with the custome of good men, brought
forth letters sent to him from a friend, some offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
betweene? what is this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, but to take out of this
life, the societie of the liuing? how many merriments vse
to bee in letters, which seeme foolish, if they bee vttered?
how many serious things, that are no waies to bee publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed?</p>
   <p>Secondly, he faileth in modestie, in persecuting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer
with rayling speech: you shall finde fewe pages of
his booke,<note place="margin">Impu. 1.</note> which are not pestred with the imputation of
lying, forgerie, falsie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, heresie, blaspemie, atheisme, Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auellisme,
and such like. Thus hee bestirreth him as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Shimei,</hi> or <hi>Rabshekah:</hi> which I may well requite with
round and smart speech, but will not with like railing: for
as he saith,<note place="margin">Cicer. Philip. 8.</note>
      <hi>vehementer me agere fateor, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>acunde nego: I
confesse I deale earnestly, but not angerly:</hi> and I consider
that it is much better, according to that saying, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:
<hi>to heare euill, then to speake
euill.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly, he forgetteth common <hi>honestie,</hi> in loading the
<pb facs="16"/>
Replyer with slaunders and vntruths;<note place="margin">Imput. 2. 3.</note> God forgiue him
this wrong:<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 44.</note> he knoweth who is called the <hi>father of lies,</hi> &amp;
the <hi>accuser of the brethren:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apocal. 12. 10.</note> farre be it from me to repay
him in the like. I say with the Orator, <hi>Ego dabo operam, vt
&amp; pro me minimo cum fastidio respondeam,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>icer. contra Sallust.</note>
      <hi>&amp; in hunc mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
mentitus esse videar:</hi> I will doe my indeauour, that I
may both answer for my selfe, with the least irkesomnesse,
and without lying of him.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, his discretion might haue beene better, then
euery where vntruely to obiect those things, whereof hee
is guilty himselfe; as throughout this my defence appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
not remembring the saying of our blessed Sauiour:
<hi>why seest thou the mote that is in thy brothers eie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math 7. 3.</note>
      <hi>and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuest
not the beame that is in thine owne eie?</hi> And so <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>
saith,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l. Monach.</note>
      <hi>Perdit authoritatem docendi, cuius sermo opere
destruitur, vt bene Tullius, caput artis est docere, quod facis:</hi>
Hee looseth the authoritie of teaching, whose saying is
controlled by his owne doing, as <hi>Tully</hi> saith, it is the chiefe
thing in arte, to teach that which thou doest thy selfe.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, his answere is insufficient; for neither doth hee
cleare himselfe of the suspicion of beeing a fauourer of
<hi>Limbus patrum:</hi> neither hath hee answered the arguments
proposed by the Replyer,<note place="margin">Limbom. p. 11. Ans. 1. 9. lines o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: p. 37. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum. 3. 17. lines omitted: to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. 2. p. 40. 2. whole l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aues omitted, from arg. 5. to arg. 9. p. 53. ob. 6. 20. lines omitted.</note> omitting many of them of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
as I haue here obserued, as finding no colour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere
vnto them: leauing therefore, the argument of the
booke as yet vnanswered, I onely haue collected 1▪ 2. seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
imputations, by him imposed vpon the Replyer; in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
of them, first setting downe the accusation, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
iustification, lastly, the recrimination: wherein, the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
is discouered to haue writtē neither diuine-like, schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler-like,
nor Christian-like; so that the Prouerbe which
<hi>Hierome</hi> vsed against <hi>Heluidius</hi> homely dispute is verefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
vpon him, <hi>Camelum vidimus saltitantem,</hi> we haue seene
a Camel dauncing.</p>
   <p>Now one word I will adde more concerning my
selfe, mine aduersarie, and to the indifferent Reader:
As for my selfe, I had thought at the first to haue said
<pb facs="16"/>
nothing; nor to haue regarded vaine words; as the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
saith,<note place="margin">Eccles 7. 23.</note>
      <hi>Gine not thine heart to all the words that men
speake:</hi> and <hi>Aristippus</hi> said well, when flying away from
one that reuiled, beeing asked why he did so, made this
answere, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:
<hi>thou hast power to speake euill, and I not
to heare:</hi> and that saying also of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> came vnto
my minde, who when one rayled vpon him, answered;
<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: I will not enter
into that combate, where <hi>he that is conquered</hi> (indeed and
in truth) is superiour (in words) <hi>to him that conquereth.</hi>
But further considering with my selfe, that by his audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
&amp; brauing speech, (if it went currant without checke)
some might bee carried away; I thought it not amisse,
though not very needfull, to frame him some answer: and
here I say with <hi>Hier▪</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hieron. August. tom. 2.</note>
      <hi>Si in defensionē mei aliquid scripsero <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
te culpa sit qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> prouocasti, non in me, qui respond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
sum:</hi> If I write any thing in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>erence, the fault is in
you, that prouoked me, not in me which am compelled to
answer.</p>
   <p>And touching him, I haue small hope to reclaime
the man to a peaceable mind, considering his insolent kind
of writing, and his hawty spirit, who proudly refused to
haue any conference with me, when his booke was offered
to the Presse, though I earnestly desired it, (which he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
in his Preface indirect dealing, for other can hee
charge mee with none) beeing with childe, as it were, till
this his mishapen and deformed monster came forth: so
that I may say with the Orator,<note place="margin">4. Philippie.</note>
      <hi>Non est mihi cum eo hoste
certamen, cum quo aliqua pacis conditio esse possit:</hi> I haue
not to doe with such an enemie, as with whom there can
be any condition of peace. And I may say with <hi>Diogenes,</hi>
who admonishing a lewd man, beeing asked what he did,
said, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: <hi>I doe wash a blacke-a-moore
to make him white:</hi> yet I will not cease to aduise
him, that if he haue any grace, he may returne to a better
minde; that seeing he hath once done euill, hee may leaue
<pb facs="17"/>
off, and doe so no more. <hi>Seneca</hi> said well, <hi>Optima ciuilis
belli defensio, obliuio:</hi> The best defence of ciuill discord, is to
forget it. And <hi>Tullie</hi> said well, <hi>Liceat semel impune pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philippie. 12.</note>
      <hi>sit erranti medicina confessio:</hi> It may be born with, once
to offend without punishment: let confession bee a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
of error.<note place="margin">Homil. 6. in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</note> And <hi>Origen</hi> also saith, <hi>Possibile est; vt si forte
resipiscat, qui devoratus est, rursus possit evomi, sicut Ionas:
it is possible, that he which is deuoured, if he repent, may be
cast vp with Ionas:</hi> So he may vomit vp those bitter pilles
againe, which he hath swallowed, if his stomake be not
still sicke. But if he be auerse from wholesome counsell,
and so shew himselfe vnworthie of peace, which is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">Matth. 10. 13.</note>
it shall, as our Sauiour saith, returne to vs againe.</p>
   <p>Now last of all to the Christian Readers I turne me in
a word, not doubting of their godly equitie in comparing
his calumniations, and my defence together, that I shall
not need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to say with <hi>Simonides</hi> the Musician, who thus
answered to one that said <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e heard euill of him; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:
<hi>and when will you leaue to
hurt my fame with your eares.</hi> But I say vnto them in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustines</hi>
words:<note place="margin">Contra lit. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian. 3. 11.</note>
      <hi>Obsecro vos deponet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> paulisper studia par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,
&amp; inter me &amp; Petilianum cum aliqua aequitate indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate:
I praey you lay aside a little all partialitie, and iudge
betweene me, and mine (aduersarie) with equitie.</hi> And so I
commend you all to the grace of God, who in his mercie
graunt,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> that we may <hi>follow the truth in loue: And as many
as walke according to this rule,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 15.</note>
      <hi>peace (shall be) vpon them,
and mercie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Galat. 6. 16.</note>
      <hi>and vpon the Israel of God.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>