<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Baillie, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120307_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01889</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1203</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120307</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Baillie, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Spiritval marriage: or, The vnion betweene Christ and his Chvrch : As it was delivered in a sermon at Westminster, the first of Ianuarie. Anno Dom. 1626. By Iames Baillie, Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Baillie, James, Master of Arts</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, J haue not vsed (as many doe) in this Sermon, the neat Tenour of <hi>ISOCRATES,</hi> the ample Sublimitie of DEMOSTHENES, the Majestie of <hi>THVCYCIDES,</hi> the Dignitie of <hi>PLATO,</hi> nor that most full and copious stile of declamation which <hi>TVLLIE</hi> vsed before the Senate, yea I haue shunned them, as by a good Master <hi>SCILLA</hi> and <hi>CARYBDIS</hi> will bee eschewed; because I know that such garulitie, such fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible inticements of words, and such vaine ostentation in Preaching, sauoureth the flesh, and hath no power, no vertue nor efficacie to wound a proud minde and to cast it downe, nor to be a balme for the curing and raising vp of the same againe to a liuely confidence in <hi>CHRIST:</hi> Jt onely tendeth to tickle the auditors eares for the present, to enter at the one, and goe forth at the other, but neuer to descend into the heart for its circumcision and molification in time to come. A simple stile without superfluitie in words, fertile in sentences, which doth not so much smell of humaine prudencie, as sauour the vertue of the holy Spirit, is the onely eloquence that pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates the soules of Christian men, and searcheth, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward marrow of the same. It is truth that an Orator once perswaded <hi>CAESAR</hi> to retreit and rescinde the sentence of <hi>LIGARIVS</hi> after that hee was condemned, But when a Minister of Gods word, a faithfull Pastor must discharge his commission vnto his Flocke, what Rhetorick shall make them
<pb facs="5"/> beleeue that life flowed from the Crosse of <hi>CHRIST:</hi> that deaths Empire by death was subdued, that the eternall word covered with flesh, beaten with fists, nailed to the Crosse, did beare our sinnes, die, rise againe, that we by this benefit shall triumph ouer death, and by marriage be vnited vnto him. Here all humaine reason, and adminicles of art, though thundered out by a <hi>Pericles,</hi> must be abstained from. Here all pompe in preaching and sophistick ostentation must giue place to the efficatious Pastor, whose sermon is replenished with substance, matter, and the riches of the Spirit, which by Saint <hi>PAVL</hi> is called, <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>1.13. Verae doctrinae</hi> hypotyposis, <hi>The true patterne of wholsome words.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly good reader, albeit, it be barren of humaine elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, yet feare not to read it, for it may be plentifull in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and if thou thinkest that J haue stayed too much vpon the two first similitudes, J thinke so with thee myselfe, <hi>Et ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes confitentem reum,</hi> yee I pray thee to pardon mee, seeing it is for thy instruction, and discouering of much obstruce and excellent Theologie, by which I hope (and J wish it from my heart) that thou shalt be bettered, and so expecting thy friendly censure, J take my leaue. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine, in Christ to bee commanded,</hi> James Baillie.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>