<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY, AND euery way most accomplished, Sr. Thomas Penystone Knight and Ba∣ronett, my euer-honored Master.</title>
           <author>Gosselin, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120862_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01948</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12092</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY, AND euery way most accomplished, Sr. Thomas Penystone Knight and Ba∣ronett, my euer-honored Master.</title>
                 <author>Gosselin, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The state-mysteries of the Iesuites, by way of questions and answers. Faithfully extracted out of their owne writings by themselues published. And a catalogue prefixed of the authors names which are cited in this booke. Written for a premonition in these times both to the publike and particular. Translated out of French</title>
                 <author>Rivet, André</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 54, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY, AND euery way most accomplished, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Penystone Knight</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronett,</hi> my euer-honored Master.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough wee haue seene in these our later dayes, and may euery day more and more perceiue in the affliction of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> and in the pitifull and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble estate of a great many of the Reformed Churches of the world, the fearefull effects of the cruell and bloudy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of those, who vnder the sweet name of <hi>Iesus,</hi> preach and teach little else then fire, murther, and sedition: Yet because there are many, which eyther haue neuer heard of the damnable points these dangerous men doe
<pb facs="3"/>
teach and maintaine, or hauing heard of them, will not at any hand beleeue, that such holy-seeming Fathers haue in such manner sharpned their tongues like Serpents, &amp; that the venome of Aspes is hidden vnder their lips; Therefore this Treatise (by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God) fallen into my hands, discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at large those secret and abhominable positions of theirs, which no Rack, nor grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test torments could euer yet extort out of any of them, I thought good to learne it to speake the <hi>English Tongue,</hi> both to instruct them, which are not yet acquainted with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accessible mysteries; as also to informe them better, which are so caried away by the blind loue of these persons, as they will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that euer they haue been the Authors of those wofull and miserable Tragedies, newly acted vpon the Theaters of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany:</hi> To the end that the truth being knowne, it may appeare in the face of all the world, what they are, who in stead of the wholsome milke and meate of the word of God, doe feed them, which are committed to their charge, with the poyson of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable
<pb facs="3"/>
blasphemies, applying to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutor many passages of the holy Scriptures, which are onely proper and appertaining to the Diuinity: with their impious and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red doctrine of deposing and killing Kings, whereof there is in no other booke extant whatsoeuer, so much found briefly together; with their perfidous and pestilent distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for Princes to violate their faiths giuen vnto others, vpon that wicked Maxime of theirs, <hi>That faith is not to be kept with hereticks;</hi> with their pernitious Equiuocations, &amp; most leud mentall Reseruations. In all which, and the rest, the Author hath not belyed the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, for he hath cited all his affirmations out of their owne writings (iudging them like wicked seruants out of their owne mouthes) the quotations wherof, appearing in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, haue beene most punctually examined with the originals themselues, by three lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who haue both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported them for faithfull, and the booke in generall most vsefull, and to that purpose for which the Author wrote it, which was, not so much for a Discouery, as for a Caueat to
<pb facs="4"/>
all such, who being not able to weigh their reasons, are the easier to be abused by their dissembling allurements: to which end also hauing now diuulged it, I present it in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie vnto your noble Patronage, as a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my dutie and thankfulnesse for so many f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uours and benefits receiued, since it pleased you to take me into your protection and seruice, after the miserable dissipation of the most part of the Reformed Churches of <hi>Normandy.</hi> So wishing you heauen vpon earth in this world, and eternall blisse in the life to come, I rest euer in all submission,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble and truly-deuoted Seruant, PETER GOSSELIN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>