<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the honest and hie-spirited Prentises The Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120519_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13321</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120519</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the honest and hie-spirited Prentises The Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The foure prentises of London : VVith the conquest of Ierusalem. As it hath bene diuerse times acted, at the Red Bull, by the Queenes Maiesties Seruants. Written by Thomas Heyvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wright, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the honest and hie-spirited Prentises The Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you (as whom this Play most especially concernes) I thought good to dedicate this Labour, which though written many yeares since, in my Infancy of Iudgement in this kinde of Poetry, and my first practise: yet vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing (by what meanes I know not) it was in these more exquisit &amp; refined Times to come to the Presse, in such a forwardnesse ere it came to my knowledge, that it was past preuention, and knowing withall, that it comes short of that accuratenesse both in Plot and Stile, that these more Censorious dayes with greater curiosity acquire, I must
<pb facs="3"/>
thus excuse. That as <hi>Playes</hi> were then some fifteene or sixteene yeares agoe it was in the fashion. Nor could it haue found a more seasonable and fit publication then at this Time, when, to the glory of our Nation, the security of the Kingdome, and the honour of the City, they haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne againe the commendable practise of long forgotten Armes, the continuance of which I wish, the discipline approue, and the encouragement thereof euen with my soule applaude. In which great and hoped good they deserue not the least attribute of approbation: who, in the dull and sleepy time of peace, first waken'd the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of these armes in the Artillery gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which begun out of their voluntary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, prosecuted by their priuate indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stries, and continued at their owne proper cost and charge, deserues in my opinion, not onely respect and regard, but recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
<pb facs="3"/>
and reward. But to returne againe to you, my braue spirited Prentises, vpon whom I haue freely bestowed these <hi>Foure▪</hi> I wish you all, that haue their courages and forwardnesse, their noble Fates and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,</p>
   <p>Yours,</p>
   <p>Thomas Heywood.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>