<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120182_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15502</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25767</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120182</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Selfe deniall: or, A Christians hardest taske : Written by Christopher Wilson; preacher of the Word of God, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitaker, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 65, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, in this little Treatise I offer to thy view one point of thy profession, such as is thy Alpha and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega, the beginning and perfiting of a Christian: the first to bee learned ere thou canst set thy foote ouer the Threshold of Christs Schoole, and yet not perfectly learned till thou beest in Christs glorious Kingdome. The consideration of this one point will helpe, direct, and settle thy musing thoughts about many things that befall the course and condition of Religion in the World; for heere is discouered the stepmother of all true Religion, whither we consider the rule and doctrine of it, or the practise of it: Here also thou mayst see the arising and encreasing of all false Religion comming out of the earth and sea of mans
<pb facs="6"/>carnall earthly heart, and troublesome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Heere thou shalt see as it were vnder one Roofe, a Prison and a shoppe or forge; a Prison wherein thou mayst behold Diuine truth, and sacred Religion chayned and bound with many Fetters in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Iayle of Selfe-conceite, and Selfe-loue. Heere againe thou mayst behold the Shop and Forge wherein are wrought, and ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mered out the frame and fabricke of all false religions and opinions, both within and without the Church. Here thou mayst behold the Seminary of all Heresies, and factions that trouble the Church, the ground of the grand false and deceitfull religions that raigne in the World, as Pagan Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Prophane Mahumetisme, Popish Heresie and Superstition, all turbulent Schismes, as the late Arminianisme, they arise all out of one bitter roote or fountaine before named; and to giue thee a little taste and touch of them both.</p>
   <p>For the first, here thou mayst see truths Prison, wherein it is detayned in vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, and that with three chiefe bonds:
<pb facs="6"/>The first is Selfe-conceit, arising from the want of Deniall of our owne mindes, wit, opinion, reason, fancies, and wisdomes: for such beeing the naturall blindnesse of the minde that it cannot conceaue many truths, such is also the Naturall dotage to conceite and invent of it self, or to receiue from other any strange fictions, vanities, curiosities, or what pleases the carnall fancies of men, that truth is neglected either as not knowne, or rejected as not pleasing: so that, with this one chayne Selfe-conceite, doth bind vp many precious truths, or seale them vp vnder the priuie seale of Ignorances. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> notes in the <hi>Romane Gentiles,</hi> and others, that while they professed themselues wise, they became fooles, so that when in some sort they knew God, they did not glorifie him as God, but became vaine in their imaginations, or discourses raysed thence; and their foolish hearts were full of darknesse, so that in the end they turned the Truth of God into a lye.</p>
   <p>Adde vnto this as a part of it a defect or viciousnesse that is in the practuall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
<pb facs="7"/>called conscience; which when it should giue a perfect direction before, and a right verdict after our actions or conceits, it is erronious, dull, idle: not willing to examine things, apt to be deceiued, and so to excuse or witnesse with, as good, when it should accuse and witnesse against, as bad. So that as many a man of a naughty conscience as wee speake, who knowes some particular truth or fact, yet smoothers them, not caring to reueale them: so is it naturally with man through this defiled conscience, which is as a graue to burie many holy truths in. Alas lamentable experience sufficiently witnesses this same, both in the generall, and in many particulars; as is seene in many Papists eyther ignorant, and mis-in-formed, or dreaming and ill minded ones, who see and know the truth, but they loue it not, and therefore will not giue witnesse of it: but as they haue laboured to get in, and burne many Bookes of Holy Truth, so do they suppresse the same in their mindes. But if the beames of Diuine truth break &amp; pierce into the darknesse of the minde, it would
<pb facs="7"/>giue forth some luster thence to the whole man; then a second bond is at hand to bind this Truth, and that is, Selfe-will, the will taking vpon her as a Iudge to examine all evidence, all places, tenents, propositions; and if they please not the will, they are then rejected and passe no further, eyther secretly checking the vnderstanding, as too busie in her informations, or onely exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reasons projected, or cunningly turning them another way, resolued they shall not haue her assent and confirmation, and so be dead and nipped in the head: so that the will <hi>Procrustes</hi>-like stretches out each opinion to the length of her measure, or cutting off what is longer, so that partly mans inability in his electiue faculty, and partly its wilfulnes refusing truths shewed by the vnderstanding, restraynes many parts of Diuine truth; as was also seene in many Pharisies in the dayes of Christ, who saw and were oft convinced, but wilfully went from and against the same: such also is the condition of many wilfull Papists in these our dayes.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>But if truth passe the vpper part of the soule, as reason, conscience, and will, and that now there might be hope, there would bee no stoppage; to a third, and that a strong and violent band to offer violence, and to make a new faction and Head; and this is Selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue: who leades a multitude of violent and clamorous passions, drowning and crying downe the voyce and iudgement of reason, as we see oft in many elections, the greater and baser part to bee carried against the smaller and wiser. For when holy truth fals into the hands of these, shee is carried from her owne Barre where she should be tried, the Lawes by which she should bee iudged are refused, the lawfull Iudge deposed, and sometime enuy, malice, selfe-loue, pride, vaine-glory, sometime other vnruly affections and passions are made the lawfull Iurie to be empenelled against truth, and if in any thing she may be found an enemy to thy popular, sensuall and carnall state, it is sufficient to commit her to Prison: Here things are examined how they stand with Honor, Pleasure, profit, ease, or any worldly
<pb facs="8"/>respects, and as they make with or against these, so haue they approbation or disal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance: this of old was alledged against the truth, we will offer Cakes to the Queene of Heauen, for then we had plenty of all things.</p>
   <p>Thus <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his Fellowes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hard against <hi>Paul,</hi> and his religion: this carried the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisies</hi> wholly against Christ, as Christ told them, How can yee beleeue, seeing yee seeke honour one of another, and not the Honor that comes of God? and in another place, if wee let him alone, all will follow him, and the <hi>Romanes</hi> will come and take our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and then as <hi>Michaiah</hi> must bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayned because hee speakes not good for <hi>Ahab;</hi> and as the <hi>Philistimes</hi> though convinced of the truth and Maiesty of the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> yet they encouraged one another, saying, Let vs quit our selues as men, that we be not slaues to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes.</hi> Thus doth Naturall men, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with carnall passions. This is clearly seene by that answer, that learned <hi>Erasmus</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>made to the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> who requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his iudgement touching <hi>Luthers</hi> cause, answered it was true and iust: The Duke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying why then doe they rage against him, he answered because he stracke at the Popes Triple Crowne, and sought to pull the <hi>Luncions</hi> or full Dyet from the Monkes belly; so that by this, that hath beene sayd, the first point is sufficiently cleared, so that wee neede not go farre to enquire after discountenancing of Truth: ill thriving and many stoppages it findes, for sometimes it meetes with one of these, sometimes with another; so that, till the Lord breake these hands, Truth fayles, and Religion cannot enter, as the Prophet complaines in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of Iustice.</p>
   <p>For the latter, I must be briefe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needes it any further proofe: for that which is prooued an enemy to Truth, is alwayes a friend to the contrary, so that these three, Selfe-conceite, Selfe-will, Selfe-loue, they are the inventors, the establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shers, maintayners, and euery way mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifiers of all false Religions, as beeing the
<pb facs="9"/>brat of it owne braine; and therefore as the Phylosophers answered witily and truely, the earth was sparing and churlish to the good hearbes, but liberall in nourishing the weedes, because to the one shee was a Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, to the other a Naturall mother, so euery man is as a Naturall soyle for all errors, heresies, idolatries and the like, but very vnkind for Holy Truth, further then we be fitted by grace; so that false religious both arising from man, and attempered to mans Naturall reason, and humane wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, earnall affections and the like, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but they must be approued of all such who haue not learned in some measure this Lesson of Christ, of <hi>Selfe-Deniall:</hi> so that it is to too apparent hence, whence Truth findes small entertainment, but false Religion drawes multitudes, the one draws vp the the Hill, the other downe; the one with the streame, the other against it: Yea hence it appeares that consents and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes are so farre from being evidences of Truth, as that they are iust suspitions of the contrary, and a good rule in matters of
<pb facs="10"/>Religion to try particulars by, is to examine what is plausible to humane wisedome and affections, and to question that, but what crosses these and carries vs against them, is likely to be of God.</p>
   <p>These things, Gentle Reader, I commend vnto thy serious consideration as worthy of it, if thou respect the matter it selfe, as for the forme and Phrase thereof, I must craue thy fauourable censure: the Nouelty of the subiect as it was the ground of some friends importunity to publish it, so if I haue failed in any thing in the same, it deserues pardon, it is easie erring, where the way is not made before.</p>
   <p>For thee learned Reader, if any such shal vouchsafe to peruse it, I submit my selfe to his iudgement and correction: glad if I may minister but any occasion to any such of further enlarging this so necessary a subiect. For other Readers, &amp; the cōmon Christian, for whose good I haue penned this, if it shal any wayes enforme thy iudgement, settle thy thought, and helpe thee forward in the Schoole of Christ, I haue my desire, my
<pb facs="10"/>ioy shall be full; and if this my first fruites shall finde kinde entertaynment in the World, it may adde encouragement to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther assayes. In meane while, I commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the fruite of this Labour to the Lords Blessing, crauing thy Prayers, I cease remaining thy Brother in the common Faith and Saluation, and a Wel-willer of thy good:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>CHRISTOPHER WILSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>