<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120478_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02192</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120478</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tormenting Tophet: or A terrible description of Hel : able to breake the hardest heart, and cause it quake and tremble. Preached at Paules Crosse the 14. of Iune 1614. By Henry Greenvvood, Master of Arts, and preacher of the word of God</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bell, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 82, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>CHristian Reader, I commend to thy charitable view, this terrible and lamentable description of Hell, a Subiect most necessary in these dayes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Iniquity hath gotten the vpper hād:</hi> the greatest part of mankind laboreth of this dangerous disease, namely, <hi>hardnes of hart and contempt of all grace,</hi> I therefore for the remouing of this damnable euil, haue prepared this <hi>Tormenting Corrasiue.</hi> Blame mee not if I be too bitter in denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing GODS Iudgements against sinne, the presumption of the time compels me, this onely is the ayme of my intention herein, that many may bee saued from the damnation hereof.</p>
   <p>Let not the <hi>Quotations of Latine</hi> and other tongues offend thee, but know this they are but as country Stiles, stepping ouer them thou losest not the way by them, for their Expositions follow them.</p>
   <p>Thus commending this Tractate to thy christian consideration, and thy self to Gods most blessed protection, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine euerlouing and vvelvvilling brother in the Lord, HEN. GREENWOOD,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>