<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the discrete and vertuous Reader.</title>
           <author>Mar, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120860_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02962</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13101</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120860</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the discrete and vertuous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Mar, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A politike discourse most excellent for this time present: composed by a French gentleman, against those of the League, which went about to perswade the King to breake the allyance with England, and to confirme it with Spaine</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 27, that is 41, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the discrete and vertuous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this worke is a stranger, whose loue of truth; hath ouercome in him the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall loue of his countrie, in composing it. The translator is a stranger likewise, whose loue of true religion and this blessed Realme hath mooued him to translate it. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors intention was, to manifest the great difference between the English and the Spanish Nations, to the intent his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie might thereupon make a iust choice for hir benefite and vtilitie. The translator his meaning is, to publish it, to the intent the whole world may know &amp; vnderstand, that great difference. For although the Spaniard be greater in lande, and thereupon maketh great boastings and brags, yet is he to be cōpared to the Cipresse tree, the which though it be high, great and faire in sight, is neuerthelesse, weake, tender, slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and vnfruitfull. The Englishman contrariwise, though he be lesser in Land, keepeth himselfe humbly thereupon, safe, still, quiet, and wise: and is therefore to be compared to the Oliue tree, lowe, faire, strong, fruitfull, and most abundant. The third and last consideration of the Author, is grounded vpon a farre better cause than any worldly commodities, &amp; that is the contemplation of spirituall qualities which are to be reaped in England, and not in Spaine, as euery man will confesse that is indifferent in matters of religion. I say not this to flatter in praysing and exalting England in or before his owne face: but because I beleeue it, and know it to be so. For how can the Spanishmen say, as the Englishmen may say with saint <hi>Paul, God is with vs,</hi> and againe, <hi>If God be with vs, who can be against vs.</hi> We haue seene the last som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by experience the true effects of this which I speake now.</p>
   <p>Therefore I as translator ioyne willingly with the Author, and do conclude with this preface, as hee doth with his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course:
<pb facs="3"/>and say that the Spanish nation, is at hir highest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and shalt therefore no more ascende but descend: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause she goeth about not only to take and inuade hir neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours countries, but she dare say, she will haue the fist Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, that only appertaineth to Iesus Christ, who will giue it to whom it pleaseth him, and will not giue it vnto them: but I dare say he will giue it vnto Englishmen, which haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him, and he wil be with them still so long as they liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his holy will.</p>
   <p>I do not speake of things done this day, yesterday, or the day before, but by experience and obseruation of yeares more than one score. Therefore if England doth consider the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the strength, the good, or euill will of his enimies, he will beginne to perceiue what I meane, and say as I say. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if he entred into consideration of the great number &amp; strong benefites which the Almightie God hath doone vnto him through his mercie and good will, vnder the blessed protection (of his most precious maide seruant, his most ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and deare nurse of his Church) our most gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Queene Elizabeth, he will say as I say. I can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlesse. I would make of my preface a discourse, which should be out of my purpose: I will therfore conclude with my prayers, and beseech the Almightie God to defende from all enemies his holy vniuersall Church, the Queenes Maiestie, hir most honorable Councell, this blessed Realme and people, and keepe vs all in peace in Christ our Lord, so be it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Francis Mar.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>