<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH and mightie Prince IAMES by the Grace of God King of Great Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, Defendor of the Faith &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120498_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02608</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12738</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120498</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH and mightie Prince IAMES by the Grace of God King of Great Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, Defendor of the Faith &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached before the Kings Most Excellent Maiestie : in the Church of Beauly in Hampshire, the thirtieth of Iuly. M.DC.IX. By Christopher Hampton, Doctor in Diuinitie, and one of his Ma [jes] ties chapleines</title>
                 <author>Hampton, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 54, 4, 55-104 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH and mightie Prince IAMES by the Grace of God King of Great Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, Defendor of the Faith &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Renowned, most Dread, and most Gracious Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not long since I heard a Recusant of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and qualitie professe, that the <hi>Spiritual</hi> presence of our Sauiour Iesus Christ in the holy Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, contented him sufficiently. But he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired satisfaction, at the same time, in the matter of <hi>Supremacie,</hi> and to haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons why <hi>Christian Princes</hi> should chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it. I promised to resolue him in that point too; and had not any thing so readie to do it withall, as certain collections which I gathered for a Sermon preached before your most <hi>Excellent Ma<seg rend="sup">tie</seg>.</hi> Those I haue
<pb facs="3"/>
now published, that all of my charge may take cōmoditie to reade them for their sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction or vse. And that they are like to do with more cheerefulnesse, if your Ma<seg rend="sup">tie</seg> wil be Gratiously pleased to let them passe vnder your <hi>Royall protection,</hi> with the same <hi>Clemency</hi> now which you vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to countenāce them withall, when they were pronounced in your Sacred presence. The Lord that hath giuē your Ma<seg rend="sup">tie</seg> both this great power, to be his <hi>Lieutenāt,</hi> &amp; a prudent heart to exercise it, continue your happy <hi>Gouernement,</hi> to the aduancemēt of his glory, the comfort of these Churches, and your owne <hi>Eternall honour.</hi> Euen so prostrating my selfe to kisse your blessed hands, I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble and obliged Seruant and Almosner, <hi>ARMAGH.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>