<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL NICHOLAS INCE Maior of the City Chester; And to the worshipfull Aldermen his brethren, the Sheriffes, with all who beare Office in that much honoured Corporation; I.B. wisheth growth in grace, and in the knowledge of Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120873_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04269</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1439.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120873</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL NICHOLAS INCE Maior of the City Chester; And to the worshipfull Aldermen his brethren, the Sheriffes, with all who beare Office in that much honoured Corporation; I.B. wisheth growth in grace, and in the knowledge of Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A seasonable discourse of spirituall stedfastnesse : wherein, 1. it, and a relapse, with the heads, members, and degrees of both, are exactly defined. 2. The subiects, causes, and symptomes of the fearfull sinne of apostasie cleerely expressed. As also directions, incentiues, to recouer, re-inkindle the old-cold-declining zelot. Together with arguments, motiues, that the young, or strong standing convert may be in grace firmely established. By I.B. preacher of the word</title>
                 <author>Barlow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 265, that is 266, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL NICHOLAS INCE Maior of the City Chester; And to the worshipfull Aldermen his brethren, the Sheriffes, with all who beare Office in that much honoured Corporation; <hi>I.B.</hi> wisheth growth in grace, and in the knowledge of <hi>Christ Iesus.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worthy Sirs,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ts a true saying, <hi>That one sinner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyeth much good.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 9. vlt.</note> For like a <hi>bad Tree,</hi> he possesseth the place of <hi>a better:</hi> And <hi>(though barren)</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> devoureth equall nutriment with him that <hi>beareth.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides,<note place="margin">Luk 13.7.</note>
      <hi>he Cumbers the ground,</hi> bring <hi>foorth ill fruite, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he stands.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Chro. 10 13.14</note> Let <hi>Rehoboam</hi> be rooted in the <hi>land of Iudah</hi> the grave Counsell of the <hi>aged is reiected,</hi> that of <hi>greene youth is accepted:</hi> he findes <hi>shields of Gold,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 King. 14.27.</note> leaves <hi>them of brasse:</hi> And, in taxing of the <hi>subiect,</hi> makes his <hi>little finger heavier, than the whole body of his father.</hi> Set <hi>a Pilat</hi> in the <hi>soyle of iudicature,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 27.26</note>
      <hi>periurie is approved, Barabbas delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;</hi> And <hi>Iesus Christ the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous condemned.</hi> Plant a <hi>proud Pharisee</hi> in the <hi>vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the Church,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 23.5. &amp;c</note> he glorieth in <hi>swelling tytles,</hi> claimes the <hi>highest roome at the Table,</hi> And covets the <hi>chiefest seate in the Synagogue.</hi> He tythes
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Mint, Cummin;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 11.42</note> omits <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, truth;</hi> straines <hi>at a Gnat,</hi> swallowes <hi>a Camell;</hi> violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pressing the <hi>traditions of men,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 23.3.</note> desparatly neglecting <hi>the Commandments of God:</hi> He <hi>saith,</hi> and <hi>doth not;</hi> point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the way <hi>to heaven by speech,</hi> treading the path <hi>to hell by practise:</hi> And (O shameles hipocrit) the Phyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteries vpon his <hi>garmēts,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mar. 12.40</note> are the <hi>largest;</hi> his <hi>prayers</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> are the <hi>longest.</hi> And if this, be thus? Why then are the prophane <hi>Prodigalls</hi> reputed <hi>kind men?</hi> styled <hi>good fellowes?</hi> And <hi>enemies to none,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iosh. 22.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> except <hi>themselves?</hi> Did not one <hi>man sin,</hi> And <hi>wrath fell on all the Congregation?</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 21</note> Was not the whole <hi>land plagued,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>David,</hi> three <hi>yeeres together with famine</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> because <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>his bloody house slew the Gibeonits?</hi> Read and see. And from this ground, may we not be glad when vnfruitfull <hi>trees</hi> are <hi>cut downe?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. 15.1.</note> What did <hi>Moses? Deborah?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.1.</note> Let it goe well with the <hi>righteous, doth not the Citie reioyce?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 11.10.</note> And when the <hi>wicked perish, is there not shouting?</hi> Will it not also follow hence, that its a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy worke, by lawful meanes to remove <hi>gracelesse men?</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 King. 10.24.</note> To roote them out, of <hi>Church, Countrey, Kingdome?</hi> But not to <hi>aime</hi> beyond the <hi>marke;</hi> Let me be bold, from the <hi>wise kings proverb,</hi> to advise you, exhort you; that in all your <hi>elections you lay hands rashly on no man.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tim. 5.22</note> Call to minde <hi>Iothams</hi> parable. Plant <hi>a bramble in your Citie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dg. 9.14, 18</note> he will
<pb facs="4"/> hang on each good mans <hi>sleeve;</hi> And if not teare your <hi>flesh,</hi> yet prick your <hi>fingers.</hi> Set him in the <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 21.13</note> your Fathers house <hi>will be a denne of Theeues.</hi> Place him where you please,<note place="margin">Luk. 13.7.</note> he shall <hi>make the ground barren:</hi> Or else ever hold me guiltie of <hi>a damnable lye.</hi> For your selues, <hi>like Iob,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 29.14.</note>
      <hi>be clothed with the Garment of iustice: filled with the fruite of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi> In <hi>your old-age,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 1.11.</note>
      <hi>be fat &amp; flourishing.</hi> Governe your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies well:<note place="margin">Psal. 92.14.</note> So shall you the Citie better.<note place="margin">Eph. 6.4.</note> Nurse vp your Children <hi>in the feare of God:</hi> And (if need require) <hi>let them marrie.</hi> Tread not in the steppes of bastard <hi>Protestants;</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.36</note> who will yoke their <hi>sonnes</hi> to vntamed <hi>hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers,</hi> if but laden with <hi>thicke
<pb facs="5"/> clay:</hi> Their <hi>Daughters</hi> to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Asses,</hi> have they pastures <hi>large enough.</hi> Graffe yours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Gods stocke:</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.39</note> And account your <hi>Prayers,</hi> their <hi>greatest portion.</hi> Let others halt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two opinions;</hi> but as <hi>Ioshuah, doe you, and yours serve the Lord.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iosh. 24.15</note> If you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, why this <hi>little treatise</hi> is directed to you? My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is at hand. Did you not (vnexpected) give me a free and generall call, to be one of your <hi>Citie Lacturers?</hi> Shall I be thought worthy <hi>to speak,</hi> And not <hi>to write vnto you?</hi> Againe; when one meane failes, to manifest affection, gratefull minds will vse ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>Law,</hi> after <hi>Adams</hi> fall, was vnable to <hi>revive him:</hi> Then did not <hi>God</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale the <hi>Gospell?</hi> In the like
<pb facs="5"/> case, may not <hi>his practise</hi> be <hi>my president?</hi> Moreover, (not to boast) of all the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers I ever penned,</hi> these, by my <hi>iudicious friends,</hi> have bin <hi>best approved,</hi> most <hi>desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> to <hi>be published.</hi> And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how I love you, <hi>my soule knoweth right-well.</hi> But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubting of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, I <hi>commend you to God, &amp; the word of his grace;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Acts 20.32</note>
      <hi>which is able to build further, And to give you an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among all them that are Sanctified.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours (such as he is) to do you seruice. <hi>I. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>