<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120148_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15525</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25791</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120148</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie vpon the most diuine Epistle of S. Paul to the Romanes : Containing for matter, the degeneration of our nature by Adams Fall; and the restauration thereof, by the grace of Christ. Together with the perfection of faith, and the imbecillity of workes, in the cause of iustification of elect sinners before God. For forme and maner of handling, it hath the coherence and method, the summe and scope, the interpretations &amp; doctrines the reasons and vses, of most texts. All which, are set downe very familiarly and compendiously, in forme of a dialogue, betweene Tlmotheus [sic] and Silas, by Thomas Wilson, one of the six preachers in the cathedrall church of Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 556, 559-653, 2, 654-956, 955-1260, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="634"/>
   <head>Errata.</head>
   <p>Muse not courteous Reader, that thou doost meete with these faultes, for there would haue beene farre more, if the great diligence of the Printer had not preuented it, the blinde Coppy and wine owne ouer-sight were so bad. Correct therefore with thy pen these heere noted, ere thou beginne to reade, and beare with the rest.</p>
   <p>PAge 3. l. 25. read Reuocation, p. 4. l. 12. r. it. p. 8. l. 11: r. exordium. p. 9: l. 34 r. his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore free, and for after grace, and in the mar. r. the Gospel after of. p. 21. l. 3. strike out (which of it selfe) and place it before could in l. 32. P. 22. l: 16. r. gift. p. 23. l. 19. r. few. l. 22. r. meane ones. p. 25. str, the 9. and 10. lines wholy. p: 27. l: 35. r. whom. p: 32. l. 28. r: be. p: 43. l. 17. r. too high. p: 54. l. 6. r. 1 Iohn. p: 57. l: 19. r: with. P: 61, l: 14. r: by for on, in p. 63. the lines 12, 13, 14, 15. 16. must be ioyned to l. 6. p. 72 str. out whole lines, 7, 8, 9, 10 p. 73. r. all matters after attribute. P. 84 l. 18. r. these foure. p. 89. l. 13. r. <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misthia.</hi> p: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. l. 1. r. as in killing <hi>Abcl.</hi> p. 107. l, 4. r. doth not. p ibid. l 16. r. iudgement for Law, l. 32. r. coactiue. p: 112. l. 19. r. of the 1: chap. p. 133. from the two last lines vnto the 14. l of p. 135. all belongs vnto the 6. Dial. p. 186. l. 31. r. righteous. p. 189. l. 3. r. Ro. 12, 2. p. 272. str. lines 26, 27. p. 277. l: 26. r: hencc. p: 284. l: 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: hence. p. 362. mar. r. imputetur. p. 366. l. 34. str. actions. p. 385. in mar. r. habent. p. 390. l. 17. r. frced. p. 397. l. 1. str. ont hauing a little paper left. p. 409. l. 29. r. sick. p. 428. l. 18. r. now. p. 442. l. 7. r. and workes, it is a good signe. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. l. 1. r. word. and 446. morg. r. deplorat. 451. l. 14. r. good. p. 488. l. last. r. truth. p. 489. str. 5 last lines. p. 502. l. 15. r. after vnable, by his-own vnthriftinesse. p. 527. l. 15, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. r. followeth and his merites. p. 563. l. 19, 20. r. to our spirit and with our spirit. p. 596. l. 6. r. explication. p. 606. l. 25. r. our error. p. 6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> 1. l. 34. r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. p. 614. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 628. l. 14. r. or some thing which hath Analogic and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with faith. p. 650. for thirdly, r. secondly. l. 35. angels for diuels. p. 652. l. 31. read probable onely, p. 673. l. 1. r. Silas. p. 679. mar. r. vniuersum genus. p. 693. l. 19. r. be iust. p. 719. l. 30. r. having. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. l. 3. r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 759. l. 11. r. ver. 3, 4. of this chap. p. 802. r. christ for faith. p. 833. r. preaching. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. l. 21. r. hath not done. p. 848. r. are things. pa. 860. l. 32: r. it is not true. p. 862. l. 23. r. sub testo. p. 865. r: an agreement. p. 882. l. 18. reade Antopistos p. 867. mar. r. prophetarum. p. 897. l. 13. r. anomia. p. 976. r. one beleeuer. page 979 l. 11. so the promise. p. 991. l. 28. r. or for of. p. 997. l. 31. for gods iudgement; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. these are things. p. 902. l. 1. r. as christ. p. 925. l. 6. r: toward the end. p. 1016. l. 32. r. allow them. p. 1023. l. 15. r. three. p. 1041. l. 10. for but r. nor. l. 12. r. canon. p. 1042. mar. str. Orineus p. 1048. in mar. r. one for euen, and write after doc. Fulke. p. 1069. l. 5. r. correction. pag. 1085. l. 27. r. vnprofitable. 1090. l. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. good lawes, 1101. l. 13. r. acknowledge. p. 1106. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. 4. r. retchles. p. 1113. l. 21. r. for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> l hy. p. 1121. l. 1. r. also defended Peters abiuring, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter marriage. p. 1126. l. 31. r. vices for duties.</p>
   <pb facs="634"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>