<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, PHILIP EARLE OF MONGOMERY, ONE OF THE GENTLEMEN OF HIS MAIESTIES Bed-chamber, and Knight of the most Honourable Order of the GARTER.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr58_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, PHILIP EARLE OF MONGOMERY, ONE OF THE GENTLEMEN OF HIS MAIESTIES Bed-chamber, and Knight of the most Honourable Order of the GARTER.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="566"/>
   <pb n="1097" facs="566"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, PHILIP EARLE OF MONGOMERY, ONE OF THE GENTLEMEN OF HIS MAIESTIES Bed-chamber, and Knight of the most <hi>Honourable Order of the</hi> GARTER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter some vnpleasing intermissions, Ireturne to that taske of Contemplation, wherin onely my soule findeth rest. Jf in other imployments I haue indeuoured to serue God and his Church, yet in none (I must confesse) with equall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. Me thinkes <hi>Controuersie</hi> is not right in my way to Heauen; how euer the importunitie of an Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary may force me to fetch it in: If Truth oppressed by an erroneous Teacher cry (like a rauisht Ʋirgin) for my aid, J betray it, if J releeue it not; when J haue done, J returne gladly to these paths of Peace. The fauour which my late Polemicall labour hath
<pb n="1098" facs="567"/> found (beyond merit) from the Learned, cannot diuert my loue to those wrangling Studies. How earnestly doth my heart rather wish an vniuersall cessation of these Armes; that all the Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of the deare Name of Christ might bee taken vp with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but holy and peaceable thoughts of Deuotion; the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse whereof hath so farre affected mee, that (if I might doe it without danger of mis-construction) I could beg euen of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie this leaue to bee happy. I haue already giuen account to the World, of some expences of my houres this way, and heere I bring more; which if some Reader may censure as poore, none can cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as vnprofitable. J am bold to write them vnder your Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Name, whereto I am deeply obliged; that I may leaue behinde me this meane, but faithfull Testimony, of mine humble thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to your Lordship, and your most honoured and vertuous Ladie. The noble respects J haue had from you both, deserue my Prayers, and best seruices, which shall neuer be wanting to you and yours,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>From your Honours sincerely deuoted in all true duty, IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>