<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, and Patron, EDVVARD Lord DENNY, Baron of Waltham, All Grace and Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr16_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, and Patron, EDVVARD Lord DENNY, Baron of Waltham, All Grace and Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="129"/>
   <pb n="247" facs="129"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, and Patron, EDVVARD Lord DENNY, Baron of <hi>Waltham,</hi> All Grace and Happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I would haue withdrawne my hand from diuine <hi>Salomon,</hi> the heauenly elegance of this his best Song drew mee vnto it, and would not suffer mee to take off mine eies, or pen. Who can reade it with vnderstanding, and not be transported from the world, from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe? and bee any otherwhere saue in Heauen, before his time? I had rather spend my time in admiration, than Apologie. Surely, here is nothing that sauours not of extasie, and spirituall rauish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; neither was there euer so high and passionate a speculation deliuered by the Spirit of God, to mankinde: which by how much more diuine it is, by so much more difficult. It is well, if these mysteries can be found out by searching. Two things make the Scripture hard: Prophecies, Allegories; both are met in this: but the latter so sensibly to the weakest eies, that this whole Pastorall-mariage-song (for such it is) is no other than one Allegorie sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continued: where the deepest things of God are spoken in Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, how can there be but obscuritie and diuers construction? All iudgements will not (I know) subscribe to my senses; yet I haue
<pb n="248" facs="130"/> beene fearefull and spiritually nice, not often dissenting from all Jnterpreters; alwaies, from the vnlikeliest. It would bee too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to giue my account for euery line: let the learned scan and iudge. What-euer others censures be, your Honours was fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; and (as to all mine) full of loue and incouragement. That, therefore, which it pleased you to allow from my pen, vouchsafe to receiue from the Presse; more common, not lesse deuoted to you. What is there of mine that doth not ioy in your name, and boast it selfe in seruing you? To whose soule and people, I haue long agone addicted my selfe, and my labours, and shall euer continue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships, in all humble and vnfained dutie, IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>