<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOSTE NO∣ble and moste mightie Lord, Lewes Duke of Lennox, Earle of Darnley, Baron of Tarbanton and Methuen, great Chamber∣laine and Admiral of Scotland, &amp; Knight of the moste noble order of the Garter.</title>
           <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120787_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06903</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17334</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120787</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOSTE NO∣ble and moste mightie Lord, Lewes Duke of Lennox, Earle of Darnley, Baron of Tarbanton and Methuen, great Chamber∣laine and Admiral of Scotland, &amp; Knight of the moste noble order of the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cauelarice, or The English horseman : contayning all the arte of horse-manship, as much as is necessary for any man to vnderstand, whether he be horse-breeder, horse-ryder, horse-hunter, horse-runner, horse-ambler, horse-farrier, horse-keeper, coachman, smith, or sadler. Together, with the discouery of the subtill trade or mistery of horse-coursers, &amp; an explanatio [n] of the excellency of a horses vndersta [n] ding, or how to teach them to doe trickes like Bankes his curtall: and that horses may be made to drawe drie-foot like a hound. Secrets before vnpublished, &amp; now carefully set down for the profit of this whole nation: by Geruase Markham</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 88, 4, 212, 233-264, 4, 67, 58-72, 4, 54, 4, 56, 4, 64, 4, 11, 10-81, 5, 20, 25-40 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="181"/>
   <pb facs="181"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MOSTE NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and moste mightie Lord, <hi>Lewes</hi> Duke of Lennox, Earle of Darnley, Baron of Tarbanton and Methuen, great Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine and Admiral of Scotland, &amp; Knight of the moste noble order of the Garter.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He greatest and most excellent name which the famous Poet</hi> Virgil <hi>could finde out where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to adorne the most renown'd King</hi> Picus, <hi>was to call him a horseman: &amp; that the</hi> Pega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian <hi>horse was not onelie fayned to be begotten by the son of</hi> Neptune, <hi>but also to be the first founder of the learned Wel and the arte of memorie: then I doubt not but this famous Arte of horse manship, which with my best inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours I haue carefully collected, wil in your graces moste noble thoughts finde both defence and acceptance; and rather sith it is an Arte wherin I holde your grace as excellent as any prince in Christendome; &amp; is such on ornament of state, that there is no actiue greatnes vnblemished which pleadeth absolute ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in so royal a professiō. Now albe this part of horsemā, ship, which I consecrate to your noble name, be not contained within the rules or principles of the</hi> Iralian <hi>or french riders (who albe they can ride wel, yet are ignorant how to make a horse ride long) yet your grace whose daylye experience and knowledge both of the worth and vse of these hunting horses can best iudge the profit of the art as wel in pleasure, as in vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occasiōs wil I hope neither esteeme my labour vaine, nor fruitlesse, for the cuntrie wherin I liue: &amp; strengthning that hope with the noble fauours which you extend to your admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, I liue to be commaunded by you.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Geruase Markham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>