<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A delicate Disputation gallantlye dis∣coursed betweene two noble Gen∣tlemen of Italy. The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120745_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07911</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18283</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120745</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A delicate Disputation gallantlye dis∣coursed betweene two noble Gen∣tlemen of Italy. The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Zelauto. The fountaine of fame : Erected in an orcharde of amorous aduentures. Containing a delicate disputation, gallantly discoursed betweene to noble gentlemen of Italye. Giuen for a freendly entertainment to Euphues, at his late ariuall into England. By A.M. seruaunt to the Right Honourable the Earle of Oxenford</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 156 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb n="3" facs="8"/>
   <head>A delicate Disputation gallantlye dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed betweene two noble Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of <hi>Italy.</hi> The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot longe since ouer the famous and stupendious Citie of Venice, gouerned Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zalo Guicciardo, elected Duke by the most worthye Orlando Fiorentino. This aforesayde Gonzalo, (renowmed for his princely gouerment, obayed for his singuler wisdom, praysed for his pollitique suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of prowde vsurpinge enimies, and honored for his humilytie to his subiects in generall) was not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as a second Mutio among his freends and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyars, but euen amonge his very enemies was also estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as a prince worthy of eternall memory. And na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the more to agrauate his ioyes in his hoary haires: gaue hym a Sonne called Zelauto, whose singuler hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, whose puisance in feates of armes, whose dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie in witte, and whose comelye shape in personage, caused hym through all Venice to bee greatly accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of.</p>
   <p>This gallant youth Zelauto (more desirous to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce his fame by traue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lyng straunge countries: then to leade his lyngring life styll in the court of his famous
<pb n="4" facs="9"/>
father) one day by chaunce tooke courage to open the hidden thoughts which longe incombred his carefull breast, and hauing espied his father at such conuenient leasure, as serued best for his auayle, yeelding his obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunce as dutie beseemed, entred into this discourse.</p>
   <p>If (Right woorthy and renowmed Father) nature had adorned me with such rare and excellent quallities, as might procure an hartes ease and ioy vnto your prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly estate: then would dutie cause me to keepe my minde in silence, and feare (of displeasing your aged hart) byd me restrayne my vowed attempt. But sith I am desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of that which my hart desireth, &amp; willing to gaine the same by painefull industry: I hope I shall purchase no ill will of your person, nor displease the mindes of your subiectes in generall. First weigh and consider by your gratious aduisement, that a youthfull minde more desireth the fragrant fieldes: then the hidden house, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome confesseth, yea, and lawe of Nature alloweth, that it is more permanent to a princely courage, to seeke the renowmed mansion, of the most illustrious and sacred Ladye Fame: then to drowne his youthfull dayes in gulfs of gaping greef, in silēt sorrows, in vaine thoughts and cogitations, and also in trifling and idle exercises, which maketh him more prone vnto vice then vertue, more apt vnto lewdnes: then contented liuing, yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him so friuilous and fantasticall, that nothing but libidinous thoughtes, beastly behauiour, is his whole exercise. For then euery blasing beame, and euery sugred countenaunce of a woman allureth him, that floting on the Seas of foolish fansie, and hauing abid one lusty gale of winde, wherewith the Barke of his body, is beaten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Rockes of his Ladyes lookes, then the poore
<pb n="5" facs="9"/>
patient falleth into so extreme an extasie, that one worde will kill him, and an other reuiue him. Thus is he inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed amid these subtill snares, while in the warlike feeld he might enioy his libertie, and their win fame which should last eternally. These and such like crabbed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites (deere Father) vrgeth me to craue your leaue and licence, that I may a while visite straunge Countries, In which time, I doubt not but to atchieue such exploytes, that at my returne it will be treble ioy to your Princely eares to heare them recounted.</p>
   <p>Sonne Zelauto (aunswered the Duke) this your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course is both commendable, and allowable, for I lyke well of your intent, and with all my hart giue consent that for a limitted time you shal seeke aduentures, which time shall amount vnto .vi. yeares, and on my blessing I charge thee, not to breake that appointed time. In the meane while, if God call me (as my life is vncertaine) I frankly &amp; freely giue thee all is myne. Wherfore looke well to thy selfe, that good report may be heard of thee, which vnto me will be great contentation. But nowe as touching what ayde and assistance thou wilt haue with thee: speake, and it shall be graunted. Good Father (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered Zelauto) none but onely one to beare me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, which I know will be sufficient. Well (quoth the Duke) receiue heere my blessing, this portion of money, and this knight to beare thee company. And I pray God in all thy wayes to guide and protect thee, and so you may depart when you please.</p>
   <p>Zelauto accompanied with his knight, departed from the Court of his famous Father, and tooke shipping to goe vnto Naples, from thence, he trauailed vnto Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia in Spayne, and chauncing into the company of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb n="6" facs="10"/>
English Merchauntes, who in the Latine tongue told him the happy estate of England, &amp; how a worthy Princes gouerned their common weale, and all suche thinges as could not be more praysed then they deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The which Zelauto hearing, craued of them that he might sayle with them into England, and he woulde liberally reward them. They beeyng contented, and hauing laden their Shippes with such necessaryes as they best desyred: within fewe dayes hoysed sayles, and away they went.</p>
   <p>This young youth Zelauto beeyng come into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and seene the rare and vertuous vsage of the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious and thrise renowmed Princes, with the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and fauour which he obtayned among her woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lordes: purposed to stay still there. But yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that although he sawe one place: many others were as yet vnseene, after a yeere expyred, he tooke shipping into Persia, and so departed. In processe of time he had visited many straunge Countryes, sustay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many and wonderfull iniuryes among the Turkes, which after shall be declared. And returning home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, happened on the borders of Sicile, where For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was fauourable vnto him: that vnawares he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened on the caue of a valiaunt Knight, who was a Christian, and hauing committed an hainous offence: fled out of his owne Countrie, and inhabited there in a silent Cell, among the woods. This Knight beyng na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Astraepho, and hearing the trampling of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his denne: tooke his weapons, and came foorth. He beeing greatly abashed at the sight of Zelauto, for that in tenne yeeres space he neither sawe man nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: but had lyued there a sauage lyfe: forgetting all
<pb n="7" facs="10"/>
poyntes of humanitie sayd. VVhat varlet, art thou come to seeke my death? thou art welcome, and therewith all strooke at Zelauto, who alas through tediousnesse of trauell, and long beeyng without any suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce: was constrayned to yeeld, and falling on his knees submitted himselfe to his mercye, which Astraepho see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, sayd as hereafter followeth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>