<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>North, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120709_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02296</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12428</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120709</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>North, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dial of princes, compiled by the reuerend father in God, Don Antony of Gueuara, Byshop of Guadix, preacher, and chronicler to Charles the fifte, late of that name Emperour. Englished out of the Frenche by T. North, sonne of Sir Edvvard North knight, L. North of Kyrtheling</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 165, 1, 101, 103-173, 24 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="282"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat detracting tongues report of mee and my first tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in the translation of this Dyall, enlarging them at pleasure to woork my defame, disabling my dooing heerein, by brute yt was no woork of myne, but the fruit of others labor: I neede not much force, since by dayly proof wee see, that yll disposed mynds can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer frame an honest tongue in head. For my obiect, and reproofe of this their sclaunderous &amp; malignant speeche, I can allege (cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous reader) two principall causes, which thou reading and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with indifferency, mayst easely approoue, yf I shoold seeme to glose with thee. First, the basenes of my style, the playn and humble woords couched in the same, the mean, rude, and yll contryued sentences layd beefore thee, togeether with the simple handelyng of the whole: playnly sheweth to thee whence they are, and easely acquainteth thee with the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious translator. Who protesteth to god, and confesseth to the world, that hee more rashely then wysely plonged him self into so graue and deepe a matter, and whose yong yeres and vnskilfull head, might both then and now haue excused his fond enterprise heerein. For the second and last, I must needes appeal to all the woorshipfull, and my beeloued compaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons, and fellow students of our house of Lyncolnes Inne at that tyme, from whence my poore english Dyall tooke his light. To whose iust and true reports (for thy vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted satisfaction, and discharge of my poore honesty) I referre thee, and wholly yeld mee. These recyted causes, for purgacion of my suspected fame, as also for established assurance of the lyke, and thy further doubt of mee heereafter, I thought good (gentle reader) to denounce vnto thee. I myght well haue spared thys second and last labor of myne taken, in the reformacion and correction of thys Dyall, enlarging my self further once agayn, wyth the translation of the late and new come fauored courtier (and whych I found annexed to the Dyall for the fourth and last booke) If my preceeding trauell taken in the settyng foorth of the first three books, and the respect of myne honesty in accomplyshing of the same, had not incyted mee (vnwillyng) to continue my first begonne attempt, to bring the same to his perfyt and desyred end: whych whole woork is now complete by thys last booke, entituled the fauoured courtyer. Whych fyrst and last volume, wholly as yt lyeth, I prostrate to the iudgement of the graue and wyse Reader, subiecting my self and yt, to the reformation and correction of hys lerned head, whom I beeseech to iudge of mee wyth fauor and equity: and not wyth malyce to persecute my same, and honest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, hauyng for thy benefit, (to my lyttle skill and knowledge) imployed my symple talent, crauyng no other guerdon of thee, but thy good report, and curteous acceptaunce heereof. Whych dooyng thou shalt make mee double bound to thee. First, to bee thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thy good will. Secondly, to bee considerate how hereafter I take vppon mee so great a charge. Thirdly, thou shalt encourage mee to study to increase my talent.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, and lastly, most freely to beestow thincrease thereof on thee, and for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of my countrey and common weale, whereto duety byndeth mee: Obseruing the sage &amp; prudent saying of the renowmed orator and famous <hi>Cicero:</hi> with which I end, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to leaue thee. <hi>Non nobis solum nati sumus, ortus{que} nostri partem patria vendicat, partem parentes, partem amici.</hi> In defence and preseruation whereof (good reader) wee ought not alone to employ our whole wittes and able sences, but necessity enforcing vs, to sacrifice our selues also for benefit thereof. From my lord Norths house nere London the <hi>.10.</hi> day of May. <hi>1568.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine that accepteth mee. <hi>Th. North.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>