<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To euery godly, zealous, and sincere Pro∣fessor of Gods true Religion; the wish∣es of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120537_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15819</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26081</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120537</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To euery godly, zealous, and sincere Pro∣fessor of Gods true Religion; the wish∣es of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods arraignement of hypocrites : with an inlargement concerning Gods decree in ordering sinne. As likewise a defence of Mr. Calvine against Bellarmine; and of M. Perkins against Arminius</title>
                 <author>Yates, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 344, 5, 346-413, 3 pages, folded leaf, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To euery godly, zealous, and sincere Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor of Gods true Religion; the wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Author.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THis vacant white, I could not passe away,</l>
      <l>Perchance the blacke is worser, thou wilt say:</l>
      <l>The worst is said, and better is my creed,</l>
      <l>That thou in this my loue wilt euer read.</l>
      <l>To <hi>giue</hi> and <hi>take</hi> is neither <hi>more</hi> or <hi>lesse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But loue is more, then can our gifts expresse.</l>
      <l>The former tearmes as <hi>relates, thine</hi> and <hi>mine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Let's passe <hi>proud tearmes,</hi> and then the gift is thine.</l>
      <l>Thine as his owne, if better were his owne,</l>
      <l>Loue is the best, hence let the rest be knowne.</l>
      <l>As purest <hi>wine</hi> runnes from the homely <hi>presse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>So plainest loue giues comfort in dissresse.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Perfumes</hi> haue sweetest smell, which fire find,</l>
      <l>And loue the greatest grace, which zeale can mind.</l>
      <l>The <hi>rose</hi> in still is sweeter then on stalke,</l>
      <l>Distill thy loue, and sweete shall be thy talke.</l>
      <l>My good to God is none, to thee is all,</l>
      <l>Yet both to God must for a blessing call.</l>
      <l>The sillie <hi>Bee</hi> suckes honie from the weedes,</l>
      <l>But flowers seene, full soone on fairest feeds.</l>
      <l>Make some thing of the worst, but gaine the best,</l>
      <l>That after death thou may haue happie rest.</l>
      <l>The presse hath stamp'd these lines, for thee to presse</l>
      <l>A deeper stampe then can my lines expresse.</l>
      <l>Presse not my skill, for art presume my heart</l>
      <l>As thine, that loues no further for to starte.</l>
      <l>The gift is thine by due, the debt is mine,</l>
      <l>God grant thee ioy in reading of each line.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>