<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR HENRY MOVNTAGVE, Knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of the Pleas, Holden before his most Royall Maiestie, &amp;c</title>
           <author>M., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120712_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12430</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR HENRY MOVNTAGVE, Knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of the Pleas, Holden before his most Royall Maiestie, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>M., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archontorologion, or The diall of princes : containing the golden and famous booke of Marcus Aurelius, sometime Emperour of Rome. Declaring what excellcncy [sic] consisteth in a prince that is a good Christian: and what euils attend on him that is a cruell tirant. Written b the Reuerend Father in God, Don Antonio of Gueuara, Lord Bishop of Guadix; preacher and chronicler to the late mighty Emperour Charles the fift. First translated out of French by Thomas North, sonne to Sir Edward North, Lord North of Kirthling: and lately reperused, and corrected from many grosse imperfections. With addition of a fourth booke, stiled by the name of The fauoured courtier</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 331, pages 933, 341-424, 429-542, that is 560, 2, 561-654, 659-768, that is 766 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR</hi> HENRY MOVNTAGVE, <hi>Knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of the Pleas, Holden before his most Royall Maiestie, &amp;c</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Emperour <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iane</hi> (Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) writing a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning the weightie and carefull condition of Princes; among many other matters, vsed these wordes of himselfe. <hi>I doe freely confesse vnto you, that, since I tasted the cares and trauels attending on this Imperiall dignitie: I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented a thousand times, that euer I did vndertake it, because, if it bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Honour to enioy an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, there consisteth farre greater paine and labour, to order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne it as it ought to be. But beside, what enuie doth hee expose himselfe to, &amp; multitude of mislikes, that hath the charge of gouerning others? If hee be iust, hee is branded with cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elry: if mercifull, hee is contemned: if beautifull, tearmed lauish and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall: if hee hoorde vp money, then basely couetous: if inclined to peace, then hee is a coward: If full of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, proudly anbitious: if discreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graue, surly and scornefull: if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fably courteous, silly and simple: if affecting solitude a dissembling hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite: if addicted to mirth and pleasure, then wantonly dissolute.</hi> In the end of all, te worthy Emperour thus concluded. <hi>Although willingly, I accepted this high office at the first: yet sorrow hath (since) made mee shrinke vnder so brdensom a charge: For, the Sea and dignitie are thinges pleasing to looke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n, but very peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to meddle withall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue alledged his example (wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Lord) because present vnto your gracious acceptance, his ancient and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Booke, called <hi>The Diall of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> wherein is at lige, and amply set downe, what care and respect awayteth on the liues of Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s and great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: for if they canot runne into the smallest errour, but redoundeth to the hurt of many, nor neglect their duty, without other mens userie: Then sayde the Philosopher well. <hi>A Prince should not appropriate the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>to himselfe, but shape him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe wholy to the Common wealth.</hi> And so much the rather, because he stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding accountable to no man in this Life, ought to remember a farre stricter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, before him that maketh no respect of Princes, saue onely in this, that they shall finde the Iudge the more seuere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, by how much they haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused their place of eminencie, as also their power and princely authority.</p>
   <p>In the learned Discourses following, set downe by that good Emperour <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius,</hi> the honourable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all this worke; are three especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duties and actions obserued, necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily required in an absolute and perfect Prince, as namely; In <hi>Ruling, Iudging,</hi> and <hi>Defending: To rule by iust lawes, and good Example; To Iudge by Wisedome, Prouidence,</hi> and <hi>Iustice;</hi> And <hi>Defend by valour, care, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy.</hi> And this is that which the Spirit of God so often intimateth by the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ap. <hi>22.</hi> verse <hi>3. To execute Iudgement and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse: To deliuer the oppressed from the handes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> the oppressour, Not to vexe the Stanger, fatherlesse, or Widdow: Neyther to doe violence, or shedde the innocent bloud.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Into infinite other famous presidents for Princes I could enter, and set them downe expressely; but that I know, they are so frequent to your Honour, both in reading and memorie, that it were as lost labour, as to hold a burning Taper in the bright Sunne at Noone-day, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore these few shall suffice, Nor doe I dedicate this vnto your graue and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned iudgement, as a new labour of mine owne, or as a worke neuer seene before; because it hath already past diuers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions: albeit not in so exact a maner, nor with the like paines, as hath now bin bestowed vpon it, from many absurde, and grosse imperfections, and yet not so cleanely purged, as I could wish it were, nor as it shall bee, if euer it come to the Presse againe. Wherefore I humbly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate your Honour, to accept it as it is, and as an oblation of my loue vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to you, which gladly would shew it selfe by any possible meanes, as time hereafter may better enable me. Til when, I remain ready at your Honours seruice, to the very vtmost of my best abilitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all duty.
A. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>