<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Wither, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120210_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15623</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25892</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120210</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Abuses stript, and whipt. Or Satirical essayes. By George Wyther. Diuided into two bookes</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>336 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eaders; I speake to you that
haue vnderstanding; when
these first fruits of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
<hi>Muses,</hi> shall come to
your iudicious censures, Do
not look for <hi>Spencers,</hi> or <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi>
wel composed numbers;
or the deep conceits of now florishing <hi>Iohnson;</hi>
no; say tis honest plain matter, &amp; there's as much
as I look for. If I haue seem'd to err in any thing
suppose me not so obstinate, or wel conceited of my
own opinions, but that I may be perswaded by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
that shal produce stronger <hi>reasons</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.
If any thing may seeme to haue a doubtfull
interpretation, assure your selues the honestest
meaning in it is mine, and although some may
think <hi>I</hi> haue not so wel ioyned things together as
<hi>I</hi> might haue done, <hi>I</hi> know whē you haue conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
the nature of the <hi>Subiect,</hi> &amp; the diuersity of
things therin hādled, you wil accept my good wil
&amp; let my yeeres be an excuse for that &amp; al other
ignorant ouer-sights whatsoeuer. Some no doubt
<pb facs="8"/>
will mistake my plainnes, in that <hi>I</hi> haue so blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
spoken what <hi>I</hi> haue obserued, without any <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi>
additions or fained <hi>Allegories, I</hi> am sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<hi>I</hi> haue not pleased them therein, but should
haue been more sorry if <hi>I</hi> had displeased my selfe
in doing otherwise; for <hi>I</hi> know if <hi>I</hi> had wrapt vp
vy meaning, in dark riddles, <hi>I</hi> should haue been
more applauded and lesse vnderstood, which I
nothing desire. <hi>I</hi> neither feare nor shame to
speake the <hi>Trurh,</hi> and therefore haue nakedly
thrust it forth without a couering. To what
end were it, if <hi>I</hi> (as some do) had appareld my
mind in darke <hi>Parables,</hi> that few or none
might haue vnderstood mee? <hi>I</hi> should doe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to be silent; but if it be more in request <hi>I</hi> may
hereafter be obscure enough, yet in this tis not
my meaning, for indeed, if <hi>I</hi> knew how, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
is to be so plaine, that the bluntest <hi>Iober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nole</hi>
might vnderstand mee. Our Grand-vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines
care not for a secret ierk; well wee may
shew an honest wit in couertly nipping them; but
either 'tis in vaine cause they perceiue it not, or
else ridiculous, seeing they only vnderstand it
who will but either malice or flout vs for our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors.
Many may dislike the harshnes of the <hi>Verse</hi>
but you know, although it be not stately, yet it we
<pb facs="8"/>
enough befits the matter, and whereas <hi>I</hi> may seem
blame-worthy in mixing <hi>Diuinity</hi> with <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi>
yet when you haue found my generall ayme;
considered with what reuerent respect <hi>I</hi> haue done
it, and what commendable authorities <hi>I</hi> may haue
for it, I nothing misdoubt your approbation. Those
things which concerne my selfe, may seeme chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish,
nothing pleasing, but you must consider I had
a care to please my selfe aswel as others; and if the
<hi>World</hi> blame mee as to sawcy with her, 'tis for
want of manners, but her owne fault, that would
allow mee no better education. To bee briefe, if I
haue any way offended I am so well perswaded you
wil mildly conster my errors and infirmities, that
<hi>I</hi> rest wholly, and onely on your sound and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<hi>Iudgements.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>*But*</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Readers;</hi> I meane you that are no more but <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi>
I make no question if this book come to your
spelling, it will haue many halting verses, and
disioynted sentenses: for I haue had experience
of your insufficiencie: yet haue <hi>I</hi> striu'd to bee
for your sakes <hi>I</hi> tell you (because <hi>I</hi> would if it were
possible bee vnderstood) as plaine (as they
say) as a pack-saddle, and now the doubt is then
fooles will ride me. If they doe certainly, <hi>I</hi> shall
<pb facs="9"/>
be rough &amp; vneasie for their tendernes. Though
you vnderstand them not yet because you see this
wants some fine <hi>Phrases</hi> &amp; flourishes, as you find
other mens writings stuft withal, perhaps you
wil iudge me vnlearned. Wel; and right enough.
Yet you will be counted but saucy <hi>Coblers</hi> to go
beyond your <hi>Lasts.</hi> And if that be a fault did not
the subiect and your ignorances, require me to be
in that sort faulty? <hi>I</hi> could with ease haue amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
it, for it cost me (<hi>I</hi> protest) more labour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
this plainenesse then if <hi>I</hi> had more <hi>Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi>
trim'd ii, but for feare if <hi>I</hi> speake much, <hi>I</hi>
confound your <hi>Memories, I</hi> will say no more but
this, <hi>Read and welcome,</hi> but <hi>Censure not,</hi>
for your iudgement is weake and <hi>I</hi> vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
renounce it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Valete</hi>
George Wither.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>