<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader. O Lord strengthen vs, that wee may fight thy battell, stand by vs, or els we can not preuaile. Giue vs faith, and we shall haue victorie for euer. Amen.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120782_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18639</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5154</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120782</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader. O Lord strengthen vs, that wee may fight thy battell, stand by vs, or els we can not preuaile. Giue vs faith, and we shall haue victorie for euer. Amen.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>1587. A Christian and wholesom admonition : directed to the Frenchmen, which are reuolted from true-religion, and haue polluted themselues with the superstition and idolatrie of poperie</title>
                 <author>Constant, Léonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Christian Reader.</hi> O Lord strengthen vs, that wee may fight thy battell, stand by vs, or els we can not preuaile. Giue vs faith, and we shall haue victorie for euer. Amen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anie men are of many minds. And few there are, that accept thankefully the labours of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, in these vnthankefull and last times. Yea it may be, they will thinke the publishing of this booke to be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, considering that we, neither (thankes be to God) now suffer, or are like to suffer persecution. For amongst vs, Gods word is preached, the Churches are in peace; and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish: all things goe with with vs, and not against vs. Againe, the gospel hauing continued so long, by all likelihood, it taketh such deepe root, as we shall not need to feare, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, or springing vp againe of Poperie. In deed, if these things were as they ought to be, receiued, followed, and obeyed: if men did know, and would confesse the goodnes of
<pb facs="4"/> the Lord in calling them, and vouchsafing them so manie mercies, in waiting so long for worthie fruites of their conuersion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: then no doubt, we should the lesse neede to feare that which our sins doe threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: that in so great light, and after so manie happie dayes: in the broad day of so manie graces of knowledge &amp; wisedom of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto men, that euer either darke po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie in the course of Idolatrie or heresie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme, or such like iniquitie should euer so grow again, as that persecution should be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But none of these things giue vs anie comfort. For howsoeuer Gods word be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, (which yet is done with great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that as scantlie as may be) yet it is not followed. We haue in deed some outward peace, but the spirituall peace of God, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie established in the Ministerie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, that is farre from vs: for alacke, we are waxed wantō at home, &amp; we prescribe God abroad according to our owne lusts, in the matters of his owne worship: we eate and drinke with the drunkard, and say: Our maister is gone into a farre iourney, and will be long a comming home. Gods enimies, the <hi>Amorites</hi> and <hi>Edomites</hi> may doe what they will, and the way is not taken that
<pb facs="4"/> should stocke vp by the roote these cursed fruites and wicked generations. For they haue long looked, though God in fauour and long patience haue waited for our repentance and therefore disappointed them, for the day, wherein they might once againe leade vs forth as sheepe to the cruel slaughter. And what shall we say. Is not God iust, that hee should chastice his children and be obeyed of his enimies? Yes verelie. In all times the godlie haue, and must beare their crosses. As long as Christ shall haue a Church on earth, Antichrist shall haue his Sinagogue. There will euer be children of the flesh, to persecute those that are of the spirit. And therefore those that dreame of an earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they deceyue them selues: for it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible that Gods seruants should haue their heauen in this world. God hath his cup in his hand fully mixed. His children must not onely kisse the cuppe, and drinke the first draught, but also his enimies shall sweepe vp the dregges euen to the bottom. Wherefore my good brother, whosoeuer thou art, reade such like exhortations as this is. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer God shall worke, pray that thou maiest abide such fierie tryals as he doth see meete and expedient for thee. Looke not vpon men,
<pb facs="5"/> but looke vpon the truth of thy God. All the men of the world, shall not be able to stand to plead any thy least reuolt from the truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the almighty God. Therefore neither for liuing nor land, for life nor limme, deny not the least iot of his euerlasting will. In time of peace, while it is yet sommer, prouide against winter. Before the stormes come, prepare the cables. Remēber the anker that may hold the ship fast in all dangers. For surely God will come, he can not but visite, that he may purge this land frō hipocrises, will-worships, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; follies, wherewith it is in a manner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed euerie where. And albeit this be to be looked for, yet feare not thou, whosoeuer thou be that art Gods childe. <hi>For these rods shall be for thy good. Thine eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies crueltie shall bring thee to feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and themselues to euerlasting woe. God will make way for thee, to escape all peril. Though they would send thee to hell, yet thou shalt goe to heauen. In killing thee, they shall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thee, and thou shalt liue for euer.</hi> The grace of our Lord Iesus Christ be with thee. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>