<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120602_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120602</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands bane: or, The description of drunkennesse. Composed and written by Thomas Young, sometimes student of Staple-Inne</title>
                 <author>Young, Thomas, student of Staple Inn</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Bailey (Baily, Baley, Bayly), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>ONG</hi> I am I confesse who take vpon mee to correct an enormitie crept into my country, too much frequented by yong and old of all conditions. Yet (gentle Reader) let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade thee to peruse the same, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different eye: not contemning any part thereof, because it is compiled by the Yong. And although thou mayest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps iustly say, that I haue beene equall with thee in this aspersion, yet let mee entreat againe that thou wilt no lesse equall me in my contrition) then resolue fully to concurre with me in my conuersion. Our Nation hath had for many yeeres since this imputation, that we should ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like imitate Forraigne countries in their vices, wherein I will not particularize for auoiding of offence, and the rather because it is to all iudiciall men too perspicuous, I could rather wish that leauing their examples in the worst, we did frame our selues to imitate, to compare, nay to excell them in their vertues and heroicall atchieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which may very easily be performed by vs in that God of his especiall goodnes to our Nation, hath indued vs with singularitie of apprehension, dexteritie of inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and meanes for discipline, exceeding all the borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring countries of the world. There is an vse and an abuse of the best creatures, and we can not deny, as well by the assertion of God himselfe, who in the creation saw all that he had made to be good, but that they were all made for the comfort for the seruice and for the vse of man. If we
<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>then neglecting the vse, doe fall into the abuse of those good creatures, and make them euill and hurtfull to vs: that followeth that wee contradict God in his purpose: we alter the nature and qualitie of the creature, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from our selues, that precedency and superioritie, which God hath giuen to man ouer those creatures: how doe we abase our selues from that soueraigntie which God hath giuen vs: who said <hi>(let man rule and haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer all creatures on the earth,</hi> when we suffer a poore inanimate creature, so to conquer and ouercome vs, that we lye grouelling on the earth speechlesse: nay sometimes lifelesse (ouer come by the strength of a Grape a weake and feeble substance) we all desire (as good reason we haue) to extenuate the power and kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than: but I dare boldly affirme, he gaineth more soules by this deadly sinne of Drunkennesse, then by all the sinnes of the world: and hath drowned and swallowed vp more in this gulfe, then were drowned in the generall deluge of <hi>Noahs</hi> floud. Lend me onely thy good will, for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of thy safety, which thou mayest haue or not haue at thine Election. But better it were to forbeare to reade this same, vnlesse thou practise the same in thy life and conuersation: Which thing grant both thy selfe and me, hoping thou wilt pray for me, as I haue done for thee, leauing thy will to Gods directions.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>