<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISMENT OF THE AVTHOR to the Catholicke Reader.</title>
           <author>W., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120085_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15506</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25771</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120085</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISMENT OF THE AVTHOR to the Catholicke Reader.</title>
                 <author>W., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English martyrologe : conteyning a summary of the liues of the glorious and renowned saintes of the three kingdomes, England, Scotland, and Ireland. Collected and distributed into moneths, after the forme of a calendar, according to euery saintes festiuity. VVherunto i annexed in the end a catalogue of those, who haue suffered death in England for defence of the Catholicke cause, since King Henry the 8. his breach with the Sea Apostolicke, vnto this day. By a Catholicke priest</title>
                 <author>Wilson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 356, 30 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISMENT OF THE AVTHOR to the Catholicke Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERAS all Bookes (good Reader) of what subiect soeuer, that are published to the view of the world, must passe the censures and iudgments of many sortes of people; I haue thought it not amisse before thou enter any further into the contentes, to giue thee two or three short aduertisments in this place; as well therby to preuent all occasions of misconstruction or cauill, that any man, perchance, may take against this little worke or Sanctiloge of myne; as also the better to informe thy vnderstanding, concerning diuers doubtes or other difficultyes, that in the reading therof may happily occurre vnto thee.</p>
   <p n="1">1. First then I would haue thee to vnderstand, that what I haue heere set downe in this ensuing Martyrologe concerning the liues and miracles of these glorious and renowned Saintes of our <hi>Great-Britany,</hi> and of the Ilands belonging therunto; I haue done the same with all truth, sincerity &amp; conscience, to my knowledge: not contenting my selfe with bare wordes and relations only; but haue in the margents quoted also the bookes and places of the Authors, out of whome I haue gathered al that is heere alleaged. Neyther haue I vsed any other Authors herin, but such as are approued by the Sea Apostolick, or at leastwise permitted by the same reiecting all Apocryphall Legends or other fabulous Historyes, that may be any way suspected of the least note of falsity or errour whatsoeuer.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Secondly I haue not taken vpon me in this Catalogue or Calendar to make an vniuersall Martyrologe, but haue gathered togeather only the ancient Saintes, Martyrs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours &amp; Virgins of our three Kingdomes, <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
&amp; <hi>Ireland:</hi> Yet for that, besides these of our owne, there are some others also of foraine Nations, by whome our said Countreys haue receyued some notable or pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar benefit, either publicke or priuate; as hauing byn our Apostles or Patrons, eyther by way of preaching, teaching, protection, or otherwise in the cooperation to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion, and consequently to be by vs honoured and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced for such, as all our Cath. Ancestours and forfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done before vs, and as we see all other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Countreys round about vs to do the like in the same case: These (I say) I haue thought good to accompt as our owne, &amp; togeather with our owne to place thē on their proper festiuall dayes, to the end we may as well with due honour obserue their Memoryes and Solemnityes: as also therby auoyd the vngratefull obliuion of so great &amp; inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefits receyued by them and their merits.</p>
   <p n="3">3. The third Aduertisement may be, that wheras it hath pleased God to giue vnto our little Dominions so many glorious Saintes, both Martyrs, Cōfessours &amp; Virgins (besides these later of our dayes, whose Names I haue also put downe in a Catalogue a part by thēselues, in the later end of this booke) who may be more then sufficient, to make a whole and complete Calendar, throughout euery Moneth, placing on euery day one; yet for that a great number of our ancient Saintes haue no proper festiuityes in our English Catholicke Church, and many of them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and almost out of memory, by this vnfortunate fall of our Countrey, frō the true and ancient Catholicke faith, and vnion of the Sea Apostolicke: I haue thought it most conuenient for the more full accomplishing and perfecting of a Martyrologe, that where any day falleth out to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather voyd; there to place one or more of the forsaid ancient Saintes, whose publicke celebrity hath not byn hitherto kept; &amp; therof to make a Commemoration only (which in the Roman &amp; other Martyrologes is often vsed) noting the same with the signe of an Asteriske or Starre in the Margent, to the end it may be knowne and obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="9"/>
of the Reader. And where none of these forsaid Markes, so noted, is to be found; then vpon that day is put the true festiuity of the Saint, whome there thou shalt find placed.</p>
   <p n="4">4. And lastly, I do not meane by this ensuing Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrologe to introduce any other publicke obseruation or festiuity of any of the Saintes heerin by me set downe, then that which the Catholicke Church of England hath in formertymes, and doth also at this present celebrate: but only my intention is to lay forth the summe of their liues and miracles as briefly as I may, for the increase of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Catholicke people, and for the duty and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced owe vnto them both: leauing the rest to euery mans pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>re and particular deuotion, as he shall, by reading the same, be affected to their glorious veneration. Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ing hartily all such Catholickes of our said Coūtreys, to whose hands this little worke may chance to come; that if they haue any other notes, concerning these our ancient Saintes lying by them, they would vouchsafe, eyther to impart the same vnto me, or be pleased themselues, by reuiewing this small labour of myne, to publish the same anew, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>end my imperfections heerin, if any shalbe found; as well for the honour of the glorious Saintes themselues, as the publike vtility of these our Kingdoms and Countreys. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>