<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>May, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120174_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07323</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17710</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120174</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>May, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of the estate of clothing now vsed within this realme of England : 1 The royaltie and benefit of wooll and woollen cloth. 2 The condition of the makers, being two sorts. 3 The antiquitie and power of the alneger. 4 The manner of search and searchers, now vsed. 5 The seuerall faults and abuses practised in cloth. 6 The inconuenience and hurt by the abuses. 7 The remedie to be made by the alnegers prouision. VVith an apologie for the alneger, shewing the necessarie vse of his office. Written by Iohn May, a deputie alneger</title>
                 <author>May, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 51, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I must confesse that my ouerdaring attempt, deserues a disgracefull checke, who like <hi>Icarus,</hi> with waxen wings hath soard so high, but that the sun beames haue beene fauourable, my downfall might be as sodains: this president is none of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and beeing so farre vnfit intend not to make it my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctize. An extraordinarie cause compels me to this worke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you must expect an explanation by an Alneger and not by an Oratour: and as I most desire the good opinion of the best, who doe alwaies censure well, so I least regard the taunts of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser sort, who commonly carpe at all. If amongst these rude weeds, you can gather any wholsome herbes to serue your vse I shall then gaine what I most sought for. I am the more inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to aduenture because this vessell is bound to that port, where yet noe other hath beene before mee with like lading, whose better beautified wares had spoilde my market: yet haue I trauelled as much to collect, and beene as carefull in the choise of this fraight as any whatsoeuer: and imagine that he which in this, trades farther, shall deale for a doubtfull gaine, beeing commoditie not vendible for all, but rather vtterly reiected by some, yet good hope may drawe them on, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that the same sort, or the least companie and worst con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who knoweth not that from one flower the Bee drawes hony and the Spider poyson, and that the content of the good, is the contempt of the euill: Therefore my reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is set, hap how it wil, if the voiage mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie I am not the first whom hope hath deluded, but will striue to rest sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied howsoeuer. And so I take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to his power, <hi>IOHN MAY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>