<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the quicke-sighted Reader.</title>
           <author>Petowe, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120613_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09528</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19807</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120613</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the quicke-sighted Reader.</title>
                 <author>Petowe, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of Hero and Leander : Conteyning their further fortunes. By Henry Petowe</title>
                 <author>Petowe, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 <publisher>Harris, Andrew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the quicke-sighted Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Inde Gentlemen, what I would I cannot, but what I could with that litle skill I had, I haue presumed to present to your fauourable viewes: I am not ashamed to beg your kind fauours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I finde my selfe altogether insufficient to performe that which my good will hath taken in hand: Yet with my soule I wish my labours maye merite your kynde fauours. Yf not for the toyle herein taken, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse haue no way deserued the least iotte of fauour: yet for the <hi>Subiects</hi> sake, for <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leanders</hi> sake. Yf neyther of these purchase fauour, the frowning browes of sad discontent, will banish my poore harmeles <hi>Muse,</hi> into the vast wide wildernesse of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall obliuion. I am assured Gentlemen, you will maruell what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or rather furie inforced mee to vndertake such a waightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I beeing but a slender <hi>Atlas</hi> to vphoulde or vndergoe such a massie burthen: yet I hope you will rather assist, and further mee with the wings of your sweete fauours, then to hinder my forward indeauours with your dislikings: esteeming it as the first fruits of an vnripe wit, done at certaine vacant howers: In which hope I rest captiuated till I be freed by your liberall and kinde Censures.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours still, if mine euer.</hi> Henrie Petowe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>