<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY RIGHT VVORTHY AND WOR∣SHIPFVLL FRIEND, MASTER IOHN GIFFORD of Lancrasse in Deuon, Esquire, All Grace and Peace.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr66_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY RIGHT VVORTHY AND WOR∣SHIPFVLL FRIEND, MASTER IOHN GIFFORD of Lancrasse in Deuon, Esquire, All Grace and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="651"/>
   <pb facs="651"/>
   <head>TO MY RIGHT VVORTHY AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL FRIEND, MASTER IOHN GIFFORD <hi>of</hi> Lancrasse <hi>in</hi> Deuon, Esquire, All Grace and Peace.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>J hold it (as I ought) one of the rich mercies of <hi>GOD,</hi> that he hath giuen me fauour in some eies which haue not seene me; but none, that J know, hath so much demerited me, vnknowne, as your worthy Familie: Ere therefore you see my face, see my hand willingly professing my thankefull Obligations: Wherewith may it please you to accept of this parcell of thoughts, not vnlike those fellowes of theirs, whom you haue entertained aboue their desert. These shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto you our bountifull <hi>SAVIOVR,</hi> magnifying his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to men, in a sweet varietie; healing the diseased, raising the dead, casting out the Deuill, calling in the Publican, and shall raise your heart to adore that infinite goodnesse; Euery helpe to our deuotion deserues to bee precious; So much more, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit
<pb facs="652"/> age of the World declines to an heartlesse coldnesse of Pietie: That <hi>GOD,</hi> to whose honour these poore labours are meant, blesse them in your hands, and from them, to all Readers. To his protection J heartily commend you, and the right vertuous Gentlewoman, your worthy wife, with all the pledges of your happy affection, as whom you haue deserued to be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your truly thankfull and</hi> officious friend, <hi>IOS. HALL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>