<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120266_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08592</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18904</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120266</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A wife novv the widdow of Sir Thomas Overburye : Being a most exquisite and singular poem of the choice of a wife. Whereunto are added many witty characters, and conceited newes, written by himselfe and other learned gentlemen his friends</title>
                 <author>Overbury, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HY ignorance may challenge libertie enough, not to relish the deepe Arte of Poetry: because opinion makes thee obstinate; and rude tradition hath taught thee nothing but an abuse of knowledge. For when thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest a quaffing fellowes barbarisme, a worthy-written stile in Tragedies, and a collusiue flourish onely fronted with the name of excellent; thou ouer-lookst them all with the vsuall contempt or aspersion of friuolous, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasticke labours, putting no difference betwixt the horse pictured on a signe-post, and the curious limbd <hi>Pegasus:</hi> But the age giues one comfort in extremitie, that as there is a <hi>Lizard</hi> which assailes; so is there one, which wonders at the maiestie of man: sure I am if any shall neglect, nay not commend the worth of this so generally approued Poem; he may (if it proceeds from nice critiscisme) bee well excluded as a churlish retainer to the Muses; (if
<pb facs="3"/>
from a direct plaine dealing) he must be degraded for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficiencie. For had such a volume been extant among the ancient Romanes, though they wanted our easie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations of wit, by printing; yet would they rather, and more easily, haue committed the sense hereof to brasse, and cedar leaues, then let such an Author, baue lost his due eternitie. If to converse with a creature so amiable, heere described, be thought more then difficult, let then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of it be admirable, which hath expressed the soule in so compact aforme of body. The surplusage, that now exceeds the last edition, was (that I may bee honestly impartiall) in some things only to be challenged by the first author, but others now added, (little inferior to the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due) being in nature answerable, and first transcrib'd by Gentlemen of the same qualitie, I haue vpon good induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made publike with warrantie of their and my owne credit. Not doubting therefore to be doubly discharged, both by the verdict of conscience and the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deserued thankes of all iudicious Readers, I bid you euery one farewell, May 16. 1614.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>