<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all the busie Horsecorsers, both of the Citty and Country where∣soeuer.</title>
           <author>Billingsley, Martin</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120787_Fr8_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06903</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17334</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120787</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all the busie Horsecorsers, both of the Citty and Country where∣soeuer.</title>
                 <author>Billingsley, Martin</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cauelarice, or The English horseman : contayning all the arte of horse-manship, as much as is necessary for any man to vnderstand, whether he be horse-breeder, horse-ryder, horse-hunter, horse-runner, horse-ambler, horse-farrier, horse-keeper, coachman, smith, or sadler. Together, with the discouery of the subtill trade or mistery of horse-coursers, &amp; an explanatio [n] of the excellency of a horses vndersta [n] ding, or how to teach them to doe trickes like Bankes his curtall: and that horses may be made to drawe drie-foot like a hound. Secrets before vnpublished, &amp; now carefully set down for the profit of this whole nation: by Geruase Markham</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 88, 4, 212, 233-264, 4, 67, 58-72, 4, 54, 4, 56, 4, 64, 4, 11, 10-81, 5, 20, 25-40 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="367"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To all the busie Horsecorsers, both of</hi> the Citty and Country where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Magin not because I haue discouered vnto the world those secret deceits wherewith the world is hourely beguiled, that I with a more spleeny spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit do condemne you, then all other trades what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer: for if the Marchant will haue a dark shop to make bright sulled ware: if the Shoe-maker will cut Leather but halfe tand, the Carpenter worke his Timber halfe seasond, if the Baker will not giue his true waight, the Butcher will not forgoe his imbosture of prickes, nor any trade whatsoeuer but will preserue to himselfe some disception; beleeue it I conclude you as good, and loue you as much as any, and think it agreeable with the law of reason, that you haue as much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge as any whatsoeuer in this worldly Charter. But foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as some (because they deceiue themselues) make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in deceiuing others, and thinke the gaine most honest, how euer gathered by the hand of corruption, I thought it not amis to make my selfe a warrant without authority, and to lay open what with long experience, and diligent obseruation I haue noted, and sometimes purchased at too deere a reckoning, both to fortify the honest against vnconscionable practise, and to make thē loath those grosse deceits, of which euen Boyes and Babes may detect them, which if it reape thankes from them that reape profit, I haue my wish, if it offend the contrary I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect not, because they may amend their losse if they will buy with care, and sell with a good conscience.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Farewell.
G. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>