<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all men of Warre
in generall.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120635_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15466</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25733</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120635</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all men of Warre
in generall.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discourse of vvarre. VVritten by Sir Roger VVilliams Knight; vvith his opinion concerning some parts of the martiall discipline. Newly perused</title>
                 <author>Williams, Roger, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To all men of Warre
in generall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Souldiers of what qualitie soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
where I discourse of the vertues
and vices that aduanceth and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth
all actions, all that hath
their honor to lose may claime part of
the vertues, neither needes any to
bee grieued at the vices vnlesse they
condemne themselues guiltie; the
greatest Captaines of <hi>Europe,</hi> can
witnesse, that I robbed neither superiour nor companion of his
right, much lesse hath been euer my thoughts to wrong any ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
action: the which all or the most of you that knowe me
will beare witnesse, when my Netherlanders discourses with
others, comes out. I thinke <hi>Gonsalua</hi> was called the last
graund Captaine, but I perswade my selfe neither he nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
before him had euer carried that name, without the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conding
of a number of braue companions. The most worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<hi>Caesar</hi> although hee was highly ambitious, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
in his <hi>Commentaries</hi> written by himselfe, hee imputed
part of his honour vnto his Lieftenants and Officers. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
should not others doo at the least the like, being not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
to be compared vnto the basest sort of his followers: no
honorable minds can bee free from honorable ambition, but
the ambitiō may be such (let the minde be neuer so great) if hee
robbs the honor of his companions, he wrongs himselfe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates
his action. Few men of iudgement but knowes it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
for one man to conduct an Armie without Officers, &amp;
vnpossible for any state to knowe the worth of their Captaines
without being in action with great enemies: but for that triall
<pb facs="4"/>
the <hi>Parisians, Gauntois, Antwerpians</hi> and such, would one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
place squadrons in battailes, chuse grounds, march in what
order you would, arme men in good order, fortifie and discourse,
with other matters, to the shew, as though they had been great
masters of Campes: but when they were tried with the furie
of expert executioners, their warres prooued but May-games.
Although I perswade myselfe my Discourse bee Vnpleasant,
with small iudgement: notwithstanding, being perswaded
by honourable good friends, I tooke courage to print it: true
it is, no action ought to be printed without the consent of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
Actors, or at the least by one Principall, which ought to
signe his workes with his name, otherwise wee finde the most
Actors wronged and robbed of the most of their reputation:
some with enuie or malice, others with glorious ambition:
sometimes you haue most honorable quiet Estates wronged
with ambitious follies libells, the which are hardlie knowne
and found out: but being signed by the author, deserues hee
well, the honour is his; if ill, the shame shall be his. Men of
Warre ought to bee more open hearted, more liberall, and more
affable, than any other profession, although their secrets ought
to bee but vnto fewe, their hearts must be open vnto the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,
and liberall to confesse good deserts as well as with their
purses: although their resolutions be agreed on by two or three,
notwithstanding the more affable they shewe themselues vnto
the multitude, the greater will be their voges and loues. Some
tearme men wise for not speaking many words: true it is, idle
speaches are windes, and a disgrace vnto the speaker; but bee
they to good purpose, the more hee speakes, the greater is his
praise. You must thinke to repeate great actions, it requires
many words, to perswade the fewe expert companions to offend
or defend, a fewe words will serue: but to animate or disswade
the rude multitude, the more words and the oftner the better.
Wee doo finde the most Conquerours were greatlie aduanced
with the orations of their Orators, as well amongst the serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest
sort as the rude multitude: without speaches, the wise can
not be discerned from the foolish, nor without triall of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="4"/>
against equall enemies, the perfects Captaine cannot bee
knowne from the most ignorant. Otherwise ignorance will
condemne Generalls, their followers and actions let them bee
euer so great, although themselues neuer carried places of repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
either in field or towne, nor commanded more than ouer
their owne seruants, saying wee haue knowne great Potentates
Campes, and Courts. Let no man bee so simple to iudge them
worthie to condemne great actions or their actors, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
imployed in their great affaires, it is hard for men to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne
themselues well, harder to gouerne a few, more harder to
gouerne many, much more a great multitude; some can gouerne
a houshold, and cannot gouerne a towne; some can gouerne a
towne, and not a whole countrie. A man may be sufficient to
conduct a priuate companie, and not sufficient to command a
Regiment; likewise sufficient for a Coronell, and not for a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.
But whether it be for policie or Armes, it is an error to
thinke men without triall worthie to bee compared vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
tried, in what place soeuer great or small. Diuers play <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
on the stages, but fewe or none in the field. Our
pleasant <hi>Tarleton</hi> would counterfeite many artes, but hee
was no bodie out of his mirths. Many haue a vertue, few
hath many, none haue all: the most men lookes into their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
faults, but fewe lookes into their owne; beare with mine,
I will beare with thine; loue mee, I will loue thee; let vs loue
each other, and God will loue vs all: on that condition noble
superiours, <hi>Roger Williams</hi> wisheth to you all honour and
happines, and to you companions, no worse than to himselfe▪
Farewell.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>