<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A GENER ALL PRO∣LOGVE VPON THE BOOKE. ENTITVLED THE DYALL OF PRINCES: WITH THE FA∣mous Booke of MARCVS AVRELIVS, Compyled by the Reuerend Father in GOD, the Lord ANTONY of GVEVARA, By∣shop of Guadix: Confessor and Chronicler to Charles the fifth, Em∣perour of Rome: vnto whom, (and to all other Princes, and Noble-personages) this worke was directed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120712_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12430</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A GENER ALL PRO∣LOGVE VPON THE BOOKE. ENTITVLED THE DYALL OF PRINCES: WITH THE FA∣mous Booke of MARCVS AVRELIVS, Compyled by the Reuerend Father in GOD, the Lord ANTONY of GVEVARA, By∣shop of Guadix: Confessor and Chronicler to Charles the fifth, Em∣perour of Rome: vnto whom, (and to all other Princes, and Noble-personages) this worke was directed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archontorologion, or The diall of princes : containing the golden and famous booke of Marcus Aurelius, sometime Emperour of Rome. Declaring what excellcncy [sic] consisteth in a prince that is a good Christian: and what euils attend on him that is a cruell tirant. Written b the Reuerend Father in God, Don Antonio of Gueuara, Lord Bishop of Guadix; preacher and chronicler to the late mighty Emperour Charles the fift. First translated out of French by Thomas North, sonne to Sir Edward North, Lord North of Kirthling: and lately reperused, and corrected from many grosse imperfections. With addition of a fourth booke, stiled by the name of The fauoured courtier</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 331, pages 933, 341-424, 429-542, that is 560, 2, 561-654, 659-768, that is 766 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="general_prologue">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A GENER ALL <hi>PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOGVE VPON THE BOOKE. ENTITVLED</hi> THE DYALL OF PRINCES: WITH THE <hi>FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Booke of MARCVS AVRELIVS, Compyled by the</hi> Reuerend Father in <hi>GOD,</hi> the Lord <hi>ANTONY</hi> of <hi>GVEVARA,</hi> By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Guadix:</hi> Confessor and Chronicler to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Rome:</hi> vnto whom, (and to all other Princes, <hi>and Noble-personages) this worke was directed.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Polonius Thianeus</hi> disputing with the schollers of <hi>Hiareas,</hi> said: that among all the affections of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nothing is more naturall, then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that all haue to preserue life.</p>
   <p>Omitting the dispute of these great Phylosophers herein, wee our selues hereof haue daily proofe: that to liue, men do trauell: to liue, byrds do flie: fishes do swimme: and to liue, beasts do hide themselues for feare of death. Finally, (I say) there is no liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture so brutish, that hath not a naturall desire to liue.</p>
   <p>If many of the auncient Paynims so little regarde life, that of their owne free willes, they offered themselues death, they did it not for that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised <note place="margin">The heathē may teach Christians how to liue.</note> life, but because they thought that for their little regarding life, wee would more highly esteem their fame For, wee see men of hauty courages, seeke rather to winne a long-during-Fame, then to saue a short lasting-life. How loth men are to die, is easily seen by the great paines they take to liue. For it is a naturall thing to all mortall men, to leaue their liues with sorrowe and take their deaths with feare.</p>
   <p>Admit that all doe taste this corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death, and that generally both good and euill doe die: yet is there great difference between the death of the one, and the death of the other.</p>
   <p>If the good desire to liue, it is onely for the greater desire they haue to do more good: but if the euill desire to liue, it is for that they would abuse the world longer. For the children of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity call no time good, but onely that wherein they liue, according to their owne desires. I let you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that are at this present, and you also that shall come heereafter: that I direct my writings vnto those which embrace vertue, and not vnto such as are borne away with vice.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>GOD</hi> doth not weigh vs, as we are, but as wee desire to bee. And let no man say, I would, and cānot be good: for as wee haue the audacitie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a faulte, so (if we list) wee may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our selues to worke amendes. All our vndoing proceedeth of this, that wee outwardly make a shewe of vertue, but inwardly in the deede wee employ our whole power to vice: which is an abuse, wherewith all the world is corrupted and deceiued. For
<pb facs="4"/>
Heauen is not furnished but with <hi>good deedes,</hi> and hell is not replenished but with <hi>Euill-desires.</hi> I graunt that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man nor beast desireth to die, but all trauell, to the ende they may liue: But I aske now this question.</p>
   <p>What doth it auayle a man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire his life to be prolonged, if the same be wicked, vngodly, and defamed? <hi>The man that is high-minded, proude, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant, cruell, disdainfull enuious, full of hatred, angry, malicious, full of wrath, couetous, a Lyer, a Gluton, a Blasphemer,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>and in all his doings disordred: Why will wee suffer him in the world?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The life of a poor man that for need stealeth <hi>a gowne, or any other small trifle</hi> is forthwith taken away: <hi>Why then is hee that disturbeth the whole Common-wealth left aliue?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Oh would to <hi>GOD</hi> there were no greater theeues in the world thē those which robbe the <hi>temporall goods of the Rich, and that wee did not winke</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually at them, which take away the <hi>good renowne, as well of the Rich,</hi> as of <hi>the Poore.</hi> But wee chastise the one, and dissemble with the other, which is euidently seene, how the theefe that stealeth my neighbours gown is han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged forthwith, but hee that robbeth mee of my good-name, walketh still before my doore.</p>
   <p>The diuine <hi>Plato</hi> in the first booke of laws, saide: We ordaine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, that hee which vseth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe honestly, and hath not his house well-reformed, his Riches well gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">A worthy sentence of Plato.</note> his family well instructed, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not in peace with his neighbors, that vnto him bee assigned Tutours, which shall gouerne him as a Foole, and as a vacabonde shall he be expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from the people, to the intent the common-wealth be not through him infected. For there neuer riseth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention or strife in a commonwealth, but by such men as are alwayes out of order.</p>
   <p>Truely, the diuine <hi>Plato</hi> had great reason in his sayings, for the man that is vicious in his person, and doth not trauell in things touching his House, nor keepeth his Familie in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor liueth quietly in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, deserueth to be banished, and driuen out of the countrey.</p>
   <p>Truely we see in diuers places mad men tyed and bound fast, which if they were at libertie would not doe so much harme, as those doe that daylie walke the streetes at their owne willes and sensualitie. There is not at this day so great or noble a Lord, nor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die so delicate, but had rather suffer a blow on the head with a stone, then a blot in their <hi>good-Name,</hi> with an euill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue. For the wound of the head in a month or two may well bee healed: but the blemish of their <hi>good-name</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life will neuer be remoued.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Laertius</hi> sayth in his booke of the liues of Phylosophers, that <hi>Dyogenes</hi> being asked of one of his neighbours, what they were that ordayned theyr Lawes? Aunswered in this wise.</p>
   <p>Thou shalt vnderstand, my friend, that the earnest whole desire of our Fore-fathers, and all the intentions of the phylosophers, was only to instruct <note place="margin">A prettie sentence.</note> them in their Common-wealth, how they ought to speake, how to be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed, how to eate, how to sleepe, how to treat, how to apparrel, how to trauell, and how to rest: And in this consisteth all the wealth of worldly wisedome.</p>
   <p>In deede this Phylosopher in his aunswer touched an excellent point: <hi>For the Law was made to none other end, but only to brydle him that liueth without Reason or Law.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To men that will liue in rest, and without trouble in this life, it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site and necessarie that they chuse to themselues some kinde and manner of Liuing, whereby they may maintaine their house in good-order, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb facs="4"/>
their liues vnto the same.</p>
   <p>That estate ought not to be as the folly of the person doth desire, nor as may bee most pleasant to the delights of the bodie: but as reason teacheth them, and God commaundeth them, for the surer saluation of theyr soules. For, the <hi>Children of vanitie embrace that onely, which the sensuall appetite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sireth: and reiect that which Reason commaundeth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Since the time that Trees were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they alwayes (remaining in their first nature vntill this present day) doe beare the same leafe and fruite: which things are plainly seen in this: that the <hi>Palme</hi> beareth <hi>Dates,</hi> the Fig-tree figs, the Nut-tree Nuttes, the Peare-tree Peares, the Apple-tree Apples, the Chestnut-tree chest-nuts, the Oke A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes: and to conclude, I say, all things haue kept their first nature, saue onely the <hi>Sinnefull-Man,</hi> which hath fallen by malice.</p>
   <p>The Planettes, the Starres, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, the Water, the Earth, the Ayre, and the Fire: the brute beasts, and the <note place="margin">The trees of the earth sheweth the malice of man.</note> Fishes, all continue in the same estate wherein they were first created: not complaining nor enuying the one the other. Man complaineth continually, hee is neuer satisfyed, and alwayes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteth to chaunge his estate. For the shepheard would be a Husbandman, the husbandman a Sqiure, the Squire a Knight, the Knight a King, the King an Emperour, &amp;c. Therefore I say, that fewe is the number of them that seeke amendment of life: but infinite are they that trauell to better their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, and to increase their goods.</p>
   <p>The decay of the Common-wealth (at this present) through all the world is, that the drye and withered Okes, which haue been nourished vpon the sharpe mountains, would now seeme to be daintie. Date-trees cherished in the pleasant gardains. I meane, <hi>that those which yesterday could haue bin plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant with drye Acornes in a poore cottage at home: at this day will not eate but of delicate Dishes in other mens houses a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>What estate men ought to take vpon them, to keepe their conscience <note place="margin">A good les<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son for all persons to follow.</note> pure, and to haue more rest in theyr life, a man cannot easily describe. For ther is no state in the Church of God, but men may therin (if they will) serue God, and profite themselues. For, there is no kinde of life in the world, but the wicked (if they perseuer and continue therein) may slaunder their persons, and also lose their soules.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> in an Epistle that hee wrote to <hi>Fabatus</hi> his friend, saith: There is nothing among mortall men more common and daungerous, then to giue place to <hi>vaine imaginations,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man beleeueth the estate of one to bee much better then the estate of another. And hereof it proceedeth, that the World doeth blinde men so, that they will rather seeke <hi>that which is an other mans</hi> by trauell and daunger, then to enioy their owne with quiet and rest.</p>
   <p>I say the state of Princes is good, if they abuse it not. I say the state of the people is good: if they behaue themselues obediently. I say the state of the rich is good, if they will God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vse it. I say the estate of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious is good, if they be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite others. I say the estate of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie is good, if they will content themselues: I say the estate of the poore is good, if they haue pacience. For it is <hi>no merite to suffer troubles, if wee haue not pacience therein.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>During the time of this our misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life we cannot denie, but in euery estate there is both trouble &amp; danger. For then onely our estate shall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, when we shall come gloriously in soule and bodie without the feare of death: and also when we shall reioyce without daungers in life.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Returning againe to our purpose, (Mightie Prince) although wee all be of value little, wee all haue little, we all can attaine little, wee all know little, we all are able to doe little, we all loue but little: yet in all this little, the state of Princes seemeth some great and high thing. For that worldly men say, There is no such felicitie in this life, as to haue authoritie to cōmaund many, and to be bound to obey none. But if eyther subiects knew how deere Princes by their power to command, or if princes knew how sweet a thing it is to liue in quiet, doubtles the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects would pittie their rulers, and the rulers would not enuie their subiects. For, full fewe are the pleasures which Princes enjoy, in respect of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that they endure.</p>
   <p>Since then, the estates of <hi>Princes</hi> is greater then all, that hee may do more then all, is of more value then all, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth more then all: And finally, that from thence proceedeth the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of all, it is more needefull that the <hi>House,</hi> the <hi>Person,</hi> and the <hi>life of a Prince,</hi> be better gouerned and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered then all the rest. For, euen as by the <hi>meate-yard</hi> the Marchaunt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sureth all his wares: So by the life whole of the Prince is measured the whole common-weale.</p>
   <p>Many sorrowes endureth the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in nourishing a way-ward child: great trauell taketh a Schoolmaster in <note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</note> teaching an vntoward scholler: much paines taketh an Officer in gouerning a multitude ouer-great. How great then is the paine and perill, wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I offer my selfe, in taking vpon mee to order the life of such an one, vpon whose life dependeth all the good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of a Common-weale?</p>
   <p>For, Noble Princes and great Lords ought of vs to bee serued, and not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: wee ought to exhort them, not to vexe them: wee ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create them, not to rebuke them: wee ought to aduise them, and not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame them. Finally (I say) the right simple, reckon I that Surgion, which with the same plaisters hee layed <hi>to a harde heele, seeketh to cure the tender Eyes:</hi> I meane by this comparison, that my purpose is not to tell Princes and Noble-men in this booke what they be, but to warne them what they ought to bee: not to tell them what they do, but to aduise them what they ought to doe. For, that Noble-man which will not amende his life for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of his owne conscience: Iidoe thinke hee will doe it for the writing of my pen.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Paulus Dyaconus</hi> the first Hystorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher, in the second booke of his <hi>Commentaryes,</hi> sheweth an antiquitie, right worthie to remember, and also pleasaunt to read: Although indeed to the hinderaunce of my selfe I shall rehearse it.</p>
   <p>It is, as of the Henne, who by long scraping <hi>on the Dung-hill, discouereth the knife, that shall cut her owne throate.</hi> Thus was the case, <hi>Hanniball</hi> the most <note place="margin">A Sentence of Paulus Dyaconus:</note> renowmed Prince and captain of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> (after hee was vanquished by the aduenturous <hi>Scipio)</hi> fled into <hi>Asia,</hi> to king <hi>Antiochus,</hi> a prince then liuing of great vertue, who receyued him into his realme, tooke him into his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and right honourably intertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him in his house. And truly king <hi>Antiochus</hi> did heerein, as a pittyfull prince: For what can more beautifie <hi>the honour of a Prince,</hi> then to succour <hi>Nobilitie</hi> in their needefull estate?</p>
   <p>These two Noble Princes vsed diuers exercises to spende the time honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie: and thus they diuided their <hi>time.</hi> Sometime to hunt in the mountains, otherwhiles to disporre them in the fields, oft to view their Armeys: But chiefly, they resorted to the Schooles, to heare the Phylosophers. And true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they did like wise and skilfull men. For there is no houre in a day other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise 
<pb facs="5"/>
so well employed, as in hearing a wise pleasant tongued man. There was at a time in <hi>Ephesus</hi> a famous Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher called <hi>Phormio,</hi> which open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publikely read and taught the people of the realme. And one day as these two Princes came into the Schoole, the Philosopher <hi>Phormio</hi> chaunged the matter whereupon he read, and of a sudden began to talke of the meanes and wayes that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ought to vse in warre, and of the order to bee kept in giuing battell: Such, so strange, and high phrased was the matter which hee talked of, that not onely they maruelled which neuer before saw him: but euen those also that of long time had daily heard him. For herein curious and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing wits shew their excellency, in that they neuer want fresh matter to entreate vpon.</p>
   <p>Greatly gloried the King <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> that this Philosopher (in presēce of this strange Prince) had so excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently spoken, so that strangers might vnderstand he had his realme stored with wise men: For couragious and noble Princes esteem nothing so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as to haue men valiāt to defend their Frontiers, and also wise to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne their common-weales.</p>
   <p>The Lecture read, King <hi>Antiochus</hi> demaunded of the Prince <hi>Hannibal,</hi> how he liked the talke of the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Formio?</hi> to whom <hi>Hanibal</hi> stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly answered, and in his answer shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himselfe to bee of that stoutnesse he was the same day, when he wan the great battell at <hi>Cannas:</hi> for although noble hearted and couragious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces lose all their estates and realmes: yet they will neuer confesse their harts to be ouerthrowne nor vanquished: And these were the words that at that time <hi>Hannibal</hi> sayde. Thou shalt vnderstand K. <hi>Antiochus</hi> that I haue seene diuers doting old men, yet I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer saw a more dotard foole thē <hi>Phor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio,</hi> whom thou callest such a great Philosopher: For the greatest kinde of folly is, when a man that hath but a little vaine science, presumeth to teach not those which haue onely sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, also such as haue most certaine experience.</p>
   <p>Tell me King <hi>Antiochus,</hi> what hart can brooke with patience, or what tongue can suffer with silence, to see a silly man (as this Philosopher is) nourished all his life time in a corner of <hi>Greece,</hi> studying Philosophie, to presume, as hee hath done, to talke before the prince <hi>Hannibal</hi> of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of warre, as though hee had beene eyther Lord of <hi>Affrique,</hi> or Captaine of <hi>Rome?</hi> Certes, hee ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther full little knoweth himselfe, or else but little esteemeth vs: For it appeareth by his vaine wordes, hee would seeme to know more in mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of warre, by that hee hath read in bookes, then doth <hi>Hanniball</hi> by the sundry &amp; great battels which he hath fought in the fields.</p>
   <p>Oh King <hi>Antiothus,</hi> how farre <hi>and how great is the difference, betweene the estate of Phylosophers, and the state of Captaines: betweene the skyll to reade in Schooles, and the knowledge to rule an Armey: betweene the science that wise men haue in bookes, and the experience that the others haue in warre: betweene their skill to write with the penne, and ours to fight with the Sword: betweene one that for his pastime is set round with deskes of bookes, and an other in perill of life, encompassed with troups of Enemyes.</hi> For, many there are <hi>which with great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, in blazing deeds don in warres, can vse their tongues: but fewe are those that at the brunte haue hearts to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their liues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Phylosopher neuer saw man of war in the field, neeer saw one Armey of men discomfited by an other, neuer
<pb facs="6"/>
heard the terrible Trumpet sound to the horrible &amp; cruel slaughter of men, neuer saw the Treasons of some, nor vnderstood the cowardnes of others, neuer saw how few they be that fight, nor how many ther are that run away. Finally (I say) as it is seemly for a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher and a learned man, to praise the profite of peace: <hi>Euen so it is in his mouth a thing vncomely, to prate of the perills' of warre.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>If this Phylosopher hath seene no one thing with his Eyes that hee hath spoken, but onely read them in sundry bookes, let him recount them to such as haue neyther seene nor read them:</hi> For, warlike feates are better learned in the bloudy fields of <hi>Affricke,</hi> then in the beautifull schooles of <hi>Greece.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thou knowest right well (king <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus)</hi> that for the space of thirty and sixe yeares, I had continuall and daungerous warres, as well in <hi>Italie</hi> as in <hi>Spayne:</hi> In which <hi>Fortune</hi> did not fauour mee (as is alwayes her manner to vse those, which by great stoutnesse and manhood, enterprise things high, and of much difficultie:) a witnesse whereof thou seest mee here, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my beard beganne to growe was serued: and now it is hoare, I my selfe beginne to serue.</p>
   <p>I sweare vnto thee by the God <hi>Mars</hi> (king <hi>Antiochus)</hi> that if any man did aske mee, how hee should vse and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himselfe in warre: I would not aunswer him one word. For they are things which are learned by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of deedes, and not by prating in words. Although Princes beginne warres by justice, and followe them <note place="margin">The end of warre both fickle &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant.</note> with wisedome, yet the ende standeth vppon fickle <hi>Fortune,</hi> and not of force, nor pollicie.</p>
   <p>Diuerse and sundrie other things <hi>Hannibal</hi> sayde vnto king <hi>Antiochus:</hi> who so bee desirous to see, let him reade in the <hi>Apothegmes</hi> of <hi>Plutarche:</hi> This example (Noble Prince) tendeth rather to this end, to condemne my boldnesse, and not to commend my enterprise, saying that the affayres of the common wealth bee as vnknowne to mee, as the dangers of the warres were to <hi>Phormio.</hi> Your Maiestie may iustly say vnto me, that I being a poor simple man (brought vp a great while in a rude Countrey) doe greatly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to describe, how so puissant a Prince as your Highnes ought to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne himselfe and his Realme: For of truth, the more ignorant a man is of the troubles and alterations of the world, the better he shall be counted in the sight of God.</p>
   <p>The estate of Princes is to haue great traines about them, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of religious men is to bee solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: for the seruant of God ought to be alwaies void from vaine thoughts, &amp; to be euer accompanied with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditations. The estate of Princes is alwayes vnquiet: but the state of the religious is to bee enclosed: For otherwise he aboue all others may be called an <hi>Apostata,</hi> That hath his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Cell, and his heart in the market place.</p>
   <p>To Princes it is necessary to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune and speake with all men, but for the religious it is not decent to be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersant with the world: For solitary men (if they do as they ought) should occupy their hands in trauel, their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in fasting, their tongue in prayer, and their heart in contemplation. The estate of Princes for the most part is employed to war, but the estate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious is to desire &amp; procure peace: For if the Prince would study to passe his bounds, and by battell to shed the bloud of his enemies: the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ought to shed teares, and pray to God for his sinnes. O that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Almighty God, as I know what my bounden duty is in my heart, so that hee would giue me grace to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish the same in my deedes.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Alas, when I ponder with my selfe the weightines of my matter, my Pen (through slouth and negligence is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fall out of my hand) and I halfe minded to leaue off mine enterprize. My intent is to speake against my selfe in this case. For, albeit men may know the affaires of Princes by experience: yet they shall not know how to speake nor write them but by science.</p>
   <p>Those which ought to counsell prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, those which ought to reforme the life of princes, and that ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct them, ought to haue a cleare iudgement, an vpright minde, their words aduisedly considered, their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine wholesome, and their life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out suspition.</p>
   <p>For, who so wil speake of high things, hauing no experience of them: is like vnto a blinde man, that would leade and teach him the way, which seeth better then hee himselfe. This is the sentence of <hi>Xenophon</hi> the great, which saieth. <hi>There is nothing harder in this life, then to know a wise man.</hi> And the <note place="margin">A speech of Xenophon.</note> reason which hee gaue was this.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>That a wise man cannot bee knowne, but by another wise man:</hi> wee may gather by this which <hi>Xenophon</hi> sayeth: <hi>That as one wise man cannot be knowne but by another wise man: so likewise it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site that he should be, or haue bin a Prince, which should write of the life of a Prince.</hi> For, hee that hath bin a marriner, and hath sailed but one yeare on the Sea: shall bee able to giue better counsell and aduise, then he that hath dwelled ten yeares in the hauen.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Xenophon</hi> wrote a booke touching the institution of princes, &amp; bringeth in <hi>Cambyses</hi> the king, how hee taught, and spake vnto king <hi>Cyrus</hi> his sonne. And he wrote an other book likewise <hi>of the Arte of Chiualry,</hi> and brought in king <hi>Philip,</hi> how he ought to teach his sonne <hi>Alexander</hi> to fight. For the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers thought that writing of no authoritie, that was not entituled and set foorth vnder the Names of those Princes, who had experience of that they wrote.</p>
   <p>Oh if an aged Prince would with his penne (if not with word of mouth) declare, what misfortunes haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened since the first time hee beganne to raigne: how disobedient his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects haue bin vnto him, what griefes his seruants haue wroght against him, what vnkindnesse his Friendes haue shewed him: what wiles his enemies haue vsed towards him, what daunger his person hath escaped: what jarres hath bin in his Pallace; what faultes they haue layde against him, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times they haue deceyued straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: Finally, what griefes hee hath had by day, and what sorrowfull sighs he hath fetched in the night: Truely I thinke (and in my thought I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing deceiued) that if a prince would declare vnto vs his whole life, and that hee would particularly shewe vs euery thing, wee would both wonder at that bodie which had so much suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: and also we would be offended with that heart which had so greatly dissembled.</p>
   <p>It is a troublesome thing, a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing, and an insolent and proud enterprise, for a man to take vpon him <hi>with a penne to gouerne the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and with a Prince to reason of his life.</hi> For in deed men are not perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to liue well by faire words, but by vertuous deedes. And therefore not <note place="margin">How dāge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a thing it is to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Princes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</note> without cause I say, that <hi>hee is not wise, but very arrogant, that dare presume vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asked to giue a Prince counsell.</hi> For prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in many things haue their mindes occupyed, and haughtely bent, and som of them also are affectionate, and whereas wee (peraduenture) thinke to haue them mercifull, wee finde them more angrie and heauie against vs.</p>
   <p>For, counsell doeth more harme then profite, if the giuer thereof be not very wise, and hee also which receyueth it
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>very pacient.</hi> I haue not bin a Prince, for to know the trauels of Princes, nor am as president to counsell Princes: and yet I was so bolde to compile this <hi>Booke:</hi> it was not vpon presumption to counsell a Prince, so much as by an humble sort to giue mine aduise. For to giue counsell, I confesse I haue no credite: but to giue them aduise, it suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth mee to bee a subiect.</p>
   <p>What the order is in that I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in this Booke: how profitable it is to all men, and how vnpleasaunt to no man: how wholsom and profound doctrine in it is contayned, and how the Historyes bee heerein applyed: I will not that my pen doe write, but they themselues shall judge, which shall read this worke.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>We see it oft come to passe that diuers Bookes doe loose their estimation: not for that they are not very good and excellent: but because the Authour hath been too pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous and vaine-glorious.</hi> For, in mine opinion, <hi>for a man to praise his owne wrytings much, is nothing else but to giue men occasion to speake euill both of him, and of his workes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, let no man thinke that I haue written this which is written without great aduisement and examination. I doe confesse, before <hi>the Redeemer of the whole world,</hi> that I haue consumed so many yeares to seeke what I should <note place="margin">The paines that the Authour tooke in this booke.</note> write, that these two yeares, one day hath scarcely escaped me, wherein my Pen hath not done his dutie, to write or correct in this worke. I confesse that I tooke great paines in writing it, for of truth it hath been written twice with mine owne hand, and thrice with another mans hand. I confesse I haue read and searched, in diuers and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie partes, manie good and straunge books, to the end I might finde good and pleasaunt doctrine: and besides that, I trauelled much to set and apply the Hystories to the purpose. For, it is an vnseemely thing to applie an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie without a purpose, I had great respect, in that I was not so briefe in my wrytings, that a man might note mee to bee obscure: nor yet in anie thing so long, that any man should slaunder mee with too much talke.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>For, all the excellencie of Wryting consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth, where many and goodly Sentences are declared in fewest and aptest words. For, oft times the long stile is loathsome and tedious both to the Hearers and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperour was in loue with a Ladie in <hi>Rome</hi> named <hi>Pompeia,</hi> the which in beautie (to his fantasie,) exceeded all others. In the ende part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with intreatie, partly with Money <note place="margin">The inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate loue betweene Nero and Pompeia.</note> and presents, he obtained of her that hee desired. For, in this case of loue, where prayers and importunities bee paciently heard, resistance doth lacke.</p>
   <p>The inordinate loue that <hi>Nero</hi> bare to <hi>Pompeia,</hi> proceeded of the yealow haires she had: which were of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Amber, and in praise of her he compiled diuers, and sundry songs in <hi>Heroicall-Meeter:</hi> and with an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment sang them himselfe in her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Nero</hi> was a sage Prince, wise, and excellently well learned in the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue, and also a <hi>good Musitian:</hi> yet <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his book of the jests of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble women (to declare the vanitie and lightnes of <hi>Nero)</hi> reciteth this history: and describing <hi>Pompeia,</hi> that her bodie was small, her fingers long, her mouth proper, her eyelids thin, her nose som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what sharpe, her teeth small, her lips red, her necke white, her fore-head broad, and finally, her eyes great, and rowling, her brest large &amp; well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: What think you would <hi>Nero</hi> haue done, if hee had so affectionately set his fantasie vpon al other her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful properties, since that for the loue only of her yellow locks, he was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both of his wisdom, &amp; also senses. <hi>For vaine &amp; light men loue commonly not</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>that which reason commandeth but that which their appetite desireth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The loue of the Emperour increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with folly so much, that not onely he counted seuerally al the haires that <note place="margin">The folly of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note> his louer <hi>Pompeia</hi> had on her head, but also gaue to euery hayre a proper name, and in prayse of euery one of them made a song, insomuch that this effeminate Prince spent more time in banqueting and playing with his louer <hi>Pompeia,</hi> then he did to reform and amend the faults of the common wealth: yea, his folly so much surmoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all reason, that he commaunded a combe of golde to bee made, and therewith hee himselfe combed her yellow locks. And if it chaunced that any one hayre in combing fell off, hee by and by caused it to be set in golde, offered it vp in the Temple to the Goddesse <hi>Iuno:</hi> For it was an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent custome among the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that the thinges which they entirely lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (whether it were good or euill) should bee offered vp to their gods. And when it was once knowne that <hi>Nero</hi> was so in loue with those haires of <hi>Pompeia</hi> which were of the color of amber, all the Ladies endeauoured themselues, not onely to make artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially theyr hayre of that colour, but also to weare their garments and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther attires of the same colour, in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that both men and women did vse collers of amber, brooches, and ringes set with amber, and all their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iewels were of amber. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes it hath beene seene, and euer shall be, that those things whereunto the Prince is most addicted, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple follow, and aboue all other couet the same.</p>
   <p>Before this Emperour <hi>Nero</hi> plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this light part in <hi>Rome,</hi> the amber stones was had in little estimation, &amp; after that hee set so much by it, there was no precious stone in Rome, so much esteemed: Yea, and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, the Marchant gained nothing so much (whether it were in golde or silke) as he did in the amber stones, nor brought any kind of marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize to Rome more precious, or more vendible then that was. I do maruell at this vanitie, foras-much as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the world do loue, desire, and labour, more to follow the straunge follie of another: then to furnish and supplie their owne proper necessitie.</p>
   <p>Therefore returning againe to my purpose, (most excellent Prince,) by this example you may coniecture what I would say, that is, that if this writing were accepted vnto Princes, I am assured it would be refused of no man: And if any man would slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously talke of it, hee durst not, remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that your Maiesty hath recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it: For those things which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces take to their custody, wee are bound to defend, and it is not lawfull for vs to diminish their credite.</p>
   <p>Suppose that this my worke were not so profound as it might be of this matter, nor with such eloquence set out as many other bookes are: yet I dare bee bolde to say, that the Prince shall take more profit by reading of this worke, then <hi>Nero</hi> did by his loue <hi>Pompeia:</hi> For in the end by reading and studying good bookes, men turn and become sage and wise, and by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ill company, they are counted fooles and vitious.</p>
   <p>My meaning is not, nor I am not so importunate and vnreasonable, to perswade Princes that they should so fauour my doctrine, that it should be in like estimation now in these parts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a the amber was there in Rome. But that onely which I require and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund is, that the time which <hi>Nero</hi> spent in singing and telling the hayres of his loue <hi>Pompeia:</hi> should now bee employed to redresse the wrongs &amp; faults of the common wealth. For the noble and worthy Prince ought
<pb facs="8"/>
to employ the least part of the day in the recreation of his person: After hee hath giuen audience to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours, to the Ambassadours, to the great Lords and Prelates, to the rich and poore, to his own countrey men &amp; strangers, and after that he be com into his Priuy Chamber, then my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire is, that hee would reade this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, or som other better then this: for in Princes chambers oftentimes those of the Priuie Chamber, and other their familiars lose great time in reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vaine and trifling matters, and of small profit, the which might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bee spent in reading some good good booke.</p>
   <p>In all worldly affayres that wee do, and in all our bookes which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pile, it is a great matter to bee fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: <hi>For to a man that fortune doth not fauour, diligence without doubt can little auaile.</hi> Admit that fortune were against mee, in that this my worke should bee acceptable vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, without comparison it should be a great griefe and dishonour vnto mee to tel you what should be good to reade for your pastime, if on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part you would not profite by my counsell and aduise: For my mind was not onely to make this booke, to the end Princes should reade it for a pastime, but to that end (in recreating themselues) sometimes they might thereby also take profit.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Aulus Gelius</hi> in the 12. Chapter of his third booke entituled <hi>De nocte at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> sayde that amongst all the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers which the diuine <hi>Plato</hi> had, one <note place="margin">A commen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation of Demosthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher.</note> was named <hi>Demostenes,</hi> a man among the Greekes most highly esteemed, &amp; of the Romanes greatly desired. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause hee was in his liuing seuere, and in his tongue and doctrine a very Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre. If <hi>Demosthenes</hi> had come in the time of <hi>Phalaris</hi> the tyrant, when <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> was peopled with tirants, and that hee had not beene in <hi>Platoes</hi> time, when it was replenished with Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers, truely <hi>Demosthenes</hi> had been as cleare a lanterne in <hi>Asia,</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> the great was in <hi>Europe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Great good hap hath a notable man to bee born in one age, more then in another.</hi>
      <note place="margin">How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a thing it is to liue vnder a vertuous prince.</note>
      <hi>I meane, that if a valiant Knight come in the time of a couragious and stout Prince such a one truly shall bee esteemed and set in great authority. But if hee come in the time of an other effeminate and couetous Prince, bee shall not bee regarded at all: For hee will rather e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme one that wel augment his treasure at home, then him that can vanquish his enemies abroad.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>So likewise it chanceth to wise and vertuous men, which if they come in the time of vertuous and learned prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are esteemed and honoured: but if they come in time of vaine and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Princes, they make small ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them. For it is an auncient custom among vanities children, not to honour him which to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth is most profitable: but him which to the Prince is most ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.</p>
   <p>The end why this is spoken (Most puissant Prince) is because the two renowmed Philosophers were in <hi>Greece</hi> both at one time: and because the diuine Philosopher <hi>Plato</hi> was so much esteemed and made of, they did not greatly esteeme the Philosopher <hi>Demosthenes:</hi> For the eminent &amp; high renowne of one alone, diminisheth the fame and estimation (among the people) of many. Although <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sthenes</hi> was such a one indeed as wee haue sayde, that is to witte, eloquent of tongue, ready of memory, sharpe and quicke of witte, in liuing seuere, sure and profitable in giuing of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, in renowne excellent, in yeares very auncient, and in Philosophy a man right well learned: yet hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused not to goe to the Schooles of <hi>Plato</hi> to heare morall Philosophie. He
<pb facs="8"/>
that shall reade this thing or heare it, ought not to maruel, but to follow it, and to profit likewise in the same, that is to vnderstand, that one Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher learned of another, and one wise man suffred himself to be taught of another: <hi>For knowledge is of such a quality, that the more a man knoweth, dayly there encreaseth in him a desire to know more. All things of this life (after they haue beene tasted and possessed) cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man, wearieth and troubleth him, true science onely excepted, which neuer doth cloy, weary, nor trouble them.</hi> And if it happen wee weary any, it is but the eyes, which are wearied with loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and reading: and not the spirite with seeling and tasting.</p>
   <p>Many Lords, and my familiar friends doe aske mee how it is possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble I should liue with so much study? And I also demaund of them, how it is possible they should liue in such continuall idlenes? For considering the prouocation and assaults of the flesh, the daungers of the world, the temptations of the deuil, the treasons of enemies, &amp; importunity of friends: what hart can suffer so great and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall trauell, but onely in reading and comforting himselfe in bookes? Truely a man ought to haue more compassion of a simple ignorant man then of a poore man: For thereis no greater pouerty vnto a man then for to lacke wisedom, whereby he should know how to gouerne himselfe.</p>
   <p>Therefore following our matter, the case was such, one day <hi>Demosthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> (going to the schoole of <hi>Plato)</hi> saw in the market place of <hi>Athens</hi> a great assembly of people, which were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Philosopher newly come vnto that place: and hee spake not this without a cause, that there was a great company of people assembled. For that naturally the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are desirous to heare new and strange things.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Demosthenes</hi> asked what Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher hee was, after whom so many people went? and when it was aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered him that it was <hi>Calistratus</hi> the Philosopher, a man which in eloquēce was very sweete and pleasant: hee determined to stay and heare him, to the end hee would know, whether it were true or vaine that the people tolde him: For oftentimes it hapneth that among the people some get thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues great fame, more by fauor, then by good learning.</p>
   <p>The difference betwixt the diuine <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Philosopher <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Calistratus</hi> was, in that <hi>Plato</hi> was exceedingly wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the other very eloquent: and thus it came to passe, that in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing they followed <hi>Plato,</hi> and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence of speech they did imitate <hi>Calistratus.</hi> For, there are diuers men sufficiently well learned, which haue profound doctrine, but they haue no way nor meanes to teach it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Demosthenes</hi> hearing <hi>Calistratus</hi> but once, was so farre in loue with his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that he neuer after heard <hi>Plato:</hi> nor entered into his Schoole, for to harken to any of his lectures.</p>
   <p>At which newes diuers of the Sages and Wise men of <hi>Grecia</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled much, seeing that the tongue of a man was of such power, that it had put all their doctrine vnto si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
   <p>Although I apply not this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, I doubt not but that your Maiesty vnderstandeth to what ende I haue declared it.</p>
   <p>And moreouer I say, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Princes and great Lordes haue in their Chambers Bookes so well corrected, and men in their Courts so well learned, that they may worthily keepe the estimation which <hi>Plato</hi> had in his Schoole: yet in this case it should not displease me
<pb facs="9"/>
that the difference that was between <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Calistratus,</hi> should bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Princes and this Booke. God forbid, that by this saying men should thinke, I meane to disswade Princes from the company of the sage men, or from reading of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke but this; for in so doing, <hi>Plato</hi> should bee reiected which was diuine, and <hi>Calistratus</hi> embraced which was more worldly. But my desire is, that sometimes they would vse to reade this booke a little, for it may chaunce they shall finde some wholesome counsell therein, which at one time or other may profite them in their affayres: <hi>For the good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Prince ought to graffe in their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory the wise sayings which they reade, and forget the cankred iniuries and wrongs which are done them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I do not speake it without a cause, that hee that readeth this my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, shall finde in it some profitable counsell: For all that which hath bin written in it, hath beene euery word and sentence with great diligence so well wayed and corrected, as if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in onely consisted the effect of the whole worke.</p>
   <p>The greatest griefe that learned men seele in their writing is, to thinke that if there bee many that view their doings to take profite thereby, they shall perceyue that there are as many more which occupie their tongues in the slaunder and disprayse thereof. In publishing this my worke, I haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued the manner of them that plant a new garden, wherein they set Roses which giue a pleasant sauour to the nose, they make faire greene plattes to delight the eyes, they graft fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trees to bee gathered with the hands; but in the end as I am a man: so haue I written it for men, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently as a man I may haue erred: for there is not at this day so perfect a painter, but another will presume to amend his worke.</p>
   <p>Those which diligently will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour themselues to reade this booke, shall finde in it very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counsels, very liuely lawes, good reasons, notable sayings, sentences very profound, worthy examples, and histories very ancient: For to say the truth, I had a respect in that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was auncient, and the Stile new. And albeit your Maiesty bee the greatest Prince of all Princes, and I the least of all your Subiects, you ought not for my base condition to disdaine to cast your eyes vpon this booke, nor to thinke scorne to put that thing in proofe which seemeth good. For a good letter ought to be nothing the lesse esteemed, although it be written with an euill pen.</p>
   <p>I haue sayde, and will say, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and great Lords, the stouter, the richer, and the greater of renowme they bee, the greater need they haue of all men of good knowledge about them, to counsell them in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, and of good bookes which they may reade: and this they ought to doe as well in prosperity, as in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity, to the end that their affayres in time conuenient, may be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and redressed: For otherwise they should haue time to repent, but no leasure to amend.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plinie, Marcus Varro, Strabo,</hi> and <hi>Macrobius,</hi> which were Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, <note place="margin">Diuers Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers at controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, what things were most au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentike.</note> no lesse graue then true, were at great controuersie, improouing what things were most authenticke in a common weale, and at what time they were of all men accepted.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Seneca</hi> in an Epistle hee wrote to <hi>Lucullus,</hi> praysed without ceasing the Common wealth of the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> in the which (with much ado) they bent themselues altogether to keepe one selfe thing, and after they had ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon agreede, they kept and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it inuiolably.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
The diuine <hi>Plato</hi> in the sixt booke entituled <hi>De Legibus</hi> ordained and commanded, that if any Cittizen did inuent any new thing, which neuer before was read, nor heard of, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentour thereof should first practise the same for the space of ten yeares in his own house, before it was brought into the Common-wealth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it should bee published vnto the people, to the end, if the inuention were good, it should be profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: and if it were nought, that then the daunger and hurt thereof should light onely on him.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Apothegmes</hi> sayeth, that <hi>Lycurgus</hi> vpon grieuous penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties did prohibite, that none should bee so hardy in his Common wealth to goe wandring into strange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, nor that hee should be so hardy to admit any strangers to come into his house: and the cause why this law was made, was to the end strangers should not bring into their houses things strange, and not accustomed in their Common wealth, and that they trauelling through strange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, should not learne new Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes.</p>
   <p>The presumption of men now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes is so great, and the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people so small, that what soeuer a man can speake, he speaketh, what so euer he can inuent he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, what hee would hee doth write, and it is no maruell, for there is no man that wil speak against them. Nor the common people in this case are so light, that amongst them you may dayly see new deuises, and whether it hurt or profit the Common wealth they force not.</p>
   <p>If there came at this day a vaine man amongst the people, which was neuer seene nor heard of before, if hee bee any thing subtill: I aske you but this question: Shall it not bee easie for him to speake, and inuent what hee listeth, to set forth what he pleaseth, to perswade that which to him seemeth good, and all his say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be beleeued? truly it is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing, and no lesse slaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that one should be sufficient to peruert the senses and iudgements of all, and all not able to represse the lightnesse and vanity of one. Things <note place="margin">New things and vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed ought not to be vsed.</note> that are new, and not accustomed, neyther Princes ought to allow, nor yet the people to vse: For a newe thing ought no lesse to bee examined and considered, before it be brought into the cōmon wealth, then the great doubts which arise in mens mindes. <hi>Ruffinus</hi> in the Prologue of his secōd Booke of his Apologie reprooueth greatly the Egyptians because they were too full of deuises, and blamed much the <hi>Grecians,</hi> because they were too curious in speaking fine wordes: and aboue all other hee greatly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Romanes; for that they were very hard of beleefe, and that they scarcely alwayes credited the sayings of the Greekes, and because they were discreete in admitting the inuentions of the Egyptians.</p>
   <p>The Author hath reason to prayse the one, and disprayse the other. For it proceedeth of a light iudgement, to credit all the thinges that a man heareth, and to doe all that he seeth.</p>
   <p>Returning therefore now to our matter. <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> sayde, that there were fiue things in the Worlde very hard to bring in, whereof none (after they were commonly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) were euer lost or forgotten, for euen as things vainely begunne, are easily left of: so thinges with great feare accepted, are with much care and diligence to bee kept and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued.</p>
   <p>The first thing that chiefly throgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the World was accepted, was all men for to liue together: that is for to say, that they should
<pb facs="10"/>
make places, Towns, Villages, Citties and Common wealthes. For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the saying of <hi>Plato,</hi> the first &amp; best inuentors of the common-wealth were the Antes, which (according to to the experience wee see) do liue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, trauell together, do go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; also for the winter they make prouision together: and furthermore <note place="margin">The proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Ants.</note> none of these Antes doe giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to any priuate thing, but all theirs is brought into their common wealth.</p>
   <p>It is a maruellous thing to behold the common wealth of the ants, how nearely they trim their hils, to behold how they sweepe away the graine, when it is wette, and how they drye it when they feele any moysture, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how they come from their work and how the one doth not hurt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and to behold also how they do reioyce the one in the others trauell, and that which is to our greatest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion is, that if it comes so to passe, 50000. Ants wil liue in a litle hillocke together, and two men onely cannot liue in peace and concord in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
   <p>Would to God the wisedome of men were so great to keep themselus as the prudence of the ants is to liue: When the world came to a certaine age, and mens wits waxed more fine, then tirants sprang vp which oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the poore, theeues that robbed the rich, rebels that robbed the quiet, murderers that slew the patient, the idle that eate the swet of other mens browes: all the which things consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by them which were vertuous: they agreed to assemble and liue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that thereby they might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the good, and withstand the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. <hi>Macrobius</hi> affirmeth this in the second booke of <hi>Scipions</hi> dreame, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That couetousnes ond auarice was the greatest cause why men inuented the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. Plinie</hi> in the seuenth booke 56. Chapter sayth, the first that made small assemblies were the Athenians; and the first that built great Cities, were the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The second thing that was accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted throughout al the world, were the letters which wee read, whereby wee take profite in writing. According whereunto <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> sayth, the Egyptians prayse themselues and say, that they did inuent them, and the Assyrians affirme the contrary, and sweare, that they were shewed first of all amongst them.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> in the 7. booke sayth, that in the first age, there was in the alphabet no more then 16. letters, &amp; that great <note place="margin">A descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Alphabet.</note>
      <hi>Palamedes</hi> at the siege of <hi>Troy,</hi> ladded other 4. and <hi>Aristotle</hi> saith, that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the beginning, there were found 18. letters. And that afterwards <hi>Palamedes</hi> did add but 2. and so there were 20. and that the Philosopher <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picarmus</hi> did adde other 2. which were 22. it is no great matter, whether the Egyptians or the Assyrians first foūd the letters. But I say and affirme, that it was a thing necessary for a common wealth, and also for the encrease of mans knowledge: For if wee had wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted letters and writings, wee could haue had no knowledge of the time past, nor yet our posterity could haue bin aduertised what was done in our daies.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the second booke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>De viris illustribus,</hi> and <hi>Pliny</hi> in the seuenth booke, and 56. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, doe greatly praise <hi>Pirotas,</hi> because hee first found the fire in a flint stone.</p>
   <p>They greatly commended <hi>Prothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> because he inuented barneyes, and they highly extolled <hi>Panthasuea,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause she inuented the hatchet. They praysed <hi>Citheus,</hi> because hee inuented the bowe, and the arrowes, they greatly praysed <hi>Phenisius,</hi> because hee inuented the Crossebow, and the sling.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
They highly praised the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> because they inuented the Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, the Speare, and the Sworde, and moreouer, they commende those of <hi>Thessalie,</hi> because they inuented the combat on hors-back: and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend those of <hi>Affrike,</hi> because they inuented the fight by Sea. But I doe praise, and continually will magnifie, not those which found the <hi>Art of figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting:</hi> and inuented weapons to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure warres, for to kill his neighbour: but those which found <hi>Letters,</hi> for to learne <hi>Science,</hi> and to make peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two Princes.</p>
   <p>What difference there is <hi>to wet the Penne with inke and to paint the Speare with bloud: to be enuironed with bookes, or to be laden with weapons.</hi> To studie <hi>how euery man ought to liue, or else to goe priuily and robbe in the Warres, and to kill his Neighbour.</hi> There is none of so vaine a iudgement, but will praise more the <hi>Speculation of the Sciences,</hi> then the practise of the warres. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that in the ende, he that learneth sciences, learneth nought else but how he and others ought to liue. And he <hi>that learneth warlike feats, learneth none other thing, then how to slay his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and to destroy others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The third thing, that equally of all was accepted, were lawes. For admit that all men now liued together in common, if they would not be subiect one to another, there would contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on arise amongst them, for that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the saying of <hi>Plato,</hi> That <hi>there is no greater token of the destruction of a</hi>
      <note place="margin">A worthy sentence of Plato:</note>
      <hi>Common-weale, then when many rulers are chosen therein.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> in his seuenth booke, 56. chap: sayth, that a Queene called <hi>Ceres,</hi> was the first that taught them to sowe in the fields, to grinde in Milles, to paste and bake in Ouens, and also shee was the first that taught the people to liue according to the Law. And by the meanes of these things our Fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers called her a Goddesse.</p>
   <p>Since the time we neuer haue seene heard, nor read of any realme, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nation (as well strange as barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous) whatsoeuer they were, but haue had Lawes, whereby the good were fauoured: and also institutions of grieuous paines, wherewith the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked were punished.</p>
   <p>Although truely I had rather, and it were better, that the good should loue reason: then feare the law. I speake of those which leaue to doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill workes, for feare onely of falling into the punishments appoynted for euill doers. For, although men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue that which they do for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, yet God condemaeth that which they desire.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Seneca</hi> in an epistle hee wrote vnto his friende <hi>Lucille,</hi> saide these wordes, Thou writest, vnto mee <hi>Lucille,</hi> that those of <hi>Scicile,</hi> haue carryed a great quantitie of Corne into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and into <hi>Affrike,</hi> the which was forbidden by a <hi>Romaine</hi> law, and therefore they haue deserued most grieuous punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
   <p>Now because thou art vertuous, <hi>Thou mayest teache mee to doe well: and I that am olde, will teach thee to say well:</hi> and this is, because that amongst wise and vertuous men it is enough to say, that the Law commaundeth, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and suffereth this thing, but in as much as it is agreeing with reason. For, the crowne of the good, is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the scourge of the wicked, is the law.</p>
   <p>The fourth thing that commonly through the worlde amongst all men was accepted, was the Barbers. And let no man take this thing in mockery. For, if they doe reade <hi>Plinie,</hi> in the 59. chapter, and the seuenth booke, there they shall finde for a Trueth, that in those former times, the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> were in <hi>Rome</hi> 454. yeares, without eyther powling or shauing
<pb facs="11"/>
the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ires off the bearde of anie man.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> said, that <hi>Publius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> was the first that brought the barbers from <hi>Scicilie</hi> to <hi>Rome:</hi> But admit it were so or otherwise: yet notwithstanding, there was a great contention among the <hi>Romaines.</hi> For, they sayd, they thought it a rash thing for a man to commit his life vnto the curtesie of another.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Dyonisius</hi> the <hi>Syracusian</hi> neuer tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted his Beard with any barbor, but when his Daughters were very little, they clipped his beard with sisers: but after they became great, hee would not put his trust in them, to trimme his beard, but hee himselfe did burne it with the shales of nuttes.</p>
   <p>This <hi>Dyonisius Syracusan,</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded why hee would not trust any Barbours with his beard? He aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, <hi>Because I know that there bee some which will giue more to the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to take away my life, then I will giue to trimme my beard.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> in the seuenth booke sayeth, that the great <hi>Scipio</hi> called <hi>Affrican,</hi> and the Emperour <hi>Augustus,</hi> were the first that caused them in <hi>Rome</hi> to shaue their beards. And I thinke the end why <hi>Plinie</hi> spake these things, was to exalt these two Princes, which had as great courage to suffer the rasours to touch their throats: as the one for to fight against <hi>Hanniball</hi> in <hi>Affricke,</hi> and the other, against <hi>Sextus Pompeius</hi> in <hi>Scicilie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The fifte thing which commonly throgh the world was accepted, were the Dyalls and clockes which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> wanted a long time. For as <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> and <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> say, the <hi>Romaines</hi> were without clockes in <hi>Rome,</hi> for the space of 595. yeares.</p>
   <p>The curious Hystoriographers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> three manner of dyalls that were in old time: that is to say, <hi>Dyalls of the houres, Dyalls of the Sunne, and Dyalls of the Water.</hi> The dyall of the Sunne <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neximenides Millesius</hi> inuented: who was great <hi>Animandraes</hi> scholler. The dyall of the water <hi>Scipio Nasica</hi> inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; the dyall of houres, one of the Schollers of <hi>Thales</hi> the phylosopher inuented.</p>
   <p>Now of all these Antiquities, which were brought into <hi>Rome,</hi> none of them were so acceptable to the <hi>Romaines,</hi> as the Dyalls were, whereby they measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the day by the houre. For, before they could not say, we will rise at seuen of the clocke, wee will dine at ten, we will see one the other at twelue: at one wee will doe that wee ought to doe.</p>
   <p>But before they sayde, after the Sunne is vp wee wil doe such a thing, and before it goe downe, wee will do that wee ought to doe.</p>
   <p>The occasion of declaring vnto you these fiue antiquities in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble, was to no other entent, but to call my Booke the <hi>Diall of Princes.</hi> The name of the Booke beeing new (as it is) may make the learning that is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in greatly to be esteemed. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that I should bee so bolde to say, they haue been so long time in <hi>Spaine</hi> without dayes of learning, as they were in <hi>Rome</hi> without the Diall of the Sunne, the water, and of the houres: For that in Spaine haue beene alwaies <note place="margin">Spayne cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for learned mē, &amp; expert in the warres.</note> men well learned in Sciences, and very expert in the warres. By great reason, and of greater occasion, the Princes ought to bee commended, the knights, the people, their wits, and the fertility of their Countrey: but yet to all these goodnesse, I haue seen many vnlearned bookes in Spaine, which as broken Dials deserue to bee cast into the fire to bee forged anew. I doe not speake it without a cause, that many bookes deserue to bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and burnt: For there are so many that without shame and honesty doe set forth bookes of loue of the world, at this day as boldlie, as if they taught them to despise and speake euill of the world.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
It is pitty to see how many dayes and nights be consumed in reading vaine bookes (that is to say) <hi>Orson</hi> and <hi>Valentine,</hi> the Court of <hi>Venus,</hi> and the foure sonnes of <hi>Amon,</hi> and diuers other vaine bookes, by whose doctrine I dare boldly say, they passe not the time but in perdition: for they learne not how they ought to flye vice, but rather what way they may with more pleasure embrace it.</p>
   <p>This Diall of Princes is not of sand, nor of the Sunne, nor of the houres, nor of the water, but it is the Diall of Life. For the other Dials serue to know what houre it is in the night, and what houre it is of the day: but this sheweth and teacheth vs, how wee ought to occupie our minds, and how to order our life.</p>
   <p>The property of other Dials is, to order things publike, but the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ooke of the Dyall of Princes.</note> of this dyal of Princes is, to teach vs how to occupie our selues euerie houre, and how to amend our life eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment.</p>
   <p>It little auaileth to keepe the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls well, and to see thy Subiects dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely without any order, to range in routes, and dayly rayse debate and contention among themselues.</p>
   <trailer>The End of the generall Prologue.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>