<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Cooke to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120622_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16293</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3204</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120622</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Cooke to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pronostication for diuers yeares : ryght vtyle and profytable to al sortes of people, wherin is declared what persons hath mooste and leaste dominacions ouer the starres and elementes, whereby the iudgementes of the astrologiens be scarsely true, geuynge together great consolation to those who muche fear the constellations. Also of the fourth and laste monarchie, the whiche Charles the. v. ryghte victorious Emperoure of the Romaynes, and Edwarde the. vi. mooste noble Emperoure of great Bryttayne, by the grace of God, gouerneth, comprehendynge also brieflye some words of the last age of the world, gathered together by Master Arnold Bogarde doctour in medecyne, resident in Bruxels and translated into Englysh oute of Frenche by Iohn Coke, clarcke of the Recognysances, or vulgerly called clark of the Statutes</title>
                 <author>Bogaert, Arnould</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Awen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Iohn Cooke to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N semblable manner, as people beynge free of infir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mities, customably are not desyrous of Phisicke, so those as lyue prosperously seke scarcely remedies in tribulation. But if it be discretion among world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people, in peace tyme to be in a redines for the battayle, and to exercyse ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours before the daunger approche, it is no lesse necessary for all Christians, beyng borne to haue no peace, but a dayly conflycte whyles they abi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in this fleshe, to preuent in prosperitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> suffre afflictions, and to put in a redines w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>pon agaynst aduersitie, considerynge we be subiecte to aduersitie, troubles, persecutions, miseries, in firmities, and death. And albeit in holy scripture haboundaunce is left to vs of such furniture, yet our slouth and negligence is suche, that we reste peaceably, as if we were in assuraunce, we take no sorow, as thoughe we were cleare withoute daunger, and not mynded to searche and prouyde municions of warre for vs defensible, whiche causeth vs in tyme of affliction or death (sodenly approchynge) for the more parte to be founde slomberynge, naked, and out of a redines, &amp; thus withoute resistence constrayned shamefullye to yelde our selues vnto dispayre. Agaynst the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che stormes, let vs fortifye our selues with holy scripture, and walke in the commaundementes of God, that by the grace of his holy spirite, we may he conforted in suche wyse in our couraiges
<pb facs="2"/>
that we may feare no daungers, perylles, nor yet death. Although thende of the worlde approche at hande, as by this moost necessarye and godlye pronostication, set forth by the worshypful clark maister Arnolde Bogarde, doctour of Phisicke resident in Bruxelles maye appeare, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nostication beyng in Latyn, Frenche, &amp; Dutche was delyuered vnto me by a louynge frende of myne, to be translated out of Frenche in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Englysh, whiche I haue gladlye done. Desyringe the gentle reader to accepte my good wyll. And in the translation, though I haue not curiously folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the letter, I haue very litle or nothynge varied from the mynde of the aucthour.</p>
   <closer>Fare you well. (?)</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>