<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT OF THE BOOKE: ENTITVLED, THE FA∣uoured Courtyer: wherein the Authour sheweth the in∣tent of his worke; exhorting all men to studie good and vertuous Books, vtterly reiecting all Fables, &amp; vaine trifling storyes, of small doctrine &amp; erudition.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120712_Fr2_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12430</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT OF THE BOOKE: ENTITVLED, THE FA∣uoured Courtyer: wherein the Authour sheweth the in∣tent of his worke; exhorting all men to studie good and vertuous Books, vtterly reiecting all Fables, &amp; vaine trifling storyes, of small doctrine &amp; erudition.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archontorologion, or The diall of princes : containing the golden and famous booke of Marcus Aurelius, sometime Emperour of Rome. Declaring what excellcncy [sic] consisteth in a prince that is a good Christian: and what euils attend on him that is a cruell tirant. Written b the Reuerend Father in God, Don Antonio of Gueuara, Lord Bishop of Guadix; preacher and chronicler to the late mighty Emperour Charles the fift. First translated out of French by Thomas North, sonne to Sir Edward North, Lord North of Kirthling: and lately reperused, and corrected from many grosse imperfections. With addition of a fourth booke, stiled by the name of The fauoured courtier</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 331, pages 933, 341-424, 429-542, that is 560, 2, 561-654, 659-768, that is 766 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <head>THE ARGVMENT OF <hi>THE BOOKE: ENTITVLED, THE FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured Courtyer: wherein the Authour sheweth the</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his worke; exhorting all men to studie good <hi>and vertuous Books, vtterly reiecting all Fables, &amp; vaine trifling storyes, of small doctrine &amp; erudition.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ʋlus Gellius,</hi> in <hi>his Booke De noctibus Atticis</hi> saith: That after the death of the great Poet <hi>Homer, 7-famous cities of Grece</hi> were in great controuersie, one with the other: each one of them affirming that by reason the bones of the saide <hi>Poet</hi> was theirs, and only appertained <note place="margin">Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rned men greatly honored in times past.</note> to them, all 7. taking their oaths, that he was not only borne, but also nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed &amp; broght vp in euery one of thē. And this they did: <hi>(Supposing that they neuer had so great honor in any thing, but that this was far greater to haue educated so Excellent and rare a Man as hee was. Euripides</hi> also <hi>the phylosopher</hi> born and broght vp in <hi>Athens:</hi> trauelling in the realm of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> was suddēly struc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with death, which woful newes no soner came to the <hi>Athenians</hi> eares (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for a truth) but with all expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they dispatched <hi>an honorable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>basie:</hi> only to intreat the <hi>Lacedemoniās to be contented to deliuer them the bones of the said phylosopher: protesting to them that if they wold frankly grant them, they would regratifie that pleasure done them: and if they would denie them, they should assure themselues they would come and fetch them with the sword in hand.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>K: <hi>Demetrius</hi> helde <hi>Rhodes</hi> besieged long time (which at length he won, by force of arms) &amp; the <hi>Rhodiās</hi> being so stubborn that they wold not yeeld by composition, nor trust to his princely clemencie, hee cōmanded to strike off al the <hi>Rhodians</hi> heads, &amp; to rase the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the hard foundations. But when he was let vnderstand, that there was euen then in the Cittie <hi>Prothogenes,</hi> a Phylosopher and Paynter, and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting least in executing others, hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so vnknowne, might bee put to the sword, reuoked his cruell sentence &amp; gaue straight commandement forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they should cease to spoile and deface the towne further, and also to stay the slaughter of the rest of the <hi>Rhodians.</hi> The diuine <hi>Plato</hi> beeing in <hi>Athens,</hi> aduertised that in the city of <hi>Damasco,</hi> in the realme of <hi>Palestine,</hi> were certaine bookes of great antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which a Philosopher borne of that Country left behind him there: when he vnderstood it to be true, went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediately, led with the great desire he had to see them, &amp; purposely
<pb n="576" facs="308"/>
(if they did like him) afterwards to buy them. And when hee saw that neyther at his suit, nor at the requests of others he could obtaine them, but that he must buy thē at a great price.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plato</hi> went and solde all his patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to recouer them: and his owne not being sufficient, hee was faine to borrow vpon interest of the commō Treasury to helpe him: so that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding he was so profound and rare a Philosopher (as indeed he was) yet he would sell all that small substāce hee had onely to see (as hee thought some prety new thing more of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophy As <hi>Ptolomeus Philadelphus</hi> king of <hi>Egypt,</hi> not contened to bee so wise in al sciences as he was, nor to haue in, his Library 8000. bookes as hee had nor to study at the least 4. houres in the day, nor ordinarily to dispute at his meales with Philosophers, sent neuerthelesse an Ambassage of Noble men to the Hebrewes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire them they would be contented to send him some of the best learned and wisest men amongst them, to teach him the Hebrew tongue, and to reade to him the books of their Laws.</p>
   <p>When <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was borne, his father King <hi>Philip</hi> wrote a notable letter immediately to <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> among other matters hee wrote, there were these, I let thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. <note place="margin">The letter of K. Phili, to Aristol at the birth of his sonne Alexander.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>O greatest Philosopher</hi> Aristotle <hi>(if thou knowest it not) that</hi> Olimpius <hi>my wife is brought to bedde of a sonne, for which incessantly I giue the Gods immortall thankes, not so much that I haue a sonne, as for that they haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him mee in thy time. For I am as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assured hee shall profite more with the doctrine thou shalt teach him, then he shall preuayle with the Kingdomes I shall leaue him after me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now by the examples aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, and by many more wee could alledge, wee may easily consider with what reuerence and honour the auncient Kings vsed the learned and vertuous men in their time. And wee may also more plainely see it, sith then they helde in greater price and esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation the bones of a dead Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, then they doe now the doctrine of the best learned of our time. And not without iust occasion did these famous and heroycall Princes ioy to haue at home in their houses, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with them in the field, such wise and learned men, whilest they liued, and after they were dead to honour, their bones and carcases, and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, they erred not a a iot: For whosoeuer accompanieth continuall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with graue and wise men, enioyeth this benefit and priuiledge before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that he shall neuer bee counted ignorant of any: therfore continuing stil our first purpose, let vs say, that whosoeuer will professe the company <note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creweth by company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with wise men.</note> of sober &amp; wise men, it cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be, but he must maruellously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by their cōpany: for being in their company, they wil put al vain and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest thoughts from him, they will teach him to subdue &amp; resist al sudden passions &amp; motions moued of choler: by thē they shal win good friends, and learn also neuer to be troublesom, or enemy to any, they will make him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake all sinne &amp; vice, declaring to him what good works he shall follow, and what hee shall most flye and eschew: they will let him vnderstand how hee shall humble and behaue himselfe, in prosperity, and they will also comfort him in his aduersity, to keep him from all sorrow and despaire. For though a man be neuer so carefull and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, yet hath he hath always need of the councell of another in his affaires: if therefore such a person haue not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him good, vertuous, &amp; sage men, how can it otherwise bee, but that he must stūble oft, and fall down right on his face, hauing no man to aid or help him.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="577" facs="308"/>
      <hi>Paulus Dyaconus</hi> sayth, that albeit the <hi>Affricanes</hi> were wilde and brutish people, yet had they notwithstanding a law amongst them, that the senators amongst them, could chuse no other Senator, if at the Election there were not present a philosopher.</p>
   <p>So it hapned on a day amongst the rest, that of manie phylosophers they had in <hi>Carthage,</hi> amongst them there was one named <hi>Apolonius,</hi> who ruled for the space of 62. yeares, all their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat with great quyet, and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation of all the Senators, which to shew themselues thankfull to him, ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the market place so many ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of him, as hee had gouerned their <hi>Common-weale</hi> yeares, to the ende the fame and memorie of him should bee immortall: and yet they did dedicate to their famous <hi>Hannibal,</hi> but one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly image, and to this <hi>Phylosopher</hi> they set vp aboue 60. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, whē he was most bēt to bloudy wars, went to see &amp; speake with <hi>Diogines</hi> the <hi>Phylosopher,</hi> offring him great presents &amp; discoursing with him of diuers mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. So that wee may iustly say, This good Prince of himselfe tooke paines to seeke out wise men to accompanie him, electing by others choyce and aduise all such, as hee made his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to serue him in the warres.</p>
   <p>It is manifest to all, that <hi>Dyonisius</hi> the <hi>Syracusan</hi> was the greatest Tyrant in the worlde: and yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Tiranny, it is a wonder to see what sage and wise men he had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in his Courte with him: And that, which makes vs yet more to won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of him is, that hee had them not about him to serue him, or to profite one jote by their doctrines and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell: but onely for his honour, and their profite, which enforceth mee to say, concurring with this example, that sith Tyrants did glorie to haue about them Sages, wise, and worthie men: Much more should those reioice, that their works &amp; deeds are noble, &amp; free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harted. And this they ought to do, not onely to bee honoured with them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, but also to be holpen with their doctrine and counsells secretly.</p>
   <p>And if to some this should seeme a hard thing to follow, we will say, that worthy men not being of abilitie and power to maintayne such Wise-men, ought yet at least to vse to reade, at times, good and vertuous books. For by reading <hi>(of vertuous Bookes)</hi> they may reape infinite profite. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: By reading (as I say) these <hi>Good Authours,</hi> the desire is satisfied, their iudgement is quickned, ydlenesse is put away, the heart is disburdened, the Time is well employed, and they lead their liues vertuously, not being bound to render account of so manie faults, as in that time they might haue committed. And to conclude, it is so good an exercise, as it giueth good example to the Neighbour, profite to himselfe, and health to the soule.</p>
   <p>We see by experience, after a man taketh vppon him once the Studie of holie Scriptures, and that hee frameth himselfe to bee a Diuine, hee will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer willingly thenceforth deale in any other studyes: and all because he will not forgoe (the great <hi>comfort and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> he receyueth) to reade those holy sayings. And that causeth, that we see so manie learned &amp; wise men (for the more part) subiect to diuers diseases: and full of Melancholike humours. For, so sweete is the delight they take in theyr Bookes, that they forget and leaue all other bodily pleasure.</p>
   <p>And therefore <hi>Plutarche</hi> writeth, that certaine phylosophers being one day met at the lodging of <hi>Plato,</hi> to see him: &amp; demanding what exercise he had at that time? <hi>Plato</hi> answered thē, thus. Truely my brethren, I let you know, that euen now my onely exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise was, to see what the great Poete <hi>Homer</hi> said. And this he tolde them, because that they took him euen then
<pb n="578" facs="309"/>
reading of some of <hi>Homers</hi> bookes, and to say truely, his aunswere was such, as they should all looke for of him. For to reade a good booke, in effect is nothing else, but to heare a wise man speake,</p>
   <p>And if this our iudgement and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise seeme good vnto you, we would yet say more, that you should profite more to reade one of these bookes, then you should to heare speake, or to haue conference with the Author him selfe that made it: For it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, that all Writers haue more care and respect in that their penne doth write, then they haue in that their tongue doth vtter. And to the end you should not thinke we cannot proue that true that we haue spoken, I giue you to vnderstand, that euerie Author that will write, to publish his doing in print, to lay it to the shew, and iudgement of the world, and that desireth thereby to acquire honour, &amp; fame, and to eternize the memory of him, turneth many bookes, confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with other wise and lerned men, addicteth himselfe wholy to his book, endeauoureth to vnderstand well, oft refuseth sleepe, meat and drinke, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his spirites, doing that he putteth in writing exactly with long aduise, and consideration, which he doth not when hee doth but onely speake and vtter them, though oft in deede (by reason of his great knowledge) in speech vnawares there falleth out of his mouth, many godly and wise sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. And therefore God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him a goodly gift that can reade and him much more that hath a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sire to study, knowing how to chuse the good bookes from the euill. For to say the truth, there is not in this world any state or exercise more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and profitable then the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of good books. And we are much bound to those that read, more to those that study, and much more to those that write any thing, but most doubtlesse to those that make &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pile goodly books, and those of great and high doctrine: for there are many vaine and fond bookes, that rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue to be throwne into the fire, then once to be read or looked on: for they do not only shew vs the way to mocke them, but also the ready meane to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs, to see them occupie their braines and best wittes, they haue to write foolish and vaine things, of no good subiect or erudition. And that which is worst of all yet, they are occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, that diuers others spend as much time in reading their iests and mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as they would otherwise haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied in doctrine, of great profit and edifying, the which to excuse and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their error, say they did not write them for men to take profite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, but only to delight and please the Readers, to passe the time away meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whom we may rightly answer thus: <hi>That the reading of ill and vaine bookes, cannot bee called a pastime, but aptly a very losse of time.</hi> And therefore <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Gelius</hi> in the fifteenth of his booke writeth, that after the Romanes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood the Orators and Poets of <hi>Rome,</hi> did giue themselues to write vain, voluptuous, and dishonest bookes, causing Enterludes and Poeticall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to be played, they did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly banish them from <hi>Rome,</hi> but also out all the parts of <hi>Italy:</hi> for it besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not the Romane grauity, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it decent for the Weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, to suffer such naughty bookes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and much lesse for to beare with vicious and lasciuious go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours. And if the Romane Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims left vs this for example, how much more ought wee that are Christians to continue and follow it, since that they had no other Bookes for to reade saue onely Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, and we now a dayes haue both Histories, and holy Scriptures
<pb n="579" facs="309"/>
to read, which were graūted vs by the church, to the end that by the one we might take some honest pleasure and recreation, and with the other procure the health of oursoules.</p>
   <p>Oh how farre is the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth nowe-adayes digressed from that wee wryte and counsell, since we see plainely, that men occupie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, at this present, in reading a nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Books, the which only to name I am ashamed. And therfore said <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Gelius in his</hi> 14. <hi>book,</hi> That there was a certain philosopher wrote a book of hie and eloquent stile, but the subiect very harde and diffuse to vnderstand: which <hi>Socrates,</hi> &amp; other philosophers hearing of, cōmanded immediatly the <hi>Booke</hi> to be burned, and the <hi>Author</hi> to be banished: by which exāple we may well perceiue, that in that so perfit and reformed <hi>Vniuersitie,</hi> they would not onely suffer any Lasciuious or vicious booke, but also they would not beare with those, that were too hawtie and vainglorious in their stiles, and whose matter was not profitable, and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to the <hi>Publike-weale.</hi> That man therfore that walloweth in idlenes lap, that vouchsafes not to spēd one houre of the day to read a graue sentence of some good <hi>Booke,</hi> wee may rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruedly cal him a brutish beast, then a reasonable creature. For euery wise man ought to glory more of the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge he hath, then of the aboundance of goods he possesseth. And it cannot be denyed, but that those which reade <hi>vertuous Bookes,</hi> are euer had in better fauor, and estimation then others. For they learne to speake, they passe their time without trouble, they know ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pleasant things, which they after tel to others: they haue audacitie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue others, &amp; euery man delighteth to heare them, &amp; in what place or com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panie soeuer they come, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reuerenced &amp; honored aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: euery man desireth their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and acquaintance, and are glad to aske them counsell. And that, that is yet of greater credit to them is, that they are not few in number, that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth them with their bodie &amp; goods.</p>
   <p>And moreouer (I say) that the wise and learned man which professeth stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, shall know very well how to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel his friend, and to comfort himselfe at all times, when neede doeth serue, which the foolish ignorant person can not doe: For he cannot only tell how to comfort the afflicted in aduersitie, but also hee cannot helpe himselfe in his own proper affaires, nor take coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of himselfe, what is best to doe.</p>
   <p>But returning againe to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose (we say) because we would not be reproued of that we rebuke others of, wee haue beene very circumspect and aduised: and taking great care, and paines in our study, that all our books and workes, wee haue published, and compyled, should be so exactly done, that the <hi>Readers</hi> might not find any ill doctrine, nor also any thing worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. For the vnhonest <hi>bookes,</hi> made by lasciuious persōs do giue (deserued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) euident token to the <hi>Readers</hi> to sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the <hi>Authours:</hi> and troubleth the iudgements of those, that giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue care vnto them.</p>
   <p>And therefore I counsell and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish him that will enterprise, and take vppon him to bee a wryter, and a setter forth of Bookes, that hee bee wise in his matter hee sheweth, and compendious in the wordes hee wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: and not to bee like to diuers Wryters, whose workes are of such a phrase and style, as we shall reade ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times to the middest of the booke, ere wee finde one good and notable sentence, so that a man may say, that al the fruit those reape for their paine, watches, and trauell, is none other but onely a meere toye and mockery, they being derided of euery man that seeth their workes.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="578" facs="310"/>
That Authour that vndertaketh to write, and afterwardes prostrateth to common iudgement the thing hee wryteth, may bee assured that hee set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his wittes to great trauell and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and hazardeth his honour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent perill. For the iudgement of men being variable, and diuers (as they are indeede) manie times they doe med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and enter into iudgement of those things, whereof they are not only not capable to vnderstand, but also lesse skilfull to reade them.</p>
   <p>Now in that booke wee haue set out, of <hi>The Dyall of Princes:</hi> and in that other wee haue translated of the <hi>Life of the Romaine Emperours,</hi> and in this wee haue now set forth <hi>Of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured Courtiers,</hi> the Readers may bee assured, they shall find in them goodly and graue sentences, whereby thy may greatly profit, and they shall not read any wordes superfluous, to comber or weary them at all. For, we did not once licence our pen to dare to write any word, that was not first weyed in true ballāce, &amp; measured by iust mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. And <hi>GOD</hi> can testifie with vs, that without doubt wee haue had more paine to be briefe in the wordes of our books we haue hitherto made, then we haue had to gather out the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, and graue sentences thereof.</p>
   <p>For to speake good words, and to haue good matter and wise purposes, is the property of one that naturally is modest, and graue in his actions: but to write briefely, he must haue a deepe vnderstanding.</p>
   <p>When at the <hi>Fonte of the Printers Forme,</hi> we first baptized the Booke of <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> wee intituled it <hi>The Dyall of Princes:</hi> and this therefore that we haue now made and added to it, we call it (more for briefnes) <hi>The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured Courtyer:</hi> which portendeth the whet-stone and instruction of a Courtyer. For if they will vouchsafe to reade, and take the fruitfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selles they finde written heerein, they may assure themselues, they shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken out of the vanityes, they haue long slept in: and shall also open their eies, to see the better, that thing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they liue so long deceyued. And albeit indeed this present work shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to you but a fewe contriued lines, yet <hi>GOD</hi> himselfe doeth knowe, the paines we haue taken herein hath bin exceeding great, and this for two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: the one for that the matter is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry straunge and diuerse from others; the other, to thinke that assuredly, it should be hated of those that want the taste of good discipline. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee haue taken great care, it should come out of our hands well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and corrected: to the ende that Courtyers might finde out many Sentences in it, profitable for them, and not one word to trouble them.</p>
   <p>Those Noble-men, or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that will from henceforth haue their children brought vp in the Courtes of Princes, shall finde in this Booke, all things they shall neede to prouide them of: And those also which haue beene long Courtyers, shall finde all that they ought to doe in Court.</p>
   <p>And such also as are best fauoured of Noble Princes, and carrie greatest reputation of honour with them, shall find likewise excellent good counsels, by meane whereof, they may alwayes maintain and continue themselues, in the chiefest greatnesse of their credite and fauour: so that it may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Mithridaticall Electuary:</hi> recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and healing all malignant opila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
   <p>Of all the Bookes I haue hitherto compiled, I haue Dedicated some of them vnto the <hi>Imperiall Maiestie,</hi> and others, to those of best fauor and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite with him: where the Readers may see, that I rather glorie to bee a <hi>Satyr</hi> then a <hi>Flatterer,</hi> for that in all my
<pb n="579" facs="310"/>
sentences they cannot finde one clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked word, to enlarge and embetter my credite and estate. But to the contrary, they may reade an infinite number of others, where I doe exhort them to gouern their person discreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and honorably, and to amend their liues thenceforth.</p>
   <p>When I Imprinted the Diall of Princes, together with <hi>Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius,</hi> and brought them to light. I wanted not backbiters and detractors that beganne forthwith to teare me in pieces; neyther shall I want at this present (as I beleeue) such as will not spare with venemous tongues, to poyson my worke: But like as then I little wayed their slaunderous speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of me, euen so much lesse do I now force what they can say against mee, being assured they shall finde in the end, they haue ill spoken of mee, and my poore workes, proceeding from them rather of a certaine enuie, that gnaweth their heart, then of any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault they finde in my doctrine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting my selfe yet in the assurance I haue, that all their spight shall one day haue an end, and my workes shall euer be found good and perdurable</p>
   <trailer>The end of the Argument.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>