<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, WISDOME TO DISCERNE HIS E∣state aright, and grace to grow for∣ward to perfection.</title>
           <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120771_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19293</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5700</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120771</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, WISDOME TO DISCERNE HIS E∣state aright, and grace to grow for∣ward to perfection.</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A familiar treatise : laying downe cases of conscience, furthering to perseuerance in sanctification. By Thomas Cooper, preacher of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 92 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, WISDOME TO DISCERNE HIS E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state aright, and grace to grow for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to perfection.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in the Lord Iesus, it is a most <hi>dangerous,</hi> and yet very <hi>easie</hi> and <hi>plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible delusion,</hi> to <hi>conceit</hi> vnto our selues an <hi>estate in grace,</hi> when as yet we remain the bond slaues of Satan. And it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>difficult,</hi> and yet most <hi>necessarie</hi> triall, to discerne our constant abiding and proceeding in this estate of grace. For (to passe by these who make a mocke of conuersion, as being a <hi>touch of noueltie,</hi> a <hi>brand of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancie,</hi> and <hi>imputation of hypocrisie</hi>) who is there almost that flatters not himselfe to bee in the fauour of God, and so interessed in his grace? And hath hee not many such pretences and colours hereunto, which may so abuse his iudgement,<note place="margin">Galat. 6.5.</note> that he may <hi>thinke himselfe to bee somewhat, when he is nothing;</hi> and so refusing to bee found in Christ, by being lost and emptied in himselfe, thereby become worse then nothing? Better neuer to haue beene borne, then so to be deceiued. Oh how the wisedome of the flesh prooues heere enmitie against God!<note place="margin">
         <p>Rom. 8.7. Iohn 9 43. Occasions to conceiue a false conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
         <list>
            <item>1. <hi>Complexion.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>2. <hi>Natures im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
      </note> Is not this the iudgement vpon the world, that <hi>they which see not, might see; and that they which see might bee made blinde?</hi> Consider first, I pray you, how <hi>nature</hi> occasions this deceit. Is any lesse badlie disposed by the benefit of his <hi>complexion?</hi> Is any restrained from <hi>some act</hi> of euill by <hi>natures impotencie</hi> and <hi>deformitie?</hi> Behold, euen these to the naturall man prooue very <hi>dangerous
<pb facs="6"/>
stumbling blockes</hi> to rest in nature, as affoording some shew of good, more then is of others of an harder constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as breaking out lesse into grosse euils, then such who by natures ability are more prone and prouoked thereto, and so to reiect the holy meanes of conuersion: and is it not esteemed a sufficient measure of goodnesse, to bee lesse euill then others, howsoeuer the desire and fountaine of corruption be the same in all? Is not the seeming good which by natures benefit shewes foorth in the world, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted currant holinesse, and thereby excludeth the true power of well-doing?</p>
   <p>For is this any more then what brute beasts may boast of? Is the heart lesse euill, because the hand cannot act, nay is it not more rebellious, the lesse it hath it desire? do not such wish for, and talke delightfully of what they cannot doe: will they not sport themselues in others that can do the same? will they not take their fill, if power be restored? or is the heart the better, because through benefite of complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we are ingenuous, sociable, &amp;c. are not these fitter matter for Satan to worke on, to draw vs into fellowship in euill, to make vs instruments to deceiue our selues and others?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">3. <hi>Education.</hi>
      </note>Especially, if to this shew of natures righteousnesse, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation</hi> be adioyned, whereby the minde being informed in <hi>knowledge,</hi> and restrained by <hi>ciuilitie,</hi> natures <hi>euill</hi> is heereby more kept vnder, and it <hi>seeming good,</hi> set out more saleable and beautious to the sinister iudgement: howsoeuer now nature being puft vp hereby, hath gained no other then a <hi>weapon of vnrighteousnesse,</hi> to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God and his word, to commit sinne more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously, by how much it is enabled to couch it more closely, and smooth it more cunuingly; yet this with the world passeth for a <hi>currant conuersion;</hi> Must we not onely not doe euill, but also doe good, and can wee doe any good of our selues, vntill we be in Christ? and will we hunger of Christ, vntill we deny our selues: especially if some such change now appeare in the outward man, whereby wee may either
<pb facs="6"/>
differ from the rudenesse and grosse abuses of our parents, or differ from the barbarous and desperate sprouts of our childhood, and vntamed youth? Is it not hence conceiued that we are now conuerted, seeing now our childish and youthfull vanities are restrained, seeing wee are growne more sober and regular: although all tends to no better then ciuill honestie, to fit vs for the world, that so we may more hopefully and easily swallow the baites thereof? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though when wee are from vnder the rod, wee breake out more desperately into all grosse wickednesse, or else at the best exchange our sinnes, from wantonnesse to coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse, from frowardnesse to ambition, encreasing still in our lusts and plotting the satisfying thereof, that wee may set vp our rest in the world, and cast care away.</p>
   <p>And if now the Lord shall giue the wicked their desire,<note place="margin">
         <hi>4.</hi> Restraining spirit.</note> in affoording them so farre the vse of his blessed Spirit, as to <hi>restraine</hi> yet more inward corruption, by it power, and terrour, that so they may be fitter for such outward prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as they haue especially made choice of in this life, and so renounced their interest in Heauen: And withall may frame better to societie, both of the <hi>good,</hi> to whom now they shall doe lesse hurt, as also of the <hi>euill,</hi> whom by this meanes they may prouoke to good; that so Gods go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the world may bee more beautifull and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and his will more righteously accomplished in the elect and reprobate. Is not this <hi>restraint</hi> apprehended, as <hi>a great conquest ouer corruption;</hi> and so a <hi>conuersion</hi> hence <hi>vainely</hi> concluded, seeing the inward heart is no whit renued, but onely the corruption restrained from the outward act? Nay, is not corruption <hi>more inraged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,</hi> the more it is outwardly bridled and smothered? and so sinne made out of measure sinfull: as being more <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excusable,</hi> the more it is curbed:<note place="margin">Rom. 7. <hi>Note.</hi>
      </note> as <hi>breaking out more desperately,</hi> when the bridle is reiected: as <hi>ripening</hi> more dangerously, the more it boileth within: and so <hi>sealing vp</hi> vengeance more certainely, yea more <hi>fearefully hastning</hi> it, as proceeding to <hi>despight the spirit of grace.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 10.27.28</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <note place="margin">5. <hi>Spirit of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> Math. 7.</note>And what though the Lord bestow on the wicked <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent graces of his Spirit,</hi> inabling them to <hi>teach others,</hi> to doe <hi>wondrous things,</hi> furthering them so farre in the shew of holinesse, as that they shall seeme for a time to <hi>outstrip the sincere professor?</hi> May they not teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">1. Cor 9.</note> and yet themselues bee <hi>reiected?</hi> May they not doe miracles, and yet heare, <hi>I know you not?</hi> May they not begin in the Spirit, and yet end in the flesh? and can they continue that haue taken no roote? can they call on God at all times, that haue made the world their hope and their belly their Gods can these earth wormes endure any thing that may purge out their drosse, and prepare them to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">Iob. 27. Gal. 6.10. 2. Tim. 3.</note> who sew to the flesh, and shall they not of the flesh reape corruption? Shall not <hi>the candle of the hypocrite bee put out?</hi> Doth not this <hi>faire shew of the flesh, deceiue,</hi> and <hi>prooue deceiued?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">6. <hi>Afflictions,</hi>
      </note>What should I tell you of that change that is wrought by afflictions? Will not the wicked in their troubles seeke the Lord diligently? Must not the vilest forbeare, when they cannot otherwise chuse? And is it any masterie, not to reuenge,<note place="margin">Psal. 78. 2. Pet. 2.</note> when power is not in our hands? Will not the swine that is now cleansed, returne to the mire againe? Is it charity, then to forgiue the world, when we see no <hi>time</hi> left for execution of malice? Is it patience, to forbeare when we can neither will nor chuse? Is it obedience, to tremble vnder the whip? to feare God onely for his iustice, and not to loue him for his mercy?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">7. <hi>Prosperitie.</hi>
      </note>Oh but wee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> of trouble, and restored to <hi>great happinesse.</hi> Behold, wee are blessed on the earth: and are not wee then truely blessed? Is not this a marke of holinesse, to bee prosperous in the world? Would God blesse our labours, if we did not serue him? May not this change from affliction to prosperitie be a certaine euidence of an inward change from worse to better, and so prooue vnto the flesh a conceit of <hi>conuersion?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Surely, if the world bee Iudge, the case is quickely ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Who is the good man, but the rich man? Either his
<pb facs="7"/>
riches shall be the cloake to hide his faults by greatnesse, bribery, cunning packing, friendship, &amp;c. or his euill by the <hi>flattery</hi> of the world shall be accounted good, he will not doe so for his credit: he needs not steale, oppresse: he hath wheren it hall: his couetousnesse is thrift; his pride, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse; his prodigality, bounty; his loosenesse, liberty and prerogatiue Hath he not power of all in his hands? And may he not doe what he list? Is not his lust a law, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample a rule and warrant? He feares no trouble; therefore he deserues none. Who can say <hi>Blacke is his eye?</hi> because, who dares say so? Nay, who will not say, blacke is white, if it may please him? Thus prosperity makes a conuert, if the world may giue in euidence.</p>
   <p>Especially if our fulnesse in the world be graced with some ciuill calling, whereby we are honoured of the people,<note place="margin">
         <hi>8.</hi> Ciuil calling.</note> and taken vp with imploiments; is not idlenesse now much preuented, and so such sinnes as doe accompany the same? Doth not credit now restraine, where conscience can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not? Is there not now a cloake for sinne, and countenance for iniquity? What defence is fathered hence for neglect of spirituall duties▪ What opportunity offered, to colour oppression and deceit? What pretence for licentiousnesse, and excesse in the abuse of the creatures? What <hi>wrapping</hi> vp of abuses, where there is fellowship in euill? Is not here a glorious maske, for sincerity and religion, where out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward honesty in a ciuill calling becomes a warrant of <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnesse,</hi> seeing our <hi>faith is shewed by workes?</hi> Are we not true and iust in our dealing, doe we not pay euery man his owne, doe we not helpe our neighbour by trusting him with our goods, being surely for him, do we not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine good neighbourhood, by feasting one another, and making peace among men. And what more obuious and commendable then our ciuill imploiments, so beneficiall to the Common-weale so necessary for our priuate, so suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessefull in the issue, as who (in opinion) more blessed? What is it, if not godlinesse, that is so plentifully recompenced in this life? If now the wicked eat the labours of their hands,
<pb facs="8"/>
and drinke their wine in bowles, may they not sacrifice to their nets? May they not crie ay me vnto their soules, Oh well is thee, and happy shalt thou be? Thus ciuill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment with worldlings is accounted religion: and to be morally iust and true in contracts and bargaines, goes cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant with men for stanch and sound holinesse.</p>
   <p>But if we enter into Gods sanctuary, and by the rule of the word determine hereof; Is not the Lord good vnto all, and doe we know loue or hatred by these things. Eccl. <hi>9.1.</hi> Nay is not prosperity the portion of the wicked. Psal. <hi>17.14.</hi> Are they not hereby fatted vp to the day of slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Ierem. <hi>12.3.</hi> Is not an hypocrite in affliction, an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theist and mocker in prosperity. Is not a proselite in pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, an Apostate and Blasphemer in affliction. Haue not the best lost by prosperity, and are not the worst made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excusable thereby? doth it not vsually peruert and spoile them of what they seemed to haue had, breaking all bonds of ciuill honesty, and so makes them worse then bruit beasts, without vnderstanding. Doe not the poore receiue the Gospell, when the rich and mighty are sent empty away, because either they cannot come, or come with their outward man: their hearts runne after their couetousnes: Is the word entertained with such, otherwise thē for state or cōplement, or else to make them merry. To condemn the rashnesse and folly of such as will reproue, or to deride their flattery, that will call light darknesse, must it not dance after our pipe, and serue our lusts, to harden vs in sinne and ripen vs to vengeance. Is not thus the prosperity of the wicked their destruction,<note place="margin">Prou. 1. Psal 55. Ier. 48.11.</note> and not their conuersion? Doth not the old sent remaine in <hi>Moab,</hi> because he was not changed from vessell to vessell, but enioyed constant pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity thereby, was setled on his lees, and rooted more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately in natures dregges, thereby exercised more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and desperately the lusts thereof?<note place="margin">Ose 4.7. Psalm 78. Ose 5.</note> Can the change of the outward estate change the inward man from worse to better? As they were increased, so, did not Gods people rebel against him, who in their afflictions sought vnto him
<pb facs="8"/>
deceitfully? Is not here a change from better to worse? we fawne on God till we haue our desires, and when our turne is serued, then depart from vs Lord, we will not the knowledge of thy waies, what profit shall we haue if we serue the Almighty. Iob. <hi>21.15.16</hi> We haue now no need of God, and therefore it is in vaine to serue him.</p>
   <p>As for walking in a ciuill calling,<note place="margin">Ciuill honesty no euidence of conuersion.</note> howsoeuer this (being sanctified by the <hi>spirituall</hi>) may be a meanes to lay vp a good foundation against the day of Christ. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>6.19.20</hi> yet to the naturall man there is not a more dangerous outward meanes to exclude grace, then the greatest mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of honesty that is seene therein. For is it not the grace of this calling <hi>to rest in it selfe,</hi> for good successe, without inuocation of Gods assistance, or reference to his blessing? Is not our pursuit hereof a priuiledge to exempt from holy duties, We must liue, and therefore we cannot be bookish. We haue no leasure to the Church. Or is it not enough to come when we may haue leisure? Is it not sufficient that we are not Papists in profession, though we are Papists in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and prophanation to; yea grosse Idolaters in making our belly our God, the world our confidence: Is it not meritorious that we giue almes, and receiue our maker once a yeere. Psal. <hi>15.4.</hi> that we are no whores nor theeues, we doe no body any wrong: we liue of our own, doth not this vtterly exclude religion in the family? doth it not ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish all loue to the power of religion? doth it not extinguish all sense of inward corruption. Is it not to sticke in the forme of Religion, and so to renounce the power thereof. Is not this to say in our hearts there is no God, seeing he is onely in our lippes and not in our raynes, do we not deny him in our liues, and carnall worship, who is a spirit and will be worshipped in spirit and truth: howsoeuer we boast that we know him enough? And doe our mouthes otherwise acknowledge him then at best, by prophaning his great name, and blaspheming it ordinarily in our daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication? Nay, is it not a price proposed to incourage di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in these worldly businesses, euen licence to prophane
<pb facs="9"/>
the Sabbaths, to despise the word? &amp;c. And what if men keepe touch and day in paiments and contracts? What if a little eie seruice be vsed in the outside of their wares. Is it for conscience to God, to whom they desire to approue the truth of their hearts, or onely a care for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of trading, and mutuall commerce, which without this outward seeming equity must needs be abolished? Who will trust, or shall be trusted, if word be not kept? But is it kept any further, then may cleere from touch of mans law? Is promise <hi>kept here to our hinderance,</hi> so we may winde out by the arme of flesh? Is the substance of our wares any thing lesse then answerable to the shew? Is not God robbed of his glory, while we sacrifice to our labour and wit? <hi>Is not this great Babel, which I haue built for the honor of my name?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.1.</note>Surely as these outward things are common to all: so no man knoweth loue or hatred, either by prosperity or aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity. Well may a good man (by right vsage) make these good vnto him; but these of themselues may well make him worse: otherwise they haue no power inwardly to better him Onely it belongeth vnto God (through the ministery of his word) to conuert the soule, as tendring (to this end) vnto vs,<note place="margin">Psal. 19. 1. Per. 1.18.</note> not corruptible things, as <hi>siluer</hi> and <hi>gold,</hi> which make outwardly happy in this life; but <hi>the precious blood of Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.8.</note>
      <hi>as a Lambe vndefiled, &amp; without spot,</hi> whreby we are cleansed from all our sinnes, and redeemed from our vaine conuersation, receiued by the tradition of the fathers.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">8. <hi>Profession Practise.</hi> Math. 7. Luke 8, Mark. 6.25.</note>But harken I pray you, vnto a further plea of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite: <hi>Haue we not heard thee teaching in our streets?</hi> Nay, <hi>Haue we not taught in thy name? Haue we not receiued the word with ioy, and done many things</hi> accordingly? Can the best doe more? Doe not we in many things offend all? Is not this a sufficient euidence of an effectuall conuersion?</p>
   <p>Surely where the grace of God which bringeth saluation to all men,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> hath appeared effectually, there it teacheth
<pb facs="9"/>
vs, not onely to eschew all euill, in thought,<note place="margin">Math. 5. Act. 15.19.</note> warde and deed; but on the contrary to prosecute all good, both <hi>1. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> in heart and minde, as being <hi>purified by faith,</hi> whereby with constant purpose we cleane vnto God, and also <hi>2. outwardly</hi> in the life and conuersation: <hi>Iam. 3.1.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 11.23.</note>
      <hi>Ephes. 1. Rom. 12.1. 1. Cor. 6.</hi> yea <hi>generally and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersally, hauing respect to all Gods commandements: Psal. 119.7.8.</hi> and <hi>constantly,</hi> also continuing and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, yea <hi>increasing</hi> in grace, and <hi>finishing</hi> our course, that no man take away our Crowne: <hi>Reuel. 3. 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Profession and some practise of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of true conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. 2. Cor. 2.14. Ioh 15. Psal. 119. Ezech. 33.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, 31. Heb. 4.2.</note>
      <hi>58. Ephes. 3. Collos. 1.2. Pet. 1.8.9. 2. Tim. 4.3. Phil. 13.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And therefore seeing the word of God must be a sauour of death vnto death, vnto some who are to bee renounced, and made inexcusable thereby; hence is it, that though they receiue it <hi>1.</hi> with <hi>ioy,</hi> as being rauished with the sweetnesse thereof; yet being not <hi>mixed with faith,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes vnprofitable; yea a witnesse aegainst them, and so the ioy of the hypocrite lasteth but a moment, hee is like to bee beaten with more stripes, because hee knowes his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters will, and doth it not: <hi>Math. 12.47.</hi> yea though it commeth also to passe, that for carnall respects, as vaine-glorie, credit, satisfaction of others, whom they desire to be like, the hypocrite also may <hi>do many things</hi> according to the <hi>letter of the word,</hi> though not answerable to the power thereof; nor from the purpose of his heart, renued by the holie Ghost; but executing therein the lust of his heart, as spirituall pride, hypocrisie, &amp;c. Yet neither shall he be able to continue in any substance of well-doing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he hath no root; how soeuer for his credit and profite he must sometimes shew religious, yet by reason of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of companie, change of times and occasions, he must euen for the same ends of credit and profite, cast off his visour of holinesse, and so appeare in his true likenesse, to the satisfying of such, to whom nothing but grosse and desperate wickednesse will giue any contentment. This is certaine, that as the hypocrite in his best deuotions,
<pb facs="10"/>
aymes onlie at carnall ends, so in his best worship he fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons himselfe to the world, and measures himself by it loue: either he must only goe, and so farre as the time will beare, or his leaders go before, or flesh and blood will brooke; and it is his wisedome to turne with the time, to be ruled by his betters, to bee indifferent to all straines, that so hee may gaine by all. Nay doth not this necessity lie vpon the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, that howsoeuer for a time he must glose and fawne vpon the truth, while it is his pack horse to further him to promotion, riches, &amp;c. yet when by plunging himselfe into worldly courses, he must necessarily crosse in his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward actions, the power of that truth which he makes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of, and so thereby wound and gall his conscience: must he not now for his credit abase and vilifie that truth which before hee so magnified? as being either too seuere and precise because he cannot reach it:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> or being foolishnes and madnesse: and therefore he is now more wise, more sober, then to be guided by it. you must pardon his former folly and giddinesse: he will do no more so; he will be more wise, moderate, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>And all this but a colour to hide or ease his wounded conscience, which not being able to endure the power of the word, must therefore in wisedome reiect it; and so flie vnto carnall Physicke, to purge out melancholie, and yet still vnder pretence of Christian libertie, that hee hath knowledge enough, and yet more desperately to deceiue himselfe hereby and others, as preseruing an opinion of his righteousnesse, as if hee were vniustly chalenged, and therefore may iustlie except against this euidence, and so preuenting sound repentance, and thereby, casting off the bridle, giues libertie to sinne, and so hasteneth vengeance.</p>
   <p>This is the issue of an hypocrites supposed conuersion, answerable euen vnto the measure thereof: which being not rooted in the heart, nor aiming at Gods glory, no maruell if the glory of an hypocrite prooue his confusion. And is hee not iustly deceiued in this fancie
<pb facs="10"/>
of regeneration? Is he not hereby excluded from the power of conuersion, because hee resteth in the shadow thereof?</p>
   <p>But to admit a true conuersion: Is the combate now at an end? or not rather now begun? Is there any place here for idlenesse, security, remisnesse in our calling? Surely though the foundation standeth sure in respect of God,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19 2 Pet. 1.10</note> who knoweth who are his; yet it lieth much in vs, either to make sure and beautifie the building, by being watchfull and diligent in well-doing;<note place="margin">2 Phil. 12 Psal. 51 Psal. 73 Malach. 3</note> or else by our negligence and security, to deface and interrupt it, yea many times to our <hi>sense</hi> and <hi>feeling,</hi> euen vtterly to ouerthrow the same. For proofe heereof, take wee wisely a scantling of the times wherein we liue, and then lay we thereto such expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience as this Treatise affoordeth.</p>
   <p>Concerning our times it may not bee denyed, but that our meanes might haue yeelded such a growth in holinesse as by the time wee might all haue been tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of others, in regard of our aboundant measure of knowledge: yea we might haue been leaders to other Nations in the power and practise of godlinesse, hauing by Gods mercy such liuely presidents of sanctification set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs: And therefore, as wee stand only vpon our name, and credit of profession, it must be assumed, that seeing we haue had such meanes, therefore the Lord shall finde no iniquity in vs, that were shame and wickednesse,<note place="margin">Ose 12 1 Reg. 22</note> seeing God hath a few names among vs, that walke in white, and keepe themselues vndefiled from the great offence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when went the spirit of God from vs vnto them? why should they that haue had the same meanes yeeld also like fruit of conscionable obedience? why should not we stand vpon our holines with the best: seeing we haue found out riches in all our labours: God prospereth vs in our affaires abroad, and all is peace and husht at home;<note place="margin">Zach. 11.5 Reuel 31 7</note> and therefore blessed be God, for we are rich, and increased with goods, and haue need of nothing: Thus as the bountifull loue could doe nothing vnto vs which he hath not done, so if
<pb facs="11"/>
our owne words will be taken,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Saul.</hi> 1 Sam. 15 Esay 66.5 Ioh. 26.1.</note> wee haue fulfilled the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of our God, all the Congregation is holie, whatsoeuer we doe, let the Lord be glorified, we thinke we doe God good seruice, in casting out of the Synagogues. Thus continuance of gratious meanes brings vs to a forme of godlinesse and the forme of godlinesse prouokes vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the power thereof, that so we might be more inexcusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, because we cannot plead ignorance nor iustly chalenge our God of any failing towards vs: and hasten hereby vpon vs the iust iudgement of God, because we hate that in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whereof we assume the glory, and deny that in our obedience, which we arrogate as our chiefest hold in the fauour of God, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord. And shall not then our glory be our shame, because we are earthly minded; and doth not our securitie in this estate, presage speedie vengeance? And is not the sickle alreadie put in? haue wee not sharpened the sword that threatens our destruction? shall the Lord repent him of any euill he intends towards vs, seeing wee harden our hearts daylie, and will not repent? Will the Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs, seeing mercie and compassion is banished from among vs? Euery one seekes his owne, and not each others good, our mercies are plaine cruelties, our tables snares, our loue to the flesh the betraying the soul? thus lest we should be counted non proficients, we presume of practise answerable to the meanes, And hereby we would seeme to haue hit the iust measure of holinesse, because wee compell others to our measure, and stent them by our line, as if wee were absolute paternes to them of godlinesse, as if whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer were beyond our compasse, were superfluous, and exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant. If now it please God to awaken the conscience of any that hath bene ouertaken with the deceitfulnesse of the time, or otherwise damped with the security thereof: so that he beginnes to bethinke himselfe, and remember whence he hath fallen: is it not the policie to stoppe his mouth with offals of the world, to drowne him in pleasure, to ariue away melancholie, to drink away this hart qualms
<pb facs="11"/>
or play it away, in abuse of Christian libertie. Or if yet the Lord maintaine his controuersie, by the terrors of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, to bring to repentance: Oh then the cry is, that he is mad, or desperate, a foole, or an hypocrite. Thus are the hearts of Gods children more cast downe, whom the Lord hath humbled, and all to maintaine our seeming hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, all this to harden our hearts, that we may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And haue we not to this purpose in great estimation, many accursed and damnable engines of Satan, the rather yet to harden the heart, by making a mocke of sinne? What shall we conceiue of that common practise? let no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue: sinne must not be dealt withall in earnest, lost our confidence be confounded: or if it must bee dealt withall, then let vs heare of it in iest, it must bee taught vpon the stage, and yet made matter to sport with, that so wee may account it but a sport, that so the foole may make a mocke of sinne surely, though blessed be God, sinne goes not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controuled, and that by Gods holy ordinance to conuince and confound the same: yet is not the sacred word of God made a iest of too: a subiect for stage playes, a by-word at tables, that so we may yet more desperatly scorne the same and so yet further harden our hearts, that we may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And though the glorious Lord hath euen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen auenged his cause against those horrible Theators of all abomination, burning one of them to the ground, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting daylie the markes of his wrath vpon them, by madnes, epilepsie, &amp;c. yet will not the filthy bee filthy still? Must they not still remaine to be factors for Popery: brokers for Atheisme, and bauds to all odious wickednesse, so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the pride of our holy mountaine; to nouzle in security; as if wee now had leisure still to play, as if still wee might doe nought else, but eat and drinke, and rise vp to make our selues merry with surfeiting on the sinnes of others. And hath Satan compassed in vaine by these his wiles? Is not Popery encreasing, and growne to some hope to build <hi>Iericho</hi> againe. Doth not close Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isme abound generally, the Lord is acknowledged in word,
<pb facs="12"/>
but in our works we do deny him? Doth not grosse and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Atheisme raigne aloft in our cursed blasphemies of God in taking his glorious Name in vain:<note place="margin">Iude 15</note> Is not this the crown of our pride to draw neer vnto God with our lippes, when our hearts are far from him: and is not our glory our shame:<note place="margin">Esay 29 Iob 3</note> because we with the same mouth breath out cursing &amp; blessings? Is not this another bitter fruit of this accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed tree, to pretend what we are not, nor euer meane to be? And hath not desperat prophanesse hence got his strength? Is not liberty giuen hereby to all licentiousnesse? Doth not Popery on the one side satisfie the flesh whiles it pretends to haue it in no estimation, nourishing the pride of the flesh in voluntary deuotions, iustifying and satisfying the lusts of the flesh, vnder a pretence of wisdome, notably discouered, in auricular confessions, in indulgences, voluntary vowes, counsels of perfection, &amp;c. pretending perfection, to cloak sin, that we may not be chalenged for it, confessing sin, that we may commit it more greedily, vowing continence &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, that we may enioy the contrary more secretly, &amp; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon for sinne, that we may practise it more secure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And doeth not Atheisme on the other side encrease the score, giuing the bridle more desperately vnto sin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Lord is hid in the clouds, and will neither do good nor euill, because he forbeares, therefore he is like vnto vs, he likes of our sinne: or els we say in our hearts, there is no God at all: no hell for sinners, but to be hindered in sinne, no Heauen, but this, to satisfie the lusts of the flesh: And doth not hypocrisie now make vp the measure, presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on Gods mercy, that we may sinne continually, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending infirmities, that we may be borne withall howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, resting on the forme of godlinesse, to cloake any despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wickednesse: Therefore we shall be deliuered, though we haue committed all these abominations; because we are Christians, the iust Temple of the Lord is with vs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he shall see no iniquitie, and stinting Religion to flesh and blood, that so flesh and blood may take it swing, and thereon be most religious,<note place="margin">Iob 9</note> because it doth it best, it cannot
<pb facs="12"/>
do otherwise, it doth what others do: It acknowledgeth no failings, and therefore it makes vp it measure: therefore sinne remaines vpon it, because it sees no sinne, it acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth no iniquity. And doth not the kingdome of Satan swarme hereby, and therefore shall not the hypotrites bee beaten with more stripes: The Lord make vs wise to see the plague, and hide our selues. Hath not the Lord been as a moth vnto Israel, and to the house of Iudah as rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: haue we not a name of peace, and yet behold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diuisions and heart burnings on all sides, <hi>Ephraim</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Manasseh,</hi> and <hi>Manasseh</hi> against <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both against <hi>Iuda.</hi> Doe we not boast of aboundance, and yet behold scarsitie, our wealth moltereth away, and wee know not how we enioy outward peace on all sides, and yet are impouerished hereby, whereas our neighbours are inri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with continuall warres, we sow much, and reape litle, and what we bring in is put into a broken bagge: Doth not the iust Lord secretlie blow vpon vs, because wee preferre not Ierusalem before all our mirth. The Lord giue vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in these things. Haue we not a blessed peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able gouernment, and yet still remaine discontent? Haue we not aboundance of the Gospell, and yet grow worse and worse. And is not this an argument of inward rottennes: Though our pretences are glorious, and meanes to be desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet haue we for the most part, yeelded any better fruit then moathie rottennesse, fained shewes without inward soundnes? Blessed bee God in Iesus Christ, that yet the meanes are continued vnto vs, is not there yet hope of our repentance? is not this the way speedily to effect it: euen to lay the axe to the roote of the tree. Behold how the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit here deales with this Church of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> and take this for thy glasse to behold thy present state in: discerne wisely what thou hast receiued, &amp; if thou hast left thy first hold, learne to take holde again by vnfained repentance. It is no shame to be chalengd of failings for the best ar not without &amp; it shalbe thy wisdom to reform the least seing otherwise thy God may come against thee. For thy better enabling herein.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>Peruse this <hi>treatise ensuing:</hi> let it be in Gods feare, a <hi>touch-stone</hi> vnto thee, to make triall of a <hi>sound conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reuel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> and take it as a <hi>preseruatiue,</hi> to keepe thee in the power of godlinesse, that so thou mayst not leaue thy first loue. If by <hi>pride</hi> or <hi>security</hi> thou hast bene left to thy selfe, and so hast left thy former measure: view thy selfe diligently in this present glasse, and vse it as a meanes for thy recouerie and perseuerance. If by second thoughts, thou hast now gained more light: glorifie God for any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and comfort thy selfe, that thou maist also encrease yet remember that we are still to grow: and therefore, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not what may be said, seeing my health and study af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords only breuitie, and my manifold afflictions might haue occasioned a decrease, or at least haue cut off all liberty to impart my store vnto thee: and therefore blesse God the rather, for this lengthening of dayes and do not distast, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it smels of the smoake, least if thou feare affliction, thou shalt find no comfort herein. And let me againe aduise thee, not to stare vpon the colour which happily may bleare thine eyes, but to looke into the woofe, to humble thine heart. Neither misconstruing what may be well digested, left thou bee peruerted by a stumbling blocke, nor despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the pearle,<note place="margin">Math. 22.14</note> because it is vnpolished, least thou loose the nut, because thou canst not crack the shell. Though many are called, yet but few are chosen: and therfore if few digest this pill: let them not condemne the physicke, but their own il-disposed hearts.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6, 7</note> Those that can get meat out of the eater and sweetnesse out of the strong, let them praise the glorious Lord,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12</note> who bringeth light out of darkenesse, and not cease praying vnto our gracious Father, that he would turne our darknesse into light, and enable vs to worke while yet wee haue the light: that so we may approue our selues the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the light, and be prepared to that light which shall neuer be changed into darknes. Euen so be it. <hi>Come Lord Iesus. Come quickely.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>In whom I rest thine vnfainedly, THOMAS COOPER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>