<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE Right Worshipfull, &amp; my worthy freinds Master RICHARD GORE, Deputy, the Asistants, and Generality, of the famous fel∣lowship of Merchant Adventurers of England, resident in Hamburgh, IOHN WING wisheth all present prosperity on earth, and all perfect happi∣nes in heaven.</title>
           <author>Wing, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120115_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15579</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25846</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120115</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE Right Worshipfull, &amp; my worthy freinds Master RICHARD GORE, Deputy, the Asistants, and Generality, of the famous fel∣lowship of Merchant Adventurers of England, resident in Hamburgh, IOHN WING wisheth all present prosperity on earth, and all perfect happi∣nes in heaven.</title>
                 <author>Wing, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iacobs staffe : To beare vp, the faithfull. And to beate downe, the profane. Touching the one's assured, and the others conceited title, vnto God himself, and all his precious promises. VVherin. The saints interest is justified, to be absolutely infaillible, the sinners clayme detected, to be apparantly deceivable, notwithstanding all infernall suggestions of feare, and infidelity in the one, or of presumption, and security in the other. Formerly preachcd [sic] at Hamburgh by Iohn VVing late pastor to the English Church there, as his farewell to the famous followship [sic] of Merchant Adventurers of England resident in that city. And now published, and dedicated, to the honor and vse, of that most worthy Society, there, or wheresoever being</title>
                 <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Flushing</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Nolck (Nolick), Marten Abrahamsz van der</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 216 pages, coats of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE <hi>Right Worshipfull, &amp; my worthy freinds</hi> Master RICHARD GORE, Deputy, the <hi>Asistants,</hi> and <hi>Generality,</hi> of the famous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship of Merchant Adventurers <hi>of England,</hi> resident in <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> IOHN WING wisheth all <hi>present</hi> prosperity on earth, and all <hi>perfect</hi> happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in heaven.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I have sometimes <hi>read,</hi> &amp; oftentimes <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated,</hi> the kinde question of that <hi>Pagan Prince,</hi> concerning the honorable reward of his faithfull <hi>servant;</hi> So have I beene abash't in my self, that I have not enquired soe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, what was due to you for your <hi>loue,</hi> as he did to him for his <hi>loyalty. [VVhat honour (sayd he) hath beene done to Mordocay for this?]</hi> should I not have asketd my self <hi>the same</hi> long since, for your <hi>kindnes,</hi> not much inferior to his <hi>seruice?</hi> And now that (of late) I have begun this inquisition, my conscience answers with shame: <hi>[There hath nothing beene done]</hi> with shame <hi>(I say)</hi> &amp; blushing, that a <hi>heathen</hi> shall thus remember an <hi>inferiour,</hi> and a <hi>christian</hi> should thus forget such <hi>freinds,</hi> as I have founde <hi>you all</hi> to be: whose favour &amp; kindnes though it be not vpon recorde in <hi>chronicle,</hi> yet doth it <hi>well</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue soe to be. And now to doe you the best <hi>honor,</hi> that can come within my <hi>power;</hi> I doe here present <hi>vnto you,</hi> and to <hi>all men,</hi> this true commemoration, and thankefull acknowledgment of these your <hi>favours,</hi> which were soe abundantly bestowed <hi>on your part,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though soe vndeserved <hi>on myne.</hi> We <hi>Schollers,</hi> have
<pb facs="3"/>nothing but <hi>papers</hi> to honour our <hi>best freinds</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, our <hi>most,</hi> and <hi>best</hi> is done, when we have put their <hi>good names in print,</hi> and by publike jmpression, given <hi>the world</hi> notice of the precious respects, their <hi>good nature</hi> hath cast vpon vs.</p>
   <p>And if this my <hi>endeavour,</hi> may be accounted but your <hi>least honour,</hi> I have what I desire, as one <hi>ayme</hi> of this publication. The <hi>matter</hi> published, intendeth an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour jnfinitely <hi>higher,</hi> even of <hi>God,</hi> who once enabled me to <hi>speake</hi> it, and hath now encouraged me to divulge it, <hi>principally</hi> for the glory of <hi>his</hi> name, &amp; <hi>next,</hi> for the renowne, and fame of <hi>yours,</hi> whose rare <hi>libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> it were most jnjurious to <hi>bury</hi> in these dayes, wherin <hi>so litle</hi> of the like is <hi>alive.</hi> I beseech you take <hi>in good part,</hi> what I present vnto you from <hi>a good hart.</hi> I was <hi>once</hi> hopefull to have beene more happy in my residence with you, then I can be in <hi>writing</hi> to you. But the <hi>almighty</hi> meant it otherwise, on him I cast all my cares, and strive daily for <hi>contentment,</hi> and <hi>comfort,</hi> in a state (in many regardes) much more <hi>meane.</hi> I hope nothing shalbe <hi>offensive</hi> to you, of that I have written, it being all <hi>gratefull,</hi> when it was spoken. If in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end I seeme more <hi>playne,</hi> and <hi>downe-right,</hi> in divers passages both concerning <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>my self.</hi> I pray you pardon me, it was to sustaine my owne <hi>vprightnes,</hi> and to wype away those foule and vnworthy <hi>jmputations,</hi> wherwith some malignant mindes and mouthes did as <hi>falsely,</hi> as <hi>basely,</hi> reproach and traduce me, <hi>(and that to my face)</hi> for such <hi>grosse miscarriage</hi> among you, as made me <hi>incapable</hi> of soe good a condition &amp; service as yours was. <hi>God for bid J should justify them till I dye</hi> (sayd <hi>Iob,</hi> and soe say <hi>I) and giue away my jnnocency.</hi> I had rather dye <hi>blameles,</hi> then live <hi>blemisht.</hi> And to <hi>bunge
<pb facs="3"/>vp,</hi> &amp; make <hi>mute</hi> for ever, these evill tongues, I could not but relate, that <hi>truth,</hi> which is able to <hi>remooue</hi> their <hi>sclanders,</hi> and <hi>reveale</hi> my <hi>integrity,</hi> to all persons, that shall please to pervse these particulers. The Lord of his infinite <hi>goodnes,</hi> make <hi>good</hi> this poore attempt of myne to you <hi>all,</hi> and to <hi>all</hi> others, into whose <hi>hands</hi> &amp; <hi>harts,</hi> I desire it may come. The same <hi>God,</hi> be ever <hi>your God,</hi> and shyne vpon <hi>you</hi> in the pure light of his sweete <hi>countenance,</hi> that all things may be fully <hi>disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered</hi> vnto you, which may <hi>further</hi> you to him, where you may <hi>shyne</hi> with him, in that glorious and <hi>inacces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible</hi> light, which noe <hi>corruption</hi> can inherit, or attaine. To his grace and blessing, in <hi>vncessant</hi> desire of your temporall <hi>prosperity</hi> in your <hi>Society,</hi> and spirituall and eternall <hi>prosperity,</hi> of soule &amp; body; I commend every one of you, with my owne soule, and soe rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your late <hi>Pastor,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned <hi>wellwiller for ever</hi> IOHN WING.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my house in Flushing <date>September 12. 1621,</date>
         </hi>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>