<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipful Sir IOHN SHVRLEY Knight, all health and happinesse from Christ Iesus our Sauiour.</title>
           <author>Attersoll, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120393_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22472</idno>
           <idno type="STC">889.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120393</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipful Sir IOHN SHVRLEY Knight, all health and happinesse from Christ Iesus our Sauiour.</title>
                 <author>Attersoll, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nevv couenant, or A treatise of the sacraments : Whereby the last testament of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, through the shedding of his pure and precious blood, is ratified and applyed vnto the conscience of euery true beleeuer. Diuided into three bookes 1. Of the sacraments in generall. 2. Of baptisme. 3. Of the Lords Supper. Verie necessarie and profitable for these times: wherein we may behold the truth it selfe plainly prooued, [the] doctrine of the Reformed Churches clearely maintained, [the] errors of the Church of Rome soundly conuinced, [the] right maner of the receiuing of the [m] comfortably declared and sundry doubts and difficult questions decided. By William Attersoll, minister of Gods word at Isfield in Sussex</title>
                 <author>Attersoll, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 576, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY KNIGHT SIR THOMAS SMITH, Gouernour of the East-India, Muscouia, Northwest Passages, <hi>SOMMER</hi> Ilands Companies, and Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer for the first Colonie in <hi>Virginia</hi>: AVGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STINE SPAVLDING <hi>wisheth all</hi> happinesse, and encrease of honour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onourable Sir, the world hath iust occasion to take knowledge of your continuall trauels, cares and endeuours for the good of those sundry Companies, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by publike assent you haue been chosen Gouernour. Your erecting of the Lecture of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation at your owne expences, for the better instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Mariners in that most needfull art: your setting downe of better orders in dispatching forth of our East-Indian fleetes: your employment with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie entertainment of skilfull Mathematicians and Geographers in the South and North parts of the world: This your prouidence and liberalitie is like, in time to come, to worke many speciall good effects. Lastly, you haue caused these Dialogues of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages of the Isle of <hi>Madagascar</hi> and of the <hi>Malaian</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
tongues, presented vnto you by Master <hi>Richard Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luyt,</hi> a singular furtherer of all new discoueries and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest trades, to be set forth in our English tongue: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the speciall vse and benefit which your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and seruants, residing in all the Southeast Islands of the world, may reape thereby. And that nothing might be omitted on your behalfe, it hath pleased you further to aske mine opinion, and to enioyne me to take speciall care for the correction of such errors as were committed in the first edition, because of my ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or twelue yeeres employment in those Countries, as seruant and Factor for your Worship and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie: which your commandement I haue performed in the best sort I can. If this my small seruice be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in good part, I hope hereafter to giue your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship a true relation, as leasure and opportunitie shall permit, of the chiefe things, which I haue obserued and performed in the time of my continuance in your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, in those remote parts of the world. And in the meane season I shall not cease to pray to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie for the long prosperitie of your selfe, and all the Worshipfull and worthie Companie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your seruant alwaies to be commanded, <hi>Augustine Spaulding.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>