<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120095_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08783</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19072</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120095</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Romes ruin. or A treatise of the certaine destruction of Rome and of Antichrist before the ende of the world : Wherein is cleerely manifested out of the Holy Scriptures, conferred with the historie of the Papacie, that he hath but a short time. A worke published to strengthe the faith of such as suffer vnder him. By I.P</title>
                 <author>I. P.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath neuer beene any part of my intent, Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in the writing or publishing of this litle Treatise, to take on me after the manner of some precisely to finde out, and peremptorily to set downe the verrie yeare wherein <hi>Rome</hi> or Antichrist shall be destroyed, or to name the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Prince</hi> or Kingdom, whose Kinge shall be Generall at the Seidge, and ruin of that <hi>Babylon;</hi> the worke it selfe will both quit me of such fond presumptions, and witnesse that my aime herein is not to get a vaine glorious name of knowledge in such mysteries; nor to fill the world with stronge delusions, opinions and expectations of improbable alterations; but rather for the honour of Almightie God (now in theese wauering and fainting times, wherein <hi>mens hearts faile them for feare,</hi> that the preuailing aduersaries will subdue all to Romish obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) to winne men to an assured confidence in his promised meraies of deliuerance; and what they can, to serue and waite on his almightie power, and prouidence with such iust meanes, as he hath appointed therevnto; espetially now when they shall see it manifested by those vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable testimonies, the prophesies of holy Scripture, and Histories of the Papacie answering them, that <hi>Romes Ruin</hi> must needes be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching, and can not choose but fall out within a few yeares of this present: which is sufficient for me to haue manifested. As for those who professe themselues Protestants, and yet in theese dangerous times are so far from affecting or approuing such knowledge, that on the contrarie they doubt whether it be lawfull and proffitable, to looke into theese Prophesies for the time and meanes of deliuerance, and ouerthrow of the aduersaries; whether such looking be not rather curiosity, folly, &amp; presumption; whether courses of iustice and warres vndertaken for the defence of the Gospell and ouerthrow of Poperie, and the Supporters thereof, be lawfull or necessary; whether a peace with them all is not much rather to be wished; and whether it be not much better that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants &amp; Papists should first ioyne together against theire cōmon ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie the <hi>Turke:</hi> In theese and the like scruples, such as are not partiall and obstinate, may by a thorow reading of this small booke receiue compotent satisfaction.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>In the meane time, I answer noe more heere to theire suggestions, then this, 1. That noe man can more detest, then I doe, all warres vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for desire of spoile, territories &amp; Empire, all not worth the life blood of one Christiā; knowing that the miseries, that euer follow thē, are great &amp; lamentable; that peace &amp; mercie can neuer be sufficiently admired &amp; extended; but not toward <hi>Amalek</hi> or <hi>Romish Babel</hi> and her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, because theire destructions are cōmaunded in holy Scriptures, and he is counted <hi>happie</hi> that shall <hi>serue her</hi> as she hath <hi>serued</hi> others. 2. That it was lawfull, proffitable, and comfortable for the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Israel</hi> in the time of the captiuity,
<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>9.2.</hi>
      </note> to looke, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did, after the time and meanes of deliuerance, espetially when the seauentie yeares were almost out; to looke also into the Prophesie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> for the last period of those seuerall Beasts, &amp; hornes mentioned Dan. 7. &amp; chap. 8. espetially for deliuerance from <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> that litle <hi>horne</hi> chap. 8.9. for the time and ende of the desolation he causeth, expresly noted vers. 13.14. and for the comming and saluation of Christ, and other occurrēts signified in those propheticall weekes of <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 9. Euen as old <hi>Simeon waited for the consolatiō of Israel;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. <hi>2.</hi> Mark. <hi>15.43</hi>
      </note> and <hi>Ioseph of Arimathea</hi> is saide to haue <hi>waited for the Kingdom of God:</hi> and that therefore, it is as lawfull now for all true Christians, beholding the desolations that Antichrist, and his Adherents make, to looke into the prophesies of holy Scripture for the time and meanes of the deliuerance, there promised, espetially seeing that when <hi>Rome</hi> the cause of theese miseries is destroied,
<note place="margin">Reu. <hi>19.</hi>
      </note> it is saide, <hi>Alleluia: for the Lord God omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent raigneth:</hi> whereas, before that, she raigned in matters of faith and saluation,
<note place="margin">Reu. <hi>17.18.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>ouer the Kings of the earth.</hi> But then <hi>Gods Kingdom commeth:</hi> this wee are taught to <hi>pray</hi> for, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. <hi>6.33.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>seeke.</hi> And therefore when after the writing of this small booke, I had kept it a longe time, without imparting the sight of it to any man, I thought I could now doe noe lesse then publish it, with some few additions, and that indeede, that such as see the miseries of the Church, and seeke to redresse them, may striue to doe it by that right meanes which God hath prescribed, and not by any contrarie to that which God, <hi>that changeth not,</hi> hath in his <hi>Holy Word</hi> reuealed to be the only sure remedie, and that by which he hath determined to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme his Church from Antichristian persecution, bondage and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ection.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>