<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable, SIR WIL∣LIAM CRA∣VEN Knight, Lord Mayor of the Augu∣stious Citty of LON∣DON, and the flow∣er of all Noble-minded Mer∣chants. &amp; SIR IOHN ARNOT Knight, Lord Prouost of the Royall City of EDINBVRGE, and Collector of the Crowne-rents of Scot∣land. All desirable Felicity.</title>
           <author>Maxwell, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120331_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07312</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17700</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120331</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable, SIR WIL∣LIAM CRA∣VEN Knight, Lord Mayor of the Augu∣stious Citty of LON∣DON, and the flow∣er of all Noble-minded Mer∣chants. &amp; SIR IOHN ARNOT Knight, Lord Prouost of the Royall City of EDINBVRGE, and Collector of the Crowne-rents of Scot∣land. All desirable Felicity.</title>
                 <author>Maxwell, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden art, or The right way of enriching : Comprised in ten rules, proued and confirmed by many places of holy Scripture, and illustrated by diuers notable examples of the same. Very profitable for all such persons in citie or countrie, as doe desire to get, increase, conserue, and vse goods with a good conscience. By I.M. Maister in Arts</title>
                 <author>Maxwell, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Leake, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 213, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Right Honourable,</hi> SIR WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM CRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN Knight, Lord Mayor of the <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stious</hi> Citty of LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON, and the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all Noble-<hi>minded Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</hi> &amp; SIR IOHN ARNOT Knight, Lord Prouost of the <hi>Royall</hi> City of EDINBVRGE, and Collector of the Crowne-rents <hi>of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> All desirable Felicity.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> BEING of late in reuoluing and reuiewing the confused Masse of mine vnpolished pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, among mine other exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and essayes, I found the proiect and platforme, of this present Art: and hauing taken some paines about the polishing and finishing thereof, I was loath it should perish, or yet lye any longer shut vp in the obscure corner of a cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. And therefore partly presuming, and partly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that it might do some good, vnto such as labour,
<pb facs="3"/>
either to get goods with a good conscience, or to vse their goods already gotten in a good and godly manner, I was somuch the more willing to set it out to publicke veiw. And because it was mine hap to prosecute my stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and to run my Philosophicall course in the Noble Citty of <hi>EDINBVRGE,</hi> whereby my small capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city hath herein been furthered; and my fortune to write and finish this present Arte in this famous Citty of <hi>LONDON,</hi> where now I liue: therefore I thought it my duty to dedicate the same vnto the foresaid two most Honourable Citties of this Ile, and that for a testimony of mine obseruancy, and gratefull affection towards them both; Being somuch the more moued to implore and imploy their honourable patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage therein, as for because that the subiect thereof doth especially concerne Citties and Citizens, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all such in Citty or country as labour to be rich in the right way. In it truely is contained whatsoeuer thing the Sacred Scripture dispersedly doth afford concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pouerty and riches, and the vertues and vices which are incident or conuersant about the same. Out of the which holy Booke, I haue collected the whole rules reasons, probations, and exemplifications of this Arte, and therfore I haue not amplyfied nor enlarged my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, as I might haue done with the forraine stuffe of humane testimonies, and that for these three reasons. First because that the holy Scripture beeing diligently searched is no lesse-sufficient to shew a man the right way of <hi>Enriching,</hi> then it is of <hi>Beleeuing;</hi> &amp; that the reasons and testimonies thereof are of vncontroullable authority. Secondly because I did foresee how that this Arte by such enlarging would arise to such a volume,
<pb facs="3"/>
that it should bee both hardly reade ouer of rich men, who haue too little time to peruse large bookes, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compassed or got of poore men, who haue too little money to buy big bookes. And lastly, because it is my purpose, God willing, to discourse both Theologically, and Philosophically, in the Arte of <hi>Flying,</hi> how that no lesle then these ten Schoolemaisters, <hi>1. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God; 2. The glorious Angels; 3. The holy Pen-men of sacred Scripture, Prophets and Apostles; 4. The reuerend Doctors of the Church; 5. The wise Philosophers of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; 6. The Worlds frame in the Heauens, Starres, and Elements, 7. The Fowles of the Aire; 8. The Fishes of the Sea; 9. The Beasts of the Field; 10. And the creeping things of the earth,</hi> do all of them coniunctly concurre to teach <hi>Man,</hi> how to become a <hi>Bird</hi> of <hi>Paradise;</hi> that is to say, how to flie from all <hi>vices,</hi> to all opposite <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues:</hi> Accept therefore, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> in good worth, in the name of your foresaid two flourishing <hi>Citties</hi> the <hi>Golden Arte of Enriching,</hi> such as it is, being the first Arte that euer was written vpon this subiect, yea, and the first Arte, that euer was ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally written in the common language of this most noble Ile, and as I suppose the first booke, that euer did beare this Vnionall kind of Dedication. Grace it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with your fauourable visage, and guarde it with your worthy patronage, So shall it bee secured vnder your shadow, and I encouraged to offer, God-willing, one day, vnto the honour of these your two most Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Sister-citties,</hi> our <hi>IAMES ANNA,</hi> that is, the patterne of a perfite Citty. That which resteth is my
<pb facs="4"/>
thrise hearty wish vnto God, who hath planted peace in your Borders,<note place="margin">Psal. 147.13.14.</note> strengthned your gates, and satisfied you with the floure of wheate, that it would be his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pleasure, to crowne you more and more with all kind of Spirituall and Temporall blessings, that your <hi>Sonnes</hi> may be as the plants,<note place="margin">Psal. 144.12.13.14.</note> growing vp in their youth, and your <hi>Daughters</hi> as the corner-stones grauen after the similitude of a Palace,<note place="margin">Psal. 65.9.10.11.12.13.</note> that your corners may be ful, and abounding with diuers sortes, and the furrowes of your fieldes may be made soft with showers, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with fatnesse. That your pastures may be replenished with dewy grasse, and clad with sheepe, bringing forth thousands in your Territories, together with kine sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth the soft streames of sweet milke, and likewise with oxen strong to labour your land. That your vallies may be couered with corne,<note place="margin">Psal. 132.15. Zach. 9.17.</note> and your trees and orchards loaden with fruite; so that your <hi>Poore</hi> may be satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with bread, and your <hi>Yong-men</hi> and <hi>Maids</hi> for ioy may shoute and sing.<note place="margin">Psal 144 14.</note> That there be no inuasion from without, nor sedition from within, nor no crying in your streetes,<note place="margin">Isay 23.58.</note> and circumiacent townes. That your <hi>Merchants</hi> may be as Princes, and your <hi>Chapmen</hi> and <hi>Shopmen</hi> as the Nobles of the earth, that they may be rich in godlinesse and in good workes, no lesse then in gold and in goods, ready to distribute and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.18.19.</note> laying vp in store for themselues a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation against the time to come, that they may obtaine eternall life.<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21.25. &amp; 23.1.2 3.6.7.8.9. Deut 1.13.16.17. 2. Chron. 19.5.6.7.</note> That your <hi>Lawyers, Iustices,</hi> and <hi>Iudges</hi> may be replenished with wisdome, &amp; vnderstanding in the Law, &amp; with conscionablenesse and courage in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the good cause, and in doing of Iustice and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without respect of persons, or yet of reward.
<pb facs="4"/>
That your Preists may be clothed with saluation,<note place="margin">Psal. 132.16. Malach. 2.7. Mat. 5.14.15.16. Deut. 32.5. Philip. 2.15.</note> that their lips may preserue knowledge, and that they may shine as lightes by their sound instruction and sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conuersation in the middes of the blind and naughty multitude of sinnefull and earthly minded men. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, that it would please his Diuine clemency alwaies to rescue <hi>Dauid</hi> his seruant, and to shew his saluation and word more and more vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> our Soueraigne,<note place="margin">Psal. 61.6.7, &amp; 91, 14, 15, 16, &amp; 144, 10, 11, &amp; 147.19, Hosh, 14, 6, 7, 8.</note> to satisfie him with long life, and to make his yeares as many ages, to be with him in trouble, to amplifie his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, and to increase his glory in the sight of all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that hee may grow as the Lillie, and fasten his rootes in <hi>Albion,</hi> as the trees of <hi>Lebanon.</hi> That his branches may spread, and his beauty may be as the oliue tree, and his smell as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that they that dwell vnder his shadow may flourish as the vine, and that the sent of <hi>Albion</hi> may be as the wine of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> That so a blessed <hi>Princes</hi> blessed <hi>People</hi> may goe on from blessednesse to blessednesse, and thus blessed may alwaies blesse him, who is the blesser of you both, euen he whose name is <hi>Iehouah,</hi> who will blesse you in this life, with temporall and spirituall prosperity and crowne you after this life with eternall felicity.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>And thus I rest an earnest louer
<hi>Of your Lordships, and your honourable Citties honour, IAMES MAXVVELL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>