<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To those Honoured, Noble, and right Vertuous Friends, my Visi∣tants in the Marshalsey: And to all other my vnknowne Fauourers, who either priuately, or publikely wished me well in my imprisonment.</title>
           <author>Wither, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120366_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68914</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25911</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To those Honoured, Noble, and right Vertuous Friends, my Visi∣tants in the Marshalsey: And to all other my vnknowne Fauourers, who either priuately, or publikely wished me well in my imprisonment.</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iuuenilia. A collection of those poemes which were heretofore imprinted, and written by George wither</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 308, 313-387, 209 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="38"/>
   <pb facs="38"/>
   <head>To those Honoured, Noble, and right Vertuous Friends, my Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the <hi>Marshalsey:</hi> And to all other my vnknowne Fauourers, who either priuately, or publikely wished me well in my imprisonment.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Friends; you whose vertues made me first in loue with <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;</hi> and whose worths made mee be thought worthy of your loues: I haue now at last (you see) by Gods assistance, and your encouragement, run through the <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie</hi> of imprisonment; and by the worthy
<pb facs="39"/>
fauour of a iust <hi>Prince,</hi> stand free againe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least touch of deiected basenesse. Seeing therefore I was growne beyond my <hi>Hope</hi> so fortunate (after acknowledgement of my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors loue, together with the vnequall'd Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of so gracious a Soueraigne) I was troubled to thinke, by what meanes I might expresse my thankefulnes to so many well-deseruing friends: No way I found to my desire, neither yet ability to performe when I found it. But at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering with my selfe what you were (that is) such, who fauour honesty for no second reason, but because you your selues are good; and ayme at no other reward, but the witnesse of a sound conscience that you doe well, I found, that thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse would proue the acceptablest present to sute with your dispositions; and that I imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned could be no way better expressed, then in manifesting your courtesies, and giuing consent to your reasonable demaunds. For the first, I
<pb facs="39"/>
confesse (with thankes to the disposer of all things, and a true gratefull heart towards you) so many were the vnexpected Visitations, and vnhoped kindnesses receyued, both from some among you of my Acquaintance, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnknowne Well-willers of my Cause, that I was perswaded to entertaine a much better conceit of the <hi>Times,</hi> then I lately conceyued, and assured my selfe, that <hi>Vertue</hi> had far more followers then I supposed.</p>
   <p>Somewhat it disturbed me to behold our ages Fauourites, whilst they frowned on my honest enterprises, to take vnto their protections the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregiousts fopperies: yet much more was my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, in that I was respected by so many of <hi>You,</hi> amongst whō there are some, who can and may as much dis-esteeme these, as they neglect me: nor could I feare their Malice or Contempt, whilst I enioyed your fauours, who (howsoeuer you are vnder-valued by Fooles for a time)
<pb facs="40"/>
shall leaue vnto your posterity so noble a memory, that your names shall be reuerenced by Kings, when many of these who now flourish with a shew of vsurped <hi>Greatnesse,</hi> shall eyther weare out of being, or dispoyled of all their patched re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, grow contemptible in the eyes of their beloued Mistris the <hi>World.</hi> Your <hi>Loue</hi> it is that (enabling me with patience to endure what is already past) hath made me also carefull bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to prepare my selfe for all future misaduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by bringing to my consideration, what the passion of my iust discontentments had almost quite banished from my remembrance.</p>
   <p>Further, to declare my thankefulnesse, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king apparant my willing minde to be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in any seruices of loue, which you shal thinke fit (though I want abilitie to performe great matters) yet I haue according to some of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, been contented to giue way to the printing of these <hi>Eglogues;</hi> which though it to many
<pb facs="40"/>
seeme a sleight matter, yet being well considered of, may proue a strong argument of my readinesse to giue you content in a greater matter: for they being (as you well know) begotten with little care, and preserued with lesse respect, gaue suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient euidence, that I meant (rather then any way to deceiue your trust) to giue the world occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of calling my discretion in question, as I now assure my selfe this will: and the sooner, because such expectations (I perceiue) there are (of I know not what Inuentions) as would have been frustrated, though I had employed the vtmost and very best of my endeauours.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding for your sakes, I haue heere aduentured once againe to make tryall of the Worlds censures: and what hath receyued <hi>beeing</hi> from your Loues, I here re-dedicated to your Worths, which if your noble dispositions will like well of; or if you will but reasonably respect what your selues drew mee vnto, I shall
<pb facs="41"/>
be nothing displeased at others cauils, but rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my selfe contented with your good opinions, scorne all the rabble of vncharitable detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors: For none, I know, will maligne it, except those, who eyther particularly malice my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or professe themselues enemies to my former Bookes; who (sauing those that were incensed on others speeches) as diuers of you (according to your protestations) haue obserued, are eyther open enemies of our Church; men notoriously guilty of some particular Abuses therein taxt, such malicious <hi>Critickes</hi> who haue the repute of being iudicious, by detracting from others; or at best, such Guls, as neuer approue any thing good, or learned, but eyther that which their shallow apprehensions can apply to the soothing of their owne opinions, or what (indeed rather) they vnderstand not.</p>
   <p>Trust me, how ill soeuer it hath been rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, my loue to my Country is inuiolate: my
<pb facs="41"/>
thankefulnesse to you vnfained, my endeauour to doe euery man good; all my ayme, content with honestie: and this my paines (if it may be so tearmed) more to auoid idlenesse, then for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of praise: and if notwithstanding all this, I must yet not onely rest my selfe content that my innocencie hath escaped with strict im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment (to the impayring of my state, and hinderance of my fortunes) but also be constray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to see my guiltlesse lines, suffer the despight of ill tongues: yet for my further encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let mee intreate the continuance of your first respect, wherein I shall find that comfort as will be sufficient to make mee set light, and so much contemne all the malice of my aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that readie to burst with the venome of their owne hearts, they shall see</p>
   <q>
      <l>My Minde enamoured on faire <hi>Vertues</hi> light,</l>
      <l>Transcends the limits of their bleared sight,</l>
      <l>And plac'd aboue their <hi>Enuy</hi> doth contemne,</l>
      <l>Nay, sit and laugh at, their disdaine, and them.</l>
   </q>
   <p>
      <pb facs="42"/>
But <hi>Noble Friends,</hi> I make question neyther of yours, nor any honest mans respect, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will no further vrge it, nor trouble your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: onely this Ile say, that you may not think me too well conceited of my selfe; though the <hi>Time</hi> were to blame, in ill requiting my honest endeauours, which in the eyes of the World de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued better; yet some what I am assured there was in me worthy that punishment, which when God shall giue me grace to see and amend, I doubt not but to finde that regard as will be fitting for so much merit as my endeauors may iustly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge. Meane while, the better to hold my selfe in esteeme with you, and amend the worlds opinion of <hi>Vertue,</hi> I will study to amend my selfe, that I may be yet more worthy to be called</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Friend, GEO: WITHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>