<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           <author>Lo, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Ba4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 <author>Lo, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE end of making <hi>Tables</hi> is not that thereby men might bee made <hi>Truants,</hi> but it is rather to <hi>helpe</hi> to those memories that are weake; or whose <hi>occasions</hi> are so great, as that they cannot intend to turne ouer such a <hi>Volume</hi> as <hi>this</hi> (though worth thy <hi>dayly</hi> and <hi>diligent reading</hi> and <hi>reuiewing.</hi>) For the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther benefiting of thy selfe therefore take to thee <hi>this Rule.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Where euer thou findest any <hi>Obseruation</hi> or <hi>Aphorisme,</hi> there (if thou wilt make any further vse) cast thine eyes on that which goes before, or followes after, and thou shalt finde it offering thee both excellent comfort, and a furthering of thine inuention, to the benefiting both of <hi>thy selfe,</hi> and <hi>others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And this I will promise thee further; that if God shall lend <hi>this Mellifluous Bernard</hi> of Our Times the time of <hi>perfecting His Contemplations,</hi> thou shalt haue in an other <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume</hi> as compleat a <hi>Table</hi> as <hi>this,</hi> for finding euery particular <hi>word</hi> or <hi>Sentence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And because there is feare on the <hi>Buyers</hi> part, that there shall bee still additions of his <hi>Contemplations,</hi> whereby he is discouraged from buying this <hi>Volume,</hi> let me assure thee that it is the <hi>Authors</hi> intention to set out no more parts thereof, vntill it riseth to a complete <hi>second Tome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But content thy selfe with <hi>this</hi> that thou hast, and pray to God with mee for the life and health of this <hi>Great Light,</hi> and <hi>shining Lampe</hi> of <hi>our Church,</hi> and I doubt not but he will giue good satisfaction vnto those that are industrious and ingenious. And so I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine as farre as thou wishest well to this Workman and his Labours, Ro. Lo.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="725"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>