<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and much ho∣nored Iohn Potham, Knight and Baronet, a poor Souldier wisheth all happines in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Mayeres, Randulfh</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120913_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07361</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17745</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120913</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and much ho∣nored Iohn Potham, Knight and Baronet, a poor Souldier wisheth all happines in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Mayeres, Randulfh</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mayeres his travels : containing a true recapitulation of all the remarkable passages which befell in the authors peregrination and voyages, as namely in these imployments following: viz. his 1 voyage for the wars in Ireland in Queen E.R. 2 At Breda, under one of the four English Colonell regiments. 3 With Count Mansfield. 4 To Cales. 5 To the Ile of Rhee. Wherunto is added a speech the author held with great King Hunger in his journey over the alpes. Collected and written by him who was both an actor, and an eye witnesse in the above named severall imployments, th space of forty yeeres, R.M.S. Gent. Published with license and authority</title>
                 <author>Mayeres, Randulph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harper, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 47, 1 page, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored</hi> Iohn Potham, <hi>Knight and Baronet, a poor Souldier</hi> wisheth all happines in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFULL,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is said that the silly <hi>Wren,</hi> the least of all Birds, takes her chiefest shelter under the <hi>Eagles</hi> wings, and that the Princely <hi>Vnicorne</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
delighting in Musick would stand stil to heare (after the sweet singing <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomela</hi> had sounded out her melodious and silver sounding tunes) the poore <hi>Thrush</hi> to warble out her chat, and so sometimes, that great <hi>Augustus</hi> (who made the VVorld to tremble) would vouchsafe to hear and read, the home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly work of a rustick Shepherd, aswell as the learned and lofty Verse of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill:</hi> All which imboldneth me (poor Vassall) to dedicate this poore Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, being the tragicall discourse of my lives Catastrophe to your noble selfe, Verse I dare not call, neither prose; it is but a poor, plain, brief and true rehersall of my disasters in that little service and poore travell that I have undergone, being the space of forty yeares: Beseeching your noble
<pb facs="3"/>
selfe, to be the <hi>Eagle,</hi> to shelter this my poore <hi>Wren</hi>-like worke, under the shadow of your loving wings; and to heare the <hi>Rurall</hi> tune of a poore Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticke Souldier clattering in an Iron coat, aswell as <hi>Orpheus</hi> with his dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Musick, clad in a Peacock coloured sute, singing out his delighting Sirens songs more then <hi>Philomela</hi> like, and as <hi>Augustus</hi> to daigne to looke down so low, as to take the view of tragicall discourse of a poor souldiers unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate passages, as the thrice noble verse of learned <hi>Spenser, Draiton,</hi> and their fellows: happy shall I think my selfe, if you will not be displeased at my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, but much more happy shal I bee, if your Worship will but give my poor widows mite your kind and favourable acceptance: I hope the
<pb facs="4"/>
better, in regard I found your favour once in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> being utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, being then (as I am still) very poore, it was not then, nor is not now for any gift I sought or seek more then your noble and loving countenance, and respect. Thus will I rest, leaving your noble self to the Lords protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and my self and my poore Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe to the VVorlds view, and sharpe censure of many viporous and malignant tongues.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all service, RANDULFH MAYERES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>