<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN APOSTROPHE OF THE TRAN∣slatour to his Authour Persius.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120195_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09495</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19778.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120195</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN APOSTROPHE OF THE TRAN∣slatour to his Authour Persius.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Aulus Persius Flaccus his Satires translated into English, by Barten Holyday Mr of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Persius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_note">
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <head>AN APOSTROPHE OF THE TRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slatour to his Authour <hi>Persius.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>THou art Redeem'd; Nor has the Fate of Time</l>
      <l>And Vice seiz'd on thy glory. The Worst crime</l>
      <l>Which does o'recloud the Guilty, addes to Thee</l>
      <l>A Lustre, which out shines obscurity.</l>
      <l>Who thought not, that the Great-borne Spirit of <hi>Rome</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Had lien o'rewhelm'd in her Last <hi>Brutus</hi> tombe?</l>
      <l>Yet did it Not: but did at last bring forth</l>
      <l>Thee, the Example of her Ancient worth.</l>
      <l>Jn whom, had <hi>Vesta's</hi> fire by which <hi>Rome</hi> Stood</l>
      <l>Beene out, there might haue yet beene found as good.</l>
      <l>Mount then, thou purer fire, and let thy heate</l>
      <l>Strongly exhale from their infectious seate</l>
      <l>Th' envenom'd fogges of vice; And then inflame</l>
      <l>Them, that they may be lights to their Owne shame;</l>
      <l>Which, as a Comet, may affright the earth</l>
      <l>With horror, at its owne prodigious birth;</l>
      <l>And, with its darting taile threatning dread</l>
      <l>Vengeance, point-out to wrath each guilty head.</l>
      <l>Bee thou the <hi>Vestall</hi> fire, thy Priest Ile bee,</l>
      <l>And consecrate my vigilance to Thee.</l>
      <l>Bee thou th' enlifening Sunne, Ile bee the Earth,</l>
      <l>And offer vp to Thee this gratefull birth</l>
      <l>Of thankes: which thus now giv'n, though straight it Die,</l>
      <l>Jt has liv'd Ages in its Infancie.</l>
      <l>Action, not Time, does number age. Who giues</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="35"/>A iust praise to great Vertues Patrone, liues</l>
      <l>Himselfe by his iust Gratitude. Let Spight</l>
      <l>Then doe its worst, and with eternall night</l>
      <l>Labour to clowd my name. Obscure to lie</l>
      <l>With Vertue, is an immortalitie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>THis lash has but <hi>Sixe</hi> knots: but see thou mend;</l>
      <l>Or <hi>peradventure</hi> Else I shall intend.</l>
      <l>(Although my Angry <hi>Muse</hi> saies Shee will bee</l>
      <l>No more thus Wit-bound, thus Tongue-tied, not Shee)</l>
      <l>To come in Fury; and thee Naked strippe;</l>
      <l>And Scourge thee with a <hi>Sixteene</hi>-knotted whippe.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>