<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE Right Honorable, THE OPHILVS, Lord Clinton, EARLE of Lincolne, And to the vertuous, and Right Honorable, the Lady BRIDGET his wife.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120118_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15575</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25842</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120118</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE Right Honorable, THE OPHILVS, Lord Clinton, EARLE of Lincolne, And to the vertuous, and Right Honorable, the Lady BRIDGET his wife.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Abels offering. Or The earely, and most accepted sacrifice of a Christian : Shewing how soone every soule is bounde to begin, &amp; betake himself, not only to the true, but also to the timely service of God. A sermon preached at Hamburg in November 1617. and now published at the instant entreaty of a godly Christian. By Iohn Wing (then) pastor to the English church, there</title>
                 <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nolck (Nolick), Marten Abrahamsz van der</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Flushing</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 73, 70-71, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> THE OPHILVS, Lord <hi>Clinton,</hi> EARLE of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> And to the <hi>vertuous,</hi> and Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> BRIDGET his wife.</head>
   <head type="sub">AND TO The Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> WILLIAM, Lord <hi>Say,</hi> and <hi>Seale,</hi> with the <hi>Vertuous</hi> and Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> ELISABETH his wife.</head>
   <head type="sub">IOHN WING A poore vnworthy <hi>Minister</hi> of Iesus Christ, wisheth all increase of all true <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>happines,</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>men.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight <hi>honorable Lords,</hi> and <hi>Ladyes,</hi> I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe it shall not be any way distastefull, or vnpleasing to your <hi>honours,</hi> that a <hi>stranger</hi> is bolde to salute you, from <hi>beyonde the seas,</hi> and to publish your <hi>names,</hi> there, where your <hi>persons</hi> may be as vnknowne to <hi>others;</hi> as <hi>myne</hi> is to your <hi>selves.</hi> I have not presumed on this <hi>double dedication</hi> without all reason; for why? it is <hi>famously</hi> knowne, that you are the <hi>worthy</hi> examples of this subject, wherof I <hi>here</hi> treat. And I cannot but thinke, that they are the <hi>fittest Patrones</hi> of divine bookes, whome God hath made, the <hi>faithfull Patternes</hi> of the doctrine contayned in them. It is <hi>long</hi> since I have heard of your <hi>early,</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> proceedings in piety. Having <hi>now</hi> this opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, I could not <hi>longer</hi> contayne in silence, but resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="3"/>to place you in the <hi>beginning</hi> of this litle booke, that they which reade, seeing such <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>noble</hi> presidents, of the practise <hi>herein</hi> pressed, might have the more <hi>powerfull jnducements,</hi> to draw them, to doe the same. The <hi>Lord</hi> of heaven, keepe you <hi>all,</hi> in your most <hi>holy</hi> course, &amp; bring you to the <hi>end</hi> of this happy <hi>race,</hi> that every of <hi>you</hi> may, (after all <hi>honorable falici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes</hi> enjoyed on earth) posesse those <hi>infinite,</hi> and endles glories, prepared, for all that love his name, in whome I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>FLVSHING. <date>the 30. of October 1621.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours <hi>Honours</hi> in all service, for the <hi>honour</hi> of God. IOHN WING. <hi>Pastor</hi> to the <hi>English</hi> church, at <hi>Flushing</hi> in ZEELANT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>