<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christian, and faithfull Reader.</title>
           <author>Northbrooke, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120959_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08335</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18663</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120959</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christian, and faithfull Reader.</title>
                 <author>Northbrooke, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Spiritus est vicarius Christi in terra. A breefe and pithie summe of the Christian faith : made in fourme of a confession, vvith a confutation of the papistes obiections and argumentes in sundry pointes of religion, repugnaunt to the Christian faith: made by Iohn Northbrooke, minister and preacher of the worde of God. Seene and allowed, according to the order appointed in the Queenes iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Northbrooke, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Williamson, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 143, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>¶ To the Christian, and faithfull Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignoraunte (gentle reader) howe daungerous an enterprise it is, in this our age, either to write, or diuulgate any woorke abroade: consideryng the furious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of certaine snuffyng detractours in the worlde, and bityng zoilous persones at home,<note place="margin">
         <hi>August.</hi>
      </note> would make one like <hi>Augustines</hi> counsaile, that saieth: <hi>Tutior est discentis, quam docentis conditio.</hi> More safe is the condition of the learner,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10▪ 11.12.13. <hi>Wisd.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.7. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> then of the teacher. For it is no marueile, sithe that pernitious and hurtfull step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame (of Uertue) Disdaine, and Enuie, continually putteth in her foote, to hinder and let euery honest enterprise. How hard a thyng it is, and what greate impedimentes, and lettes there are to enterprise any acte, not onely daiely experience suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declareth: but also that Prouerbe confirmeth it, whiche saieth, that all thynges are hearde whiche are faire and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. For assuredly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2.1.</note> there is no condition without his enemie: no calling without some temptation, no estate sure and cleare. Therfore, the estate of man, so much the more is to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, how muche the lesse it is regarded, woulde make a godlie harte to muse much and oftentimes, how he might be a fruict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and painfull labourer in Goddes Uineyarde.</p>
   <p>Therefore, what soeuer the wicked shall saie of me, I will saie with Dauid,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 109.4.</note>
      <hi>Detrahebant mihi: ego autem orabam:</hi> For my frendship thei were myne enemies: but I gaue my self vnto praier. After that I had ended this my booke, it happened by Goddes prouidence (gentle reader) that in a Lecture of myne, at Redclif in Bristoll, I had occasion giuen me by the text, whiche was taken out of the .xxxj. Psalme (where Dauid commendeth his spirite into the handes of God) to proue that all the soules of the righteous, that died before Christes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng in the fleshe, were in heauen, and not in any Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Limbo, or Hell. That christes soule should not néede to goe
<pb facs="9"/>
downe thither to fetch them out. And also declared that Christ vsed the like woordes vpon the Crosse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.46.</note> by whiche is declared, that his soule (departyng from his bodie) wente straight into heauen, and not into hell, the place of the dampned: But that the efficacie, vertue, and power of his death and passion, did pearce through and into the verie hell it self, by his diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Godheade:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. <hi>Colo.</hi> 1.13.14 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.24.25. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.13.</note> that all the damned soules, felt their full paine, and iuste damnation for their infidelitie: And Sathan hym self, felt all the power, and strength of his tyrannie, and darkenesse, was weakened, vanquished, and fallen to ruine and vtter decaie. &amp;c. And that the soules of all them that died in the faithe of Christe (beyng in heauen) felte the fulnesse of their redemption:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.30.</note> how it was now fullie perfected, and ended for them. &amp;c. This beyng by me taught, it was noysed abroade in the peoples eares (and that by no meane men) that I hadde denied an article of the <hi>Creede,</hi> and that I was an open here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and suche a one as was not worthie of life, but cruell death.</p>
   <p>When those reportes, and false rumours came vnto mine eares, I besought God to strengthen me in his faith, and giue me pacience,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Actes.</hi> 24.14.</note> knowyng well, that after the waie (which they call heresie) so worship I, and teache the God of my fathers: beleuyng all thynges whiche are written in the lawe and the Prophetes. I also considered with my self, what will this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple saie and reporte, when as thei shall happen to reade my booke, wherein this article of Christes deseension into hell, is handeled, that thus beginne to condemne and iudge me, before they haue knowen or heard the trueth opened: vpon the occasion whereof, I cleane altered my former preface to the reader, that I had made before, &amp; made this as an apologie or defence thereof, against suche as will, or shall carpe against it. Wherefore, I beseche thee (frendly reader) to lende me thy eares, to heare me, thy eyes to see me, thy tongue to reade me, thy mynde and harte to iudge me, with an vpright iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, accordyng to the truthe of Goddes woorde: whiche (as Dauid saith) is a Lanterne vnto our féete,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.105. <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.7.8.9.10.11.</note> and a light vnto our pathes: that is it that giueth wisedome vnto the simple, it is
<pb facs="9"/>
that,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Wisd.</hi> 10.21.</note> that giueth lighte vnto the eyes, by it the seruaunte of God is made circumspecte: our Sauiour Christe willeth vs to searche the scriptures,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Actes.</hi> 17.11.</note> for those are thei that beare witnesse of hym. For, the mynde muste bee taught, and instructed of the will of God, by the woorde, like as the eyes are taughte, and instructed by outwarde thynges.<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. de doctr. christia. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 37.</note> For as <hi>Augustine</hi> saieth: <hi>Titubat fides, si diuinarum scripturarum vacillat authoritas.</hi> If the aucthoritie of the holie scriptures wauer, then dooeth faithe stumble.</p>
   <p>I will nowe (accordyng to my small skill) saie of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, somewhat more largely, then I haue saied alreadie in my booke: whether sufficient, or insufficient, I shall praie thee to stand an indifferent iudge. To thee it is dedicated: and for thy sake it is written. Here must I saie vnto thée, euen as <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> somtime said to his reader in the like case:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. aduer. error. Iohan. Hierosoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitani.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Quaeso lector, vt memor Tribunalis domini, &amp; de iuditio tuo, te intelligēs iudicandū, nec mihi, nec aduersario meo faueas: neue personas loquentiū, sed cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam consideres</hi>: That is: I beseche thee, good reader, that, remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryng the iudgement seate of the Lorde, and vnderstandyng, that as thou iudgest, so thou shalt bee iudged, thou fauour nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther me, nor myne aduersarie: And that thou regarde not the persons, but the cause onely.</p>
   <p>Firste, thou shalte vnderstande (gentle reader) that this Article of Christes descendyng into helle, is not reade (as <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finus</hi> saith) in the <hi>Romaine Crede,</hi> nor yet in the <hi>Nicen Crede,</hi> the Easte Churche had it not, the Counsaile of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> and <hi>Constantinople</hi> left it out. For, wee maie reade by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges of the olde Fathers, that that parte whiche is reade in the <hi>Crede,</hi> was not in olde tyme so muche vsed in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (yet I doe confesse it is a necessarie article, meete to haue a place in the <hi>Crede,</hi> as a thyng that conteineth a verie profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble misterie of a waightie matter.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cyprian in Symbo. expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitio.</hi>
      </note>) Sainct <hi>Cyprian</hi> vnto this saieth: <hi>Sciendum sane est, quod in Ecclesia Romana, Symbolo non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur additū, descendit ad inferna. Sed neque in Orientis ecclesiis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur hic sermo.</hi> Knowe ye for certaintie, that the Churche of Rome hath not added this in the <hi>Crede,</hi> he descended into hel: No, neither yet the Easte Churches hath added this kynde of
<pb facs="10"/>
speache (in the <hi>Crede.</hi>) Unto this <hi>Erasmus</hi> fullie agreeth, sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng: <hi>Atque adeo quum Symbolum Nicenae,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Erasmus in Symbolum cathechesis.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>sine Constantinopolitanae Synodi, nihil aliud sit, quam huius Symboli explanatio, ne illic quidem quicquam est, quod huic particulae respondeat. Ipsa deni{que} inconcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas sermonis arguit ab alio quopiam intertextum emblema:</hi> That is, Moreouer, although the Simbole, or <hi>Crede,</hi> of the Sinode hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Nice,</hi> or the Sinode holden at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> is none other thyng, then a declaration of this Simbole, or <hi>Crede</hi> (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Apostles <hi>Crede</hi>:) yet there is not so much as any thyng that is correspondent to this particle. Finallie, the verie incō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnitie, and vnhandsome ioyning, or hanging together of the speache and oration, is an euident argumente, that this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, or particle (he descended into hell) was put in among the other Articles, by some other man. (As is supposed by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas of <hi>Aquine</hi>) and immediately after, he sheweth the cause, why the auncient fathers put not this Article into the <hi>Crede,</hi> (he descended into hel.<note place="margin">
         <hi>In eodē loco.</hi>
      </note>) <hi>Quia vetustissimi patres magna Religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> cauebant, ne quid asseuerarent duntaxat in Symbolo, quod non esset e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidenter expressum in sacris literis vtriusque testimenti: Tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> sunt ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuli omnes, hoc vno excepto:</hi> That is, because the fathers of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientest tyme, with great Religion, toke heede &amp; were war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that thei would not affirme any thyng, namely in the <hi>Crede,</hi> whiche was not expressed in the Scriptures of bothe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Suche maner Articles are all the other, onely this one (he descended into hell) excepted. Thus farre <hi>Erasmus.</hi> Sainct <hi>Augustine</hi> in his booke, <hi>de Fide &amp; Symbolo,</hi> expoundyng the <hi>Crede</hi> of the Apostles,<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>de &amp; Symbo. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> comming to the Article of Christes sufferynges, declareth of his pacience, and humilitie in suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng death, euen the death of the Crosse, to take awaie the horror of death from vs: and that he was crucified and buried, vnder <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> addyng <hi>Pilates</hi> name for the certaintie of the tyme, and that he laie in a graue, and before that in the wombe of his mother, in whiche graue and bellie, neuer none laie before, nor after. &amp;c. But of this article of Christes descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into hell, he neuer speaketh worde of it, nor yet reciteth it: for if it had been an Article putte in the <hi>Crede</hi> at the firste, would sainct <hi>Augustine</hi> haue left it out thinke you, or at least▪
<pb facs="10"/>
neuer to haue spoken woorde of it in this place, hauyng suche an occasion, and oportunitie as he had in entreatyng of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife? I can neuer beleue that, for of al the old writers, he was moste precise, and vigilante in suche poinctes of Religion that touched faithe. So that it must euidently appeare, that it was putte in by some aftercommers, as <hi>Erasmus</hi> before hath saied. Whereby we maie vnderstande, the care of the godlie ones then, that woulde not putte foorth, or affirme any thyng, whiche could not bee proued by the Scriptures. So <hi>Hierome</hi> saieth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> psal.</hi> 98.</note>
      <hi>Omne quod loquimur, debemus affirmare de scripturis sanctis:</hi> What soeuer we affirme, we must proue it by the holie scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For <hi>Augustine</hi> saieth: <hi>Sine scripturarum autoritate: nihil definiendum est.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>August. in epist.</hi> 157.</note> Nothyng is to bee determined, or affirmed, without the aucthoritie of the holie and sacred scriptures. And likewise Saincte Paule saieth: Now is the righteousnesse of God made manifeste without the Lawe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21.</note> hauyng witnesse of the Lawe, and of the Prophetes. Whereby is gathered, that all truthe and righteousnesse of Gods Religion, and our faith in the redemption of his sonne, muste haue the witnesse of the Lawe and the Prophetes: that is to saie, the holie Scriptures will euer acknowledge and allowe it. And whereto it giueth no witnesse, that is alwaies false and erronious. For as sainct <hi>Hierome</hi> saieth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hiero. in Matth.</hi> 23.</note>
      <hi>Hoc quia ex sacris literis authoritatem non habet, eadem facilitate refellitur, qua probatur:</hi> Seyng this, saieth he (speakyng againste those Fathers, that did affirme, that that <hi>Zacharie</hi> whiche Christ spake of, beyng the sonne of <hi>Barachie,</hi> was <hi>Iohn Baptists</hi> father) hath no aucthoritie out of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it maie bee as easely denied, as affirmed. Therefore I saie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Actes.</hi> 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> searche the holy scriptures, as they of <hi>Berea</hi> did as cōcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng this matter in question: and yet thou shalte neuer bee able to finde there, that euer Christe our Sauiour, in bodie or soule, descended into hell after his death, to the place of the dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pned, or into any Limbo. Onely thou shalt finde there, that he died, and rose againe the thirde daie. &amp;c. Some will here replie and saie: What sir, you saie not truely? Are there not scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res sufficient to proue, he descended into hell? although there are sondrie places, yet there are fower principall places, as in
<pb facs="11"/>
the Psalmes, in Zacharie, in the Actes of the Apostles, and in Saincte Peters Epistle?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Actes.</hi> 2.31. 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.19.</note> I praie you saie thei, is it not wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Psalme thus? <hi>Non derelinques animam meam in infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no?</hi> I doe graunte it is so written, but it followeth not hereby to proue that his soule, or that Christes soule should goe vnto hell, the place of the damned: for soule in this place, doeth not signifie the soule of Christe, but it signifieth the bodie, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone of Christe: and by hell he vnderstandeth, not the place of the damned, but the graue or sepulchre, and therefore <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> translation hath, <hi>Non relinques corpus meū in sepulchro,</hi> thou shalte not leaue my bodie or persone in the graue: So hath the <hi>Tygurian</hi> translation also. For this Hebrue woorde, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pesch,</hi> signifieth a bodie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Leui.</hi> 21.1.11. <hi>Num.</hi> 9.10.</note> or person, as you maie reade in <hi>Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> and in <hi>Numeri.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Also, for this worde, <hi>Soule,</hi> in that place and many others, is taken for the whole naturall man: for we reade in <hi>Genesis,</hi> that all the soules that came with <hi>Iacob</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.26.</note> whiche came out of his loynes, were in the whole, thréescore and sixe foules: that is, thréescore and sixe persons or bodyes. And in the Actes it is sayde:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Actes.</hi> 2.41.</note> There were added to the Churche (by <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon) about thrée thousande soules:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20.</note> that is, thrée thousand persons. And so <hi>Peter</hi> vseth the same when he saith: Wherein fewe, that is, eight soules were saued in the water: that is, eight persons or bodyes S. <hi>Paul</hi> also vseth that worde, saying:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> Let euery soule be subiect vnto the higher powers. &amp;c. That is, let euery body or person be subiect. &amp;c. By this you may soone perceaue what <hi>Dauid</hi> meaneth by this word, soule: that it shoulde not lye in the graue for euer, but shoulde rise vp againe.<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ob.</hi> 19.20.</note> So <hi>Iob</hi> saieth, in matter one, although in other wordes, where he saieth: Though after my skinne, wormes destroy this body, yet I shall see God in my fleshe. As for this worde, Hell, it is taken in diuers significations in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ée in my booke, where I do intreate of this article: but in this place it signifieth not the place of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but the graue wherein he was buryed. So likewise, S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth expounde that worde (hell) saying: <hi>Vis tamen verbi eadem videtur esse in eo quod sepultu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> dicitur:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cypr. in Symbo.</hi>
      </note> That is, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit,
<pb facs="11"/>
there séemeth to be the same strength of the worde (hell) in that he is sayde to haue béen buryed.</p>
   <p>As for the place of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> where he saieth: Thou also shalt be saued through the blood of thy couenaunt:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11.</note> I haue loosed thy prisoners out of the pit wherein is no water, serueth litle and nothyng at all for the proofe of Christes descention into hell. For the Prophetes meanyng is in that place, that God saueth his Churche by the blood of Christe, whereof the blood of the sacrifices was a figure, and is here called the couenaunt of the Churche,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9.</note> which he did make with <hi>Abraham,</hi> promisyng vnto him, that all nations should be blessed in his séede, which is our sauiour Christ. And so <hi>Zacharie</hi> compareth the babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall ouerthrowe, (wherein the people was oppressed) to a drie pyt. So that he vnderstandeth by the prisoners, (not any soules in hell, but) the children and seruauntes of God, which were and are captiues vnder Sathan the deuyll, mans ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: who was prefigured before, by that cruell tyraunt <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao,</hi> and by the king of Babylon: And by the waterlesse pit, he vnderstandeth the goulfe of all miseries &amp; calamities, whence it is impossible for man to come out by any meanes: without the helping hande, and out stretched arme of Gods almightie power. And that you shall not thinke this to be of my owne exposition,<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. de ciuit. dei. lib.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 35.</note> I wyll shewe you what S. <hi>Augustine</hi> saith vppon this place: <hi>Alio loco ad ipsum Christum in spiritu Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ia loquens, de remissio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e peccatorum per eius sanguinem: Tu quo{que} inquit, in san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Testamenti tui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>misisti vinctos tuos de lacu in quo non est aqua. Quid per hunc locum velit intelligi, possunt diuersa sentiri etiam se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum rectam fidem. Mihi autem videtur non eo significari melius, nisi humanae miseriae si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cam profundi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atem quodammodo, &amp; sterilem, vbi non sunt fluentia iustitiae, sed iniquitatis lucum. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> hoc quippe lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> in psalmo dicitur: &amp; eduxit me de lacu miseriae, &amp; de lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mi:</hi> that is to saie: And in an other place, speakyng of the spirite of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie vnto Christe hym selfe, touchyng the remission of syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes through his blood: Thou also saieth he, hast through the blood of thy Testamente, lette the prisoners out of the pitte where no water is: what he will haue to bee vnderstanded by this lake, or pitte, men maie iudge many waies, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="12"/>
the right faithe. But I thinke, that nothyng can better bee vnderstanded by it, then the drie, and as it were the barraine profunditie of the depenesse of mans miserie, where the strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of righteousnesse are not, but the mudde of iniquitie. And of this pitte it is spoken in the Psalme:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 59.2.</note> and he hath (saieth he) broughte me▪ out of the pitte of miserie: and out of the myre and claie. Hitherto <hi>Augustine.</hi> Thus you may easely perceiue that this saiyng of the Prophete, nothyng appertaineth vnto the deade, whiche are alreadie deliuered from those miseries, that are signified by the waterlesse pitte: but vnto the liuyng. For he saieth directlie after. Turne you to the strong holde, ye prisoners of hope. Whiche woordes can not bee applied to the deade:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.12.</note> but to the liuyng onely. For, the Prophete biddeth them turne into the holie lande, where the citie and temple are, where God will defende them. Sainct <hi>Hierome</hi> therefore saieth, to all them that doe hang vpon bare wordes of the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures: <hi>Nec putemus in verbis scripturarum esse Euangelium,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hiero. in Epist. ad Gala. cap.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>sed in sensu: non in superficie, sed in medulla: non in sermonum folijs, sed in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice rationis.</hi> That is: Neither lette vs thinke that the Gospell cōsisteth in the wordes of the scriptures, but in the meanyng: not in the barke, but in the pithe: not in the leaues of wordes, but in the roote of the meanyng.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.20.</note> Peter cōfirmeth this, saiyng: So that ye first knowe this, that no prophecie in the scripture is of any priuate interpretation. Thus much as concernyng the place of the Prophete <hi>Zacharie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for the place in the Actes of the Apostles, what is saied aboue,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 2.30.</note> vpon the Psalme maie suffice: for that that was spoken by Dauid in the Psalme, was prophetically spoken of Christ, not that his soule should goe and preache, or bryng out any soule from hell, that was nothyng the Prophetes meanyng. But he prophecied there, onely of the death and resurrection of Christe.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 2.30.</note> For so dooeth saincte Peter open and expounde it, saiyng: Therefore, seyng he was a Prophete, and knewe that God had sworne with an othe to him, that of the fruicte of his loynes, he would raise vp Christe, concernyng the fleshe, to set hym vpon his Throne.<note place="margin">31</note> He knowyng this before, spake of the resurrection of Christe, that his soule (that is his person or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die)
<pb facs="12"/>
should not be left in graue: neither his fleshe should se cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Here note,<note place="margin">32</note> that where in one place he calleth it by the name of the soule, or bodie, immediately he nameth it fleshe. Thus you maie see howe one Scripture openeth another. So <hi>Hierome</hi> saieth: <hi>Moris scripturarum obscuris, manifesta subnectere:</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. in Esai. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>August. in lib.</hi> 83. <hi>questio. quest.</hi> 64.</note> It is the order of the scriptures, after harde thynges, to ioyne other thynges that bee plaine. Sainct <hi>Augustine</hi> also saith: <hi>Solet circumstantia scripturarum illuminare sententiam:</hi> The circumstaunces of the scriptures is wont to giue light, and to open the meanyng. M. <hi>Theodorus Beza,</hi> translateth that verse, <hi>Non derelinques animam meam in inferno,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Theodo. Beza. in Act.</hi> 2.</note> thus, <hi>Non relinques ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauer meū in sepulchro.</hi> For as he saith, <hi>Nequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> enim Petrus hic di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputat de animi immortalitate, sed de corporis resurrectione, ea{que} eius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi vt nulla praecesserit corruptio.</hi> Peter (faith he) doeth not here in this place, dispute of the immortalitie of the soule, but of the resurrection of Christes bodie, in suche maner that no corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could, or should, corrupte it. Againe he saieth: <hi>Dico igitur nunquam praetermissuros fuisse Euangelistas istiusmodi historiam des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>census animae Christi ad inferos,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>odē loco.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>&amp; arbitror (quod cum veterum pace dictum sit) somnia esse quacunque de hac re apud illos cōmemorantur:</hi> that is: Therefore I saie, that the Euangelistes would neuer haue ouer passed, or lette slippe (with silence) suche an historie of the descendyng of the soule of Christ into hell (if it had been so) and I iudge &amp; say (by the leaue of the auncient fathers) what soeuer of this matter thei haue written, or remembred amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geste them, to bee but dreames and phantasies. &amp;c. Therefore sainct <hi>Augustine</hi> giueth this counsaile:<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. de tempore. Serm.</hi> 145.</note>
      <hi>Nemo de Christo creda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, nisi quod dese credi voluit Christus:</hi> That is. Lette no man beleue more of Christe, then Christe hath willed thee to beleue. And this bee spoken as sufficiente for this present, vpon this place of the actes.</p>
   <p>Nowe lastly,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter</hi> 3.18.19.</note> is that place of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> where he saieth that Christ was put to death concernyng the flesh: but was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the spirite,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Erasmus</hi> is very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt vpon this place, but it seemeth that he well vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it not, for he saith in the margene it is, <hi>locus dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s. Caluin in com.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> by the which he also went, and preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the spirites that were in prison. Herevpon they blowe vp the Trumpet, but yet stay a litle, thou must note (gentle reader) that here is no mention made, <hi>Anima Christi,</hi> of the
<pb facs="13"/>
soule of Christe: but that he went, <hi>tantum spiritu,</hi> onely in his spirite. For as M. <hi>Caluin</hi> saieth: <hi>Sunt autem haec longe diuersa, animam Christi venisse, et Christum praedicasse spiritus sui potentia.</hi> These are (saith he) great differences (to say) that the soule of Christe to haue come: And (to say) Christe to haue preached by the power of his spirite. Nowe (friendly reader) here is the difficultie in these two wordes: <hi>Spiritus, &amp; carcer:</hi> the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and the prison. Understande that by this worde (spirite) is not meant nor taken in this place, for the soule of Christe: but for the power of his Godhead. For it was not his soule that was able to quicken him self, but the spirite of god quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him: that is, his godly and diuine power that quickned his humanitie. <hi>Paul</hi> openeth this very plainly to the <hi>Cor.</hi> saying: Christ was crucified concernyng his infirmitie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4.</note> yet liueth he through the power of God. &amp;c. Where <hi>Peter</hi> nameth it the spirite, <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it the power of God. And he calleth it the operation of God, which raysed (and quickned) him from the dead.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Coloss.</hi> 2.12.</note> And to the Romanes he shewth that the vertue of the spirite was not onely shewed in the person of Christe: but is shewed also vpon vs all, saying: If the spirite of him that ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vp Iesus from the dead,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</note> dwell in you: he that raysed vp Christ frō the dead, shall also quicken your mortall bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that his spirit dwelleth in you. By these places we may vnderstande what <hi>Peter</hi> meant by the spirite: that is, Gods diuine power and might, and not the soule of Christ.</p>
   <p>Nowe, in that <hi>Peter</hi> calleth it a prison, is not to be taken here,<note place="margin">The Greke worde signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth an high towre where watche is kept. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.</note> that he vnderstandeth by it, the place of hell for the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but he aludeth it to that place of <hi>Genesis,</hi> where it is sayde: <hi>Non permanebit spiritus meus in homine inaeternum, quia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro est:</hi> My spirite shall not striue with man, because he is but fleshe. So that it is a common phrase of speache in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that <hi>Peter</hi> here vseth, for the Prophete <hi>Esai</hi> hath the like saying:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isaiah.</hi> 42.7.</note>
      <hi>Vt aperires oculos caecorum, &amp; educeres de conclusione vinctum, de domo carceris sedentes in tenebris:</hi> That thou mayest open the eyes of the blinde, and bryng out the prisoners from the prison, and them that sit in darknesse out of the prison house.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isaiah.</hi> 29.9.</note> And in another place he saith: <hi>Vt dicetis his qui vincti
<pb facs="13"/>
sunt, exite: &amp; his qui in tenebris, reuelamini:</hi> That thou mayest say to the prisoners,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gala.</hi> 4.3.23.</note> go foorth: and to them that are in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, shewe your selues. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in a maner vseth the like phrase, saying: Before saith came, we were kept vnder the lawe, and shut vp vnto the faith, which should afterwarde be reuealed.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.1.</note> Our sauiour Christe vseth it often, where it is written: The spirite of the Lord is vpon me, because he hath annoynted me, that I should preache the Gospell to the poore: he hath sent me, that I shoulde heale the broken hearted, that I shoulde preache deliueraunce to the captiues, and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of sight to the blinde: that I shoulde set at libertie them that are bruised. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> him selfe, in the fourth Chapter folowing,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.6.</note> speaketh of this matter: but yet in other wordes, saying: For vnto this purpose was the Gospell preached also vnto the dead, that they myght be condemned accordyng to men in the fleshe: but myght lyue accordyng to God in the spirite: that is to say, the Gospell was preached (not to the dead bodyes in the graues, nor to the soules in hell) but to them of tyme past, which nowe are dead, to the entent that they might haue béen condemned, or dead vnto sinne in the fleshe, and might haue liued to God in the spirite: which two are the effect of the Gospell.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> And in his seconde Epistle, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them the worlde of the vngodly, saying: Neither hath spared the olde worlde, but saued <hi>Noe</hi> the eyght person, a preacher of righteousnesse, and brought in the flood vppon the worlde of the vngodly. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>So nowe, we may perceaue by the conference of those places, what <hi>Peter</hi> meaneth by the spirites that were in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, that are all those whiche were in the prison of sinne and death. &amp;c. For <hi>Peters</hi> onely purpose in this place is, to set foorth the vniuersall preaching of repentaunce, which was preached in the tymes of <hi>Noe</hi>: euen with the same open and vniuersall preachyng,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.5.</note> that was dooen in all the worlde, in the tyme of Christ the sonne of God, after his resurrection from the dead. For, the sonne of God did preache in the tyme of <hi>Noe,</hi> in the spirite: that is, by his spirituall preachyng of repentaunce, did call the spirites that were in prison, that is, those wicked men
<pb facs="14"/>
that were shutte vp in the prisone of wickednesse and synne, and for their synfulnesse, are worthie of death, and hell. So saieth <hi>Titleman,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Franciscus Titlemanus. Hesselensis in</hi> 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>Veniens ad illos incredulos homines, qui tunc in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrosa caligine errorum snorum iacebant demersi▪ veniens (inquam) spiritu, praedicauit eis ad poenitentiam reuerti, vt possent cum Noe sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uari, inspirando Prophetas &amp; Noe, qui ex ore domini populum a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis reuocare quaerebant</hi>: That is, Commyng to those vnbeleuyng men, whiche then did lye drowned in the darekenesse of their errours: Commyng (I saie) in spirite, did preache to them, to tourne to repentaunce, that thei might bee saued with Noe, inspiryng the Prophetes and <hi>Noe</hi>: did seeke to call the people backe from their euilnesse, by the mouthe of God. Also he set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth foorth the mercifull goodnesse, and long sufferaunce, in that he called theim to repentaunce by <hi>Noe,</hi> whiles the Arke was a preparing, by the space of a hundred and twentie yeres, whiche leuitie, goodnesse, and long sufferaunce of GOD they did despise,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.15.</note> and neglecte: for whiche the flood of Goddes ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce came vpon them, that were disobedient, in the tymes of <hi>Noe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The verie texte it self, plainly declareth that this expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is true. For if wee marke the woordes of the texte, as they lye in order,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.19.</note> it will soone open Peters whole meanyng. The wordes are these: But was quickened in the spirit: by whiche he also went, and preached vnto the spirites that were in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone (then immediately followeth what those spirites were) whiche (saieth he) were in time passed disobedient, when once the longe sufferyng of God abode. (Now he sheweth when it was) in the daies of <hi>Noe.</hi> (Then he declareth the tyme, and how long thei were disobediente) while the Arke was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng (saieth he.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.</note>) Which latter wordes maketh it plaine. For he saieth, he preached in the spirite, to the prisoners that were disobedient, while the Arke was a makyng. So that it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that those prisoners were a liue, at the makyng and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryng of the Arke. And duryng all that tyme of a 120. yeres, Christe preached to them in his spirite,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2.20.21.</note> by <hi>Noe</hi> the eight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, a preacher of righteousnesse, to tourne them from their synnes, and so bee saued. And because they would not, in their
<pb facs="14"/>
life tyme obey Gods worde: are cast now after their life, into iudgemente of hell fire, as wee haue saied before. And by the same argumente,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.20.</note> Peter goeth aboute to moue the Iewes, by their example, to bee obedient to Goddes callyng, that calleth theim by his spirite, through his Preachers and Ministers, by his long sufferaunce to repentaunce, and amendement of life, whiles thei are here in the earth. Otherwise, for their disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, nowe in their life tyme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.40. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13.20.</note> vnto the preachyng of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, shall be damned after this life, as thei are. Christe our Sauiour dooeth teache this plainely, at whose mouthe Peter learned this, that nowe he hath taughte in this Epistle to the Iewes: When as he spake of the ende of the worlde, saiyng: As the daies of <hi>Noe</hi> were, so likewise shall the commyng of the sonne of man be.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.37.38.39.42.44. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.26.</note> For, thei did eate and drinke, marrie, and giue in mariage, vnto the daie that <hi>Noe</hi> entred into the Arke: And knewe nothyng, till the floodde came and tooke them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, so also shall the commyng of the sonne of man bee. And then immediatly after, he giueth this cōmaundement to thē, saiyng: Wake therefore, for ye knowe not what houre your maister will come.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.33.</note> Therefore bee ye also readie: for in the houre that ye thinke not, will the sonne of man come. Nowe wee maie see, that all this is spoken to that ende, to moue vs by their example, to tourne from our synnes, and wicked life: and not to proue hereby,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.</note> that the soules of any of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before Christes commyng were in hell: and so Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes soule must fetche them out, whiche are but the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men. For so saieth <hi>Erasmus:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Erasmus in Symbolum.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Talia multa &amp; circa hanc adiecticiam particulam quidam commenti sunt, narrantes quos Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus abduxerit, quos ibi reliquerit, quae quibus ad singulos circulos sit loquutus. &amp;c:</hi> That is, Many suche maner of thinges haue cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine men imagined also, about this particle (he descended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell) whiche wee haue shewed to bee an addition to the <hi>Crede,</hi> tellyng what persones Christe did bryng from hell, and whom he did leaue there still, and what thynges: with what woordes he did speake to euery one of the Circles. &amp;c. Therefore he saieth: <hi>Tibi satis est profiteri Christum sic descendis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se ad inferos,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In eodē lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>quemadmodum sentit scriptura. &amp;c.</hi> It is sufficient for
<pb facs="15"/>
thée (saieth he) to professe that Christe did so descende to helle, as the scripture meaneth.</p>
   <p>For we muste vnderstande, Christ beyng from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, head, and gouernour of his Churche, came in the daies of <hi>Noe,</hi> not in body, which then he had not: but in spirite, and preached by the mouth of <hi>Noe</hi> to the disobediēt, which would not then repent: and therefore, nowe are reserued to the last iudgement. For <hi>Paul</hi> saieth, Iesus Christe, yesterday and to day,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.58. <hi>Ephe</hi> 2.20.21.22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.11. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</note> the same is also for euer: as if he woulde say, Christ was, and shall be the foundation of all his Church for euer. <hi>Peter</hi> also saith: The prophecie came not in olde time by the wyll of man: but holie men of God spake, as thei were moued by the spirite (of God). Wherevpon I saie, as the sonne of GOD did preache in his spirite, to theim that were in prisone (as Peter saith) that is,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.19.</note> to them that were then in the prison of their sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that thei should repent (as we haue before written) &amp; so be saued.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.26. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.7.8.13.</note> Euen so now, at this day, he is quickened in the spirite, and by the same spirite, continually doeth preache, and teache, by his ministers,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.12.13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.3. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Actes</hi> 2.36.37.38.39.40.41. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 18. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Hylarius. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Trinita.</hi>
      </note> vnto the worldes ende, to those people, that are in the prisone of synne, ignoraunce, and disobedience, to tourne them to the Lorde, that euery one that beleueth, maie bee saued. This is the verie meanyng of this place, therefore we muste not gather, or descante vpon bare wordes, and take them literally, as we liste: But wee must gather of the cause. For so saieth saincte <hi>Hillarie. Intelligentia dictorum, ex causis est assumenda dicendi, quia non sermoni res, sed rei est sermo subiectus.</hi> That is. The meanyng of woordes is to bee gathered, by the causes of the speakyng, for the matter is not subiecte to the worde:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Erasmus in Symbol.</hi>
      </note> but the worde to the matter. <hi>Erasmus</hi> saieth, that some came after, and seemed to gather out of the Scriptures, some sentences, whereto thei added some reasons. <hi>Non illas quidem adamantinas:</hi> But not those reasons (saieth he) verelie moste strong: but suche as are of no weighte. And after that he hath recited vp all the places that seme to make for Christes soule to haue descended into helle, the place of the dampned: he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, saiyng.<note place="margin">
         <hi>In eodē loco.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Verùm horum nihil est, quod cogat credere, Christi animam per se decendisse ad tartarum, si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, vt illi loquuntur, ad Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum.</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>
That is. There is none of all those aucthorities (of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) that maie constraine any to beleue, that the soule of Christe, wente doune by hym self personally to hell, or as thei call it, to <hi>Lymbum.</hi> Hereunto agreeth one <hi>Pampolitanus,</hi> that saieth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Richard. Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politanus in Symbo.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>In inferno igitur damnatorum pro peccato actuali, Christus non fuit, quia vt ipse dicit: inter vos &amp; nos chaos magnum statutum est &amp;c. Sicut enim coelum Empyrium est locus gloria: Ita infernus est lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus aeterne poenae. Sicut ergo damnatus non potest ascendera coelum Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyrium: Ita nullus saluatus potest descendere in locum damnatorum:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.26.</note>
      <hi>ergo neque Christus.</hi> That is to saie. In the hell of the dampned, for actuall synne committed, Christe was not, for because he saieth: Betwene you &amp; vs there is a great goulfe set. &amp;c. For, as the Emperiall heauen is a place of glorie: So hell is a place of extreme paine and punishemente. Therefore, as the damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned cannot ascende into the Emperiall heauen: So none of the saued,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Wisd.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3. <hi>wisd.</hi> 3.1.2.3.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> can descende into the place of the dampned: Therefore, muche lesse Christ. By whiche testemonies it is plaine, agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the worde of God, that Christes soule, after his death, neuer wente doune to helle the place of the dampned, or into any <hi>Lymbum</hi>: but it went directly into heauen, as he did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende it vpon the Crosse.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The reason that moueth men to iudge, that his soule wēt into helle, is, for that thei supposed all the soules of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, before Christes commyng, wente doune to helle. And of this grosse iudgemente was saincte <hi>Augustine, Origene, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Chrisostome, Gregorie, Folengius.</hi> &amp;c. And therefore, thei affirmed that Christes soule did fetche out <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eue, Abel, Seth, Noe, Abraham, Isaac, Iacob. &amp;c.</hi> Howe farre wide all thei were, from the truthe herein, it maie easely appere by the sacred Scriptures. For there it is fullie expressed, that the Churche of Christ did beginne, frō the creation of the worlde and from the firste righteous man that euer was, and that it shall continue, and indure vnto the laste daie, for euer. For, the Churche of the Patriarkes and Prophettes, that haue been before Christes commyng, is all one, with the Churche of his Apostles and Euangelistes: and the faithfull of the olde Testamente: and the faithfull of the newe, are all one people
<pb facs="16"/>
and one Churche:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6.</note> thei haue had all one God, one Christe, and the very same promises. Thei haue had all one spirite of faith, and haue all eaten of one spirituall foode,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3.4.</note> and drunke of one spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall drinke, with vs. So saieth <hi>Leo. Misteria pro temporum ratione variata sunt,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Leo de natti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate domi. Serm.</hi> 3.</note> quū fides, qua viuimus nulla fuerit aetate diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa:</hi> That is. Their Sacramentes, by reason of the tyme were diuerse, when as the faithe, by the whiche wee all liue, in no age was diuerse.<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. in Ioh. tract.</hi> 26.</note> So saieth saincte <hi>Augustine</hi> likewise. <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēta illa fuerunt in signis diuersa, in rebus quae significabātur pariae:</hi> that is: Their Sacramentes in outward signes, were diuerse (from oures) but as concernyng the thynges whiche thei did signifie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. de utilitate poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niton. cap.</hi> 1.</note> are equall, and one (with oures.) <hi>Tunc Christus ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, modo Christus venit, venturus: &amp; venit: diuersa verba sunt: sed idem Christus.</hi> That is: Then was, Christ shall come: nowe is, Christ is come. Shall come, and is come, are sundrie wordes: But Christe is all one, wherevpon I maie well conclude, that all the faithfull, in the olde Testament: and the faithfull in the newe, haue had, and haue now: but one place of reste, and ioy, to bee receiued in after their life.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Chrisost. in Lucā. Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>Hom.</hi> 15.</note>
      <hi>Chrisostome</hi> herein saieth: That the bosome of Abraham, was vnto the poore Lazarus, Paradise, or heauen. Some wil replie (saieth he) in Paradise: but I confesse also the holie Paradise. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Now (gentle Reader) vnderstande, that the promise was made vnto Adam,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> touching the seede of the womā, that should breake the Serpentes head: and that hath been confirmed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and more plainely set forth vnto the other Patriarkes, and especially vnto Abraham and Dauid, all thei (I saie) that did giue credite vnto it,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.4. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.7.8.9.10. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12.13 14.15.16. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.6.</note> and beleued that thei should bee saued by the blessed promised seede, haue all entered into the heauē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioye: whiche hath been purchased vnto them, and vs, by our sauiour Iesus Christe. And for thy better learnyng (good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) marke this what I saie. Although our Sauiour Christe hath been offered vp vpon the Crosse, for to make satisfaction vnto the righteousnes of God for vs,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4.4.</note> at the tyme that was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincted him of the father: yet was he slaine, and offered in the presence of God, frō the beginnng of the world. For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: The Lambe was slaine from the beginning of the world.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13.8.</note>
      <pb facs="16"/>
Againe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.8.</note> Iesus Christe yesterdaie, and to daie, the same also is for euer. In this, the Apostle cōprehendeth all the whole tyme passed▪ presente,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.56.</note> and to come. Iesus hym self had respecte here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, when he saied, your father <hi>Abraham</hi> reioyced to see my daie, and he sawe it, and was glad. Uerely, verely, I saie vnto <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> you,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.10.</note> before Abraham was, I am: that is to say, not onely God, but the mediatour, betwene GOD and man, appoincted from before all eternitie. For, although in respect of vs, he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in the fulnesse of tyme, and in the latter daies: yet in the presence of God,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.4.</note> he hath been alwaies crucified, and his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice hath been euerlastingly present with hym. For, in God is no difference of tyme, as is in vs, because that all thynges are presente vnto hym, and for that he is aboue, and beyonde the tyme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 90.4. 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.8 <hi>August. in lib. qustio.</hi> 85. <hi>quest.</hi> 15.16. <hi>In lib. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinatione &amp; gratia. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>In lib. de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici habitacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. cap.</hi> 5.</note> and out of it. For, a thousande yeres, are vnto hym, but as as one daie. So sainct <hi>Augustine</hi> saieth: <hi>Apud deum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem nihil deest, nec praeteritum igitur, nec futurum: sed omne praesens est apud deum.</hi> That is: With God there is nothing wantyng, nothyng paste, or to come, but all thynges are presente. &amp;c. Wherefore, euen as the death, and passion of Christe, dooeth serue vs now vnto saluation, whiche beleue that he hath been crucified for vs, although he hangeth no more on the crosse: So bee ye certaine and sure, that it hath profited them▪ that haue liued before that he was Crucified, whiche beleeued that he should come, and dye for them: as wee dooe beleeue that he is come, and hath died for vs.</p>
   <p>Therefore wee ought to acknowledge, no iij.iiij.v.vj.vij.viij.ix.x. or a xj. places, as if some soules had been lodged in hel, some in Limbo, some in a darke place in hell, where was no paine: Some in Paradise, some in heauen, some in earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, some in Purgatorie fire, some in the water, some in the ayre, some in houses and cloisters, and some in fieldes. &amp;c. But notwithstandyng all these phantasies of mens deuises,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. <hi>Wisd.</hi> 3.10. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Matth</hi> 25.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>August. de verbis Apost. Serm.</hi> 18.</note> Christ giueth vnto them all their lodgyng, either in Abrahames bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some: or in the vnquencheable fire of hell: that is to saie, either in heauen, or hell. For so <hi>Augustine</hi> saieth. <hi>Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> quippe habit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones sunt, vna, in igne aeterno, alia in regno aeterno.</hi> There are but twoo habitations, one is in the euerlastyng fire of hell, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="17"/>
is in the euerlastyng kingdome of heauen. Wherevpon wee maie gather, that Christes soule wente straighte (beyng separated from his bodie) into heauen,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.</note> and not to helle. For, he saieth hym self to the Theife that honge on the crosse (after he desired to remember hym,<note place="margin">42</note> when he came into his kyngdome) to daie shalte thou bee with me in Paradise.<note place="margin">43</note> Also, Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his soule into the handes of his father.<note place="margin">46</note> His bodie was laied in the graue,<note place="margin">53</note> his soule was in heauen, for so he saied the Theife should bee there that daie with hym. &amp;c. And so he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired his father in his praier,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.24.</note> that al thei whiche his father had giuen vnto hym, might bee with hym euen where hee is. &amp;c. Now I maruaile what parte should goe into helle then?</p>
   <p>The principalleste cause of this erroure is (as I iudge) for that thei thinke and suppose, God the father did neuer loue vs nor fauour vs, before, we, and thei, were reconciled to hym by the death of his sonne: whiche is cleane contrary: For, GOD the Father did with his loue preuente,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.29.</note> and goe before, as the efficiente cause,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.37.</note> of our reconciliation in Christe: Yea, because he first loued vs, therefore he afterwardes reconcileth vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym self. And for this cause sainct Paule saieth, God setteth out his loue towardes vs,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.16.</note> seyng that while wee were yet syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Christe died for vs. And sainct Ihon saieth, God so loued the worlde, that he hath giuen his onely begotten sonne, that who soeuer beleeueth in hym,<note place="margin">The efficiēt. The mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall. The formall. The finall cause of our saluation. 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.2. <hi>August. in Ioh. tract.</hi> 110.</note> should not perishe, but haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastyng life. For the free election of Goddes loue is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cause of our Saluation: Christes obeidience the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cause: our callyng by the outwarde woorde, the formall cause: Our sanctification by the holie Ghoste, the finall cause. Herevnto agreeth that saiyng of saincte <hi>Augustine,</hi> where he saieth, <hi>Quapropter, incomprehensibilis est dilectio qua diligit Deus: neque mutabilis. Non enim ex quo si reconciliati sumus per sanguinem fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> eius nos caepit diligere, sed ante mundi constitutionem dilexit nos: vt cum eius vnigenito etiam nos filij eius essemus: priusquam omnino ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid essemus. Quod ergo reconciliati sumus deo per mortem Christi, non sic accipiatur, quasi ideo nos reconciliauerit ei filius, vt iam amare inciperet quos oderat: Sed iam nos diligenti reconciliati sumus ei, cum quo, propter peccatum, immicitias habeamus. Quod vtrum verum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam,
<pb facs="17"/>
attestetur Apostolus. Commendat, inquit, dilectionem suam deus erga nos,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.</note>
      <hi>quoniam cum adhuc peccatores essemus, Christus pro nobis mortuus est, habebat itaque ille erga nos charitatem, etiam cum inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citias aduersus eum exercentes, operaremur iniquitatem. Proinde mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro &amp; diuino modo, &amp; quando nos oderat, dilegebat. Oderat enim nos, quales ipse non fecerat: &amp; quia iniquitas nostra, opus eius non omni ex parte consumpserat. Nouerat simul in vno quoque nostrum &amp; odisse quod feceramus, &amp; amare quod fecerat</hi>: that is to saie in Englishe: The loue of God is incomprehensible, and vnchaungable. For he began not to loue vs, since the tyme that wee were recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to hym, by the bloud of his sonne: but before the makyng of the worlde he loued vs, euen before wee were any thyng at all, that wée might also bee his children, with his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten sonne. Therefore, whereas we are reconciled by the death of Christe, it is not so to bee taken, as though the Sonne did therefore reconcile vs vnto hym, that he might now beginne to loue vs, whom he hated before: But wee are reconciled to hym, that alreadie loued vs, to whom wee were enemies, by reason of synne. And whether this bee true or no, that I saie, lette the Apostle beare witnesse.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.</note> He doeth commende (saieth he) his loue towardes vs, because when we were yet sinners, Christe died for vs: he therefore had a loue to vs, euen then when wee were enemies to hym, and wrought wickednesse. Therefore, after a marueilous and diuine maner he loued vs, euen then when he hated vs. For, he hated vs in that we were suche, as he had not made vs, and because our wickednesse had on eche side, wasted awaie his woorke, he knewe how in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of vs, bothe to hate that whiche our selues had made, and to loue that whiche he had made. Thus farre <hi>Augustine.</hi> Whereby we haue to learne what a comfortable doctrine the Predestination of GOD is (whiche many can not abide,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> of whom saincte Paule long before spake of). Also howe so euer we bee synners by our owne faulte,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iude.</hi> 1.10.</note> yet we remaine his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And howsoeuer we haue purchased death to our selues: yet he made vs vnto life. So is he moued by méere and free lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of vs, to receiue vs, and also to reconcile vs by his sonne Christ, into his fauour. Therefore, in respecte of our corrupte
<pb facs="18"/>
nature,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.32.</note> and then of euil life added vnto it: truely we are in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure of God: guiltie in his sight, and borne to dampnation of hell. But because the lorde will not loose that whiche is his in vs, he findeth yet somewhat, that he of his onely goodnesse, maie loue vs (without any goodnesse or worthinesse that is in vs) through his Sonne Christe, our onely Sauioure. To this saincte <hi>Augustine</hi> saieth: <hi>Due res sunt homo &amp; peccator. Quod au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis homo, fecit deus. Quod audis peccator ipse homo fecit: dele quod fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisti, vt deus saluet quod fecit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>August. in Ioh. tract.</hi> 12. <hi>and in psal.</hi> 137.</note>
      <hi>oportet vt oderis in te opus tuum, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in te opus dei.</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e are twoo thynges, Man, and Synner, That thou hearest man, God made it. That thou hearest syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Man hymself made: take awaie that thou haste made, that God maie saue that he hath made. It behoueth that thou hate in thy self, thine owne woorke, that thou maiest loue the woorke of God in thee.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13.14.</note> Hereto Dauid saieth: Beholde, I was borne in iniquitie, and in synne hath my mother cōceiued me. Pourge me with Hysope, and I shall bee cleane: Washe me, and I shall bee whiter then Snowe▪ &amp;c. This doctrine well waighed, will easely teache vs, that all the righteous Soules departed (in the faithe) before Christes commyng, were in heauen. And therefore no neede for Christe his soule to goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, to fetche them out, for in that place thei neuer were: nor none of Goddes predestinate, and electe children was, or euer shall bee. For whom the Lorde euer loued (saieth the Scripture) be loueth vnto the ende.</p>
   <p>Nowe if any man should aske me, when Christe wente downe to hell? I will aunswere hym. When he praied to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape death, he began to goe downe: and so all his sufferynges, that he suffered afterwarde in bodie and soule, for our synnes, was his goyng into hell. For he felt the burden, and waight of Gods wrathe for our iniquities,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isaiah.</hi> 53.3.4.5.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.17. 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.21.22.23.24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.18.</note> in suche sort, that no paine, tormente, griefe, sorrowe, nor punishement that euer synne and disobedience, had deserued in hell. But that it was laied vpon Christ for vs, to bryng vs vnto God, whiche paines and torments he felt in his bodie and soule. Wherby we maie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how greeuous and terrible tormentes he suffred, whē he knewe himselfe to be arained for our cause, before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente
<pb facs="18"/>
seate of GOD. For there can bee imagined, no more dreadfull bottomelesse depth, then for one to féele hymself for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken and estraunged from God, and not to bee hearde when he calleth vpon hym: euen as if God hymself had conspired his destruction. Euen thither wee see that Christe was throwne downe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.44.</note> so farre that by inforcemente of paine, and tormentes of hell,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.2. <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.46.</note> did sweate, and his sweate was like droppes of bloud, trickelyng doune to the grounde. And he was compelled to cry out: My God, my GOD: why haste thou forsaken me. &amp;c. Here thou maiest note, that in the <hi>Crede,</hi> we reade not in the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler nomber, <hi>descendit ad infernum,</hi> hee descended into hell (as thoughe it did speake of a place certaine, where into he was gone): but in the plurall nomber, <hi>descendit in inferna,</hi> he descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the helles, Comprehendyng all that was before saied in many woordes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13.</note> how he suffered vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead and buried: in this one woorde, helles.</p>
   <p>Now (gentle Reader) I praie thee, not to take me in this my writyng, that I dooe deny this Article, of Christes descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng into hell: for, I doe constantly beleue it, and will in no wise (God willyng) denye it, but affirme that he descended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell accordyngly: But of the maner of his descension into hell, is our question. They saie his soule went downe thither: whiche thei can not proue by the woorde of God, and therfore I can not beleue it. But I saie this, that the force, efficacie, and strength of his death and passion, did pearce vnto the damned soules in hell (through his diuine power and godheade) to the greater increase, and certifiyng of their eternall and iust dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. For I saie vnto thée (in the worde of God, and lye not) that all Christes sufferynges, sorrowes, and passions, that he sustained here (for vs) vpon the earth, and vpon the Crosse, in body, and in his soule (for our sinnes) was his going downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the helles▪ Wherefore, let vs constantly beleeue this, that he was once in the flesh,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.31.32. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Cap.</hi> 26.38.</note> a verie man, like vnto vs in al thing, (sinne only excepted) and came downe for vs men, and for our saluation: that he did verely suffer passion of bodie and soule: that he hath verely died, and been buried. And that he hath been verely reuiued againe, and the verie same soule retourned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb facs="19"/>
into his owne naturall bodie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.40.41.42. <hi>Cap.</hi> 27.17. <hi>Cap.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.51. <hi>Actes.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.25.</note> and after did ascende vp into heauen, and there sitteth on the right hande of the father to make daiely and continuall intercession for all his electe, and to saue all them that come to God by hym. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>As many therfore, as be Christians, haue giuen their faith vnto Christ in their Baptisme, vnder the witnesse of a greate meany. There they promised to forsake the fleshe, the world, and the deuill. If now thei will bee at league with the synner, and at agreement with the deuill, and the euill doer, thei haue broken their firste promise,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.12.</note> and are founde vnfaithfull: for wherevnto thei are ouercome,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.33. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.62. 2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10.26. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.5.6.7</note> his seruauntes thei are, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee of synne vnto death, or of obedience vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse. And for their faithe thus violated, giuen vnto the immortall God: God againe will breake with them his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte of mercie, if in tyme thei repente not. Lette vs holde therefore vnitie in doctrine: Secondlie, vniuersalitie in ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of voyces: Thirdlie, consente in spirite and iudgement. For the Papistes haue tourned vnitie, to diuision: Uniuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, to singularitie: Consente, to open and plaine discention. And so, vnder the name of the faithe, thei persecute the faithe. &amp;c. For if thou doest forsake Christes Shippe, and wilt rowe in the Popes Boate, his Oares will directly rowe thée to that hauen and porte, where doctour Storie, of late caste his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and brake his necke: and for that his handes were halte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he gaue all traiterous Papistes, the Popes blessyng with his heeles at Tybourne. An ende and blessyng mooste meete for all sortes of Papistes. God of his mercie quickely conuerte theim that are aliue, or els good Lorde sende a merie winde, to blowe them all into that course, that Felton, and Storie before haue runne. For I am fullie perswaded, that what soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he bee, high or lowe, riche or poore, that holdeth with any Popishe, or Papisticall doctrine, he is a rancke traitour in his harte:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8. <hi>Psa.</hi> 21.11.12. <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.29. <hi>Psal.</hi> 121.5.6.7.8.</note> and when tyme serueth, it will so fall out in proofe, as daiely experiēce teacheth vs, by our late traiterous rebelles, whiche soughte the suppressyng of the faithe of Christe: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe of the Queenes Maiestie, and vtter desolation of this our Realme: If the almightie Lorde had not preuented
<pb facs="19"/>
them, of his mercie towardes vs.</p>
   <p>What resteth now,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 127..1. <hi>Psal.</hi> 118.10. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.27▪ <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Titus.</hi> 3.1. 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Isaiah.</hi> 66.1. <hi>Actes.</hi> 7.48. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. <hi>Isaiah.</hi> 30.21. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39. <hi>Actes.</hi> 17.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.14.</note> but that we loue God, and his worde: and obeye our Queene and her Magistrates, and also to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our waies, and sée whether wee walke as he hath taught vs. For, there is no heauen, but his dwellyng place: no wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng vnto it, but by his cōmaundementes: and his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes no where to be founde, but in the holy Scriptures, which he hath left vs. Next vnto Gods glory, we haue nothing so precious, as the sauegarde of our soules. And where shal we finde it, but in the worde of God. And here I make an ende of this my long preface, most heartely besechyng thée, to accepte in good parte, this simple and rude worke of myne, consider my good meanyng and wyll, towardes the buildyng of Gods Churche, who woulde haue giuen thée better, if better he had in store. I must warne thée, not to looke in this booke: for the pleasaunt speache of <hi>Isocrates,</hi> nor the high stile of <hi>Demosthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> nor for the excellent dignitie of <hi>Plato,</hi> nor the eloquent wordes of <hi>Cicero,</hi> or for the reuerende maiestie of <hi>Theucidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi>: For then thou wilt foulie be deceiued: But for bare and simple wordes:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.24. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14.</note> for I seeke not goods, but God: not gasinges, but gayne: not prayse, but profite: not mony, but men. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, (gentle and freendly reader) if thou receiue any fruicte of my labours, helpe mée with thy prayers to God our Father, in the name of his Soonne and our onely Sauiour. In readyng hereof, let reason leade thée: lette the aucthorities perswade thée: and let trueth enforce thée. GOD of his mercie quickely conuerte, or soone ouerthrowe al his enimies, and the Quéenes fooes that holde of any doctrine, contrarie to the true and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian faith: Confounde all errours (O Lorde,) giue the victory to thy trueth, and glory to thy holy and blessed name, now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi> ¶ Fare well (Gentle Reader) from Redcliffe in Bristoll.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶<hi>Thy poore brother in Christ, Iohn North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke</hi> Preacher.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>