<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE SEDVCED Catholiques of England. {inverted ⁂}</title>
           <author>H., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120922_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12880</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120922</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE SEDVCED Catholiques of England. {inverted ⁂}</title>
                 <author>H., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of egregious popish impostures : to with-draw the harts of her Maiesties subiects from their allegeance, and from the truth of Christian religion professed in England, vnder the pretence of casting out deuils. Practised by Edmunds, alias Weston a Iesuit, and diuers Romish priests his wicked associates. Where-vnto are annexed the copies of the confessions, and examinations of the parties themselues, which were pretended to be possessed, and dispossessed, taken vpon oath before her Maiesties commissioners, for causes ecclesiasticall</title>
                 <author>Harsnett, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 284 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE SEDVCED <hi>Catholiques</hi> of England. {inverted ⁂}</head>
   <p>SEduced &amp; disvnited Brethren, there be two grand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the world, that seduce the soules of the simple, &amp; lead them to perdition: <hi>Lying wonders,</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit zeale.</hi> The power of these two, the spirit of God hath most liuely expressed vnto vs, one in the person of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> the Sorcerer, who with his lying wonders had so bewitched the simple people, as they followed him with this acclamation: <hi>This man is the power of the great and mighty GOD.</hi> The other in the person of some of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who by the feigned zeale of the counterfeite Apostles, were bewitched, and carried from S. <hi>Paule,</hi> the true and blessed Apostle of our Sauiour Christ. These two witching powers haue many yeeres since combined and vnited themselues in the Pope of Rome, and his disciples, who take vpon them the soueraigne power of our sauiour Christ, with authority to commaund vncleane spirits, and to make them obey: and doe pretend such a burning holy zeale vnto you, as that they regard neither the pleasures, profits, nor prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this world, nay not theyr owne liberty, and liues, but doe offer them vp both as a sacrifice for your soules consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. These are mighty powers to sway your iudgements, and affections from vs vnto them. Now if it shall appeare vnto you as cleere, as the light of the sunne, that these powers be feigned, and counterfeite in them, and that they be in truth nothing els, saue the mists, and allusions of Satan, to dimme
<pb facs="3"/>
the ey of your vnderstanding, and bewitch your affections to doate vppon theyr impious superstition, what can you, or any ingenious spirits doe lesse, then bewaile your seduced misaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vnto vs, and to account them as the grand Impostors, and enchaunters of your soules? And that this may be cleerly manifested vnto you, I beseech you in the bowels of our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sauiour, to let open your eares &amp; eyes to this short decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: to peruse and read it with a single ey, and impartiall affection, and if it shall not most perspicuously appeare vnto you, that the Pope, and his spirits he sendeth in here amongst you, do play Almighty God, his sonne, &amp; Saints vpon a stage, do make a pageant of the Church, the blessed Sacraments, the rites &amp; ceremonies of religion, do cog &amp; coine deuils, spirits, &amp; soules departed this life, to countenance and grace, or face out their desperate abhominations, then stand disvnited, and disaffected as you doe. It is not in any man (I cōfesse) to feele those diuine beames of burning zeale that were in S. <hi>Paule,</hi> who wished himselfe <hi>Anathema</hi> for his kinsmen according to the flesh: yet a man of <hi>Ionas</hi> spirit I can easily name, that would most gladly be cast into the sea, to calme this tempest of opposition risen here amongst vs, and of <hi>Ieremies</hi> deuotion, that doth pray for a fountaine of teares to bewaile the lamentable blindnes of his owne nation, that men as you are, borne free of an vnderstanding spirit, and ingenious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, should so basely degenerate, as to captiuate your wits, wils, &amp; spirits, to a forraine Idol Gull, composed of palpable fiction, and diabolicall fascination, whose enchaunted chalice of heathenish drugs, &amp; Lamian superstition, hath the power of <hi>Circes,</hi> and <hi>Medaeas</hi> cup, to metamorphose men into asses, bayards, &amp; swine. Is it not their owne brand they haue stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped on your forheads, that England hath beene alwayes good asse to the Pope?</p>
   <p>Who doth not bewaile the sely doating Indian Nation, that falls downe and performes diuine adoration to a rag of red cloth: and the besotted Aegyptians, that kissed with earnest deuotion the Asse vppon which the Idol <hi>Isis</hi> sate, and the
<pb facs="3"/>
lymphaticall priests of <hi>Baal,</hi> that launced theyr owne flesh before an Idol of wood? Would God your bewitched dotage were not as palpable, and more lamentable then theyrs, that fall downe &amp; adore a morsell of bread, that kisse &amp; clip with religious deuotion the Popes toe, for bearing the feigned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit of our Sauiour on earth: performed with the right Aegyptian glose, <hi>non Papae sed Petro, non asinae sed deae,</hi> this honour is not to the Pope, but to <hi>S. Peter,</hi> not to the asse, but to <hi>Isis.</hi> Your Popes beeing proclaimed by your owne O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclists to the world, one to be an Asse, another a Fox, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Wolfe.</p>
   <p>What people, but you, were euer so bewitched, as to be borne in hand, that a house was carried in the ayre from <hi>Palestina</hi> to <hi>Loretto:</hi> that a painted Image in a wall, doth worke as high miracles, as euer were performed by the eternall sonne of God: that the prints of S. <hi>Frauncis</hi> stripes, the tayle of our Sauiours Asse, the milke of our blessed Lady are this day to be seene: and these gracelesse saltlesse gulleries either to be belieued, or countenaunced, by men of wit, vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and spirit, such as are this day many in the Romish Church? If you aske me the cause, what can it be but this, that God hath giuen them ouer to the spirit of illusion, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue vnsauory lies, for refusing in their pride to embrace the pure naked synceritie of the Gospell of Christ. He that sits in the heauens, Almighty God, with his Angels, and Saints, do laugh these mishapen monsters to scorne.</p>
   <p>And who can but bleede in hart, to see you as farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched on our imposturising renagadoes, that come fresh frō the Popes tyring house, masked with the vizard of holy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning zeale. First it may please you to obserue, that the wiser grauer sort of thē do keepe themselues warme in theyr Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters at home, and doe feede themselues fat with the spoiles of your confusion. These lighter superfluities, whom they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge amongst you, how they play the Bats, and Moales, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trenching themselues in the mines of your labyrinths at home, or masking in your gold and siluer abroade in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion
<pb facs="4"/>
of great Potentates, vntill Gods reuengefull arme doth vncase them to the view of the world, &amp; then they suffer the mild stroke of iustice with a glorious ostentation, as you in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled simplicitie doe imagine for theyr conceited religion: but as the wiser see, the state did alwaies know, and is of late published in theyr own writings, for high &amp; odious treasons: and professed by their owne Maisters, that haue made them after their own images, to be of a spirit of contradiction to our Gouernours and Prince: and it is wondred at by themselues, considering theyr treasonable machinations that her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and the state, haue carried so milde, and mercifull an hand ouer them, &amp; that any one of them is left aliue to libell against the admirable lenity of her Maiesties gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. Wherein be ye well assured, that if the sword of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice were drawne, and inflicted according to the waight and measure of their detestable designes, that fewer of thē would come ouer, and that this couey of night-birds, would shrowde thēselues warme vnder the gentle wings of theyr holy father at Rome. But admit (as you conceiue) that they died for the credit of their conceited superstition: what did <hi>Lucians Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrinus</hi> lesse, then offer himselfe in fire at <hi>Olimpia</hi> for the credit of his fascination? What did <hi>Aesculapius</hi> vppon the hill <hi>Aetna</hi> to get himselfe a name, but cast himselfe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the burning flames? What doe the Indian-priests at this day, but sacrifice themselues for the countenauncing of theyr diabolicall incantation. It is no new, nor strange thing for the authors, and maintainers of sects, and factions in all kindes, to die with seeming shew of glorious resolution. Doe but seriously recount the quality of this fugitiue generation, &amp; see what pious resolution can lodge in theyr breasts. What are they afore they goe ouer but discontended, ruinate, stig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall refuse people: of a factious, ambitious, exorbitant conuersation abroade, exploded, or cunningly discarded their owne Societies where they liued: and how ghostly &amp; priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they demeane thēselues here amongst you at theyr returne, I referre you for demonstation to this short, and perspicuous
<pb facs="4"/>
declaration. Wherein you may plainly see, if you doe not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hoodwinke your owne eyes, that the holy pretended hote zeale of the fiery spirits from Rome, is the meer Heathenish iugling of <hi>Bells</hi> priests, to deuour your goods, lands, &amp; patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, the rights of your posterity, and auncient monuments of your name, to defraude your children of theyr bread, and cause you offer it to impure dogs, to enrich theyr owne Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Colledges, &amp; Churches, with the spoyles of your deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to defile your chast houses, pollute your tender virgins, depraue, and inueigle your owne wiues lying in your bosoms, especally by that poysonable engine of hypocriticall Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and finally to offer you vp as a pray to that Monster of Rome, the head of all vnnaturall and detestable rebellion.</p>
   <p>And that this declaration might be free from the carpe, and cauill of ill-affected, or discomposed spirits, I haue alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged nothing for materiall, or authenticall heerein, but the expresse words, eyther of some part of the <hi>Miracle booke,</hi> penned by the priests, and filed vpon Record, where it is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique to be seene, or els a clause of theyr confession who were fellow actors in this impious dissimulation. Whose seuerall confessions, and contestations (the parties beeing yet liuing) are heere published in print, that the world may be a witnesse of our integrity herein. All which had beene long ere this offered to your equall consideration, but that the <hi>Miracle-booke</hi> came but lately to hand, &amp; the getting of foure chiefe Daemoniacks together, besides many more assistants, beeing persons of that quality and condition, was a matter of some paines, and trauell to effect.</p>
   <p>If the forme and phrase be distasting to some clowdy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as too light, and ironicall for one of my profession, let the matter be my Aduocat, that draweth me thereunto, and the manner my Apologie a little too: trusting I may be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to iest at their iesting, that haue made a iest of God, and of his blessed Saints in heauen. If I haue wittingly falsified or feigned any thing out of that booke of wonders, God doe so to me, and more, for dooing them so much wrong: but if all
<pb facs="5"/>
be truly, and authentically set downe, giue GOD his glorie, his Church her honor, your Soueraigne her allegeance, your Brethren theyr due affection, and the Pope, and his iugling companions, their deserued detestation. And so I leaue you to the protector of all truth, and the reuenger of all falshood, and hypocriticall dissimulation.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christ <hi>S. H.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>