<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>Lecey, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120958_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18210</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4835</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120958</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>Lecey, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A petition apologeticall, presented to the Kinges most excellent Maiesty, by the lay Catholikes of England, in Iuly last</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>—Recusant.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mogar, John, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EVEREND SIR.</hi> There came to my hands by the way of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> on the <hi>xxviij.</hi> day of this moneth, a certayne <hi>Petition</hi> or <hi>Apologie of the lay Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes of England</hi> (as I stand informed) presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Highnes about the later end of the parliament: which seemeth so conformable to reason, so absolute in forme of their submission, and so admirable for the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance by them offered for their Priests and Pastors: that the publishing thereof cannot but giue contentment (in my opinion) to all sorts of men, that desire both to be clearely informed of the true state of things, and that iustice and equity should take place, according to mens comportments &amp; deserts, and not according to the preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate opinions of such, whome nothing but the bloud and vtter beggering of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> can satisfie. And therefore I thought good, in more publike manner then it was before, to make the world acquainted therewith.</p>
   <div type="reasons">
      <head>Reasons of publishing this treatise.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>THE</hi> publishing of this <hi>Apology</hi> cānot but t<note place="margin">His Maiesties honour and seruice.</note>end much to his Maiesties honour, and more to his satisfaction and securitie; for so much as the <hi>Catholikes</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate seruices and obligations therein contayned, must needes be argumentes of some supereminent vertue and goodnes in his sacred personage, that could drawe from them at all times such extraordinary effectes of loue and deuotion: and the more manifest the protestations of their purgations shall appeare to the world, the more manifold shall be their bonds and obligations of performaunce, and perseuerance therein.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Prelates.</note>The <hi>Protestant Prelates</hi> cannot with reason disalowe thereof, because herein is nothing required at their hands, but a reasonable conference, and satisfaction in pointes of their mission and vocation: And when they shall make it euident out of the
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
written word, that they are the true Sheepheardes and Pastors sent from God to haue charge of soules, they make profer without delay to followe them, and with all confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to obey them, and heare their voyces: which when they shall proue, the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie is charitably composed, and though they fayle of their proofes, yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne as they doe with their wealth, their wyues, their pleasures, and pallaces: the poore <hi>Catholikes</hi> desiring only a secret and silent permission of such Pastors, as shall shewe to them and the whole world, sufficient euidence and approbation for the charge of soules they vndertake.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The Puritans</note>The <hi>Puritans</hi> herewith cannot be offended, if they peaceably, and precisely seeke after contentment, and not contention: because they shall finde diuers of their max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes zealously, or rather odiously conceiued by them against <hi>Catholikes,</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne and euacuated by most euident demonstration and instances in matters of facte, practise and experience: especially in that point of conditionall subiects, which is so much vrged by the <hi>Ministry.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Academikes of Oxford &amp; Cambridge.</note>The flourishing and learned <hi>Academikes</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> may perceiue hereby that <hi>Catholikes</hi> knowe their Priests <hi>intus &amp; incute,</hi> and take them neither for ignorant in diuinitie, nor dunces in humanity; neither for <hi>Catalines</hi> towardes their <hi>Senate,</hi> nor for <hi>Absolons</hi> towardes their <hi>Dauid,</hi> that dare ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture life, &amp; liuing for their vertues &amp; loyalties. And I imagine that if your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> were put to the like plunges, they would hardly finde the like pledges: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could wish that your <hi>Ministers</hi> would endeuour rather to excell and surpasse them in their Godly qualities, then in their pamphlets and pulpets to vrge the State to suppresse them with seuere exilementes and edictes, which are nothing but argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of their feare, and whetstones of the others fortitude.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The Artisans, and Prentises.</note>The Godly and zealous <hi>Artisans</hi> and <hi>Prentises</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and other places, may learne hereby to moderate themselues a little in their outragious alarmes of <hi>Stoppe the Traytor,</hi> when they see an Innocent Priest passe their streets: for by reading hereof they may be rightly and truly informed and instructed, howe farre the poore <hi>Innocent</hi> men are from treasons, and all treasonable purposes.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note>The <hi>Catholikes</hi> at home must needes hereby be comforted, and animated in well doing, and faithfull seruing, and obeying their Soueraigne <hi>in pace &amp; gaudio,</hi> if they may be permitted; and if not that, yet in suffering with alacrity what shall be imposed vpon them for their Religion, when by this <hi>Apologie</hi> they shall be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdned of those former clogges and imputatims of disloyaltie, and treason.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes abroade.</note>The <hi>Catholikes</hi> not onely here in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> but in the whole <hi>Christian</hi> world besides must needes be hereby much edified, and excited to the sincere pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, and profession of zeale and pietie towardes God: of fidelity and obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their Princes: and of a Reuerent respect, and regard towardes their Priests and Pastors, when they finde in this present <hi>Apologie,</hi> so rare and remarkeable an example of <hi>English Catholikes</hi> constancy in the one, &amp; conformity in the other:
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
and such confidence for the third, that sithence the <hi>Apostles</hi> time, and the dayes of the priuatiue Church of <hi>England,</hi> neuer the like President, either in the time of peace, or persecution hath beene heard or read of; that the sheepe should engage them selues for their shepheardes, and make voluntary profer to bee bound body for body, and life for life for their fidelity, except that famous <hi>Protomartir</hi> of <hi>England, S. Albane,</hi> who was to them herein a patrone and president: the end of whose bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed conuersation, our <hi>English Catholikes</hi> beholding, doe Imitate his faith and fortitude, and doe succeed him in a reuerenciall but and deuotion towardes their Pastors. Which heroicall minde and resolution of our said <hi>English Catholikes</hi> must needes be as famous to posterity, as it is repugnant to all worldly wisdome and policy; and must also needes bee accompanied with asmuch honour and merit in the sight of God, and all good men; as it cannot but be incombred with dangers and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties in the sight of flesh and bloud, and of all those <hi>quorum Deus venter est,</hi> Whose God is only their belly, profit, and pleasure in this world.</p>
      <p>Of this <hi>Apologie</hi> two copies were sent ouer, the one to <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the other to <hi>Flaunders:</hi> all one in sence and substance, but it seemeth that the copie sent to <hi>Flaunders</hi> was taken <hi>verbatim</hi> out of the first fountayne and originall: And that the other which came to <hi>Paris,</hi> was not all togeather so ample and compleate. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue thought good to aduertise you, that I haue followed and setforth that copie, which I found, or at least presumed to be most consonant to the good mindes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of them, whome it most concerned.</p>
      <p>And thus willing you to make your profit spirituall of these my endeuours, and of the sequent <hi>Apology,</hi> desiring God that it may serue to mollifie the harts of our heauy aduersaries, and fortifie and corroborate the Saints &amp; seruants of God in well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ing, and patiently suffering, and carrying the Crosse of Christ, &amp; Crowne of thornes which pricke to the quicke on euery side, I wish you the two most pretious Iewels that can happen to a <hi>Christian</hi> soule.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Gratiam in hac vita, &amp; gloriam in futura.</hi>
      </p>
      <closer>
         <dateline>From my study in <hi>DOWAY,</hi>
            <date>this <hi>16.</hi> of <hi>OCTOBER 1604.</hi>
            </date>
         </dateline>
         <signed>Your very louing Sonne and seruant in CHRISTO DOMINO. <hi>IO. LECEY.</hi>
         </signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>