<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120081_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07402</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17788</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A ciuile nosgay : wherin is contayned not onelye the offyce and dewty of all magestrates and iudges but also of of [sic] all subiectes with a preface concernynge the lyberty of iustice in this our tyme newly collected and gethered out of latyn and so translated in to the Inglyshe tonge by I.G</title>
                 <author>Melanchthon, Philipp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Goodale, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 <publisher>King (Kyng), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>On<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iderynge howe in these our dayes GOD hathe wrought, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worketh suche wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; blyssed thynges, as by many ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny yeares before, the lyke hath not ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sene, nor harde of, godith and pricketh me to reioyce and say with that diuine phylosopher Plato. Tunc beatus et felix cencendus est totus orbis terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cum sapientes efficuntur reges, aut reges efficuntur sapientes. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man he sayth ought then to Iudge and thynke all the worlde to be blyssed and happye when wyse men be made Kynges, ruelers, and gouernoures, or Kynges, ruelers, and gouernoures, be made wyse. The Philosopher, Euripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des sayth that by the company of wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se men Prynces be made wyse. The roote of wysdome is to feare god, and the braunches thereof be of longe lyfe. No doubte a wyse harte, and that hath vnderstondyng wyll abstayne from yll dedes, and in workes of Iustyce his
<pb facs="2"/>
purpose shall prospere, was it not a wonderfull acte, the great thraldome the intollerable charges and the myse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable seruytude and bondage that we be exoneratyd and delyuered of, from the babylonicall strumpet, wherby the fredome and lyberty of goddes woord so longe sepulted and hydden from vs to nowe come to lyght. And yet won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull was that most valiaunt and vic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torious suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>umbynge of Frenshemen at Bullogne, and the wynnyng of the same imaculte &amp; mayden towne, with sonderye ouerthrowes of the Scottes. But most wonderfull thynge of all is the restitucion out of bondage to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of so rare so myghty so blyssed &amp; Beautyfull a person, of all people so longe optatyd, wysshed and loked for, whose outwarde kepers and watche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men this many many yeares hath ben, Mars, of the inwarde chamber lune, &amp; of the verye pryuye chamber, Sol, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the fre &amp; benynge hart and sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make of the sayd most gracious perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb facs="3"/>
was alwayes indeferent to ryche and poore yet without great oblacion and sacryfyce made and done to the sayde kepers, no man coulde optayne any benefyt, who knoweth not? howe that Amerous persons Iustice hathe this many yeares bene detayned, kept, and locked from the people? who could entre in at the streate gates (where she was) so fortely barred with yron and shet vp with stronge lockes without re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde or brybe / who myght come nere to the great chamber, vnles the custos of the dore dyd fele a porcion of syluer. And as aboute the preuy chamber, the attendaūtes and wayters vpon the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the sayd ioyfull and beauti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full person Iustice, were so ornated &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pparelled with chaynes, rynges, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and peces of Golde, that she by them was so dysgysed, her syghte so dymmed, her countenaunce so sulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ated that in a matter she was knowen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o no body. The poore for lacke of lim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes helpe stode a farre of / The ryche
<pb facs="3"/>
by the assystaunce of Sol, Alwaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> came nere, labour and frendshyppe of great persons passed all, sometyme, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection gouerned Iustice and not Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice affection / And sometyme by the dictes and sayinges of the lawe so craf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely wrested, Iustice beare no rule, but nowe, sence that the princes and goue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nours came to the the knowledge of gods worde, and the feare of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theyr tyes, this blyssed person Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice is a lytyll restored to here pristin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lybertie, the braunches of mars begyn to slyp / The gates be now wyde open the gardens of the great chamber, can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not now a byde the breth of lune / And all other attendaunces about the preuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lodge of the sayde most ioyfull parson, loueth the splendaunt and flatterynge countenaunce of Sol, As they do the detestable loke of more Affection is ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hyled. The poore with the ryche be har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a lyke / The bolde steryng and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of great men is drowned. The delayes of lawers with trackynge of
<pb facs="4"/>
tyme in in at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ers be abholyshyd / The wordes of god by his seruaūt Moyses, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o hard and obeyed, here he sayth, Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that is ryght be he cytesyn or straun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger there shall be no dystaunce of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, here as well the lytell ones as the great Iudge the people by Iust Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement declyne not to any parte, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ke rewardce, for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xcecate and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lynde the iyes of the righteous. Euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lastynge wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sayeth I sayas shall be to them that maketh vnryghtwyse lawes and do wryte agaynst Iustice / to the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent that they wyl oppresse poore mē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h Iudgement, and violently subuert the cause of the people / In the path of Iustice saythe Salon on, is lyfe the way that tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eth there from, ledeth to deathe / The fundacion of perpetuall prayse and renowne, saythe Tully, is Iustice without the which nothyng is cōmendable / The Ecclesiast. sayth the glory of a good man is to do Iustice, accordyng to the Iudge of the people, so is this offycere suche as be rulers of
<pb facs="4"/>
a citie, suche be the comons sayth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamon / The fame of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> myghty Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour Iustiniane for well gouernynge the publyke wel by his sage &amp; tempera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te Iusticiars Bellisarious &amp; Narcites is imortall. The the banis to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> {per}petual prayse of Iustice paynted theyr kyng / Theba to syt in his kingly estate with in the counseill house and on eche syde of hym a senator hauyng tronked han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / In token that iudges neyther for rewardes nor yet for fauoure of great men ought to oppresse veryte. Dauid, Salamon, and Dainiell, for theyr iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes be dayly cōmemorated in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly scripture / the one for gyuynge Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement agaynst the ryche man hauyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> many shepe, &amp; yet toke from the poore man his onelye shepe / The other for Iudgyng betwene .ii. harlottes conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> chylde. And the .iii. for dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueryng the vertuous Innocēt Susan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne out of the handes of .ii. wycked prie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stes, Iudge true Iudgement, saythe zacatie, vse and occupye marsie euerye
<pb facs="5"/>
one of you with an other, verytie and iudgement of peace iudge you in your partes. &amp;c. Christe saythe, as you do Iudge, so shall you be iudged, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uen as you do measure to other, so shall it be measured to you. That most famus Kynge Henry the .viii. In his boke cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the doctrine of a Christian man, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the exposycion of the .vi. and .ix. cōmaundement: teacheth and cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth howe Iudges ought not to gyue sentence contrarye to that whiche they knowe to be true, and that in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they do not hyde and suppresse the truth, and that no Iudge seyng no suffycient matter or cause of death or vpon lyght tryal without sufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aminacion &amp; dficussion geue sentence of deth, or whan the matter or cause of death is sufficient, and the tryall good: yet that he delyte not in the death of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> person. At writers of worthy memory haue not forgotten to extole and sette<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forth the magnyfycensy of Iustice: as the well spryng is, so is the water, that
<pb facs="5"/>
is deryued and tunneth therfr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>The chyfe Lordes therfore and mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of the comon wele, not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng howe that most mercyfull prynce Kynge henry the .viii. dyd conflytute them as a lyght &amp; spectacle to all other his magestrates and Iusticiares tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout this his realme and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, haue not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mitted to do according to their vocacion, and as to all persons it is at parant, so it is not forgotten, eyther in theyr hartes or in theyr dayly talke, muche reioysynge that men of gods knowelege be plasyd to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicial, whose godly and christian proce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge therein, shall not onely be to the hygh honour and glory of god, and to there great laude &amp; renowne, but also a generall cōfort to al good christian har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, &amp; a centynuall thankefulnes both of olde and yonge, vnto god. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>standyng the floborne and styfenecked ye, dampnable rebellions, of a certayne of our owne country. I therfore this .xxvi. yeares &amp; more, to ssyng and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belyng,
<pb facs="6"/>
both in the spirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall courtes, there much notynge as well the iustnes as the enormites of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> magestrates and Iudges, and of late, hauynge come in to my handes a boke of Phyllyp Melanctons called. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome Philippi Melāctonis, supe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rali philosophia. Thought it not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable to collect &amp; pycke out heare and there, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd the same to translate in to the Inglyshe tonge certaine saying{is} very fruytfull and necessary for euerye Christian magestrate &amp; Iudge whiche boke I cōmit vniuersally to the whole cōgregacion of magestrates, although I might worldly cōmend it to some by name, there industry &amp; payneful trauel cōcernig Iustice is so a pertely declared but because I shuld not seme to be like the dayly pycthāk{is}, ye dissimulers that doth expiscate and vigilantly gapeth for preferment by flatterye wyll that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, prayng to the lyuyng god that all magestrat{is} may so minister in theyr cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng as it maye be to the hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ure and
<pb facs="6"/>
glory of God, to whom be all prayse, nowe and euer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>