<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT OF THE BOOKE CAL∣led THE DIALL OF PRINCES. Wherein the Authour declareth, his Intention and manner of proceeding.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120712_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12430</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT OF THE BOOKE CAL∣led THE DIALL OF PRINCES. Wherein the Authour declareth, his Intention and manner of proceeding.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archontorologion, or The diall of princes : containing the golden and famous booke of Marcus Aurelius, sometime Emperour of Rome. Declaring what excellcncy [sic] consisteth in a prince that is a good Christian: and what euils attend on him that is a cruell tirant. Written b the Reuerend Father in God, Don Antonio of Gueuara, Lord Bishop of Guadix; preacher and chronicler to the late mighty Emperour Charles the fift. First translated out of French by Thomas North, sonne to Sir Edward North, Lord North of Kirthling: and lately reperused, and corrected from many grosse imperfections. With addition of a fourth booke, stiled by the name of The fauoured courtier</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 331, pages 933, 341-424, 429-542, that is 560, 2, 561-654, 659-768, that is 766 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT OF THE BOOKE CAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>THE DIALL OF PRINCES. Wherein</hi> the Authour declareth, his Intention and manner <hi>of proceeding.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rchimenedes,</hi> the great and famous Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher, (to whom <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Marcellus</hi> for his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge sake granted life, and after vsing Nigro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy deserued death, being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what time was, sayde, That <hi>Time was the inuentor of all nouelies and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gister</hi>
      <note place="margin">The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time according to Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menedes.</note>
      <hi>certaine of Antiquities, which seeth of it selfe, the beginning, the middest, &amp; the ending of all things.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And finally, time is he that endeth all. No man can deny but the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Philosopher is true: for if Time could speake, he would certifie vs of sundry things wherin we doubt, and declare them as a witnes of sight. Admit all things perish, and haue an end; yet one thing is exempted, and neuer hath end, which is truth, that amongst all things is priuiledged in such wise, that shee triumpheth of time, and not time of her: For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuine saying, <hi>It shal bee more easie to see heauen and earth fall, then once truth to perish.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There is nothing so entier, but may bee diminished, nothing so healthfull but may bee diseased, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so strong but may bee broken, neyther any thing so wel kept, but may be corrupted And finally, I say, <hi>There is nothing but by time is ruled &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, saue onely truth, which is subiect to none.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The fruits of the Spring time haue no force to giue sustenance, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect sweetnesse to giue any fauour, but after that the Summer is past, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest commeth, they ripe: and then all that wee e ate nourisheth more, &amp; giueth a better taste: I meane by this when the world began to haue wise men, the more Philosophers were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed for their good manners, the more they deserued to bee reproued for their euill vnderstanding, <hi>Plato</hi> in his second booke of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb facs="17"/>
sayde, That the auncient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers, as well Greekes as Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, <note place="margin">The saying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o Plato.</note> and Caldees, which first began to behold the starres of heauen, and ascended to the toppe of the mount <hi>Olimpus</hi> to view the influences, and motions of the Planets of the earth, deserued rather pardon of their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, then prayse for theyr know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plato</hi> sayde further, that the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers which were before vs, were the first that gaue themselus to search out the truth of the Elements in the Heauen, and the first which sowed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in thinges naturall of the earth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Homer</hi> in his <hi>Ilyades,</hi> agreeing with <hi>Plato,</hi> saieth: I condemne all that the auncient phylosophers knewe, but I greatly commend them for that they desired to know. Certes <hi>Homer</hi> saide well, and <hi>Plato</hi> saide not amisse: for, if amongst the first Phylosophers, this ignorance had not raigned, there had not beene such contrary Sects in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Schoole.</p>
   <p>He that hath read, not the books, which are lost, but the opinions which the auncient Phylosophers had, will graunt mee, though the knowledge were one, yet their sects were diuerse: that is to say, <hi>Cinici, Stoyci, Academici, Platonici,</hi> and <hi>Epicurei:</hi> which were as variable, the one from the other in their opinions, as they were repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in their conditions.</p>
   <p>I will not, neither reason requireth, that my Pen should bee so dismeasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as to reprooue those which are dead, for to giue the glory all onely to them that are aliue: For, the one of them knew not all, neyther were the other ignorant of all.</p>
   <p>If hee deserue thanks that sheweth mee the way, whereby I ought to goe, no lesse then meriteth hee, which war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth mee of that place wherein wee may erre. The ignorance of our fore-Fathers, was but a guide to keepe vs from erring: for, the errour of them shewed vs the Trueth, to their much praise, and to our great shame. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I dare boldly say, <hi>If wee that are now, had been then, wee had knowne lesse then they knewe. And if those were now, which were then, they would haue knowne more then we know.</hi> And that this is true it appeareth well: for that the auncient Phylosophers, through the great desire they had to knowe the Truth, of small and large wayes, the which wee now will not see, nor yet walke therein. Wherefore wee haue not so much cause to be wayle their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, as they had reason to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine <note place="margin">The opiniō of Aulus Gellius cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning time.</note> of our negligence. For, truth which is, (as <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> saith) the <hi>daughter of Time,</hi> hath reuealed vnto vs the errours which wee ought to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe: and the true doctrines, which wee ought to follow.</p>
   <p>What is there to see, but hath bin seene? what to discouer, but hath bin discouered? what is there to read, but hath bin read? what to write, but hath bin written? what is there to knowe, but hath bin knowne? Now-adayes, humaine malice is so experte, men so well able, and our wittes so subtill, that wee want nothing to vnderstand, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, nor euill. And wee vndoe ourselues by seeking that vaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which is not necessary for our life. No man vnder the pretence of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce can excuse his fault, since all men know, all men reade, and all men learne, that which is euident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n this case, as it shall appeare.</p>
   <p>Suppose the <hi>Plough-man,</hi> and the <hi>Learned-man,</hi> do goe to the <hi>Law,</hi> and you shall perceyue the Labourer (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that simple garment) to forge to his Counsellour halfe a dozen of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious trickes to delude his aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as finely as the other that is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, shall bee able to expound two or three Chapters of this booke. If men would employ their knowledge
<pb facs="18"/>
to honesty, wisedome, patience and mercy, it were well: but I am sorry they know so much, onely for that they subtilly deceiue, and by vsury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse their neighbours, and keepe that they haue vniustly gotten, and dayly getting more, inuenting new trades: Finally, I say, if they haue any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it is not to amend their life, but rather to encrease their goods. If the deuil could sleep, as mē do, he might safely sleepe: for whereas he waketh to deceyue vs, wee wake to vndo our selues: Well, suppose that all this heretofore I haue sayde is true. Let vs now leaue aside craft, and take in hand knowledge. The knowledge which we attaine to is small, and that which wee should attain to so great, that all that wee know, is the least part of that wee are ignorant: Euen as in things naturall, the Elements haue their operations, according to the varietie of time: so morall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines (as the aged haue succeeded) and sciences were discouered. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all fruites come not together, but when one fayleth, another commeth in season.</p>
   <p>I meane, that neyther all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors among the Christians, nor all the Philosophers among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles were concurrant at one time; but after the death of one good, there came another better. The chiefe wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which measured all thinges by iustice, and dispearseth them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his bounty, will not that at one time they should bee all Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and at another time all simple: For it had not beene reason that one should haue had the fruit, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the leaues.</p>
   <p>The old world that ranne in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes</hi> dayes (otherwise called the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den world) was of a truth much estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of them that saw it, and greatlie commended of them that wrote of it: That is to say, it was not guided by the Sages which did guild it: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there was no euill men, which did vnguilde it: For as the experience of the meane estate and Nobility tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, of one onely person depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth as well the fame and renowne, as the infamy of a whole house and parentage.</p>
   <p>That age was called golden, that is to say, of gold: and this our age is called yron, that is to say of iron. This difference was not, for that gold then was found, and now yron: nor for <note place="margin">The reason why this is called the Iron-age.</note> that in this our age there is want of them that be sage: but because the number of them surmounreth that be at this day malicious. I confesse one thing, and suppose many will fauour mee in the same.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Phauorin</hi> the Philosopher (which was master to <hi>Aulus Gelius,</hi> and his es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall friend) saide oft-times, that the Phylosophers in olde time, were hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in reputation: <hi>Because there were fewe teachers, and many learners:</hi> We now-adayes see the contrarie: <hi>For infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite are they which presume to bee Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters: but fewe are they which humble themselues to be Schollers.</hi> A man may know how little Wise-men are estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at this houre, by the great vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that the Phylosophers had, in the olde time.</p>
   <p>What a matter is it to see <hi>Homer</hi> amongst the <hi>Grecians, Salomon</hi> amōgst the <hi>Hebrewes, Lycurgus</hi> amongst the <hi>Lacedemonians: Phoromeus</hi> also a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Greeks, Ptolomeus</hi> amongst the <hi>Egiptians, Liuius</hi> amongst the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines:</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> likewise amongst the <hi>Latines: Appolonius</hi> amongst the <hi>Indyans,</hi> and <hi>Secundus,</hi> amongst the <hi>Assyrians?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>How happie were those Phyloso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, (to bee as they were, in those dayes) when the world was so full of simple personnes, and so destitute of Sage men: that there flocked great numbers out of diuers countreys, and
<pb facs="18"/>
straunge Nations, not onely to heare their doctrine: but also to see theyr persons.</p>
   <p>The glorious Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> in the prologue, to the Byble, sayth: When <hi>Rome</hi> was in her prosperitie, then wrote <hi>Titus Lyuius</hi> his deedes: yet notwithstanding, men came to <hi>Rome,</hi> more to speake with <hi>Titus Linius,</hi> then to see <hi>Rome,</hi> or the high capitol therof. <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> writing to his friend <hi>Pulio,</hi> saide these wordes: Thou shalt vnderstand (my Friende,) I was not chosen Emperor for the Noble bloud of my predecessors: nor, for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour I had amongst them now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent: For there were in <hi>Rome,</hi> of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bloud, and Riches then I, but the (Emperour <hi>Adrian</hi> my Maister) set his eyes vpon mee: and the Emperor <hi>Anthonie</hi> my Father in law, chose mee for his Sonne in law: for none other <note place="margin">For what cause Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aureli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> cause, but for that they saw me a friend of the <hi>Sages,</hi> and an enemie of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt.</p>
   <p>Happie was <hi>Rome</hi> to chuse so wise an Emperour, and no lesse happie was he to attaine vnto so great an Empire. Not for that hee was heire to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessours, but for that hee gaue his minde to studie. Truely, if that Age were then happie to enioy his person: no lesse happie shall ours bee now at this present, to enjoy his doctrine. <hi>Salust</hi> saith, they deserued great glory, which did worthie feates: and no lesser merited they, which wrote them in high stile.</p>
   <p>What had <hi>Alexander</hi> the great bin, if <hi>Quintus-Curtius</hi> had not written of him? what of <hi>Vlysses,</hi> if <hi>Homer</hi> had not bin borne? what had <hi>Alcybiades</hi> bin, if <hi>Zenophon</hi> had not exalted him? what of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> if the phylosopher <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> had not put his actes in memorie? what had been of <hi>Pyrrus</hi> king of the <hi>Epyrotes,</hi> if <hi>Hermicles</hi> chronicles were not? what had bin of <hi>Scipio</hi> the great <hi>Affricane,</hi> if it had not bin for the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cades</hi> of <hi>Titus Liuius?</hi> what had been of <hi>Traian,</hi> if the renowmed <hi>Plutarch</hi> had not bin his friend? what of <hi>Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> and <hi>Anthonius</hi> the meeke, if <hi>Phoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the <hi>Greeke</hi> had not made mention of them? How should wee haue knowne the stoute courage of <hi>Caesar,</hi> and the great prowesse of <hi>Pompeius,</hi> if <hi>Lucanus</hi> had not written them? what of the twelue <hi>Caesars,</hi> if <hi>Suetonius Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillus</hi> had not compyled a booke of their liues? And how should we haue knowne the antiquities of the <hi>Hebrues</hi> if the vpright <hi>Ioseph</hi> had not beene?</p>
   <p>Who could haue knowne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>Lombardes,</hi> into <hi>Italie,</hi> if <hi>Paulus Dyaconus</hi> had not writ it? How could we haue knowne the comming in, and the going out of the <hi>Gothes</hi> in <hi>Spayne</hi> if the curious <hi>Roderious</hi> had not showed it vnto vs?</p>
   <p>By these things we haue spoken of before, the Readers may perceyue what is due vnto the Hystoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: who in my opinion, haue left as great memorie of them, for that they wrote with their pennes: as the Princes haue done, for that they did with their swords. I confesse I deserue nor to be named amongst the Sages, neyther for that I haue written and Translated, nor yet for that I haue composed.</p>
   <p>Therefore (the Sacred and diuine letters set aside) there is nothing in the world so curiously written, but nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth correction: and as I say of the one, so will I say of the other, and that is: as I with my will doe renounce the glory, which the good for my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning would giue mee: so in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner euill men shall not want, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my will seeke to defame it.</p>
   <p>Wee other writers, smally esteeme that labour and paines wee haue to write, although indeede wee are not ignorant of a thousaund enuious tongues, that will backbite it.</p>
   <p>Many now adayes are so euil taught,
<pb facs="19"/>
or to say better, so enuious, that when the Author laboreth in his study, they play in the streetes: when he awaketh, they sleepe, when he fasteth, they eate: when hee sitteth turning the leaues of the booke: they goe hunting after vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces abroade: yet for all that, they will presume to iudge, depraue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne an other mans doctrine, as if they had the authoritie that <hi>Plato</hi> had in <hi>Greece,</hi> or the eloquence that <hi>Cicero</hi> had in <hi>Rome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>When I finde a man in the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue well seene, his vulgar tongue well p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lished, in hystories well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in <hi>Greeke-</hi>letters very expert, and desirous to spend his time with good bookes: this so Heroicall and noble a personage, I would desire him to put my doctrine vnder his feete. For it is no shame, for a vertuous and wise man, to be corrected of an other wise man. Yet I would gladly know what patiēce can suffer, or heart can dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when two or three bee assembled together at meate, and after (at the table or otherwise) one of them taketh a booke at aduenture in his handes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that which another will say it is <note place="margin">The diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of mens opinions.</note> too long, and another will say, it spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not to the purpose: another, it is very obscure: &amp; another, the words are not well couched: another will say, all that is spoken is fayned; One will say, hee speaketh nothing of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: another, hee is too curious, and the other, hee is too malicious. So that in speaking thus, the doctrine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth suspitious, and the Authour scapeth not scot-free.</p>
   <p>Suppose them to be therefore such that speake it (as I haue spoken of) &amp; that at the Table do finde such faults, sure, they deserue pardon: for they speake not according to the Bookes which they haue read, but according to the cups of wine which they haue drunke: For that, <hi>Hee that taketh not in iest which is spoken at the Table, knoweth not what iesting meaneth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is an olde custom to murmure at vertuous deedes, and into this rule entreth not onely those that make them, but also those which writethem afterwards.</p>
   <p>Which thing seemeth to be true, for that <hi>Socrates</hi> was reproued of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Plato</hi> of <hi>Aristotle, Aristotle</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerois, Sicilius</hi> of <hi>Vulpitius, Lelius</hi> of <hi>Varro, Marinus</hi> of <hi>Ptolomeus, Ennius</hi> of <hi>Horace, Seneca</hi> of <hi>Aulus Gelius, Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stonestes</hi> of <hi>Strabo, Thessale</hi> of <hi>Gellian, Hermagoras</hi> of <hi>Cicero, Cicero</hi> of <hi>Salust, Origines</hi> of Saint <hi>Hierome, Hierome</hi> of <hi>Rufinus, Rufinus</hi> of <hi>Donatus. Donatus</hi> of <hi>Prosper,</hi> and <hi>Prosper</hi> of <hi>Lupus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Then sith that in these men, and in their workes hath beene such need of correction, which were men of great knowledge, and Lanternes of the World: It is no maruell at all that I haue such fortune, since I know so little as I doe. Hee may worthily <note place="margin">One ought not rashly to cōdemne another mans wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> bee counted vaine and light, which at the first sight, as for onely once rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, will rashly iudge that which a wise man with much diligence &amp; stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath written.</p>
   <p>The Authors and Writers are oft times reproued, not of them which can translate, and compile workes: but of those which cannot reade, and yet lesse vnderstand them, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent simple folkes should count them wise, and take their parts in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this worke, and esteeme him for a great wise man. I take God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse who can iudge, whether my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention were good or ill, to compile this worke, and also I lay this my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine at the feet of wise and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, to the end they may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, and defendours of the same: For I trust in God, though som would come to blame (as diuers do) the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple words which I spake: yet others would not fayle to relate the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention that I meant.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="19"/>
And to declare further I say, that diuers have written of the time of the sayde <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> as <hi>Herodian</hi> wrote little, <hi>Eutropius</hi> lesse, <hi>Lampridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> not so much, and <hi>Iulius Capitolinus</hi> somewhat more.</p>
   <p>Likewise yee ought to know, that the Masters which taught <hi>Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius</hi> sciences, were <hi>Iunius Rusticus, Cinna Catullus, Sextus Cheronensis,</hi> which was nephew to the great <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These three were those, that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, as witnesses of sight, wrote the most part of his life and doctrine. Many may maruel to heare tell of the doctrine of <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> saying it hath beene kept hidde and secret a great while, and that of mine owne head I haue inuented it. And that there neuer was any <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> in the world. I know not what to say now vnto them; for it is euident to all those which haue read any thing that <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> was husband to <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine,</hi> father to <hi>Comodus,</hi> brother to <hi>Anntus Verus,</hi> and sonne in Law to <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> the seuenth (of <hi>Rome)</hi> Emperour</p>
   <p>Those which say, I only haue made this doctrine, truly I thanke them for so saying, but not for their so mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: For truly the Romanes would haue set my Image in <hi>Rome</hi> for perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall renowne, if so graue sentences should haue proceeded frō my head. Wee see that in our time which was neuer seene before, and heare that we neuer heard before. VVe practise not in a new world, and yet wee maruell that there is at this present a newe booke.</p>
   <p>Not for that I was curious to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> or studious to translate him. For, truely it is worthy he bee noted of wise persons, and not accused of enuious tongues. For, it <hi>chaunceth oftentimes in Hunting, that the most simplest man killeth the Deare.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The last thing which the <hi>Romaines</hi> conquered in <hi>Spayne,</hi> was <hi>Cantabria,</hi> which was a citie in <hi>Nauarre,</hi> ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>La-grogne,</hi> and scituated in a high Countrey, where there is now a vaine of Vines. And the Emperour <hi>Augustus</hi> which destroyed it, made tenne bookes, <hi>De Bello Cantabrico:</hi> wherein are many thinges worthie of noting, and no lesse pleasaunt in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which happened vnto him, in the same conquest.</p>
   <p>As <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> was brought mee from <hi>Florence,</hi> so was this other booke, <hi>Of the warres of Cantabria,</hi> brought mee from <hi>Colleyne.</hi> If per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I tooke paines to Translate this booke, as few haue done which haue seene it, they would speake the like of it, that they did of <hi>Marcus Aurclius.</hi> Because men are so long in speaking, and so briefe in studying, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any let or shame, they will auowe no Booke to be in the world this day, but that they haue eyther reade, or seene it.</p>
   <p>I haue as much profited in this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which is humane: as other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours haue done in matters, which are diuine. It is not translated word for word, but sentence for sentence. For wee other Enterpreters, are not bound to giue wordes by measure: but it sufficeth vs to giue Sentences by weight.</p>
   <p>I beganne to studie this worke in the yeare, a thousand, fiue hundred, and eyghteene: and vntill the yeare <note place="margin">The time when the Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>slate the booke of Marcus Aurelius.</note> a thousand fiue hundred, twentie and soure, I could neyther vnderstand, nor know wherein I was occupyed: and albeit I (kept it as secrete as I could) for the space of sixe yeares, yet it was knowne abroad: whervpon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour his Majestie, being with the Feauer diseased, sent to mee for it, to passe the time away. And I (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his commaundement) shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> that then was
<pb facs="20"/>
vncorrected, and humbly beseeching him sayde: <hi>That for recompence of all my trau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, I desired no other rewarde, but that no man in his Chamber might copie the Booke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And in the meane time proceeded to accomplish the worke, because I did not meane in such manner to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish it: for otherwise, I saide his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie should be euill serued, and I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of my purpose preuented: but my sinnes caused that the Booke was cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyed, <note place="margin">The booke of Marcus Aurelius, at the first im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>printed, without the knowledge of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour.</note> and conueyed from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and by the hands of Pages sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day times written, so that there increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed daily in it errours, and faultes.</p>
   <p>And since there was but one originall copie, they brought it vnto me to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect: which if it could haue spoken, would haue complained it selfe, more of them that did write it, then of those that did steale it.</p>
   <p>And thus when I had finished the worke, &amp; thought to haue published it: I perceyued that <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> was now imprinted at <hi>Seuill:</hi> And in this case, I take the <hi>Readers</hi> to be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, between mee and the imprinters, because they may see, whether it may stand with Law, and justice, that a Booke which was to his <hi>Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie</hi> dedicated: the author thereof being but an jnfant, and the booke so vnperfite and vncorrected, without my consent or knowledge should bee published.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, they ceased not, but printed it againe in <hi>Portugall,</hi> and also in the Kingdome of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> And if the first impression was faulty, truely the second and the third were no lesse. So that which was written for the wealth and good of all men generally, each man did applye to the profite of himselfe particularly.</p>
   <p>There chaunced another thing of this booke, called <hi>The golden booke of Marcus Aurelius,</hi> which I am ashamed to speake; but greater shame they should haue, that so dishonestly haue done. That is: some made themselus to be authors of the whole worke: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers say, that parte of it was made, and compyled of their owne heads: the which appeareth in a booke in priut, wherein the authour did like a man voyd of all honesty, &amp; in another booke, one vsed likewise the wordes which <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> spake to <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine,</hi> when shee asked him the key of his Studie.</p>
   <p>After these Theeues came to my knowledge, iudge you whether it were ynough to prooue my patience? For, I had rather they had robbed me of my goods, then taken away my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme.</p>
   <p>By this all men may see, that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius</hi> was not then corrected, nor in any place perfect, whereby they might perceyue, that it was not my minde to Translate <hi>Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> but to make a <hi>Dyall for Princes:</hi> whereby all Christian people may be gouerned and ruled. And as the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is shewed for the vse of manie: so I would profite my selfe, with that which the wise men had spoken and written. And in this sort proceedeth the worke, wherein I put one or two chapters of mine, and after I put some Epistles of <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> and other doctrine of some Auncient men.</p>
   <p>Let not the <hi>Reader</hi> bee deceyued, to thinke hat the one, and the other is of the Authour. For, although the phrase of the Language be mine, yet I confesse the greatest part that I knew, was of another mans, althogh the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographers and Doctours, (with whom I was holpen) were manie: yet the doctrine which I wrote, was but one.</p>
   <p>I will not denye, but I haue left out some things which were superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: in whose steade I haue placed things more sweete and profitable. So that it needeth good wittes, to make
<pb facs="20"/>
which seemeth in one language to be grosse, in another to giue it the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of gold.</p>
   <p>I haue deuided into three books this present Dyall of Princes. The first treateth, that the Prince ought to bee a good Christian.</p>
   <p>The second, how hee ought for to gouerne his wife and children.</p>
   <p>The third teacheth, how he should gouerne his person, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. I had begunne ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke, wherein was contained, how a Prince should behaue himselfe in his Court and Pallace, but the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of my friendes, caused me to withdraw my penne, to the end I might bring this worke to light.</p>
   <trailer>The end of the Argument.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>