<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL VERY WORTHY indicious and vnderstanding Gentleman Sr. FRANCIS DOWSE Knight, T. Y. wisheth encrease of health and perpetuall happinesse.</title>
           <author>Young, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120602_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120602</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL VERY WORTHY indicious and vnderstanding Gentleman Sr. FRANCIS DOWSE Knight, T. Y. wisheth encrease of health and perpetuall happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Young, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands bane: or, The description of drunkennesse. Composed and written by Thomas Young, sometimes student of Staple-Inne</title>
                 <author>Young, Thomas, student of Staple Inn</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Bailey (Baily, Baley, Bayly), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL VERY WORTHY indicious and vnderstanding Gentleman Sr. FRANCIS DOWSE <hi>Knight,</hi> T. Y. <hi>wisheth</hi> encrease of health and perpetuall <hi>happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, calling to minde my owne follies (euer from mine Infancy, prone to haue coniunction with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancie the chiefe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all mens perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and also remembring your good counsell euer giuen vnto me, that I should loath excesse, &amp; loue temperance (which I now finde of it selfe to be the treasure of vertue,) compelling men to follow Reason, bringing peace to the minde, and mollifying the affections with concord and agreement, receiuing I say from you, not onely good aduice (being as great a benefit as one friend can doe to another) but also good example which is the readyest path-way to guide men to felicitie, and for feare I should bee culpable according to the prouerbe; Thankes waxeth old as soone as gifts are had in possession I thought good although I cannot requite, yet to make knowne to your Worship, that I do not forget (for <hi>omnium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratissimus
<pb facs="3"/>est,
<note place="margin">Ingratus qui be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium accepisse negat, quod acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit: Ingratus qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>d dissimulat, vursum Ingratus qui non reddit: et omnium In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratissimus qui oblitus est.</note> qui oblitus est:</hi> neither this: nor other your manifold great &amp; continuall kindnes bestowed vpon me: And that you may see how good a schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler I haue proued in the arte of sobrietie by your discipline consiliatorie and exemplarie. I am im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened to craue your patronage to this pamphlet which will at large set downe all the subtle sleights, tempting baites, and craftie allurements, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan vseth for the ouerthrow of mankinde, by this vice of drunkennes, (which indeede is the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane citie of all the prouince of vices) which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son made me intitle my Booke, <hi>Englands Bane:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause no Nation is more polluted with this capitoll sinne, then ours. And I protest it is not ambition that made me craue the patronage to this Treatise: (considering my small deseruings) but chiefely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming vpon the affiance of your good nature and kinde constructions of my weake endeauours, and something the rather, because I know your liberall qualities inclinable to the Rule of my intentions: which is not to barre Societie, but to condemne Ebrietie;
<note place="margin">Eccles. 31.23. Pro. 22.9.</note> For <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>He that is liberall shall bee blest, and honoured of his neighbours:</hi> And of this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, I know both your selfe and all your Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Family: fully indued; for often haue I heard you say, that of the Wine and Beere you regarded not the expence: but you blamed such as would abuse these creatures to ouerthrowe their owne sence, and such voluptuous liuers are them I chiefely ayme at, that cannot take moderation to bee their guide: <hi>Omne nocet nimium, mediocriter omne geren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> I know you loue to Reade: because you
<pb facs="3"/>know to censure? Let mee therefore intreat your Worship to reade this, and to giue it fauourable protection to the world: although the lines be rude, the matters good, and it is no shame to gather a Primrose growing among Briers, had it better you should enioy it, such as it is if you entertaine I shall rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships in all faithfull obseruance,</hi> THO: YOVNG.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>