<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL AND REVEREND, Mr. Dr. HALL, DEANE OF WORCESTER, my worthie and much respected Friend, all happinesse, with my loue in CHRIST IESVS.</title>
           <author>Baguley, H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL AND REVEREND, Mr. Dr. HALL, DEANE OF WORCESTER, my worthie and much respected Friend, all happinesse, with my loue in CHRIST IESVS.</title>
                 <author>Baguley, H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="533" facs="283"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL AND REVEREND, M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> D<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> HALL, DEANE OF WORCESTER, my worthie and much respected Friend, all happinesse, with my loue in CHRIST IESVS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Euerend Sir; this Sermon, I know, is at the Presse before you expected: But I thought (as this glorious Chapell occasioned it, so) it might minister occasion of perpetuall remembrance of the Chapell, by remaining its first Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument. And altho both these were confined to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate; the Chapell for the Family of my Right Honorable Lord the Earle of Exceter, who hath giuen the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thereof sufficient luster: and the Copie of the Sermon to the Cabinet of my truly Noble, and vertuous Lady, his Countesse; yet both these are much and oft required to the publike; the Sermon to be an instruction, and so it is; the Chapell, to be an example, and so it may be. The Sermon to teach all, to be all glorious in their soules. The Chapell to teach some, who build houses for their owne habitation, to set vp another for Gods Religion. The Sermon was craued at the hands of my Honourable Ladie, that it might come to the Presse; who, of her owne pious disposition, gaue forth the Copie, and for her Noble esteeme of your selfe, and of the worth of your sermon, was willing and desirous to giue it way to the Printer. And this I thought good to impart vnto you, and to the courteous Reader, that you may be satisfied of the meanes how, and the cause why it comes in publike. And so praying for you, and desiring your prayers for me, I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your truly louing Friend, H. BAGVLEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>