<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the three greate Columbes of this Em∣pire: the Nobilitie, the Gentrie, and Yeo∣manrie of greate Brittaine.</title>
           <author>M., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120787_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06903</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17334</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120787</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the three greate Columbes of this Em∣pire: the Nobilitie, the Gentrie, and Yeo∣manrie of greate Brittaine.</title>
                 <author>M., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cauelarice, or The English horseman : contayning all the arte of horse-manship, as much as is necessary for any man to vnderstand, whether he be horse-breeder, horse-ryder, horse-hunter, horse-runner, horse-ambler, horse-farrier, horse-keeper, coachman, smith, or sadler. Together, with the discouery of the subtill trade or mistery of horse-coursers, &amp; an explanatio [n] of the excellency of a horses vndersta [n] ding, or how to teach them to doe trickes like Bankes his curtall: and that horses may be made to drawe drie-foot like a hound. Secrets before vnpublished, &amp; now carefully set down for the profit of this whole nation: by Geruase Markham</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 88, 4, 212, 233-264, 4, 67, 58-72, 4, 54, 4, 56, 4, 64, 4, 11, 10-81, 5, 20, 25-40 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the three greate Columbes of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire:</hi> the Nobilitie, the Gentrie, and Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manrie of greate <hi>Brittaine.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O sooner shal this worke of mine breake foorth into the world, but I know it will stirre vp manye thoughts in many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: some wondring what new matter I haue to speake of, some fearing old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, and some resting satisfyed in their opinions with that small treatise which I formerly published; but to all these I knowe the worke it selfe will giue indifferēt satisfactiō, only touching that small treatise of horseman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, which about foureteene yeres agone (when myne experience was but youngly fortified) I brought foorth into the world: giue mee leaue to deliuer you these few reasons. First it was not gathered for any publique viewe or benefit, but onely at the intreatie of a deare kinsman (in those daies much inamored with delight in riding) was as essayes or tastes collected for his priuate vse; and that he might with lesse difficultie attaine the perfection at which he aymed. Next, beeing intended for him, who was well grounded in the arte before, I was lesse care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to obserue those plaine rules of demonstration, then otherwaies I would haue beene, my thoughts not then plotting the benefit of any such as were ignorant, and so I must confesse I let passe the worke with more obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie &amp; darknes then otherwise I shold haue done. Lastly
<pb facs="4"/>
a coppie thereof being corruptly taken, and couetouslye offered to the printing without my knowledge. I thought it as good my selfe to publish it with his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wants, as to let it come abroad by others with vilder deformities: and hence proceeded the appearance of my first Epitomie in the world; which because it hath found fauour both amongst my friendes and strangers, and the better to satisfie them, who haue done me honour in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing allowance to mine imperfect labours, I thought good to publish this larger volume, wherein I haue not only at full laid open al the obscurities &amp; concealements which haue beene hidden both in it, and in other wrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, but also made such an euen &amp; dyrect pathe to lead the most ignorantest spirit, through the bowels &amp; hart of this praise-worthy arte, that not any man whatsoeuer (who will bestow the reading therof) but shal in his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test doubt touching any intricate proposition in Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship, finde both reason &amp; satisfaction, whether he be generall, as delighting in al things wherin the vse of horse is imployed, or particular as adicted to anye peculiar braunch or member: wherin as my labour &amp; the expēce of my best houres, hath only tended to a publique good, so I desire my reward may not be either an especiall mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>construction, or a particular enuie; &amp; that as the strength of my wish hath been to help those which know nothing in this art, so it may be an attractiue perswasion to those which knowe much more then my selfe, to publish their skils, and so to make it a moste compleat art, till when let this booke &amp; my loue be a true testimony of my zeale &amp; seruice to my Countrie, whose flourishing estate and wealthy peace I pray may neuer end, til the last of al times be ended.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>G. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>