<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT OF this Epistle to the COLOSSIANS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120678_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17389</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4216</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120678</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT OF this Epistle to the COLOSSIANS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition vpon the Epistle to the Colossians : Wherein, not onely the text is methodically analysed, and the sence of the words, by the help of vvriters, both ancient and moderne is explayned: but also, by doctrine and vse, the intent of the holy Ghost is in euery place more fully vnfolded and vrged. And besides, the very marrow of most common-places is aptly diffused through-out the body of this exposition, as the nature of of [sic] this kinde of teaching would beare. And further, many chiefe cases of conscience are here resolued. All with conuenient varietie and breuitie. Being, the substance of neare seauen yeeres vveeke-dayes sermons, of N. Byfield, late one of the preachers for the citie of Chester</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 173, that is 179, 9, 90, 10, 116, 119-137, 9, 157-202 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary_of_Colossians">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT OF this Epistle to the COLOSSIANS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are foure principall Parts of this <hi>Epistle: 1.</hi> the <hi>Proaeme: 2. Doctrine of Faith: 3. Precepts of life. 4.</hi> the <hi>Epilogue,</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion. The <hi>Proaeme</hi> is exprest in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> first eleuen Verses of the first Chapter: The <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Faith</hi> is exprest in the rest of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the first Chapter, and the whole second Chapter: The <hi>Precepts of life</hi> are set downe in the third Chapter, and in the beginning of the fourth. And the <hi>Epilogue</hi> is in the rest of the verses of the fourth Chapter.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Proaeme</hi> containes two things: First, the <hi>Salutation, vers. 1, 2.</hi> and secondly, a <hi>Preface,</hi> affectionately framed to winne attention and respect: wherein he assures them of his singular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie in remembring them to God, both in Thanks-giuing for their worthy Graces and the meanes thereof, <hi>v. 3.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</hi> and in earnest Prayer for their increase and comfortable perseuerance in knowledge and the eminencie of sinceritie in holy life, <hi>vers: 9.10, 11.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Doctrine of Faith</hi> he expresseth two wayes: first, by Proposition: secondly, by Exhortation. In the Proposition of Doctrine, hee doth with singular force of words, and weight of matter set out both the worke of our Redemption, <hi>v. 12.13.14.</hi> and the person of our Redeemer: and that first in his relation to God, <hi>verse 15.</hi> then in relation of the World, <hi>verse 15.16.17.</hi> and thirdly, in relation to the Church, both the whole in generall, <hi>verse 18.19.20.</hi> and the Church of the <hi>Colossians</hi> in particular,
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>vers. 21.22.</hi> And thus of the Proposition. Now his Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion followes, from the <hi>23.</hi> of <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> to the end of <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> and therein hee both perswades and disswades: hee perswades by many strong and mouing Reasons, to an holy endeauour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and perseuere with all Christian firmnesse of resolution, both in the Faith and Hope, was already begotten in them by the Gospell: and this is contained in the seauen last Verses of the first Chapter, and the seauen first Verses of the second Chapter. Hee disswades them from receiuing the corrupt Doctrine of the false Apostles, whether it were drawne from Philosophicall Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or from the Traditions of men, or from the Ceremoniall Law of <hi>Moses</hi>; and hee proceedes in this order: first, hee layes downe the matter of his Dehortation, <hi>Chap. 2. vers. 8.</hi> then secondly, hee confirmes it by diuers Reasons, from <hi>vers. 9.</hi> to <hi>16.</hi> and lastly, he concludes, and that seuerally, as against <hi>Mosaicall</hi> Rites, <hi>vers. 16.17.</hi> against Philosophy, <hi>vers. 18.19.</hi> and against Traditions, <hi>vers. 20.</hi> and so to the end of that Chapter.</p>
   <p>Thus of the second part.</p>
   <p>Thirdly,<note n="3" place="margin">
         <hi>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of life.</hi>
      </note> in giuing <hi>Precepts of life</hi> the Apostle holds this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: first, hee giues generall Rules, that concerne all as they are Christians: then, hee giues speciall Rules, as they are men of this or that estate of life. The generall Rules are contayned in the first seauenteene Verses of the third Chapter: and the speciall Rules from the eighteenth Verse of the third Chapter to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Verse of the fourth. The generall Rules hee reduceth into three heads: <hi>viz.</hi> first, the Meditation of heauenly things, <hi>vers. 1.2.3.4.</hi> secondly, the mortification of vices and iniuries, <hi>vers. 5.</hi> to the <hi>12.</hi> thirdly, the exercise of holy Graces, a number of which hee reckoneth, both in the kindes, meanes, and ends of them, from <hi>vers. 12.</hi> to <hi>18.</hi> The particular Rules concerne principally houshould gouernment: for hee sets downe the dutie of Wiues, <hi>vers. 18.</hi> of Husbands, <hi>ver. 19.</hi> of Children, <hi>vers. 20.</hi> of Parents, <hi>v. 21.</hi> of Seruants, <hi>vers. 22.23.24.25.</hi> and of Maisters, <hi>Chap. 4. vers. 1.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Epilogue,</hi>
      <note n="4" place="margin">
         <hi>The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</hi>
      </note> or Conclusion, contaynes in it both matter of generall Exhortation, as also matters of Salutation. The generall Exhortation concernes Prayer, <hi>vers. 2.3.4.</hi> wise Conuersation,
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>vers. 5.</hi> and godly Communication, <hi>vers. 6.</hi> Now after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle hath disburdened himselfe of those generall cares, then hee taketh liberty to refresh himselfe and them, by remembring cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that were deare both to him and them. And first, he makes enterance by a narration of his care to know their estate, and to informe them of his. To which purpose he sendeth and prayseth <hi>Tichicus</hi> and <hi>Onesimus, vers. 7.8.9.</hi> The Salutations then follow; and they are of two sorts: for some are signified to them, some are required in them. Of the first sort, he signifies the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations of sixe men, three of them Iewes, and three Gentiles, <hi>vers. 10.11.12.13.14.</hi> The Salutations required, concerne ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Laodiceans, vers. 15.16.</hi> or one of the <hi>Colossaean</hi> Preachers, who is not onely saluted, but exhorted, <hi>vers. 17.</hi> And then followes the Apostles generall Salutations to all, in the last Verse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>