<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Grati∣ous and Noble Prince Henrie, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>C., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120925_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09133</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19446</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120925</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Grati∣ous and Noble Prince Henrie, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>C., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>False complaints. Or The censure of an vnthankfull mind, the labour of Carolus Pascalius translated into English by W.C. A worke very learned and fit for all estates in this age of vnnecessarie discontentments, shewing how all complaine, but all without cause</title>
                 <author>Paschal, Carlo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72, 75-245, 1 page, illustrations c 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Right</hi> Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Noble Prince <hi>Henrie, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing all affections are imployd to pay atributarie duty, to that great happinesse, whereunto all are bownd; let it not seeme strang to any, if (after al others, and in an other manner) I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume, both to testifie my humble dutie, &amp; to make offer of that seruice, which I am able to perform: I haue done in this, little; sauing only, giuing occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siō to your Princely towardnes, for the increasing of both the tongues, to labour in this kind: there are few arguments, which carrie with them more varietie, better inuention, sounder iudgment, then this doth. And being a disease both common
<pb facs="3"/>
and dangerous, fit for all men to learne, hovv it may bee cured; if your princely Wisedome vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe but to reade this translation, and compare it at sometimes vvith the author himselfe, you shall easily see, the excellencie of the English tongue, not refusing to expresse with much proprietie the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie of the hardest latine stile; and withall, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern hovv all men, are almost wearie of their own happines, &amp; how most, most vnthankfully cōplain, that haue least cause: It vvas not (though but a translation) a labour vnfit for me, seeing it was so commended vnto me, as a paines to you, and for you. And considering that your princely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes, promising great hope, in the perfection of all vertues hath beene alreadie thus blest, to receiue in your infancy a Testamentary Councell, full of the wisest precepts, that any man, euer vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred out of the seate of a King, since the dayes of <hi>Salomon:</hi> vouchsafe (Noble Prince) to accept these, though farre weaker then the other (&amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduēture, such as shal find litle in you to reform of this error) yet they willshew vnto your Highnesse a great part of that disease, wher-with the World at this day, is so much troubled. But howsoeuer;
<pb facs="3"/>
being for this time, all that, wherein I can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse my humble affection, to your princely wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dōe: I doubt not, but your Highnes, wil (both) par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it, &amp; accustome your selfe, in your yong yeares, to a diligent consideration of all those vnspeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blessings, that are heaped vpō you; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse out of this fountaine of thankefulnes, shall flow continuall streames of far greater blessings. For which there are, and shall be many Zealous prayers, as incense offered daily vp vnto God, in your behalfe, to whome nothing can bee wanting, wherby, in all princely Graces, you may not exceed all that haue beene before you: If you your selfe (which is not to be feared) be not wanting to your self; thus desiring, that from aboue, your Highnes may be continually blessed with all the blessings of Heauen, and earth: I doe humbly craue pardon, and take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesses in all dutie.
W. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>