<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE; VVILLIAM: EARLE of PENBROOK, Lord Chamberlaine to his Maiesties Houshold, and one of his most ho∣nourable Councell, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120961_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09847</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20111</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120961</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE; VVILLIAM: EARLE of PENBROOK, Lord Chamberlaine to his Maiesties Houshold, and one of his most ho∣nourable Councell, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A gagge for the Pope, and the Iesuits: or The arraignement, and execution of Antichrist : Shevving plainely, that Antichrist shall be discouered, and punished in this vvorld: to the amasement of all obstinate papists</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 82 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE; VVILLIAM: EARLE of PENBROOK, Lord Chamberlaine to his Maiesties <hi>Houshold, and one of his most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Councell, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I intend nothing by this Discourse, but the glory of God, the good of my Country, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of <hi>Princes,</hi> and the seasoning of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: so doe I propose no man fitter to Patronise the same, then
<pb facs="3"/> your selfe, sprung from so illustrious a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our moderne Stories reioyce againe in the illustration of the name and actions of <hi>Herbert:</hi> but aboue all, my motiues arise from your Noble disposition toward <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> glory, and pious zeale to propagate the cause of Religion, which at this day is set vpon by viperous calumniation, as if either God meant not to performe his promise, concerning the stripping the <hi>Strumpet</hi> naked, <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 3.</note> who hath made drunke the Kings of the earth with the cup of abomination: or <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie</hi> determined, like <hi>Prometheus</hi> his <hi>Vulture,</hi> to feed vpon the heart of Religion, and eat out the bowels of sanctitie, and truth But O thou God of heauen, thou laughest the <note place="margin">Psalme.</note> deuises of men to scorne, and wilt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy owne cause in despight of <hi>Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> and <hi>O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ee Princes</hi> of the earth, looke yee <note place="margin">Psal. 2. 12.</note> kisse the sonne, least he be angry, and yee perish in the Way, when his wrath shall suddenly burne.</p>
   <p>Wherefore great <hi>Lord,</hi> made so much the greater by all the <hi>Concomitants</hi> of <hi>Noble birth,</hi> and remarkeable deseruing, accept I pray you of this poore <hi>Tractate,</hi> wherein though
<pb facs="3"/> I come strangely toward you with a dutie from an vnknowne name, and vnfortunate man, as we prophanely abuse the <hi>Character,</hi> yet with so good a heart, that in regard of the cause, which is Gods, and your selfe, who haue answered reputation with suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, I am cheerfully animated to wade out of this streame, by the supportation of so noble an arme, which can keep me from sinking, though there were some whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole to fall into.</p>
   <p>As for aspersion of presumption, stepping out of my own Circle, medling with trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent matters, tenuity of wit, or deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of knowledge, I wipe all away with a Principle in <hi>Euripid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s.—Nullus sibi similis in peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iphigenia in Tauris.</note>
      <hi>homo, quoties ad audaciam ex metu venerit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But indeed what should I be affrighted with the <hi>Popes</hi> fulmination, or curses, <hi>Lucan</hi> answers;
<q>
         <hi>Tollite signaduces, fatorum impellite cursum,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Lib. 5. Phars<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>l.</note>
         <hi>spem vestram prestate diis, fortuna{que} tantos det vobis animos, quantos fugientibus hostem causa dabat.</hi>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>The blastings of opinion, or windy cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Impia laetatur vulgatae nomine famae,—Thessaliis.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Lib. 5.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The displeasure or contracted brow of a Prince? <hi>No, no.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Caesaris aduentu tuta gladiator arena,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 6. de Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Ovid.</note>
      <hi>exit, &amp; auxilium non leue vultus habet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The imputations of iudicious men?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>—Simplex oratio veritatis est;</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ne{que} variarum habet vtrin{que} interpretationum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eurip. Phaenissae.</note>
      <hi>habet enim ipsa congruentiam, sed iniquus sermo aegrotans in seipsum, medicamimum habet opus sapientiam.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The desertion of friends? who be they?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Amicos in rebus aduersis conuenit amicis adesse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eurip. Orestes.</note>
      <hi>Nam cum Deus faelicitatem dederit, Quid opus est amicis? Sufficit ipse Deus prodesse volens.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In a word, so I haue your fauour and my owne ends, I am startled at nothing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficiency in so great aduenture, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines to put polluted handes into the waters of life: which as I hope the God of heauen will pardon, because of my honest desires to magnifie his greatnes: so your Honor will graciously admit, because of my willing heart to exemplifie your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>