<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Certaine aduertisements to the Christian and courteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120031_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15400</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25678</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120031</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Certaine aduertisements to the Christian and courteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An harmonie vpon the first booke of Samuel : wherein according to the methode obserued in Hexapla vpon Genesis, and Exodus, but more compendiously abridged, these speciall things are obserued vpon euery chapter: the diuers readings compared, doubtfull questions explaned, places of Scripture reconciled, controuersies briefly touched, and morall collections applied. Wherein aboue foure hundred theologicall questions are handled, with great breuitie and much varietie, by the former author of Hexapla on Genesis</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Bankworth, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Greene, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 83, 88-351, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Certaine aduertisements to the Christian and courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Commentarie vpon the first booke of <hi>SAMVEL,</hi> I haue followed a more compendious course, then in my larger Treatise vpon Genesis, and in the like vpon Exodus, which is now readie to come forth. And hereunto I was mooued by these reasons: first, in regard of the Readers, who as they are delighted with varietie of questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, so the same is more welcome when it is accompanied with breuitie: short treatises also are more easily purchased, euery one cannot reach vnto the price of larger volumes. Beside, in respect of my selfe, I saw, that a mans whole life sufficed not to goe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all the bookes of the Scriptures in that large and ample manner. And further, whereas in these Theologicall discourses, published in the vulgar tongue, the profite of the vnlearned is cheifly intended, whereas the learned may helpe themselues with treatises in other languages, I thought it not needefull cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously to handle obscure and difficult questions, but in such fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and plaine manner, as might best serue for the instruction of all. Some are too large in the discussing of questions, and resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of doubts: and some againe are too short: of the first sort, were some of the auncient writers,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. advers. Ioan. Hierosol.</hi>
      </note> who as <hi>Hierome</hi> saith, <hi>Vix singulas quaestiones explicare multis voluminibus potuerunt: could scarce handle seuerall questions in many volumes.</hi> And of the other sort he thus writeth, <hi>Repertus est nostris seculis haud grandis homunculus, qui de cunctis quaestionibus vno linguae rotatu sole clarius coruscaret: A certaine fellowe is found in our age of no great account, which with one turne of the tongue can make any question as cleare as the Sunne.</hi> I haue laboured in this booke to take a course betweene both, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="4"/>
to be superfluous in vnnecessarie prolixitie, nor obscure in affected breuitie.</p>
   <p>Those seuerall points, which in the larger <hi>Hexapla</hi> I seueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, I haue for breuitie sake, intermingled together: namely touching the diuerse readings, the explaning of questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the deciding of controuersies, and applying of morall places▪ The capitall letters euery where vsed, shew the authors names,<note place="margin">
         <hi>A.</hi> Arias Mont. <hi>C.</hi> Chalde. <hi>S.</hi> Septuagint. <hi>L.</hi> Latine text. <hi>I.</hi> Iunius. <hi>V.</hi> Vatablus. <hi>B.</hi> the Bish. transl. <hi>G.</hi> Geneva. <hi>Pell.</hi> Pellicane. <hi>Bor.</hi> Borrhaius. <hi>Mar.</hi> Martyr. <hi>Osiand.</hi> Osiander.</note> as is here expressed in the margen: whether this method which I haue here propounded to my selfe, or that in my former workes shall prooue more profitable, or beneficiall to the Reader, I leaue to the blessing of God, and the iudgement of the iudicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. In this course, which I am entred into to profit my selfe and others, many rubbes and lets I haue had to hinder me, virulent pennes, and invectiues, forraine suits and troubles in law, beside some domesticall cares: some of which God hath giuen happie issue vnto, and so he will, I doubt not in his good time to the rest: that (to vse the Apostles words) <hi>I may fulfill my course with ioy,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act. 20.24.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>and the ministration which I haue receiued of the Lord Iesus, to testifie the Gospel of the grace of God.</hi> Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>