<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the happie reuiuing of our former hopes.</title>
           <author>Wilkinson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120035_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15385</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25661</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120035</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the happie reuiuing of our former hopes.</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A paire of sermons successiuely preacht to a paire of peereles and succeeding princes : The former as an ante-funerall to the late Prince Henry, anno Dom. 1612. October 25. The first day of his last and fatall sicknesse. The latter preacht this present yeere 1614. Ianuar. 16. to the now liuing Prince Charles, as a preseruer of his life, and life to his soule</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Aspley, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 89, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the happie reuiuing of our former hopes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you (Most excellent) and to no other so properly belongeth the patronage of this fatall payre, whereof the latter was directlie for you, former before you, yea they were both preacht in your hearing, both fitted for your meditation, and now both publisht at your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
   <p>J confesse my selfe for late fauours excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly bound vnto your Highnesse; whereupon bethinking by what meanes J might best either expresse or deserue thankes, me thought a tender of these Sermons publisht might serue to doe it, but when J remembred that saying, <hi>Doth he thanke that seruant, because he did what was commanded him, &amp;c.</hi> J found that J
<pb facs="3"/>had lost my thankes, because your Highnesse had so commanded it; yea and J find this beside, that as he who comming to discharge his debt, and finding the gold in his purse to be copper, doth not onely not pay it, but is lesse able to make payment then before, so finde J it with my selfe, that either J must say with the poore debter in the Gospell, <hi>Haue patience with mee:</hi> or with the woman in the lawe, not able to bring <hi>a Lambe,</hi> J must offer <hi>a paire of Turtles:</hi> And though a paire of Turtles be not a Lambe, nor any action of necessarie dutie may goe for testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of thankes, yet J am sure it may be so, if your Highnesse shall so esteeme it, for God hath made you a Prince, and Princes are Gods, and it is a part of Gods good nature, <hi>To call things which are not, as if they were.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Concerning the funerall part of this paire, J haue been questioned with by others, and haue a little studied in my selfe, why in such varietie as the Scripture yeeldeth, J made such a choise, as to speake of a <hi>Text</hi> before a liuing, yea a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Prince, which the Minister by order rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before a dead corps: but J haue been better able to make vse of it since, then to giue a reason of
<pb facs="3"/>it before; for now J find, that euen those actions of ours, wherein we least deliberate, yet are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by God to a speciall purpose: and J finde that God had in this an vse of mee, which J knew not, as the colt caried Christ, and yet knew not whether: Jndeed J might well bee questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with, for bringing <hi>Death</hi> into the Court, which is welcome no where; but least of al there; where though euery day bring forth a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, yet the Mourning garment is so out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, as <hi>Mordecai</hi> for his garment sake, <hi>might not come within the Kings gate;</hi> but yet <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the most magnificall of the Kings, and the flower of all Courtiers said, <hi>It is better to goe into the house of mourning, &amp;c.</hi> Jnto that house doth the former of these meditations leade you, there to see and consider, how not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inferiour persons, but also Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours haue lyen downe in the dust, and they which haue taxed the whole world haue at last paid tribute themselues, and done their due to nature: Euery man tels you, that what soeuer was your Brothers, is now by deuolution yours: giue me leaue also to tel you, that as his fortunes, so his fate also shall one day be yours; and that you are
<pb facs="4"/>not so sure to succeede your Fathers in their Thrones, as in their Sepulchres: Jf this pill bee too bitter, the latter part will make amends: for it is <hi>A preseruatiue to your life,</hi> a receit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst death, and Physicke to your soule, which if your Highnesse shall receiue, and digest with that mind wherewith it was administred, it shall make you as sound and immortall, as bee the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints in heauen: And if from my store there hath come any dramme or scruple to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that, Oh how happy shal I be! yea how happy shall J be, to adde but the least drop of life-blood to him, for whose life, length of daies, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happinesse, so many soules and assemblies of men, yea so many kingdomes make dailie suite vpon their knees: Then shall J style my selfe a new, like Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> an Euangelist and a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician, and shall write, not onely, <hi>His Maiesties euer deuoted,</hi> and now of late <hi>more deuinct and obliged Chaplaine,</hi> but also</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>One of your Highnesse Soule-Physicians. <hi>Robert Wilkinson.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>