<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120020_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15535</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120020</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A crucifixe: or, A meditation vpon repentance, and, the holie passion. Written by Christopher Lever</title>
                 <author>Lever, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Writings of Men, as they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, so are they diuersly affected: yet euer in this inequalitie; that mo to the bad, than to the better be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed. The reason is, corruption in Iudgement, dulnesse of Vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, blindenesse in Election, and a deprauednesse in the whole frame of Nature: whereof it commeth that many deceiue themselues in their choise, neglecting what is of neerest consideration, yet embrace that (with strong appetite,) which is most perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and pestilent. I write not this to offend any one, but to remember all: for I had rather profite than please: and to giue friendly admonishment is better than silence. That great Apostle Saint <hi>Paule</hi> defired to knowe nothing but Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and him crucified, and dooth detest to reioyce in aught saue in the Crosse and sufferings of his Lorde and Maister. A lesson woorthy so great a Doctour, and worth our immitation. This is that one thing which is onely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary; whereof, who hath true knowledge, hath all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. This <hi>Crosse,</hi> this <hi>Crucifix,</hi> and this <hi>Passion</hi> I present thee (gentle Reader) not in their exact formes, (for that exceedes the power of Mortalitie) but in a little resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance: wishing thee to reade, not for Mirth, but for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and with holy <hi>Paul,</hi> faithfully to apply to thy soule, the glorie and reioycings of the holy Passion. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>