<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>LETTERS Written from Brussels, to Don EMANƲEL, Son of my Lord the Prince of Portugall, since his comeing over into the Vnited Provinces of the Netherlands.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120187_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21332</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7678</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120187</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>LETTERS Written from Brussels, to Don EMANƲEL, Son of my Lord the Prince of Portugall, since his comeing over into the Vnited Provinces of the Netherlands.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration, of the reasons, moveing Don Emanuel, borne Prince of Portugall : Haveing been heretofore a devotary, under the name of Pater Felix, in the Order of the Barefooted Carmelites, to forsake the Romish religion, to joyne himself unto the catholick &amp; apostolick Church; and in the same to professe the purity of the Gospell. The abridgement of this declaration was presented vnto the Consistory of the French Church at Delf signed with the hand of the said Prince, and after sermon read in his name to all the assembly, and after all, ratifyed by his owne mouth, the 15. day of Ianuary 1634. With certaine letters written from Brussels, since his coming over into these provinces. Translated out of French into English by I.R.M.D</title>
                 <author>Manuel, Prince of Portugal</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letters">
   <head>
      <hi>LETTERS</hi> Written from Brussels, to Don EMANƲEL, Son of my Lord the Prince of Portugall, since his comeing over into the Vnited Provinces of the Netherlands.</head>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <head>De son Altesse Serenissime, en Espagnol.</head>
         <p>LOs negocios corryentes importa mucho que os legueis a qui a Brusselas encubierto, dexando ay toda vuestra gente; assi os lo pido, y qui me abisareys en llegardo, pues ymporta mucho. Y Dios os guarde como desseo. De Brusse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, eu 11. de Hebrero, 1633.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>ISABEL:</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <head>In English.</head>
         <p>IT is necessary for present affaires, that you come hither to Brussells privately, leaveing there all your folkes. This it is that I desire you should doe, and that you advertise me of your arrivall, for much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon it. God keep you in his protection, as I hope. From Brussells the eleventh of February, 1633.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>ISABELL.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb n="68" facs="35"/>
         <head>From my Lord the Prince of Portugall.</head>
         <opener>
            <salute>SONNE,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>The death of her Highnesse hath cast us all into great heavinesse, the Children in such a cause serve to comfort their Fathers: Therefore I pray you to take your journy hither, as soone as you can; and I wish you could perswade your Sister <hi>Donna Louisa,</hi> to take a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse this way with you, for as little a while as shee pleaseth. You may counsell her, &amp;c. Tell her the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and security there is here. You are obliged to doe it for your honours sake, and for Gods sake above all. The advice of good Freinds shall be a great help unto you. The Lord suggest a holy Counsell unto you, full of his grace, and beleeve that I am</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>Your Father <hi>D. EMANVEL.</hi>
            </signed>
            <dateline>
               <hi>From Brussells, on S. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas-day,</hi>
               <date>1633.</date>
            </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb n="69" facs="35"/>
         <head>De Frere Elias de S. Marie Magdalaine. <hi>Ihesus Marie.</hi>
         </head>
         <p>PAx Christi. Dios quede con V. R. y noz de gracia para ne perder lo que eternamente dura, par lo que tan brevemente passa lo que mucho se deve considera, por mui cierto tengo, que a todo tiempo que V.R. quisiere continuar la vida que con tanta perfecion ha començado, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos le reciberemos en los brasos, porque assi lo merece la buena compagnia que nos hizó. Dizen que V.R. muda de Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; para salvarse muy segura es la Catholica. V.R. lo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidere, porque errar en ecte punto, sera errar eternamente. Io sere hasta la muerte, muy, verdadero amigo y servidor de V. R. y comotal, me alegrare de sus bienes, y sentire sus males, de que Dios guarde a V.R. como yo lo deseo, y le de lus para que▪vea lo mucho que pierde, en perdera a Dios que en los manos se le puso.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>
               <hi>De V.R. Humilde siervo fray</hi> Elias de S. Maria Magdalaine.</signed>
            <dateline>
               <date>
                  <hi>En 15. de Enero</hi> 1634.</date>
            </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <head>Jn English.</head>
         <p>THe Peace of Christ. God be with you, and give us his grace, not to loose that which is eternall, to possesse that which passeth away suddenly, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serveth a good consideration. I am verily assured, that at what time soever you shall please to prosecute
<pb n="70" facs="36"/>
the Religion, which you have begunne with such perfection, we all should receave you with open arms: For such deserveth the good fellowship we had of you. The speech is that you change in Religion, consider well, that the Catholick Church is full of as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of salvation, and to faile in this point is to loose himselfe eternally. I shall remaine till death your trusty freind and servant, and as such a one I shall rejoyce in your prosperity, and Symphatize with your afflictions, from which I pray God to preserve you, and that he would open your eyes, that you may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand how much you loose, in loosing God, whom you have had in your hands.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>
               <hi>Your humble Servant and Brother</hi> Elias of S. Mary Madelaine.</signed>
            <dateline>
               <date>
                  <hi>15. Ianuary, 1634.</hi>
               </date>
            </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>