<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD; KING of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the faith &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120767_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04208</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14329</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120767</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD; KING of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the faith &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian and modest offer of a most indifferent conference, or disputation, about the maine and principall controversies betwixt the prelats, and the late silenced and deprived ministers in England : tendered by some of the said ministers to the archbishops, and bishops, and all their adherents</title>
                 <author>Jacob, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 42, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO</hi> THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, <hi>IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD; KING</hi> of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender <hi>of the faith &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>MOst High and mightie Soveraigne, As it is the office of every Christian to endevour, by all good &amp; lawfull meanes, to procure the peace and prosperitie of <hi>Sion;</hi> so is it principally required of the Ministers of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, not onely that they be Gods <hi>Remēbrancers,</hi> giving him no rest, untill he set up <hi>Ierusalem</hi> the prayse of the world, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so that they be humble suiters unto those that, under him, be in supreme &amp; soveraigne Authority, that, according to their places, they will become <hi>nursing Fathers, &amp; nursing Mothers</hi> to the Churches of God within their Dominions. And as this is a duety that lyeth both upon Minister &amp; people at all times (for the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect whereof they shalbe accountable to that great and mightie God, whose servants they are) so are they then especially to be carefull of it, when they see the truth of God, and the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Christ Iesus, the sole King and Prophet of his Church, to be opposed &amp; oppugned, and the syncere Professors of the Gospell maligned and traduced, yea oppressed, and in a sort troden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote, by men who seeke nothing but themselues, and who, for the maintayning of their owne Pompe, and for the feeding of their idle bellies, stick not to wrest the <hi>Scepter</hi> out of the handes of Christ, and to thrust him out of his chaire of <hi>Estate.</hi> The consideration hereof (most deare and dread Soveraigne) hath imboldened vs, Gods most unworthy servants, your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties loving and loyall Subiectes, at this time to cast downe our
<pb facs="3"/>selues at your royall feete, and to craue your Princely favour.</p>
   <p>Your Maiestie knoweth right well what Controversies there haue been amongst us in this lād, about the <hi>Prelacy, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, &amp; Subscriptiō,</hi> ever since the bright shinīg beames of the glorious Gospell of Christ first dispelled &amp; chased away the fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie mistes, &amp; black darknes of Popery from out of our coastes. You know likwise how hotely &amp; egarly the Approbatiō of these things hath been vrged by the Prelates; who, being wise in their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haue left no stone vnrolled for the upholding of their rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous &amp; tottering kingdome; they having from time to time not onely <hi>reviled</hi> and <hi>disgraced,</hi> both in <hi>Pulpit</hi> and in <hi>Print,</hi> those whom they call their brethren, and fellow servants of Iesus Christ (who out of a fervent Zeale of the glorie of God, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect detestation of Poperie, haue witnessed against these Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) but having also <hi>suspended, deprived, degraded,</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned</hi> them, yea caused <hi>them to be turned out of house and home, denyed them all benefit of law,</hi> and used them with such <hi>contempt</hi> &amp; <hi>contumely,</hi> as if they were not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to liue upon the face of the earth. Shall these Controversies be kept a-foote for ever? Shall they not once be finally decided &amp; determined? Will it not be misery in the latter end, if the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates be not restrained in time? It is true that bookes haue been, and are daily written, on both sides: and yet the differences are as great, and greater now, then they were at the first; and so are like still to be, unles (by speciall order from your Maiestie) the matter may once come to some such direct, and iust <hi>Triall</hi> as is heere offered.</p>
   <p>Wherein that your Maiestie may be the more willing and readie to harken unto us, we beseech you to consider, and that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously, that the Cause, which here we present unto you, is not our owne, but that it is the Cause of Christ Iesus, who is become a <hi>Suiter</hi> vnto you, and desireth that he may haue <hi>Audience:</hi> for
<pb facs="3"/>whom whatsoever you shall doe, it shalbe remembred unto you, and abundātly recompensed at that great &amp; last day of account, when you shall come to stand before his <hi>Tribunall,</hi> who is King of Kinges, and Lord of Lords; who is not unrighteous that he should forget any thing that is done for him, or for any cause of his. And howsoever the Prelates, and their followers, do beare your Maiestie in hand, that the Church-Government desired is an enemy to your Crowne and dignitie; beleeue them not, we hū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseech you, neither harken to their <hi>Syren songes:</hi> It is (as we are readie to proue) a holy Ordinance of God, which will stand when all such as oppose it, and blaspheme it in the eares of your Royall Maiestie, shall melt away as snow before the Sunne. And if by such an indifferent <hi>Conference</hi> as is heere tendered, we shall not make it as cleere unto your Maiestie as the Sunne at Noone-day, that the Governement of the Churches of Christ by <hi>Pastors, Teachers,</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> is much more agreeable to the State of a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> then is the present Governement by <hi>Archbishops, Bishops, Archdeacons, Commissaries,</hi> and the rest of that <hi>Romish Hierarchy,</hi> let us then finde no favor in your Maiesties eyes.</p>
   <p>Your Maiestie professed before you came to the Crowne, that you did <hi>equally loue &amp; honor the learned &amp; graue men of either of these opinions:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Basil. dor. Epist. pag 11.</note> and it is no small heartes-griefe unto us, that, since your comming into this land, your Affections are so alienated &amp; estranged from us, who haue done you no hurt in the world, but haue wished you all the good that your owne soule desireth; nay, who, before we saw your face, laboured by all good meanes (not without some danger) to promote your Maiesties iust Title to this Crowne, and haue ever since caryed our selues duetifully towards your Maiestie, and peaceably in the service of God, and of his Churches. We are not ignorant what the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates doe pretend, and what they suggest continually in your
<pb facs="4"/>Princely eares; they cry out against us with open mouth, that we are stubberne and refractarie persons, and enemies to your Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Authoritie: wherein they doe both highly abuse your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, and wrong us exceedingly. For it is well knowne, and the Lord beareth us witnes, that we doe, in the singlenes and synce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of our heartes, ascribe much more unto your Maiestie and the Civill authoritie under you, then any Prelate in the land ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth, or is willing to doe. And for the matters in question, we professe heere in the presence of that great God, before whom we shall one day appeare to answer it, if we speake not the truth, that we stand not against them out of any wilfulnes, or peevishnes, but out of the <hi>tendernes of our Cōsciences,</hi> as being perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our very soules, that we cannot yeeld unto them, without sinning against Christ Iesus, whose Ministers and Messengers we are. And if, upon such a due <hi>Triall</hi> of our cause as is desired, the truth of the ensuing Propositions (which are the speciall groundes on which we stand) shalbe infringed by the Prelates; nay, if we shall not be able to make them so cleere and manifest by the infallible &amp; undeniable evidence of the holy word of God, that who so doth not wilfully hoodwinke himselfe may plainely see and discerne the truth of them; we doe heere promise, and binde our selues in the word of Christians, that we will presently change our mindes, and become wholly Conformable to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent State.</p>
   <p>Wherefore we, being herein privy to our owne uprightnes both to God &amp; to our Soveraigne, cannot but conceiue some hope, notwithstanding all the contrary plottes and practises of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that your Maiestie (who are even as an <hi>Angell of God</hi> to discerne betweene good and evill) wilbe pleased now at last both to take a more exact knowledge of our cause, and (out of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bowells of your compassion) to thinke upon and pity the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed estate not onely of us the Lordes poore servants, who are
<pb facs="4"/>without any iust cause cast out from serving at his <hi>Altar,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the Churches of Christ in this land, which doe mourne and grone under the burden of humane <hi>Traditions.</hi> Oh that this should be told at <hi>Gath,</hi> or published in the streetes of <hi>Ashkelon,</hi> amongst the daughters of the uncircumcised, that, under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of so worthily renowned and famous a Prince, the Churches of God haue been thus miserably wasted, and such a woful havock made in them by <hi>vsurping &amp; time-serving Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,</hi> as the like hath never been heard of in this land, under the Gospell. Oh that this should be either said, or written in succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, that in the raigne of Noble King <hi>Iames</hi> (whose name shall liue amongst men, when he, having finished his course, shall sleepe with his Fathers) so many painefull Preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell (even three hundred, or there-aboutes) haue in one yeere and a litle more, been turned out of Christs service, onely for refusing such Ceremonies, as haue their life, breath, and being from Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and such a Subscription, as the like, for ought we know, hath neuer been urged upon any Church of Christ, in any age, under a Christian Magistrate: there being in the meane time whole swarmes of idle, Idole, scandalous, Popish, and Non-resident Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters tolerated every where amongst us.</p>
   <p>The Prelates haue left no meanes of rigour and extremitie vnassayed, for the suppressing of this cause, and for the discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging and daunting of all those that either speake or write for it; and yet the glorious evidence of the truth is such, that it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no <hi>witnesses;</hi> there being at this day many hundreds of the most painefull &amp; profitable Preachers in this Kingdome (besides those alreadie turned out) which are readie to lose both their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery &amp; their Maintenance, and to expose themselues &amp; theirs to all manner of misery, rather then they will renounce this Cause, and conforme themselues to the Corruptions of the times. If therefore there be in the Prelates any loue of the truth, or any
<pb facs="5"/>sparke of desire of the peace and prosperitie of our Churches (which is the thing that they so much pretend unto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie) it will now appeare and shew it self, and you shall easily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne it, by their indeavour to procure the admittance of this <hi>Offer,</hi> which is the likeliest &amp; the readiest way, that hitherto hath been thought upon, both to finde out the truth, and to put a perpetuall end to all these long-continued Controversies. Some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges there be, which we would willingly haue brought to this, or the like <hi>Triall,</hi> as namely, the <hi>Oth ex officio,</hi> which is a cruell a racking of the minde, as the most exquisite Torture can be of the body; and sundrie of the late <hi>Canons.</hi> But because they be of another nature, and we take them to be not onely contrary to the word of God, but also directly against the lawes of the land, we mention them not in our Propositions, in which we haue endevoured to set downe onely the groundes of all the maine differences betwixt us &amp; the Prelats: which if they be once throughly debated, &amp; soundly agreed upon, your Maiestie shall see such a blessed vnitie and vniformitie in all the Churches within your Dominions, as your owne heart desireth.</p>
   <p>May it therfore please your most excellent Maiestie to reade, &amp; examine this <hi>Offer,</hi> &amp; to weigh in all the partes therof the equi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie &amp; iustice of it, &amp; the most certaine advantage that the truth (on which side soever it is) shall receiue by the acceptance of it: may it please you likewise to urge the Prelates, whom it deepely concerneth, to admitt of it; and to secure by Royall protection those that shalbe <hi>Actors</hi> in it: who, howsoever they are forced to conceale their names (in regard of the rigor and severitie of the Prelates) will notwithstanding be most willing &amp; readie to shew themselues, if your Maiestie shall vouchsafe, to signifie your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pleasure touching the admittance of this <hi>Conference.</hi> If therefore we haue found favour in your Maiesties eyes, and
<pb facs="5"/>if this great cause of Christs be regarded; Our humble suite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Highnes is, that you would make it knowne by some <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Act,</hi> that the <hi>Offer</hi> shalbe accepted, and they protected by your Royall Authority, that haue, or shall haue to doe in it. So shall we haue occasion, every day more and more, to intreat the Lord, as we haue done and will doe for ever, that he will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vpon your Maiestie, with a happy increase, all his graces both bodily and spirituall, even untill, and in the day of Christ.</p>
   <p>The Lord Iesus blesse your Maiestie, and your Royall poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and graunt vnto you a long and a happie raigne over us: the Lord multiplie all his mercyes upon you both for this and a better life, and cover with shame the faces of all such as wish you the least evill. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Majesties obedient Subjects, most readie to doe your will in all thinges, wherein they shall not disobey the will of God:</hi> Some of the late silenced and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Ministers.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>