<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
a skull with wings
SPES ADDIDIT ALAS.
 A PREAMBLE, OR INTRODUCTION to this Funerall POEME.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120799_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3567.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120799</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
a skull with wings
SPES ADDIDIT ALAS.
 A PREAMBLE, OR INTRODUCTION to this Funerall POEME.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fatall nuptiall: or Mournefull marriage : Relating, the heavy and lamentable accident lately occurring, by the drowning of 47. persons, and some of those of especiall quality, in the water of Windermere, in the North. October 19: 1635</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Bostock, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
         <figDesc>a skull with wings</figDesc>
         <head>SPES ADDIDIT ALAS.</head>
      </figure> A PREAMBLE, OR INTRODUCTION to this Funerall POEME.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the quality of griefe, none knowes it, but hee who hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally and personally felt it. That Place, which hath hitherto beene secured from the least perill, you sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll now see personated a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of Sorrow: where those, who vowed in a Sacred and Christian manner, their vowes to <hi>Hymen,</hi> the Soueraigne of Nuptialls, are now with <hi>Tethis</hi> to close in wat'ry Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls. The occasion of these sad Obits proceeded from a Marriage and a Market day, which begot to the Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants a mournefull night; yet from that Night (such was their assured expectance, and our undoubted affiance) a happy day. The place, where these drenched Soules were
<pb facs="4"/> to take Boate, was that famous and renowned Mere of <hi>Windermere;</hi> a Mere no lesse eminent and genero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sly knowne for her Sole-breeding, and peculiar kinde of fishes (commonly called <hi>Chares</hi>) as for those windy and laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian mazes, with those curiously shaded, beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sly tufted, naturally fortifide, and impregnably seated Ilands in every part of the Mere interveined. To relate the severall w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ndings of it, or more historically to describe it, were fruitles, being already explained by a genuine and learned Relater.<note place="margin">Cambd. in Brit.</note> To divert then from the Place, to the sad occasion of this Action, thus I proceed.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Windermere,</hi> or <hi>Winandermere,</hi> streaming, or rather staying in a continuate Tract or Channell, without any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible or apparent Current, and dividing the Counties of <hi>Westmerland</hi> and <hi>Lancashire,</hi> hath ever constantly kept a Boat for Passengers; especially those Inhabitants as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine or reside in the Barronry of <hi>Kendall,</hi> (a place to her honour, antiently famous for Commerce and industrious Manufacture) a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all others, who may have occasion to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse their course by that passage, to the Market of <hi>Haukeside,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Charter of which Market was procured by that industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Agen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>All<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>holso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her places adjoyning. To this Boat, upon a <hi>nuptiall</hi> but <hi>fatall</hi> occasion, sundry Passengers, and these all Inhabitants within the Barronry of <hi>Kendall,</hi> (a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as I formerly observed, highly eminent, by having such neare relation and generall correspondence with most places of trade or trafficke in this kingdome) repaired; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with a safe and secure gale to arrive, where no perill
<pb facs="4"/> had ever yet approach'd. The Boat they enter'd, securely confident, with <hi>47.</hi> in number, besides other carriages and horses, which (together with the roughnes of the water, &amp; extremity of weather) occasioned this inevitable dange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>Lanch'd had these scarcely to the medth of the water, being scantly a mile broad, but the Boat, either through the pressure and weight which surcharg'd her, or some violent and impetuous windes and waves that surpriz'd her, with all her people, became drench'd in the depths.<note place="margin">Undae sunt ossibus urnae.</note> No succour, no reliefe afforded, for Gods definite Will had so decreed: So as, not one person of all the number was saved: Amongst which, the Brides Mother, and her Brother in this liquid regiment, equally perished.</p>
   <p>To aggravate the quality of this Accident, I need not; an imaginary representment of sorrow is sufficient to it selfe. Onely, let me reare before your eyes this <hi>Theatre;</hi> on which you are not to expect ought from this Tyringhouse of heavines, but Scenes of passion and disconsolate anguish.</p>
   <p>Many of these left Wives without Husbands, other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Husbands without Wives; most of these, Children without Fathers or Mothers. Estates they had, but indisposed; because in such a moment of time prevented, as wherein they stood most secured, soonest abridged.</p>
   <p>What a <hi>fatall Nuptiall</hi> was this? when those Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall ribbons and sprigges of Rosemary, which were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as favours for a Nuptiall, became Rosemary sprigges to adorne their Funerall?</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>What an Embleme of Mortality may man see in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, in this image of himselfe? A Navigator is not to be secure in <hi>three inches,</hi> nor man of his life, which is but a <hi>spanne.</hi> How secure were these in their temperate mirth; and with what a calme Convoy they expected to arrive at their Port? If we should consider those billowes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are dayly and hourely encountred: those perillous passages, whereto we are exposed: with the difficulty of the Haven, at which we are to be landed, wee would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly tremble, and stand in feare, least every <hi>wave,</hi> every <hi>worldly care,</hi> should endanger our shipwracke.</p>
   <p>What loving associates were these to <hi>Hymen?</hi> what <hi>Conjugall consorts</hi> to a festive <hi>Nuptiall?</hi> yet see the cloze of their marriage melody, drowne it selfe in a wat'ry <hi>Lachrymae!</hi> What then on Earth is heere constant? or where in ought may wee be confident? A merry Evening makes an heavy Morning: and a glad going out, a sad returning. Sad to their friends, but chearefull to their dearest soules; which have call'd from the <hi>Depths,</hi> and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssuredly heard.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s this might bee their proper impreze:</hi> "Mergimur immersi, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pida sub gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite tui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>: "Per mare, per terras, Semita recta bonis.</note>It is a good Prayer, to deliver us from <hi>sudden Death;</hi> yet there is no sudden Death to them that die well. Gods mercy is betwixt the <hi>bridge</hi> and the <hi>brinke;</hi> Nor are wee to despaire of their helpe, who in God repose their sole hope. <hi>Abyssus abyssum invocat:</hi> These in the depth of their misery, call'd upon the depth of Gods mercy: and though they could not reach to land with the hand of their
<pb facs="5"/> body; they reach'd with their hand of faith to the Haven of Glory. As no man values the place of his <hi>Birth,</hi> so is hee not to disvalue the place of his <hi>Death.</hi> Wee have a sacred President; to whom neither place of <hi>Birth</hi> nor <hi>Death</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an Ornament.</p>
   <p>Wee are heere to passe the <hi>waters</hi> of <hi>tribulation;</hi> our Barkes are weake, our passage dangerous: Shelves wee have full of perill; <hi>presumption</hi> to transport us, <hi>despaire</hi> to deject us. If wee surcharge our <hi>vessell,</hi> what may wee expect but drowning? if wee ballase it not enough, what may wee looke for but floating? Wee have an <hi>Anchor;</hi> it is our Saviour: wee cannot faile, if through him wee suffer. Hee, who can command the Windes and the Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, will wast us o're these troublesome Seas, and conduct us to the Port of rest.</p>
   <p>It is true, that while wee are heere imbarked, there is no security; Marchant venturers wee are all, hazarding our state, stocke and store in crazy and leeking <hi>vessels.</hi> Wee hicker with waves, stormes and tempests: even our owne dissorting passions; which like so many billowes, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine in us, and threaten shipwracke.<note place="margin">Hor.</note>
      <hi>Neptunum procul à terra;</hi> wee eye, and eying, sigh for our Haven.</p>
   <p>Poore Sea-fairing Soules, what a doe wee make with our distempered Motions, (which to use the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rds of that Divine Father) swarme like so many <hi>Bees</hi> about us;<note place="margin">Basil.</note> and while they sting us, wee hold them deare unto us!</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Invironed wee are with danger on the Maine; and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Sands and Shelv's oppose us in our landing. Though the Course of our Navigation be passing short; the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Current of our dangerous passage appeares long.</p>
   <p>We account him foolishly merry, and insensible of perill, who, when the Windes rage, the Waves rise, &amp; nothing but feare and horrour become Objects to the weakned Ship, carrouseth and drinkes healths to the Winde, as One se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of his approaching sate. And what lesse doe wee, when in these weake Barkes of our Bodies, wee expose our selves to all sensuall pleasures, as if wee were a shore and secure from danger, when wee are surrounded with perill, and for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e divided from our Harbour?</p>
   <p>The Philosophers question impli'd a Divine Morall: <hi>Quanta spissitudo navium?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Anach.</note>
      <hi>4. digitorum.</hi> And that Sacred Light of the <hi>Orientall Church</hi> might seeme to answere this,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> no lesse positively then pithily: <hi>Tres cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biti terrae te expectant.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Arist.</note>That surviving glory of <hi>Stagyrus</hi> reports, that about the River <hi>Hypanis,</hi> which runneth through a part of <hi>Europe</hi> into the Sea <hi>Pontus,</hi> are bred certaine Beastes which live but one day; and surely, if wee should compare this straite confined limit or period of our age with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, (the <hi>Soules sole-harbour</hi> after her disbarking from this Sea of misery) we shall be found in regard of our frailty every way as transi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, as these day-dying Beasts.</p>
   <p>Death is such a discursive Serjeant, and so serious
<pb facs="6"/> in the discharge of his Errand, as there is no place of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to exclude him, or rescue he party arrested by him. Hee ha's a <hi>Mace</hi> for the <hi>Sea,</hi> as well as <hi>Land.</hi> Which may bee instanced in no patterne more clearely, no Object more truely, than in this <hi>Tragicke</hi> Scene of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which wee have now in action: Where, of <hi>47</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut wee have formerly related, not one secured, not one from Death rescued: And this happened the <hi>19.</hi> of October.</p>
   <p>But as waves follow waves, so it oftimes falleth in the progresse of woes: for no l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse remarkeable is it, that upon the <hi>6.</hi> of November, a <hi>Graves end Barge</hi> was by report cast away, seconding thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> former very nearely, if not wholly, in number: but the apparancy of their danger begot this report (as wee have since heard) without any other actuall disaster.</p>
   <p>The use of these should necessarily conduce to our selv's: on <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Land</hi> to recommend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s in our passage and conduct to his Sacred direction and protection, by whom wee <hi>breath and have our being. In aquis &amp; terris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e Deo meditari,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Malum est mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> in nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragio, &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num est mori febre Aug. in Psal. c. 48.</note>
      <hi>&amp; coelesti ejus custodiae no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>-ipsos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendare, est neque ab aquis nec à terris, motu vel metu discriminis imminentis, periclitari.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to reteine a charitable opinion of such, as by thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> premature and adventitious ends, are translated from us. <hi>Pauli naufragium animae salus fuit:</hi> Let us apply this, though in another sense addressed, to these hopefull
<pb facs="7"/> Soules now departed. Hee, who is the LORD of the <hi>Depths,</hi> can extend his unbounded mercy to the <hi>Depths;</hi> and put an hooke in the nose-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hrills of that <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who raigneth, ruleth and rageth in the <hi>Depths.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This <hi>Preamble</hi> hath enlarged it selfe to so extensive a measure, as it may seeme to some, to resemble a <hi>Mindian</hi> Structure: but as <hi>arguments</hi> give light to <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;</hi> so <hi>Preambles,</hi> by way of <hi>Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> have ever given life to refinedst <hi>Poems.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>