<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The High, Mighty, and inuinci∣ble CHARLES Prince of Wales: the Right Honourable GEORGE Duke of Buckingham: and IAMES Marquesse Hambleton; with the rest of his Maiesties Honourable and faithfull Councell for Warre.</title>
           <author>G., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120073_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06824</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17260</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120073</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The High, Mighty, and inuinci∣ble CHARLES Prince of Wales: the Right Honourable GEORGE Duke of Buckingham: and IAMES Marquesse Hambleton; with the rest of his Maiesties Honourable and faithfull Councell for Warre.</title>
                 <author>G., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Covnt Mansfields directions of vvarre : Giuen to all his officers and souldiers in generall</title>
                 <author>Mansfeld, Ernst, graf von</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO The High, Mighty, and inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble CHARLES Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> the Right Honourable GEORGE Duke of <hi>Buckingham:</hi> and IAMES Marquesse <hi>Hambleton;</hi> with the rest of his Maiesties Honourable and faithfull Councell for Warre.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sun is all one both to the Poore &amp; Rich: euen so (saith <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>) ought a Prince not to haue respect to the person, but to the matter: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my selfe being not worthy, in respect of Prudence &amp; Experience, to ranke with the least or meanest
<pb facs="3"/>member of your Heroick Counsell, yet daring to compare with the Greatest in my loyall meaning, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and best wishes; respectiuely to his Maiesty, your Highnesse, with restlesse prayers for the prosperous proceeding of your true Noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes; prostrate at your Highnesse feet, doe present these Directions for Warre, not to direct your Heauen-directed Counsels, but onely as a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pledge of my hearty deuotion, to acquaint you (for your better satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction) with the order of such Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Discipline, as the Forraine Friends of Great <hi>Britaine</hi> in these tumultuous times doe exercise: their Motions, Standing, Marching, Fighting, Tyring and Retyring. In a word, the whole Art of Armes, taught and deliuered by this illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="3"/>and renowned Figure of <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> (who first reuised and approued the same written) is heere exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which I submissiuely commend principally to the Patronage of your Princely Hignesse, the most remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able object of Honour: beseeching his Diuine Majestie, that like a most politicke and magnanimous Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, you may transcend not onely this Right-valorous <hi>Director,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> in Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Actions and Directions, and be <hi>Carolus</hi> surnamed <hi>Maximus:</hi> but much more Fortunate in Diuturnall fruition of your Conquests and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: And that as you are the Glory of your Royall Fathers age, (according to <hi>Zeno's</hi> testimony) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right Virtuous and Religious; so you may long suruiue and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb facs="4"/>the chiefe Columne and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his Kingdomes; and no lesse Defend the true Catholicke Faith: wherein the greatest Guider of all Hearts direct mine, firmely to perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and make mee euer ready and most willing (as at this present) to hazard my selfe and all that is mine in its Cause, as one that resteth:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Most humbly Deuoted, To your Highnesse: Your Graces: And the rest Respectiuely Jn any Honourable Seruice <hi>W. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>