<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the well disposed Reader.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120745_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07911</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18283</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120745</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the well disposed Reader.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Zelauto. The fountaine of fame : Erected in an orcharde of amorous aduentures. Containing a delicate disputation, gallantly discoursed betweene to noble gentlemen of Italye. Giuen for a freendly entertainment to Euphues, at his late ariuall into England. By A.M. seruaunt to the Right Honourable the Earle of Oxenford</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 156 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To the well disposed Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> May be deemed</hi> (cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader) more wanton then wise, and more curious then circumspect: in naming my booke by such a vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious title, for some will sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose heere are rare exploytes of martial mindes to be seen: which whē they haue prooued, they finde it to faint. Othersome will desire for <hi>Venus</hi> daintie dalliances: but <hi>Iuno</hi> dealeth so iustly in this cause, that their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so they misse their marke. Then how (will some say) can Fame be so furnished: and bothe of these absent? the matter (say I) shall make manifest what I haue attempted: and then if I be founde faultie, I will stand to your gentle iudgementes. That man is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wise that neuer offendeth in folly, that man is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry valiant that neuer meetes with his match, and that man is very circumspect that neuer talketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wry, the righteous man offendeth seuē times a day: then needes must the negligent be found very faulty. It is a good horse that neuer stumbleth, and he a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere seruaūt that neuer displeaseth his maister, then beare with my rudenesse if I chaunce to offend you: my good will did labour in hope for to please you.</p>
   <p>Againe, some will be inquisitiue, why I am so wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="2" facs="8"/>
to welcome <hi>Euphues</hi> into England? he beeyng so excellent: and my selfe so simple? If <hi>Euphues</hi> so wisely dooth wish you beware, and to preuent the perilles that heedelesse heades may haue, wishing youth likewise to frame their fancies so fit, that no crooked chaunces doo happen to harme them: Then like that <hi>Lilly</hi> whose sent it so sweete, and fauour his freend who wisheth your welfare. And although my wit be so weake: that I cannot welcome as I would, and my skyll to simple to gratifye so gentle a gueast: I trust my good will shall plead me a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, &amp; my honest intent be nothing misliked. Thus hoping to haue your courteous consentes, which is the reward I cheefest require, I wishe my woorkes may prooue as profitable to you in the reading: as they were delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me in the writing.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your freend to commaund A. Munday.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>