<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, SIR EDMVND BACON, Knight, increase of honour, strength of body, perfection of VERTVE.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, SIR EDMVND BACON, Knight, increase of honour, strength of body, perfection of VERTVE.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="27"/>
   <pb n="43" facs="27"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, SIR EDMVND BACON, Knight, increase of <hi>honour, strength of body, perfection</hi> of VERTVE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, There is no wise man would giue his thoughts for all the world: which as they are the most pleasing and noble businesse of man, being the naturall and immediate is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue of that reason, whereby he is seuered from brute creatures: so they are in their vse most beneficiall to our selues, and others. For, by the meanes hereof, we enioy both God and our selues; and hereby we make others partners of those rich excellencies, which God hath hid in the minde. And though it be most easie and safe, for a man, with the Psalmist to commune with his owne heart in silence; yet is it more behouefull to the common good, for which (both as men and Christians) we are ordained, that those thoughts, which our experience hath found comfortable and fruitfull to our selues, should (with neglect of all censures) be communicated to others. The concealement whereof (me thinkes) can proceed from no other ground, but either timorousnesse, or enuie. Which considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath induced me to clothe these naked thoughts in plaine and simple words, and to aduenture them into the light, after their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: Consecrating them the rather to your name, for that (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides all other respects of dutie) they are part of those medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="44" facs="28"/> which in my late peregrination with you, tooke me vp vnder the solitarie hilles of <hi>Ardenna,</hi> wanting as then the opportunitie of other employment. J offer them to you not for that your selfe is not stored with choice of better; but as poore men vse to bring pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents to the rich: Jf they may carrie acceptation from you, and bring profit vnto my soule, it shall abundantly satisfie mee, who should thinke it honour enough, if I might be vouchsafed to bring but one pinne towards the decking of the Spouse of Christ; whiles others, out of their abundance, adorne her with costly robes, and rich medals. J commend their successe to God, their patronage to you, their vse to the world. That God multiplie his rare fauours vpon you, and your worthy Ladie; and goe you on to fauour</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships humbly deuoted, IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>