<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull and his singuler good Mai∣stresse, ELIZABETH BARRET, wife to Ma∣ster EDVVARD BARRET Esquire: I. Marbeck wisheth long life and continuall health, to the pleasure of God.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120587_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06869</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17302</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120587</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull and his singuler good Mai∣stresse, ELIZABETH BARRET, wife to Ma∣ster EDVVARD BARRET Esquire: I. Marbeck wisheth long life and continuall health, to the pleasure of God.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holie historie of King Dauid : wherein is chieflye learned these godly and wholsome lessons, that is: to haue sure patience in persecution, due obedience to our prince without rebellion: and also the true and most faithfull dealings of friendes. Drawne into English meetre for the youth to reade; by Iohn Marbeck</title>
                 <author>Merbecke, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harrison (Harison), John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>71, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull and his singuler good Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, ELIZABETH BARRET, wife to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster EDVVARD BARRET Esquire: I. Marbeck wisheth long life and continuall health, to the pleasure of God.</head>
   <p>TO RENDER YOV THE CAVSE or rather the causes (Righte Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Maistresse) that first mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to take in hande the trauell of this diuine Historie of the holy Prophet king Dauid? This, in my iudgement, were not so necessarie, as it might proue tedious vnto you, and therefore I omit it, sauing that thus much I affirme, that aswell in the writing, as in the deliuering of it to the presse, I not meanely regarded that suche histories as Gods spirite hath left and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs in the sacred Scriptures, might be aduaunced before, and infinitely farre aboue those vayne, vnstable, and most vnfruitfull deuises whatsoeuer (so I terme them as they are to be compared with the histories of Gods holy Scriptures) whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (I saye) proceeding from the penne of man, albeit neuer so throughly dipped in the deapth and soundest parte of that that mans reason might reach vnto: But muche more I intended to the vttermost of mine habilitie, to impayre hereby the credite aswell of all leude lying legends of vnsound Saintes, consecrated and canonized in the high Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> (the soueraigne seate of that purple Whore, whom the Lorde with the breath of his mouth shall shortly destroy to the great glory of the Lambe) as also of all filthy, fonde, and vnsauery songs, bookes, and fancies
<pb facs="4"/>
farre vnfit and ill beseeming the eies of baptized Christians. And the better to bring this to passe, I haue not only endeuoured my selfe to be playne and familiar in all things, but also (for the more delectation to the Reader) haue continued the historie whole and entier of it selfe, without entermingling any matter or discourse that might seeme to digresse from the order of the Story. And now, hauing in this sort finished the same, and not finding in my selfe habilitie sufficient whereby to expresse the thankfulnes and entier affection of my heart, which I would should be manifested vnto you (to whom, as to the right worshipfull gentleman your husbande, the Lord hath graunted great measure of zeale to his trueth, and loue to his poore Saincts) what other shift shoulde I make, beeing now, as my yeeres and infirmities tell me, trudging to the end of my race, but to vse this as a pledge of these the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises which the Lord Iesus alone must make absolute at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? This litle booke therefore, in this onely consideration and respect, I humbly dedicate and exhibite vnto you, beseching you (right worshipfull Gentlewoman) that in receyuing it at my hands, you will looke into that that my heart hath herein behigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, namely that it be taken as a poore supply of the thing which I owe, but (for want of habilitie) can not otherwise render. I leaue to be tedious vnto you, beseeching that Lorde that hath a continuall eye to his Churche, to preserue you and your right worshipful husband long time as bright burning lamps to the comfort of the same, and in the end of your earthly pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, to clothe you, as he hath already cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen and called you, to waite vpon the Lambe, and with him to liue and reigne eternally.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>