<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Reader of Master Randulph Mayeres his travels.</title>
           <author>C., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120913_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07361</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17745</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120913</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Reader of Master Randulph Mayeres his travels.</title>
                 <author>C., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mayeres his travels : containing a true recapitulation of all the remarkable passages which befell in the authors peregrination and voyages, as namely in these imployments following: viz. his 1 voyage for the wars in Ireland in Queen E.R. 2 At Breda, under one of the four English Colonell regiments. 3 With Count Mansfield. 4 To Cales. 5 To the Ile of Rhee. Wherunto is added a speech the author held with great King Hunger in his journey over the alpes. Collected and written by him who was both an actor, and an eye witnesse in the above named severall imployments, th space of forty yeeres, R.M.S. Gent. Published with license and authority</title>
                 <author>Mayeres, Randulph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harper, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 47, 1 page, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the gentle Reader of Master <hi>Randulph Mayeres</hi> his travels.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>GEntle Spectators of this Pamphlet small,</l>
      <l>The Author doth desire no prayse at all,</l>
      <l>His works prayse him so worthily he writes,</l>
      <l>To read his travels he the world incites,</l>
      <l>The name of Poet he doth here refuse,</l>
      <l>Yet we may understand he hath a Muse.</l>
      <l>Souldier and Scholler, it seems he is belike,</l>
      <l>For he can use his pen as well as Pike,</l>
      <l>He is no <hi>Venus</hi> Darling, you shall know it,</l>
      <l>A sonne of <hi>Mars,</hi> a Souldier, and a Poet:</l>
      <l>So then regardlesse of vain Criticks cavils,</l>
      <l>Honour his person, and read o're his travels.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>