<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Time. EPIGR. 1.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120210_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15623</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25892</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120210</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Time. EPIGR. 1.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Abuses stript, and whipt. Or Satirical essayes. By George Wyther. Diuided into two bookes</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>336 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epigrams">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <div n="1" type="epigram">
      <head>To Time. EPIGR. 1.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>NOw swift-deuouring, bald and ill fac't <hi>Time,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Dost not thou blush to see thy selfe vncloak't?</l>
         <l>Oh that I knew but how to laugh in <hi>Rime?</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Faith I would do it though thou wisht me choakt.</l>
         <l>Did'st thou but see how thy faire <hi>antique</hi> shape,</l>
         <l>Is now transformed to a <hi>shapelesse hew:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>How like thou look'st to some <hi>Barbarian Ape,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Could'st thou I say with me thine owne selfe view</l>
         <l>Thou wouldst be <hi>Metamorphosed</hi> anew,</l>
         <l>Run quite away, and either all amend,</l>
         <l>Or wish thy selfe and all things at an end.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>And yet dispaire not <hi>Time,</hi> though thou art ill;</l>
         <l>The worst that euer yet was knowne to be,</l>
         <l>Tis not ordain'd thou shouldst remaine so still,</l>
         <l>For I my selfe this age do hope to see:</l>
         <l>The gloriou'st work that euer Time brought forth,</l>
         <l>The master-peece, and the most noble act;</l>
         <l>In the respect of which 'twere nothing worth</l>
         <l>If all the braue deeds done were but one fact,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Romes fall</hi> I <hi>meane;</hi> I heard it when it crack't.</l>
         <l>Yea from my <hi>Cradle</hi> I did still surmize;</l>
         <l>I should see <hi>Babell</hi> tumble <hi>Bethell</hi> rise,</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="epigram">
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <head>EPIG. 2.</head>
      <l>I Heare theres some aske how I dare so plaine</l>
      <l>Tax the <hi>Abuses</hi> that I now see raigne,</l>
      <l>I muse as much they dare say ill vnto it,</l>
      <l>Or dare but aske, but how I dare to doe it.</l>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="epigram">
      <head>To the Stranger 3.</head>
      <l>THou that wert so vnhappy first, to breath,</l>
      <l>Without the compasse of <hi>Great Brittans</hi> powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>And blest againe that fate did thee bequeath,</l>
      <l>The knowledge of so rich a tongue as our.</l>
      <l>If vnderstanding thou dost hap to read,</l>
      <l>This booke wherein thou seest my nations sham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>Yet do not thou against my Country plead,</l>
      <l>For thine thou know'st doth merit as much blame</l>
      <l>Our faults are many, this indeed is true;</l>
      <l>But were they moe, we were no worse then you.</l>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="epigram">
      <head>To the Satyro-mastix. 4.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>OH Lord Sir y'are deceiu'd I'me none of tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </l>
         <l>That write in Anger, or malicious spleene,</l>
         <l>I haue not taken pepper in the Nose,</l>
         <l>Nor a base forger of false libels beene,</l>
         <l>Such ones there be indeed, such I haue seene;</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="10"/>
         <l>I enuy no man for his greatnes I,</l>
         <l>Nor seeke I any honest mans disgrace;</l>
         <l>I ioy in euery ones prosperity,</l>
         <l>Ile not the credit of a dogge deface,</l>
         <l>My Aduersaery shall not prooue the case.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Then stand back sirrah Whip-Iack with your scourge,</l>
         <l>Do not incense my Satyr for thy life:</l>
         <l>Hee's patient enough vnlesse thou vrge,</l>
         <l>Contentions are now a dayes to rife,</l>
         <l>And he is very backward vnto strife,</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>But notwithstanding heere he lets thee see,</l>
         <l>As long as there is cause and reason why:</l>
         <l>In spight of all that foes to Satyrs be:</l>
         <l>He shall, if I list taxe iniquitie,</l>
         <l>It is a matter of necessity.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>What? you would faine haue all the great ones freed,</l>
         <l>They must not for their vices be controld,</l>
         <l>Beware; that were a saucines indeed;</l>
         <l>But if the <hi>Great-ones</hi> to offend be bold,</l>
         <l>I see no reason but they should be told.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Yea and they shall; their faults most hurtfull be,</l>
         <l>And though I will not put them to that shame,</l>
         <l>I no iniustice in the matter see,</l>
         <l>If they were taxed by their proper name,</l>
         <l>For no sinne can on earth haue her full blame.</l>
         <l>Then <hi>Scourge</hi> of <hi>Satyrs</hi> hold thy whip from mine,</l>
         <l>Or I will make my rod lash thee and thine.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="epigram">
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <head>To the gald Reader.</head>
      <head>EPIG. 8.</head>
      <l>SIr, he thats night-gald or hath cornes on's toes,</l>
      <l>May blame the Shoomaker and curse his shooes</l>
      <l>But those that are acquainted with the fault,</l>
      <l>Can tell the reason wherefore he doth halt;</l>
      <l>So thou maist think (perhaps) these <hi>Satyrs</hi> sting thee</l>
      <l>Where only thy owne guiltines doth wring thee.</l>
      <l>For if thou wert from these diseases free,</l>
      <l>Thou wouldst be quiet as some others be.</l>
      <l>But tis well known <hi>a ticklish beast hath tricks</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And the old <hi>Prouerb</hi> saith <hi>a gold la <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e kicks.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But I'le aduise thee, if thou feele it smart,</l>
      <l>Be rule by me and play not the fooles part,</l>
      <l>Keep't to thy selfe, and there are none shall know,</l>
      <l>Whether that thou art toucht therein or no,</l>
      <l>Thou seest thou neither art markt out nor na'md;</l>
      <l>And therefore onely to thy selfe art sham'd;</l>
      <l>Now if thou stir at best thou shalt but make</l>
      <l>The Country of thy faults more knowledge take.</l>
      <l>And (as indeed it iustly may) diuine,</l>
      <l>The worst faults that I write against are thine,</l>
      <l>Then since to be reprooued seemes a curse,</l>
      <l>And to be mooued makes the matter worse,</l>
      <l>Either for to amend thy life haue care,</l>
      <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> like a Pack! orse and an Asse stil beare.</l>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <head>To the Impartiall Author.</head>
      <l>
         <hi>CEorge,</hi> I did euer thinke thy faithfull breast,</l>
      <l>Conteind a mind beyond the common sort,</l>
      <l>Thy very looke and honest heart exprest,</l>
      <l>And seem'd an aw-full mildnes to import:</l>
      <l>Poets may vaunt of smooth and lofty straines,</l>
      <l>Thine with thy subiect fitly do agree;</l>
      <l>But then thy <hi>Muse</hi> a better praise obtaines,</l>
      <l>For whilst the greatest but <hi>time-pleasers</hi> be,</l>
      <l>Thou vnappald and freely speak'st the truth:</l>
      <l>Not any one for feare or lucre sparing:</l>
      <l>A vertue rare in age, more rare in youth;</l>
      <l>Another <hi>Cato,</hi> but I think more daring;</l>
      <l>Wel maist thou speed in these tempestuous times,</l>
      <l>Thou soone begin'st to make the world thy foe</l>
      <l>Yet I so wel do like thy honest rimes;</l>
      <l>That I could wish al Poets would write so;</l>
      <l>For thou the way of truth so rightly tend'st,</l>
      <l>I hold them double prais'd whom thou commendst</l>
      <l>Thy deare friend, <hi>TH. C.</hi>
      </l>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>