<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translater to the Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120309_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120309</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translater to the Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine path to perfect vertue: deuised and found out by Mancinus a Latine poet, and translated into English by G. Turberuile gentleman</title>
                 <author>Mancinus, Dominicus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Maylard (Maylerd), Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="71"/>
   <head>The Translater to the Booke.</head>
   <l>FArewell thou litle booke an other mans and mine,</l>
   <l>The Gods allowe thée blessed hap, report without repine.</l>
   <l>Well mayst thou liked be. and so thou shalt I trust,</l>
   <l>Of such as Vertue do imbrace: as for the rest thou must</l>
   <l>Appoint vpon as foes. I meane the sinfull sect,</l>
   <l>That neither thée for Vertues sake, nor Vertue will respect.</l>
   <l>Was neuer man that wrote of Vertue yet a whit</l>
   <l>But Enuie would with malice séeke his trauaile to requite.</l>
   <l>But force thou not at all, be bolde and neuer blushe:</l>
   <l>For Glorie euer gaines the byrde where Enuie beates the bushe.</l>
   <pb facs="72"/>
   <l> Sith thou of Vertue dost and nothing else intreate,</l>
   <l>I know thy foes are friends to Vice, with wrath and yre repleate.</l>
   <l>With them thou hast to deale: thou knowest the wonted sawe.</l>
   <l>The Iade will kicke at him that rubbs his backe if it be rawe.</l>
   <l>Then sith thou prickst with pen the galled backe, be sure</l>
   <l>Thou shalt despite, in steade of loue of wicked wights procure.</l>
   <l>For trouth doth purchase hate, and reapes that fruite for gaine</l>
   <l>A bad reward for good desert. But wotst thou what againe?</l>
   <l>The better sort of men will like thy purpose well,</l>
   <l>And ring thy praise by good report as loude as Larum bell.</l>
   <l>If be that pende thée first, and brought thée forth to light</l>
   <l>Could finde in heart to hazarde thée to hands of fowle despite:</l>
   <l>Why should I more accompt to kéepe thée vnder wing</l>
   <pb facs="72"/>
   <l> That onely phrase for phrase translate and verse to Metre bring?</l>
   <l>Thou art no new deuise, the wéede wherin thou were</l>
   <l>Is somewhat altred, but I trust <hi>Mancinus</hi> néede not feare</l>
   <l>Or stande in doubt of thée, he shall not loose his right:</l>
   <l>I would not go about to wrong a <hi>Romane</hi> if I might.</l>
   <l>But for desire to make <hi>Mancinus</hi> better knowne,</l>
   <l>I toylde anewe the soyle that he with painefull plough had sowne.</l>
   <l>I trust he shall not loath our mother tong at all:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Mancinus</hi> is <hi>Mancinus</hi> still I trust and euer shall.</l>
   <l>And thus to ende my tale I wishe (thée litle Booke)</l>
   <l>To doe no worse than him that doth vpon thy Vertues looke.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>