<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL my truly Honored friend Master Alex∣ander Thistlethwayte Esquyer, to whom I owe even my owne selfe.</title>
           <author>Gore, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120526_Fr6_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12071</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120526</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL my truly Honored friend Master Alex∣ander Thistlethwayte Esquyer, to whom I owe even my owne selfe.</title>
                 <author>Gore, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine sermons preached upon severall occasions : viz. The vvay to prosper. The vvay to be content. The vvay to vvell-doing. A summer sermon. A vvinter sermon. Vnknowne kindnesse. The poore mans hope. By Iohn Gore Rector of Wenden-lofts in Essex</title>
                 <author>Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 48, 4, 43, 5, 28, 4, 27, 5, 27, 5, 34, 6, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="92"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL my truly Honored friend Master <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Thistlethwayte</hi> Esquyer, to whom I owe even my owne selfe.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Remember how <hi>Noahs Dove</hi> (after some longer stay then was expected) returned at length unto the <hi>Arke</hi> from whence shee was sent with a branch of Olive in her mouth. Your worthy Family was the <hi>Arke</hi> out of which J was sent into these farther parts of <hi>Essex;</hi> and thus long have J beene abroad, ere J could finde out an Olive-branch fit to present you with at my returne; such as it is, I beseech you take it in good part, and let it finde (as the Authour
<pb facs="93"/>
hath done) favour and acceptance at your hands. And the God of peace lengthen your tranquilitie, and continue to preserve your house and family, that it may ever remaine as an Happie Arke wherein both you and yours may successively bee saved,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thus prayes Your poore servant and suppliant
IOHN GORE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>