<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER,</title>
           <author>N., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120712_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12430</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER,</title>
                 <author>N., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archontorologion, or The diall of princes : containing the golden and famous booke of Marcus Aurelius, sometime Emperour of Rome. Declaring what excellcncy [sic] consisteth in a prince that is a good Christian: and what euils attend on him that is a cruell tirant. Written b the Reuerend Father in God, Don Antonio of Gueuara, Lord Bishop of Guadix; preacher and chronicler to the late mighty Emperour Charles the fift. First translated out of French by Thomas North, sonne to Sir Edward North, Lord North of Kirthling: and lately reperused, and corrected from many grosse imperfections. With addition of a fourth booke, stiled by the name of The fauoured courtier</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 331, pages 933, 341-424, 429-542, that is 560, 2, 561-654, 659-768, that is 766 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="300"/>
   <pb n="561" facs="300"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER,</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat detracting tongues report of mee, and my first trauell in the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation of this Dyall, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging them at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to work my defame disabling my doing herein, by brute it was no worke of mine, but the fruit of others labour: I need not much force, since by dayly proofe wee see, that ill disposed minds can neuer frame an honest tongue of head. For my obiect and reproof of this their slaunderous and malignant speech: I can alleadge (courteous Reader) two principall causes, which thou reading, &amp; iudging with indifferency, mayest easilie aproue, if I should seem to glose with thee. First the basenesse of my Stile, the plain &amp; humble words couched in the same, the meane, rude, and ill contriued sentences layde before thee, together with the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple handling of the whole, plainely shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to thee whence they are, and easily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainteth thee with the curious Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: Who protesteth to God, and confesseth to the world, that hee more rashly then wisely plunged himself into so graue and deepe a matter, and whose young yeeres and vnskilfull head, might both then and now haue excused his fond enterprises herein.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>For the second, and last, I must needs appeale to all the worshipfull, and my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued companions, and fellow students of our house of</hi> Lincolnes Inne <hi>at that time, from whence my poore English Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all tooke his light.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>To whose iust and true reports (for thy vndoubted satisfaction and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my poore honesty) I refer thee, and wholy yeeld me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>These recited causes for purgation of my suspected fame, as also for established assurance of the like, and thy further doubt of mee hereafter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I thought good, Gentle Reader, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce vnto thee. I might well haue spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this second and last labour of mine, taken, in the rformation and correction of this Diall, enlarging my selfe further once againe, with the translation of the late and new come fauoured Courtier, and which I found annexed to the Diall for the</hi> 4. <hi>and last booke, If my procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding trauell taken in the setting forth of the first three bookes, and the respect of mine honesty in accomplishing of the same had not incited mee (vnwillingly) to continue my first begunne attempt, to bring the same to his perfect and desired end, which whole worke is now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat by this last booke, intituled, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored Courtier, which first &amp; last volume wholly as it lyeth, I prostrate to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of the graue and wise Reader, subiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my self and it, to the reformation and correction of his learned head, whom I beseech to iudge of mee with fauour and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and not with malice to persecute my fame and honest intent, hauing for thy benefite, to my little skill and knowledge imployed my simple talent, crauing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
      <pb n="562" facs="301"/>
      <hi>guerdon of thee but thy good report, and courteous acceptance hereof.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Which doing thou shalt make me dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bound to thee. First to be thankefull for thy good will. Secondly, to bee consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate how hereafter I take vpon mee so great a charge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly, thou shalt encourage mee to encrease my talent.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fourthly, and lastly, most freely to bestow the encrease thereof on thee, and for the benefite of my Country and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, whereunto duety bindeth mee: Obseruing the sage and prudent saying of the renowmed Oratour and famour</hi> Cicero: <hi>with which I end, and there to leaue thee.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Non nobis solum natisumus, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tusque nostri partem patria vendicat, partem parentes, partem amici.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>In defence and preseruation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (good Reader) wee ought not alone to imploy our whole wits and able sences, but necessity enforcing vs, to sacrifice our selues also for benefite thereof.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine that accepteth me. T. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>