<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>W., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120090_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15529</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25798</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120090</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>W., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Theologicall rules, to guide vs in the vnderstanding and practise of holy Scriptures : two centuries: drawne partly out of Scriptures themselues: partly out of ecclesiasticall writers old and new. Also Ænigmata sacra, holy riddles; or misticall cases and secrets of diuinitie, with their resolutions. Foure centuries: the vnfolding whereof layeth open that truth that concerneth saluation. By T.W. preacher of the word</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 125, 13, 206 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the words of holy Scriptures onely, but the sense and meaning, (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in Christ) which is carefully to be searched after of all those who desire the knowledge of <hi>that Truth</hi> which bringeth to saluation such as endeuour to liue thereafter. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth well by that worthy sentence


<pb facs="3"/>
of a Greeke Father, affirming,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Basill.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>That Pietie consisteth not in the sound of the Ayre, but in the force of things signified,</hi> whereunto accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that of Hierom the Latin Father.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hierom.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>The Gospell consisteth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward marrow of the sense, and not in the outward sound of words; not in the leaues of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but in the root of reason.</hi> To this purpose as I haue heretofore tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled to lay forth the signification of words in Scripture by a short and easie Dictionarie already by me published to the world, in the kinde acceptance whereof and other my labours, I haue tasted of thy curtesie, to my great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement: So haue I now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto added <hi>Two Centuries and more, of Theologicall Rules, and aboue Fower Centuries of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Cases and Secrets of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie with their Resolutions,</hi> as


<pb facs="3"/>
good helps and means to bring to light the hidden vnderstanding of the Scripture. For, certaine it is, as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Arts and Sciences, bee they Grammar, Logick, or the rest, so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diuinitie, which is the Arte of Arts, and Queene of Sciences, can either bee taught or learned without Precepts and Rules; And as it cannot be practised, so can it not bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood without speciall fit Rules to guide vs in the Interpretation. For the most of these Rules, especially such as bee deriued from ancient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I am beholden to <hi>Flaccius Illiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus;</hi> the rest I either collected out of later moderne writers, or by my owne obseruation. I haue also added an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of all the Rules which bee drawne immediately out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: To the other, which be collected out of Ecelesiasticall Authors, I haue (for the most part) ioyned both Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons


<pb facs="4"/>
and Examples, to explane them the better. Some of these Rules doe further our vnderstanding in the Old: some in the New Testament: and some in both. Some of them will steed vs in the Doctrines, some in the words and formes of speeches vsed in the Scriptures: and some serue to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne vs in the studie and practise of the word. Whatsoeuer vse or worth they bee of, (which I verily hope will be much and manifold,) I dedicate them, to all the Faithfull whersoeuer throughout this land, dispersed.</p>
   <p>If any either <hi>Ioshua</hi> or other young man, shall out of enuy or iealousie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, that by this meanes not only <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi> but (as Chrysostome speakes) the Shepherd and the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and the Spinster, will bee able to prophesie and know as much as some Preachers do. An answer is framed to my hand by <hi>Moses</hi> the


<pb facs="4"/>
man of God: <hi>I would to God that all the Lords people could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie, and that the Spirit of the Lord were put vpon them.</hi> And by Paul, <hi>Let the worde of God dwell plenteously in you in all wisdome. Col. 3. 16.</hi> If this sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie not, The next answer is, that if they who finde fault will labour to doe as much, or much more seruice to the Church by their painfull endeuours, they shall doe it I assure them without enuy on my part. As for you belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord, take in good worth, I beseech you, both these my <hi>Two Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies of Theologicall Rules,</hi> and also my <hi>Power Centuries of AEnig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata Sacra, or Mysticall Cases and Secrets of Diuinitie,</hi> annexed, (of whose vse see their proper Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face) and improoue them to your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test spirituall gaine in Christ. To whose Grace I commend and commit


<pb facs="5"/>
you to bee guided and comforted by it for euer. Farewell, from my house in <hi>Canterbury. 1615.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to his vttermost <hi>T. W.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>