<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir Thomas Stewart of Gairntilie, and his vertuous Ladie, Grizzell Mercer, Grace and peace from God the father, through our Lord Iesus CHRIST.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120025_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19491</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5917</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir Thomas Stewart of Gairntilie, and his vertuous Ladie, Grizzell Mercer, Grace and peace from God the father, through our Lord Iesus CHRIST.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defiance to death : Wherein, besides sunndry heauenly instructions for a godly life, we haue strong and notable comforts to vphold vs in death. By Mr. William Couuper, minister of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Cowper, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 382 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir <hi>Thomas Stewart</hi> of Gairntilie, and his vertuous Ladie, <hi>Grizzell Mercer,</hi> Grace and peace from God the father, through our Lord Iesus CHRIST.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apostle, <hi>If in this life onely we haue hope in Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19</note>
      <hi>wee are of all
<pb facs="3"/>
mē the most miserable:</hi> For, whereas others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er things to come, set their harts on these, which are present: if wee despising such comforts as now we may enioy, should also be disapointed of those, which afterwards we looke for, Our case indeede were most lamentable: but praised be God, it is farre otherwise; for where the comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t of the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ends, there the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test comfort of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian beginnes.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 17.14</note> The men of this world (saies <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>) haue their portion
<pb facs="3"/>
in this life:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk▪</hi> 6.24.</note> yea our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour saith, They haue receiued their consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke</hi> 16.</note> It was spoken in that Parable by Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham to <hi>Diues,</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that in thy life thou receiuedst thy pleasures: And it appertaines to all the wicked: better things then these, which pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they see, neede they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to looke for. And therfore no maruell, that as the taste of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quint, or wilde Gourd, made the children of the Prophets abhor thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> meat, so the taste of death make all the pleasures &amp;
<pb facs="4"/>
refreshments of their life loathsome to them. Or as the hand which wrote to <hi>Beltazar</hi> on the wall his imminent iudgment, did in a moment turn all the solace of that house into sorrow, for the Kings countenance was chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, his thoughts troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, his Princes astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Musitians silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, his seruants amazed, their delightfull drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing became despised, and all the house disordered: and in a worde, his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet concluded with a cuppe of wrath, sent to him from the Lord: so
<pb facs="4"/>
is it vnto all the wicked; the smallest signification of death interrupts their greatest ioyes, and causes them with the Peacocke, looking to his feet, let fall the proude feathers of their hie conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their owne mindes, what euer they pretend in countenance. As is the noise of thornes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the potte, so is the laughter of fooles, saieth <hi>Salomon,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.8.</note> both the one and the other quickely vanishes: and death like that worme, which eated vp the gourd of <hi>Ionas,</hi> deuoures at length all
<pb facs="5"/>
their Worme-eaten plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, and then woe be to them, When all these fat, and excellent things,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.14</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which their soule lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, are departed from them, and not so much as any hope of better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines vnto them: But vnto the Christian, death can doe no more but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molish this parpen wall of clay, within the which the soule is captiued for a time, it opens the doore of the prison, and giues li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the soule, to goe out and returne to her Maker, as shal at greater length appeare in the
<pb facs="5"/>
Treatis following, which I haue offered, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to your Honour, partly to testifie my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined affection toward you in the Lord; for that vnfeined and incorrupt loue, which in so corrupt a time ye haue alway car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried toward the truth of the Gospell, and by which also ye haue liued, as rare examples of pietie and loue, &amp; godly liberality, and partly that ye may be remembred of these in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions concerning life and death: w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ich ye receiued from vs by hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring, during your resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb facs="6"/>
with vs, and vnto the practise whereof shortly ye must be called: for albeit it is not long, since it pleased the Lord beyond all expectation of man to deliuer you out of the handes of the Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants &amp; officers of death, which had violently sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vpon you, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to slay you both, your selfe by sickenesse, your Ladie by the sorrow of desolation, more heauie then death vnto her: yet are yee to knowe (and I doubt not, are preparing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for it) that the same battell will shortly bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb facs="6"/>
against you, wherin both of you must bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorced from other, and diuided from your owne bodies, that yee may bee married and conioyne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> with your Lord, whom ye haue not yet seene,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> but long to see him, because ye loue him, and reioyce in him with ioy vnspeak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able and glorious. And herein, if these little fruites of my Ministery may serue any way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme you in the end, as some way they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted you in the iourney: and if for your sake they may bee profitable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="7"/>
who, cōstantly keeps with you the same course toward the face of Iesus Christ, it shall be no small comfort vnto me, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby that I haue not runne, nor laboured in vaine; for there is no thing in the world I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire more, then that I may put my talent to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost profite, fulfilling with ioy the Ministrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I haue receiued, and so may be welcommed of my Lord, as one who hath beene faithfull in little: But because all encrease comes from God, I humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend you, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
that loue the Lord Iesus to the grace of God which is able to build you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and giue you inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among them who are sanctified by faith in Christ, and so rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your H. in the Lord Iesus M.</hi> William Cowper <hi>Minist. at Perth.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>