<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120947_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68951</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120947</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reformation of a Catholike deformed: by M. W. Perkins : Wherein the chiefe controuersies in religion, are methodically, and learnedly handled. Made by D. B. P. The former part</title>
                 <author>Bishop, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 119, 1, 57, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER,</hi> I meane not here to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayne thee with many wordes: the principall cause that moued me to write, was the honour and glory of God, in defence of his sacred verity, then the imploying of his talent bestowed vpon me: as well to fortifie the weaker sort of Catholikes in their faith, as to call backe and leade others (who wander vp and downe like to lost sheepe, after their owne fancies) into the right way.</p>
   <p>I tooke in hand particularly the confutation of this booke, not onely for that I was thereunto requested, by a friend of good intelligence and iudgement, who thought it very expedient: but also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause perusing of it, I found it penned more Schollerlike, then the Protestants vse to doe ordinarily: For first the pointes in controuersie, are set downe distinctly, and for the most part truely. Afterward in confirmation of their opinion, the chiefe arguments are produced from both Scriptures, Fathers, and reason: Which are not vulgar, but culled out of their Rabbins, <hi>Luther, Peter Martir, Caluin, Kemnitius,</hi> and such like, though he name them not. Lastly, he placeth some obiections, made in fauour of the Catholike Doctrine, and answereth to them aswell as he could. And (which I speake to his commendation) doth performe all this very briefly and clearly. So that (to speake my opinion freely) I haue not seene any booke of like quantity, published by a Protestant, to contayne either more matter, or deliuered in better method. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently more apt to deceiue the simple: especially considering that he withall counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiteth to come as neare vnto the Roman Church, as his tender conscience will permitte him, whereas in deede he walketh as wide from it, as any other noueller of this age.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I esteemed my spare time best imployed about the discouering of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) an abridgement of the principall controuersies of these times, and doe endeuour after the same Scholasticall manner, without all superfluity of wordes, no lesse to maintayne and defend the Catholike party: then to confute all such reasons, as are by <hi>M. PERKINS</hi> alleadged for the contrarie.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>Read this short treatise good Christian diligently, for thou shalt finde in it the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe and pith of many large volumes, contracted and drawne into a narrowe rowme. And read it ouer as it becommeth a good Christian, with a desire to finde out, and to followe the truth, because it concerneth thy eternall saluation: and then iudge without partiality, whether Religion hath better groundes in Gods word, more euident testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie from the purest antiquity, and is more conformable vnto all Godlines, good life, and vpright dealing, (the infallible markes of the best Religion) and speedely imbrace that. Before I end this short preface, I must intreate thy patience to beare with the faultes in Printing, which are too too many, but not so much to be blamed, if it be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously considered; that it was Printed farre from the Authour, with a Dutch compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser, and ouerseene by an vnskilfull Corrector, the greatest of them shall be amended in the end of the booke.</p>
   <closer/>
   <postscript>
      <p>
         <hi>Before the Printing of this part was finished, I heard that M. PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KINS was dead. I am sorry that it commeth forth to late, to doe him anie good. Yet, his worke liuing to poison others, a preseruatiue against it, is neuer the lesse necessary.</hi>
      </p>
   </postscript>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>