<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Noble Ladie, the Ladie DOROTHIE, Countesse of Northum∣berland.
And to the highly honoured Ladies her Daughters, The Ladie DOROTHIE SYD∣NEY, and the Ladie LVCIE HAY:
N. BYFEILD Wisheth the abundance of true grace and peace.</title>
           <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120680_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17400</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4226</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120680</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Noble Ladie, the Ladie DOROTHIE, Countesse of Northum∣berland.
And to the highly honoured Ladies her Daughters, The Ladie DOROTHIE SYD∣NEY, and the Ladie LVCIE HAY:
N. BYFEILD Wisheth the abundance of true grace and peace.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The paterne of wholsome words. Or a collection of such truths as are of necessity to be belieued vnto saluation : separated out of the body of all theologie made euident by infallible plaine proofes of Scripture. And withall, the seuerall vses such principles should be pu to, are abundantly shevved. A proiect much desired, and of singular vse for all sorts of Christians. By N. Bifeild [sic], preacher of Gods word at Isleworth in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 525, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Noble Ladie, the Ladie DOROTHIE, Countesse of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland.</hi>
And to the highly honoured Ladies her Daughters, The Ladie <hi>DOROTHIE SYD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEY,</hi> and the Ladie <hi>LVCIE</hi> HAY:
N. BYFEILD Wisheth the abundance of true grace and peace.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue long since vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken (as in the course of my Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie you haue often heard) to extract out of al Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie
<pb facs="3"/>
conteined in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>the Principles,</hi> that is, such doctrines which are fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and absolutely necessarie to be knowne of as many as are to be saued. This Proiect ought to bee well accepted of all sorts of Christians, that wish their owne good; partly in respect of the necessitie of the doctrines here collected vnder their seueral heads; and partly in respect of the apparant euidence of the proofes of Scripture, which are such, as make infallible demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration to the conscience, by the expresse light cōteined in them; and partly, because the Vses which may be made of the seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Principles, are euery where abundantly shewed.</p>
   <p>And in as much as the Lord hath been pleased, to giue some testimonie to my indeuors here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="3"/>
in the publike preaching; I am not out of hope, but that the printing of those Principles may be profitable to many godly and plaine-hearted Christians, that desire in the plainest manner to vnderstand the meaning of their heauenly Fathers will.</p>
   <p>I humbly dedicate this worke vnto your Honours, and pray your acceptation, and the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of it: and to giue me leaue in the view of the world to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie this way, both my obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance of the many noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertues, which are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in each of your Honours, as also my vnfained thankefulnesse for the many fauours I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and for the countenance and incouragement of my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery; accounting it a singular mercy of God, that any labours of mine should find acceptation
<pb facs="4"/>
with persons of so high place and quality, or any way be successeful to the prospering of any part of the worke of Gods grace in your hearts.</p>
   <p>Now the God of all consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fill your Noble breasts with all riches of the true grace that is in Iesus Christ; that you may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in the knowledge of the mysteries of his Kingdome in all iudgement, and loue of the truth which is according to godlines, and in all those gifts which may be found vnto honor, and praise, and glory in the reuelation of Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all seruice <hi>N. Bifeild.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Isleworth,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>March</hi> 27. 1618.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>