<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The prolog of this present woork sheweth what one true frend ought to doo for an other: Addressed to the right honorable the lord Fraunces Conos, great commaunder of Lyon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120709_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02296</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12428</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120709</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The prolog of this present woork sheweth what one true frend ought to doo for an other: Addressed to the right honorable the lord Fraunces Conos, great commaunder of Lyon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dial of princes, compiled by the reuerend father in God, Don Antony of Gueuara, Byshop of Guadix, preacher, and chronicler to Charles the fifte, late of that name Emperour. Englished out of the Frenche by T. North, sonne of Sir Edvvard North knight, L. North of Kyrtheling</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 165, 1, 101, 103-173, 24 leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb n="98" facs="282"/>
   <head>
      <hi>¶The prolog of this present woork sheweth what one true frend ought</hi> to doo for an other: Addressed to the right honorable the lord Fraunces Conos, great commaunder of Lyon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He famous Philosopher <hi>Plato,</hi> beesought of al his disciples to tel thē, why hee iornyed so oft from <hi>Athens</hi> to <hi>Scicille,</hi> beeing the way hee tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled (in deede) very long, and the sea hee passed very daungerous: aunswered them thus. The cause that moues mee to goe from <hi>Athens</hi> to <hi>Scicille,</hi> is only to see <hi>Phocion,</hi> a man iustinal that hee dooth, and wise in all that hee speaketh: and beecause hee is my very frend, and enemy of <hi>Denys,</hi> I goe also willingly to him, to ayd him in that I may, and to councell him in all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> I know: and told them further. I doo you to weete my disciples, that a good philosopher, to visit and help his frend, and to accompany with a good man, shoold think the iorney short, and no whit paynfull, though hee shoold sulk the whole seas, and pace the compase of the earth. <hi>Appolonius Thianeus</hi> departed from Rome, went through all <hi>Asia,</hi> sayled ouer the great flud <hi>Nile,</hi> endured the bitter cold of mount <hi>Caucasus,</hi> suffered the parching heat of the mountayns <hi>Riphei,</hi> passed the land of <hi>Nassagera,</hi> &amp; entred into the great <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia:</hi> And this long pilgrimage tooke hee vppon him, in no other respect, but to see <hi>Hyarcus</hi> the philosopher, his great and old frend. <hi>Agesilaus</hi> also among the Greekes accompted a woorthy Captayn, vnderstanding that the kyng <hi>Hycarius</hi> had an other captayn (his very frend) captyue: leauing all his own affayres apart, traueling through dyuers countreis, went to the place where hee was, and arryued there, presented him self vnto the kyng, and said thus to him. I humbly beeseech thee O puissant king, thou deigne to pardon <hi>Minotus,</hi> my sole and only frend, and thy subiect now: for what thou shalt doo to him, make thy account thou hast doon it to mee. For in deed thou canst ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer alone punish his body, but thou shalt therewith also crucify my hart.</p>
   <p>Kyng <hi>Herod</hi> after <hi>Augustus</hi> had ouercome <hi>Mark Antony,</hi> came to Rome, and laying his crown at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Imperiall feete, with stout corage spake these woords vnto him. Know thou (mighty <hi>Augustus</hi>) if thou knowst it not, that if <hi>Mark Antony</hi> had beeleeued mee, and not his accursed loue <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> thou shooldst then haue proued how bitter an enemy I woold haue been to thee, and hee haue found how true a frend I was, and yet am to him. But hee, as a man rather geeuen ouer to the rule of a womans will, then guyded by reasons skill, tooke of mee but money only, and of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> counsell. And proceeding further sayd: Lo here my kingdom, my person, and royall crown layd at thy princely feete, all which I freely offer to thee, to dispose of at thy will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, pleasing thee so to accept it, but yet with this condicion (inuict <hi>August{us}</hi>) that thou commaund mee not to here nor speak yll of <hi>Mark Antony</hi> my lord and frend, yea although hee were now dead. For know thou, sacred prince, that true frends, neither for death ought to bee had in obliuiō, nor for absens to bee forsaken. <hi>Iulius Cesar</hi> last dictator and first emperor of Rome, dyd so entierly loue <hi>Cornelius Fabatus</hi> the consull, that traueling togethers through the alps of Fraunce and beeing beenighted, farre from any town or harber, saue that only of a hollow caue, which happely they lighted on: And <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the consull euen then not well at ease, <hi>Iulius Cesar</hi> left him the whole caue
<pb facs="283"/>
to thend hee might bee more at rest, and hee him self lay abroad in the cold &amp; snow. By these goodly examples wee haue resited, and by dyuers others wee coold resite, may bee considered, what faithfull frendship ought to bee bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt true and perfect frends, and into how many daungers one frend ought to put him self for an other. For it is not enough that one frend bee sory for the troubles of an other, but hee is bound (if neede were) to goe and dye ioyfully wyth him. Hee only deseruedly may bee counted a true frend, that vnasked, and beefore hee bee called, goeth with his goods and person to help and releeue his frend. But in this our yron age alas there is no such kynd of amity as that wee haue spoken of. More then this, that there is no frend will part with any thing of his to releeue his frend, much lesse that taketh care to fauor him in his trobles: but if there bee any such that will help hys frend, yt is euen then when tyme serueth rather to pity and lament him, then to ayd or succor him. It is a thing woorth the knowledge, that to make a true and perpetuall frendship, wee may not offer to many persons, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Seneca</hi> his saying, who saith. My frend <hi>Lucillus,</hi> I councell thee that thou bee a true frend to one alone, and enemy to none: for nombers of frends brings great incumbrance, which seemeth somewhat to diminish frendship. For who that considereth the liberty of the hart, it is impossible that one shoold frame and agree wyth the condicions of many, and much lesse that many shoold content them with the desiers and affections of one. <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Salust</hi> were two famous orators amongst the Romayns, and great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies beetwene them selues, and duryng thys emulation beetweene them, <hi>Tully</hi> had purchased all the Senators frendship, and <hi>Salust</hi> only had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther frend in all Rome, but <hi>Mark Anthony</hi> alone. And so these two great O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators beeing one day at woords togeethers, <hi>Tully</hi> in great anger sayd to <hi>Salust:</hi> what force or power art thou of, or what canst thou doo or attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst mee? sith thou knowst that in all Rome thou hast but one only frend, <hi>Mark Antony,</hi> and I no enemy but one, and that is hee? To whom <hi>Salust</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered. Thou gloriest (O <hi>Tully</hi>) that thou hast no mo but one only enemy, and afterwards iests at mee, that I haue no more frends but only one: but I hope in the immortall Gods, that this only enemy thou hast, shalbee able enough vtterly to vndoo thee: and this my sole frend that I haue, shalbee sufficient to protect and defend mee in al my causes. And shortly after these woords passed beetween them, <hi>Mark Antony</hi> shewed the frendship hee bare to the one, and the enimity hee had to the other, for hee caused <hi>Tully</hi> to bee put to death, and raysed <hi>Salust</hi> to great honor. A frend may well impart to the other all his own, as bread, wyne, money, tyme, conuersation, and such lyke, but hee cannot notwithstandyng geeue him part of his hart, for that suffereth it not to bee parted nor deuyded, beecause it can bee geeuen but to one alone. This graunted to bee true, as needs it must doubtles, that the hart can not bee deuyded but only geeuen to one, then is it of necessity, that hee that will seeke to haue many frends, must needs repair to the shambels to prouyde him of many harts. Many vaunt them selues, and think it a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to haue nombers of frends, but let such well consider to what vse that le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendary of frends do serue them, they shall then easely fynd they stand them in no other steed, but to eat, to drink, to walk, to babble, and to murmure
<pb n="99" facs="283"/>
togeethers, and not one to help the other with their goods, fauor, and credit at their neede, nor frendly to reprooue them of their faults and vyces, whych doubtles ought not to bee so. For where true and perfect frendship rayg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, neither I wish my frend, nor hee with mee shoold dissemble any fault or vyce. <hi>Ouide</hi> sayth in his booke <hi>de arte amandi,</hi> that the law of true &amp; vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue is so streight, that no frendship but myne in thy hart shoold herber, and in myne shoold lodge none others loue but thine, for loue is none other thing but one hart lyuing in two bodies, &amp; two bodies obeying one hart. In this world there is no treasure cōparable to a true &amp; sure frend, syth to a faith full frend a man may safely discouer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> secrets of hys hart, beewray vnto him hys gryping greeues, trusting him with his honor, comitting to his guyd &amp; custody all his goods, hee shall succor him in his misery, counsell him in peril, reioyce at his prosperity, and mourn at his aduersity: and in fyne I conclude, such a frend neuer werieth to serue him in his lyfe, nor to lament him after his death. I graunt that gold and siluer is good, kynsfolks are good, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is good, but true frends exceede them all without comparison. For all these things cannot warrant vs from necessitie (if synister fortune plunge vs into it) but rather encrease our torment and extremitie: Also they doo not reioyce vs, but rather heap further greefes vppon vs, neither doo they suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor vs, but rather ech hour geeue vs cause to complayn, much lesse doo they remember and aduise vs of that that is good, but still doo deceiue vs, not dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectyng vs the right way, but still bringing vs out of our way, and when they haue lead vs awry out of the high way, they bring vs into desert woods, and hygh and daungerous mountayns, whereof necessity wee must fal down hedlong. A true frend is no partaker of these conditions, but rather hee ys sory for the lest trouble that happeneth to hys frend, hee feareth not, neither spareth hys goods, nor the daunger of his person, hee careth not to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hym any painfull iorney, quarels, or sutes, nor yet to put his lyfe in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hasard of death. And yet that that is most of all to bee esteemed is, that lyke as the hart and bowels euer burn with pure and sincere loue, so dooth hee wish and desire wyth gladsome mynd, to bere the burthen of all hys frends mishaps, yea more then yet spoken of. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great offered great presents to the Philosopher <hi>Zenocrates,</hi> who woold not vouchsafe to receiue them, much lesse to beehold them. And beeing demaunded of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> why hee woold not receyue them, hauyng poore kinsfolks and parents to beestow them on: hee aunswered him thus. Truely I haue both brothers and sisters (O <hi>Alexander</hi>) yet I haue no kinsman but him that is my frend, and one only frend I haue, who hath no neede of any gyfts to bee geeuen him. For the only cause why I choose him to bee my sole and only frend, was for that I euer saw him despise these worldly things. Truely the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this good philosopher <hi>Zenocrates</hi> is of no small efficacy, for him that will aduysedly consider of it, sith that not seeldom but many times it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that the great troubles, the sundry daungers, and the continuall neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities and miseries wee suffer in this vale of misery, haue for the most part proceeded from our parents, and afterwards by our frends haue been medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and redressed. Therefore since wee haue thought it good and necessary
<pb facs="284"/>
to choose a frend, and that hee bee but one only, ech man must bee wise lest in such choise hee bee deceiued. For oft tymes it happeneth, that those that take litle regard herein, graunt their frendship to such one as is to couetous, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacient, a great babbler, seditious, and presumptuous, and of such condicions that sometyme it shoold bee lesse euil for vs to haue him our enemy, then to account of him as of our deere frend. Him whom wee wil choose for our faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full frend, amongst other maners and condicions hee must chiefely and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all bee indued with these, that hee bee curteous of nature, faier spoken, hard and stout to indure payn, pacient in troubles, sober in dyet, moderate in his woords, graue and rype in his counsels, and aboue all stedfast in frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and faithfull in secrets. And whom wee shall fynd with these laudable vertues and conditions adorned, him may wee safely take and accept for our frend. But if wee see any of these parts wanting in him, wee ought to shon him as from the plague, knowing for certeinty, that the frendship of a fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and fantasticall frend is much woorse and perilous, then the enmity of a knowen and open enemy. For to the hands of one wee commit our hart, and faith: and from the deceipts and treasons of the other, wee defendour selues with our whole force &amp; power. <hi>Seneca</hi> wryting to his deere &amp; faithful frend <hi>Lucillus</hi> sayth vnto hym. I pray thee (O <hi>Lucillus</hi>) that thou order &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne thine affaiers by thaduise &amp; counsel of thy frend, but also I doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee, that first thou see well what maner of frend thou hast chosen thee, for there is no marchandise in the world this day that men are so soone beegyled in, as they are in the choise of frends. Therefore the graue sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Seneca</hi> wysely wayed, wee shoold assent with him in oppinion, that sith no man byeth a horse but hee first causeth him to bee ridden, nor bread but first hee seeth and handleth it, nor wyne but hee tasteth it, nor flesh but first hee wayeth it, nor corne but hee seeth a sample, nor house but that hee dooth first value it, nor Instrument but first hee playeth on it, and iudgeth of his sound: yt is but reason hee shoold bee so much the more circumspect bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he choose his frend to examin his lyfe and condicion, since all the other things wee haue spoken of may bee put in dyuers houses and corners, but our frend wee lodge and keepe deerely in our proper bowels. Those that write of the emperor <hi>Augustus</hi> say, that hee was very straunge and scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in accepting frends, but after hee had once receyued thē into his frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, hee was very constant and circūspect to keepe them. For hee neuer had any frend, but first hee had some proofe and tryall of him, neither woold hee euer after forsake him for any displeasure doon to him. Therefore yt shoold always bee so, that true frends shoold bere one to an other such loue and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that the one beeing in prosperity, should not haue occasion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playn of him self in that hee did not reliue his frends necessity beeing in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity: nor the other beeing poore and needy, shoold grudge or lament for that his frend beeing rich and welthy, woold not succor him with all that hee might haue doone for him. For to say the truth, where perfect frendshyp is, there ought no excuse to bee made to doo what possible is the one for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The frendship of young men cometh commonly, (or for the most parte at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> least) by beeing companyons in vyce and folly: and such of right ought
<pb n="100" facs="284"/>
rather to bee called vacabonds, then once to deserue the name of true frends. For that cannot bee called true frendship, that is continued to the preiudyce or derogation of vertue. <hi>Seneca</hi> wryting agayn to <hi>Lucillus</hi> sayth these woords. I woold not haue thee think, nor once mistrust, O my <hi>Lucillus,</hi> that in all the Romayn empire I haue any greater frend then thou: but with all assure thy self, that our frendship is not so streight beetwene vs, that I woold take vppon mee at any tyme to doo for thee otherwyse then honesty shoold lead mee. For though the loue I bere thee hath made thee lord of my lyberty: yet reason also hath left mee vertue free.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>¶The aucthor proceedeth on.</head>
      <p>Applyeng that wee haue spoken to that wee will now declare, I say I wil not acknowledge my self your seruant, for so shoold I bee compelled to feare you more then loue you: much lesse will I vaunt my self to bee your kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for so I shoold importune and displease you: and I will not brag that heeretofore wee haue been of familier acquaintance, for that I woold not make any demonstration I made so lyttle account of you, and lesse then I am bound to doo: neither will I bost my self that I am at this present your famyliar and welbeeloued, for in deede I shoold then shew my self to bee to bold and arrogant: but that that I will confesse shalbee, that I loue you as a frend, and you mee as a kinsman, al bee it this frendship hath succeeded dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly tyll now. For you beeing noble as you are, haue bountifully shewed your frendship to mee, in large and ample gyfts: but I poore, and of base es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, haue only made you sure of myne in woords. <hi>Plutarche</hi> in his Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes sayd: That it were farre better to sell to our frends our woorks and good deeds, (whether they were in prosperity, aduersity, or necessity) then to feede them with vayn flattering woords for nothing. Yet is it not so general a rule, but that sometymes it happeneth that the high woords on the one syde are so profitable, and the woorks so few and feeble on the other syde, that one shalbee better pleased and delighted with hearing the sweete and curteous woords of thone, then hee shalbee to bee serued with the cold seruyce and woorks of the other, of small profyt and value. <hi>Plutarch</hi> also in his booke <hi>De animalibus</hi> telleth vs, that <hi>Denis</hi> the tyrant beeing one day at the table reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of dyuers and sundry matters with <hi>Chrisipp{us}</hi> the philosopher, it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that as hee was at diner, one brought him a present of certen suger cakes, wherefore <hi>Chrisippus</hi> cesing his former discours fell to perswade <hi>Denys</hi> to fall to his cakes. To whom <hi>Denys</hi> aunswered, on with your matter <hi>Chrisippus,</hi> and leaue not of so: For my hart is better contented wyth thy sweet and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred woords, then my tong is pleased with the delycate tast of these moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn cakes. For as thou knowest, these cakes are heauy of digestion, and doo greatly annoy the stomake: but good woords doo maruelously reioyce and comfort the hart. For this cause <hi>Alexander</hi> the great had the poet <hi>Homer</hi> in greater veneration, beeing dead, then all the other that were alyue in hys tyme: not for that <hi>Homer</hi> euer did him seruyce, or that hee knew him, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beecause of his lerned bookes hee wrote and compyled, and for the graue sentences hee found therein. And therefore hee bare about him in the day tyme the booke of the famous deedes of <hi>Troy</hi> (called the <hi>Illiades</hi>) hanged at
<pb facs="285"/>
his neck within hys bosom: &amp; in the night hee layd it vnder his bolster, at hys beddes head where hee slept. In recompence therefore (syr) of the many good turns I haue receiued at your hands, I was also willyng to compyle and dedicate this my lytle treatise to you, the which I present you wyth all my desyres, my studyes, my watches, my swett, and my troubles, holding my self fully satisfyed for all the payns I haue taken, so that this my simple tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell bee gratefull to you (to whom I offer yt) and to the publyke weale profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Beeing well assured, if it please you to trust mee and credyte my wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, you shall manifestly know how freely I speak to you, and lyke a frend, and not deceiue you as a flatterer. For if the beeloued and fauored of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces chaunce to bee cast out of fauor, it is beecause euery man flattereth hym and seeketh to please him and no man goeth about to tell him troth, nor that that is for his honor, and fittest for him. <hi>Salust</hi> in his booke of the warres of <hi>Iugurtha</hi> sayth, that the hygh heroycall facts and noble deedes were of no lesse glory to the historiographer that wrote them, then they were to the captayn that dyd them. For it happeneth many tymes that the Captayn dying in the battell hee hath woone, lyueth afterwards notwythstandyng by the fame of his noble attempt, and this proceedeth not only of the valyaunt deedes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes hee was seene doo; but also for that wee read of him in woorthy authors which haue amply written thereof. Wee may well say therefore touching this matter, that aswell may wee take hym for a true frend, that geeueth good counsell: as hee whych dooth vs great pleasure, and seruyce. For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the oppinion of the good <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> who sayd to his secretary <hi>Panutius,</hi> that a man with one pay, may make full satisfaccion and recompēce of many pleasures and good turns shewed: but to requyte a good counsell, dyuers thanks and infinite seruices are requisite. If wee wil credit the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient historiographers wee shall fynd it true, that the vertuous emperors, the fortunate kyngs, and the valyaunt Captains, when they shoold enterprise to goe conquer their enemies, either they sought for some philosopher, or they choose some other honest learned man, of whom they tooke councel touching all their affayrs, beefore they prest any soldiers. Comparing the tymes past, with the tymes present, wee think (that haue read some what) that the tyme past was as pure grayn, and this now as chaffe and straw: the one as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tyme calme and still in the sea, and this as wauering and tempesteous: that then the fyne and pure mettall, and this now the drosse thereof: The other the marie, and this the bones: the one the cleer day, and the other the dark night: For in these days in princes courts, and noble mens houses, they glory more to haue a scoffing knaue or iester to make them laugh, then they recken of a graue and wyse man to geeue them counsell. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great in all hys warres woold always bee accompanyed with the wyse <hi>Aristotle. Cyrus</hi> kyng of <hi>Persia,</hi> with the philosopher <hi>Chilo:</hi> Kyng <hi>Ptolomie</hi> wyth <hi>Pithinus</hi> the philosopher: <hi>Pirrhus</hi> kyng of <hi>Epyre,</hi> wyth <hi>Zatirus: Augustus</hi> themperor wyth <hi>Symonides: Scipio</hi> thaffrican wyth <hi>Sophocles: Traian</hi> themperor wyth <hi>Plutarche,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antonius</hi> themperor wyth <hi>Gorgias:</hi> now all these famous princes caried not w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thē so many learned philosophers, to fyght in battell w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> armed weapon in hand like other their soldiers, but only to vse their coūcel &amp; aduice.
<pb n="101" facs="285"/>
So that the great battels they ouerthrew, and the woorthy victories they wanne, with the noble tryumphs doon, was as much by the graue counsell of these good and wise Philosophers, as by the force of their army, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of their Captayns. The greatest good turn and benefit one frend can doo for an other, is to know to geeue good counsell to his frend, in his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test neede: and not without cause I say to know to geeue counsell. For it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth oft tymes, that those that thought to haue geeuen vs good remedy by their counsell, (wanting in deede discrecion and iudgement in the same) haue caused vs to runne into further daungers. And therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once demaunded of themperor <hi>Nero,</hi> what hee thought of <hi>Scipio</hi> thaffri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, &amp; <hi>Cato</hi> the censor, answered him in this maner. I think it was as neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary that <hi>Cato</hi> was born for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> comon wealth, as <hi>Scipio</hi> for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> warres, for the good <hi>Cato</hi> wyth his prudent counsell expelled vice out of the wealth publike, and the other with his noble courage and great armies did euer wythstand the force of the enemies. According to the saying of <hi>Seneca,</hi> let vs also say after him, that hee is very arrogant that presumes to geeue an other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, but with all wee say agayn: that if the counsell bee found good hee hath geeuen to his frend in his neede and necessity, asmuch praise deserueth hee that gaue it, as hee that knew how to take it. Now after thexample of the auncient philosophers, which went to the warres not to fight, but only to geeue counsell, I will (syr) for those things that pertayn to your seruyce, and profit, take vppon mee the offyce of a philosopher, and for the first doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin of my philosophy I say, that if it please you, to receiue these counsels whych my penne dooth write to you, at this present, I promise you, and by the faith of a christian man I swear, that they shalbee such excellent helps to you, for the preseruation of your credyt and fauor you are now in, as you may bee enriched by the true and diligent seruice of your seruaunts. For if a man woold with an oth ask the trueth of <hi>Plato, Socrates, Pithagoras, Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Licurgus, Chilo, Pittach{us},</hi> and of <hi>Apolonius,</hi> and also of all the vniuersity and company of the other philosophers, they woold swere and affirm that the felicity of man consisteth not in great might, in great aucthority, and pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions: but only in deseruing much. For the honor, fauor, and dignityes of this mortall lyfe, are more to bee praised and had in veneratiō when they are placed in a condigne and woorthy person: then they are beeing posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of an vnwoorthy and graceles man, allotted to hym not by vertue, but by fortune. And therefore your aucthority beeing great at this present, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereto by gods diuine will and prouydence, and now in the hyghest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of prosperity: I woold wish you my good lord, lesse then any other cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier to trust to fortunes impery. For yf the earthquakes sooner bryng to ground the proud and stately Pallaces, then the mean and low how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: if ofter fall on the highest mountayns, the dreadfull lightnings and tempests, then on the lowest hilles: if among the greater multitude of people the plagues bee rifer, then amongst the fewer nomber: yf they vse rather to spread their netts, and lay the byrdlyme on the green and thickst bows, then on the dry and wythered sticks, to snare the sely byrds withall: If always the stillest seas doo foreshew to vs a greater tempest following: and if that
<pb facs="286"/>
long health bee a watch vnto a great and daungerous sicknes ensuyng: by this also I will inferre, that those that are atchiued to sublime estate &amp; hygh degree are commonly more subiect to fall, then those of mean and baser sort. The emperor <hi>Augustus</hi> on a tyme demaunded of the Poet <hi>Virgill,</hi> that hee woold teach him how hee might conserue him self in thempire, and alwayes bee acceptable to the publike weal. To whom <hi>Virgill</hi> aunswered. I think, O mighty <hi>Cesar,</hi> that to reigne long in thempire, thou must consideratly looke into thy self, examining thy lyfe and dooings: and how much thou shalt see thy self excell and exceede all those (of thy empire) in dignity: So much more must thou endeuor thy self to surmount all others, in vertue, and we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes. For hee is vnwoorthy to rule a multitude, that is not chief himself in all vertues. Those therefore that in court of princes bere office, and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ought earnestly to desire and indeuour them selues to auoyd the fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy sink of vice, and to seeke the cleere spring of vertue. For otherwise, they shalbee more defamed for one vyce or defect found in them, then honored for their office and authority they haue.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>¶The aucthor concludeth.</head>
      <p>According to the saying of the poet <hi>Virgill</hi> to the Emperor <hi>Augustus,</hi> I am also of oppinion (my Lord) that you ought to bee very circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and well aduised, in looking into your self who you are, what po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer you are of, what you are woorth, and what you possesse: and dooyng thus, you shall fynd that among your wise councellors you are the greatest, among the rich, among the best esteemed, among the most fortunat, among your secretories, among the rulers, amongst all those of your realm &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, you are euer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greatest. And therefore as you are greatst, and supreme aboue them all: so you ought the more to force to bee the most vertuous of them all. For els it were against all reason, beeing the greatest, to bee the least and most inferior of all. For truely none ought to bee praised for good, for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hee is of power, force, possessions, wealth, much woorth, in fauor, of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, neither for any nobilitie that is in him, if these natural gifts bee not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compagnied with vertue &amp; good woorks. The auncient historiographers do highly commend the greatnes of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the knowledge of <hi>Ptholomie,</hi> the iustice of <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> the clemency of <hi>Iulius Cesar,</hi> the pacience of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus,</hi> the trueth of <hi>Traian,</hi> the pity of <hi>Antonius,</hi> the temperancy of <hi>Constantius,</hi> the continency of <hi>Scipio,</hi> and the humanity of <hi>Theodosius:</hi> so that wee may say these so great &amp; noble princes haue wonne more honor by their vertues, then they haue atchyued by tryumphant victories. Albeeit a man bee neuer so dishonest, vicious, and lasciuious, and that hee bee rooted in all ydlenes, let vs say and auouch it for a trueth, that it is impossible (if hee may return to looke back on him self, and that hee may cal to mynd what maner of man hee hath been, what hee is at this present, &amp; to what end hee may come) but that the remembraunce of his forepassed faults and deeds, shoold bee more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and yrksom to him, then the great delight his body shoold take of the present pleasures. For neither the woorms in the vynes, nor the locusts in the corn, nor the moths in the garments, nor the litle woorms in the wood are so hurtful and dommageable, as sinnes are of power to make a man so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull. For to say truely, the pleasure wee receyue when wee commyt
<pb n="103" facs="286"/>
them is not so great, as is the displeasure wee feele after wee remember them. The whych I considering, my lord, yt causeth mee to looke ouer myne old memorials, to examyne my memory, to strengthen my iudgement, and to seeke a new kynd of study, to no other end, but to fynd out sweete woords, dyuers doctryns, and straunge historyes, by means whereof I myght with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw you from vayn and worldly delights, to cause you to walk in the right path, and to affect things vertuous and honest, though I haue always kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen them as acceptable to you, as they haue been familier. For princes ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts, the more they are busied with affairs, the lesse they know them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. And therefore great payn suffereth hee, and wyth ouer venymous poyson is hee infected, that wyth others, and for other occupyeth all hys time, and for his own sowl health cannot spare a moment of tyme. O what comfort and quiet were it vnto my hart, if it were assured it had taken the ryght way, in the doctrine which I write to you, and that I had not erryd in the counsels I geeue you: so that in readyng my booke you myght acquire profit thereby, and I of my trauel therein reap my full contentation. And to the end, my Lord, wee may better expresse the matter, search the wound, and stoppe the vayns, that wee may leaue no part vncured or dreggs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, if heetherto I haue vsed playnesse, I will now speak more playnly to you, and yet as one frend vseth to an other. And therefore may it please you to accept these smal written preposes in this book, among al the residue, proceeding from the hands of one that rather desyreth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> health of your sowl, then the gayn and satisfaction of your affects and desyres.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>¶All you that bee princes familiers, and beeloued Courtiers: obserue and retayn with you these few precepts and counsels.</head>
      <p n="1">1 NEuer tell (my lord) to any all that you think. Shew not all that you haue. Neyther take all that you desire: Tell not all that you know.</p>
      <p>Much lesse neuer doo all that you may. For the right path way to bring the fauored courtier into hys Princes disgrace, is to bee addicted to hys sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall appetytes and vayne humors, and not to bee guyded wyth reason and discrecion.</p>
      <p n="2">2 Beware also you trust not, nor commit to the hasard of fortunes tickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes such things, as touch and conserue your parson, honor, goods and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. For the wyse courtier that lyueth in his princes grace, will not rashly put him self in daunger, in hope to saue him self harmles, at all tymes when hee listeth.</p>
      <p n="3">3 Although euery man offer his seruice to you, and seeme to bee at your commaundement when you shall neede him: yet I tell you (syr) I woold not wish you had eyther neede of them, or of mee: For many of those lyne and curious courtiers which are the first that offer them selues to draw on your syde, and to stand by you if neede bee, are commonly (at the very pinch) the first and redyest to throw stones at our faces.</p>
      <p n="4">4 In other mennes matters busy not your self to much: and in your own, stryue not wyth tyme, but take leysure. For lyuing after thys rule,
<pb facs="287"/>
you shall long keepe your self in the good and quyet estate you are in, and otherwise some inconuenience myght lightly fall vppon you, that shoold make you remember what you were wont to bee.</p>
      <p n="5">5 The imminent perill and daunger those are in, which are mounted to the toppe of some high thyng, or to the cliffe of some hygh and rocky moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, where they haue no other way to descend, but to fall, is much lyke to that of the famyliars of Princes. And therefore my lord, I woold wysh you woold procure you such faythfulll frends about you, that they hauyng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and care of your person, shoold always hold you by the gown for fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng. And not such as after they had let you fall, woold then lend you their hands to help you vp agayn.</p>
      <p n="6">6 All bee it the thyngs of the sowl shoold bee preferred beefore all others of thys worldly lyfe, yet neuerthelesse I wyll bee content, so that you haue as great care and consideration of your conscience, as you haue of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. All whych I was willyng to tell you (syr) to the end you may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderstand, that those that are in estimation with the prince, though they may benefit by tyme (in takyng their tyme) yet tyme dooth neuer benefyt by them at all.</p>
      <p n="7">7 You must euer doo good to your vttermost power, and neuer doo dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure to any, though it lye in your power, and that you haue iust cause. For the tears of the poore that are iniuryed, and the lamentable cryes and playnts of the oppressed, may possibly one day ascend to the presence of the tribunall seat (where god shall sitt in his maiesty) demaundyng iustyce and vengeaunce agaynst you: and also come to the ears of the prince, to cause you to bee hated of hym for euer.</p>
      <p n="8">8 Touching the fauor you will shew to any, eyther in offices, or other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits you will beestow on any man, take heede you always rather preferre honest and true Christians, then your own neere kynsmen or frends.</p>
      <p>For a man may lawfully make his frend partaker of hys goods, but not of hys conscience.</p>
      <p n="9">9 In your councels you geeue, in any wise bee not to much affectioned in them, neither scorne with those that contrary your oppinion. Bee not proud and seuere to those you doo commaund, neither doo any thing wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good aduyce and consideration. For al beeit in princes courts euery mā dooth admire and beehold the excellency and woorthynes of the person, yet are those always that are most in fauor of the Prince, more noted, regarded, and sooner accused then others.</p>
      <p n="10">10 Yf you wyll not erre in the counseils you shall geeue, nor fayl in those things you enterprise: Imbrace those that tell you the truth, and reiect and hate those, whom you know to bee flatterers and dissemblers. For you shoold rather desire to bee admonished of the thing present, then counselled after the dammage receiued.</p>
      <p>Although wee suppose assuredly all these things aboue written are not lykely to happen, nor come euen so to passe as I haue spoken: yet may yt please you (syr) to remember they are not therefore impossible. For spite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fortune permitteth oft tymes, that the sayles which the lyghtnyng and
<pb n="104" facs="287"/>
boysterous tempests could not break and teare in peeces, are afterwards vpō a soden, (euen in the sweete of the mornings sleepe, eche man taking his rest, leauing the seas beefore in quiet calme) all to shyuered, and torn a sunder. Hee that meaneth to geeue another a blow allso, the more hee draweth back hys arme, with greater force hee striketh. And euen so (neyther more nor lesse) sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fortune with those, on whom for a time shee smyleth. For the lenger a mā remaineth in her loue and fauor, the more cruel and bitter shee sheweth her self to him in the end. And therefore I woold aduise euery wise and sage per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, that when fortune seemes best of all to fauor him, and to doo most for him, that then hee should stand most in feare of her, and least trust her deceipts. Therefore (Sir) make no small accompt of this my booke, litle though it bee. For you know, that doubtles (as experience teacheth vs) of greater price &amp; value is a litle spark of a Dyamond, then a greater ballasse. It forceth lyttle that the booke bee of small or great volume, syth thexcellency thereof consys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not in the number of leaues, more or lesse, but only in the good and graue sentences that are amplie writen therein. For euery author that writeth, to make his booke of great price and shew, ought to bee brief in his woords, and sweete and pleasant in his matter hee treateth of, the better to satisfy y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mynd of the reader, and also not to bee tedious to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hearer. And (Sir) I speak not without cause that you shoold not a lytle esteeme this small treatise of myne, since you are most assured, that with tyme al your things shall haue end, your frends shall leaue you, your goods shalbee deuided, your self shall dye, your fauor and credyt shall dimynish, and those that succeede you, shal forget you, you not knowing to whom your goods and patrimony shall come: and aboue all, you shall not know what condicions your heires and children shallbee of. But for this I write in your Royall history and Chronicle of your lawdable vertues and perfections, and for that also I serue you as I doo with this my present woork, the memory of you shall remain eternized to your Successors for euer. <hi>Chilo</hi> the philosopher beeyng demaunded whether there were any thing in the world that fortune had not power to bring to nought, aunswered in this sort. Two things onely there are, which neyther tyme can consume, nor fortune distroy, and that is: the renowne of man wrytten in bookes, and the veritie that is hidden. For allthough troth for a tyme lye interred, yet yt resurgeth agayn and receyueth lyfe, appearing manyfestly to all. And euen so in like case the vertues wee fynd wryten of a man, doo cause vs at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to haue him in as great veneration, as those had in his tyme that best knew him. Read therefore (Sir) at times I beeseech you these wrytyngs of myne, allbeeit I feare mee you can scant borrow a moment of tyme with ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure once to looke vppon yt, beeing (as I know you are) allways occupyed in affaires of great importaunce, wherein mee thinketh you shoold not so sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge your self, but that you myght for your commodyty and recreacion of your spirits reserue some pryuat howers to your self. For sage and wise men should not so burden them selues with care of others toyle, that they should not spend one hower of the day at the least (at their pleasure) to looke on their estate and condicion. As recoūteth <hi>Suctonius Tranquillus</hi> of <hi>Iulius Cesar</hi> who notwythstandyng his quotydian warres hee had, neuer let slypt one day but that hee read, or wrote some thing. So that beeing in his Pauyllyon in the
<pb facs="288"/>
camp in the one hand hee held his launce to assault his enemy, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the penne to wryte with all, with which hee wrote his woorthy comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries. The reasonable man therefore calling to mynd the streight account y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hee must render of him self and of the time hee hath lost, shal always bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re careful that hee lose not his time, then hee shalbee to keepe his treasure. For the wel imployed time is a mean &amp; help to his saluation: &amp; the euil gotten good a cause of his eternal dānation. More ouer yet, what toyle and trauayl is it to the body of the man, &amp; how much more perill to the liuing soule, when hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumeth his hole days and life in wordly broile: and yet seely man hee can not absent him self from that vile drudgery, till death dooth sommon him to yeeld vp his accoūt of his lief and dooings. And now to conclude my prologue, I say this booke is deuided into two parts: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to weete: in the first tenne chapters is declared how the new come courtier shall beehaue him self in the princes court to winne fauor &amp; credit with the prince: &amp; the surplus of the woork trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, when hee hath atcheeued to his princes fauor, &amp; acquired the credyt of a worthy courtier: how hee shal then continew the same to his further aduaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement. And I doubt no whit, but that my lords &amp; gentlemen of court wil ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke pleasure to read it, and namely such as are princes familiars and beeloued of court shall mostly reap profyt thereby, putting the good lessons &amp; aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they fynd heretofore writen, in execucion. For, to the yong courtiers it sheweth them what they haue to doo: &amp; putteth in remembraunce also the old fauored courtier (lyuing in his princes grace) of that hee hath to bee circūspect of. And fynally I conclude (sir) that of al the treasors, riches, gyfts, fauors, prosperities, pleasures, seruices, greatnes, &amp; power, that you haue &amp; possesse in this mortal &amp; transitory life, &amp; by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faith of a christian I sweare vnto you also y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you shal cary no more with you, then y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> onely time w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> you haue wel &amp; vertuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly emploied, during this your pilgrimage.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>¶The Argument of the booke entituled the fauored courtier, wheare the author sheweth the intent of his woork, exhorting all men to read and study good and vertuous bookes vtterly reiectyng fables and vayn trifflyng stories of small doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine &amp; erudicion.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>AVlus Gelius</hi> in his booke <hi>De noctibus atticis</hi> sayeth, that after the death of the great poet <hi>Homer,</hi> seuen famous Cyties of Greece were in great controuersy one with the other, ech one of them affirmyng, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the bones of the sayd poet was theirs, and onely apperteined to them, all seuen takyng their othes, that hee was not onely born, but also norished and brought vp in euery one of them. And this they did, supposing that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had so great honor in any thing, but that this was farre greater, to haue educated so excellent and rare a man as hee was. <hi>Euripides</hi> also the philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, born and brought vp in <hi>Athens,</hi> trauayling in the realme of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> was sodeynly striken with death, which wofull newes no sooner came to the <hi>Athenians</hi> ears, (declared for a trouth) but with al expedicion they depeached an honorable imbasy, onely to intreat the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> to bee contented to deliuer them the bones of the sayd philosopher, protesting to them, that if they woold franckly graunt them, they woold regratify that pleasure done them:
<pb n="105" facs="288"/>
and if they woold deny them, they should assure them selues they woold come to demaund them with sweord in hand. Kyng <hi>Demetrius</hi> held <hi>Rhodes</hi> beesy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged long tyme (which at length hee wanne by force of armes) and the <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> beeing so stubborn that they would not yeeld by composition, nor trust to his princely clemency, hee commaunded to strike of all the <hi>Rhodians</hi> heads, and to rase the cyty to the hard foundacions. But when hee was let vnderstand that there was euen then in the cyty <hi>Prothogenes,</hi> a phyloso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher and paynter, doutyng least in executyng others, hee allso vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen myght bee put to the sweord, reuoked his cruel sentence, and gaue strai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght commaundement foorthwith they should cease to spoyle and deface the town further, and also to stay the slaughter of the rest of the <hi>Rhodiens.</hi> The diuine <hi>Plato</hi> beeing in <hi>Athens,</hi> aduertised that in the cyty of <hi>Damasco</hi> (in the realme of <hi>Palestine</hi>) were certayn bookes of great antiquity, whych a philosopher born of that countrey left beehynd hym there: when hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode it to bee true, went thither immediatly, led with the great desyre hee had to see them, and purposely (if they dyd lyke him) afterwards to buy them. And when hee saw that neyther at his sute, nor at the requests of others hee could obtein them, but that hee must buy them at a great price, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> went and sold all his patrimony to recouer them: and his own not beeing sufficient, hee was fayn to borrow vpon interest of the cōmon treasory to help him. So that notwithstanding hee was so profound and rare a philosopher (as in deede hee was) yet hee woold sell all that small substaunce hee had, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to see (as hee thought) some prety new thing more of philosophy. As <hi>Ptholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus Philadelphus</hi> kyng of <hi>Egipt,</hi> not contented to bee so wise in al sciences as hee was, nor to haue in his library .8000. bookes as hee had, nor to study at the least .4. howers in the day, nor ordinaryly to dispute at his meales wyth philosophers, sent neuertheles an imbassage of noble men to the Ebrews, to desire them they woold bee contented to send him some of the best lerned and wisest men among them, to teach him the Ebrew tongue, &amp; to read to him the bookes of their laws. When <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was born, his father kyng <hi>Phillippe</hi> wrote a notable letter immediatly to <hi>Aristottle,</hi> &amp; among other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hee wrote there were these. I doo thee to weete, O greatest philosopher <hi>Aristotle</hi> (if thou knowst it not) that <hi>Olimpias</hi> my wife is brought to bed of a sonne, for w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> incessantly I geeue the gods immortal thanks: not so much y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I haue a sonne, as for that they haue geeuen him mee in thy tyme. For I am assured hee shal profit more with the doctrine thou shalt teach him: thē hee shal preuail with the kingdoms I shal leaue him after mee. Now by the examples aboue recited, and by many more we coold alledge, wee may easly consider, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> what reuerence and honor the auncient kyngs vsed the learned and vertuous men of their tyme. And wee may also more playnly see it, syth then they held in greater price and estimacion the bones of a dead philosopher, then they doo now the doctrine of the best learned of our time. And not without iust occasiō dyd these famous &amp; heroycal princes ioy, to haue at home in their houses, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode with them in the feeld, such wise &amp; learned men whilst they liued, &amp; after they were dead to honor their bones and carcases: and in dooing this they er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not a iot. For who so euer accompanieth continually w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> graue &amp; wise men, enioyeth this benefit and priuiledge beefore others, that hee shall neuer bee
<pb facs="289"/>
counted ignorant of any. Therefore continuing still our fyrst purpose, let vs say, that who so euer will professe the company of sober and wise men, yt can not otherwise bee, but hee must maruelously profyt by their comapny. For beeing in their company they will put all vain and dishonest thoughts from him, they will teach him to subdue and resyst all sodein passions and motions moued of choller: by them they shal winne good frends, and learn also neuer to bee troublesome or enemy to any, they will make him forsake all sinne and vice, declaring to him what good woorks hee shall follow, and what hee shal most fly and eschew: they will let him vnderstand how hee shall humble and beehaue him self in prosperity, and they will also comfort him in his aduersity, to keepe him from all sorow and dispayre. For though a man bee neuer so ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refull and circumspect, yet hath hee always neede of the councell of an other in his affaires, if therefore such person haue not about him good vertuous, &amp; sage men, how can it otherways bee but that hee must stumble oft, and fall down right on his face, hauing no man to ayd or help him. <hi>Paulus Diaconus</hi> sayeth, that albeeit the <hi>Affricans</hi> were wylde and brutish people, yet had they withstandyng a law amongst them, that the senators amongst them coold choose no other senator, if at the electiō there were not present a philosopher. So it happened one day amongst the rest, that of many philosophers they had in <hi>Carthage,</hi> amongst them was one named <hi>Apolonius:</hi> Who ruled for the space of three score and two years all their senat with great quyet, and to the contentacion of all the senators: which to shew them selues thankfull to him, erected in the market place so many images of him, as he had gouerned their common weale years, to the end the fame and memory of hym should bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall: and yet they dyd dedycate to their famous <hi>Anniball</hi> but onely one i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and to this philosopher they set vp aboue three score. <hi>Alexander</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great when hee was most bent to bluddy warres, went to see and speak with <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> the philosoper, offring him great presents, and discoursyng with him of dyuers matters. So that wee may iustly say, this good prince of hym self tooke payns to seek out wise men to accompany him, electing by others choise and aduise all such, as hee made his captayns to serue him in the warres: It is manyfest to all, that <hi>Dionisius</hi> the <hi>Siracusan</hi> was the greatest tyraunt in the world, and yet notwithstanding his tyranny, it is a wonder to see the sage and wise men hee had continually in his court with him: &amp; that, that makes vs yet more to wonder of him is, that hee had them not about him to serue him, or to profyt one iot by their doctrine and councell: but onely for his honor, and their profyt, which enforceth mee to say, concurring with this example, that syth tyrants dyd glory to haue about them wise, &amp; woorthy men: much more shoold those reioyce, that in their woorks and deedes are noble, and free harted. And this they ought to doo, not onely to bee honored with them openly, but also to bee holpen with their doctrine &amp; councels secretly. And if to some this shoold seeme a hard thyng to follow, wee will say: that woorthy men not beeing of ability and power to mainteyn such wise men, ought yet at least to vse to read at tymes, good and vertuous bookes. For by readyng of bookes, they reap infynyt profyt, as for example, by readyng as I say these good authors, the desire is satisfyed, their iugement is quickned idlenes is put away, the hart is disburdened, the time is well imployed, and they lead their lyfe vertuously, not
<pb n="106" facs="289"/>
beeing bound to render account of so many faults, as in that tyme they my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght haue committed. And to conclude, it is so good an exercise, as it gee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth good examples to the neyghbor, profyt to hym self, and health to the soule. Wee see by experience, after a man taketh vppon hym once the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of holy scriptures, and that hee frameth hym self to bee a diuyne, hee will neuer wyllyngly thencefoorth deale in other studies, and all beecause hee will not forgoe the great pleasure hee receyueth to read those holly say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yngs. And that causeth, that wee see so many learned and wise men (for the more part) subiect to dyuers diseases, and full of melancoly humors. For so sweete is the delight they take in their bookes, that they forget and leaue al other bodely pleasure: And therefore <hi>Plutarke</hi> wryteth, that certayn Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers beeing one day met at the lodgyng of <hi>Plato</hi> to see hym, and demaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng him what exercise hee had at that tyme: <hi>Plato</hi> aunswered them thus. Truely my brethern I let you know, that euen now my onely exercise was to see what the great poet <hi>Homer</hi> sayd. And this hee told them, beecause they tooke hym euen then readyng of some of <hi>Homers</hi> bookes, and to say tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hys aunswer was such, as they shoold all looke for of hym. For to read a good booke in effect is nothyng els, but to heare a wyse man speak. And yf this our iudgement and aduise seeme good vnto you, wee would yet say more, that you shoold profyt more to read one of these bookes, then yow should to heare speak, or to haue conference wyth the autor hym self that made yt. For it is wythout doubt, that all wryters haue more care and res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in that their penne dooth wryte, then they haue in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> their tongue dooth vtter. And to the end you should not thynk wee can not proue that trew that wee haue spoken, I doo you to wytte, that euery autor that wyll wryte, to publysh hys dooyng in prynt, to lay yt to the shew and iudgement of the world, and that desyreth thereby to acquire honor and fame, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternyse the memory of hym, turneth many bookes, conferreth wyth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyse and learned men, addycteth hym self wholly to hys booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth to vnderstand well, oft refuseth sleepe, meat and drynk, quyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kneth hys spyrits, dooyng that hee putteth in wrytyng exactly with long aduise, and consideracion: whych hee dooth not, when hee dooth but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly speak and vtter them, though oft in deede (by reason of his great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) in speach vnwares there falleth out of hys mouth, many goodly and wise sentences. And therefore god hath geeuen hym a goodly gift that can read, and hym much more that hath a desyre to studdy, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng how to choose the good bookes from the euill. For to say the troth, there is not in this world any state or exercyse more honorable, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable then the study of good bookes. And wee are much bound to those that read, more to those that study, and much more to those that wryte any thing, but mostly doubtles to those that make &amp; compile goodly bookes, &amp; those of great and hye doctrine. For there are many vayn and fond bookes, that rather deserue to bee throwen in the fyer, then once to bee read or looked on. For they doo not onely shew vs the way to mock thē, but also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mean to offend vs, to see them occupy their brayns &amp; best wyttes they haue
<pb facs="290"/>
to write foolish and vayn thyngs, of no good subiect or erudicion. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> that is woorst of al yet, they are occasion that dyuers others spend asmuch tyme in readyng their iests, and mockries, as they woold otherwise haue imployed in doctrine, of great profyt and edifying, the which to excuse and defend their error, say they dyd not write them for men to take profyt thereby, but onely to delight and please the readers, to passe the time away meryly. Whom wee may rightly aunswer thus: that the readyng of yll and vayn bookes can not bee called a pastime, but aptly a very losse of tyme. And therefore <hi>Aulus Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the fyfteenth of his booke writeth, that after the romayns vnderstoode the orators and poets of Rome did geeue them selues to write, vain, voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and dishonest bookes, causing enterludes, and poetical commedies to bee played, they dyd not onely banysh them from Rome, but also out of al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parts of Italy. For yt hee seemed not the Romayn grauyty, neither was it decent for the weale publyk, to suffer such naughty bookes among them, and much lesse to beare with vitious and lasciuious gouernors. And if the Romain pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyms left vs this for example, how much more ought wee that are christians to continew and follow yt, synce they had no other bookes to read saue onely histories, and wee now a days haue both histories &amp; holy scriptures to read which were graunted vs by the church, to the end by the one wee myght take some honest pleasure and recreation, and with the other procure the health of our soules. O how farre is the cōmon wealth now a days dygressed from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wee write and counsel, sence wee see playnly, that men occupy them selues at this present, in readyng a number of bookes, the which onely to name I am ashamed. And therefore sayd <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> in his forteenth booke, that there was a certayn phylosopher wrote a booke of hye and eloquent stile, but the subiect very hard &amp; dyffuse to vnderstand, the which <hi>Socrates</hi> and other phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers hearyng of, commaundid immediatly the booke to bee burned, and the author to bee banyshed, by whych example wee may well perceyue, that in that so perfyt and reformed vniuersyty they woold not onely suffer any lasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious or vitious booke, but also they woold not beare with those, that were to hawty and vayn glorious in their stiles, and whose matter were not profyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and benefyciall to the publyk weale. That man therefore that walloweth in idlenes lappe, and that vouchsafeth not to spend one hower of the day to read a graue sentence of some good booke, wee may rather deseruedly call hym a brute beast, then a reasonable creature. For euery wise man ought to glory more of the knowledge hee hath, then of the aboundaunce of goods hee possesseth. And it can not bee denied but that those which read vertuous boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, are euer had in better fauor and estimacion then others. For they learn to speak, they passe the tyme without trouble, they know many pleasaunt thyngs which they after tel to other, they haue audacyty to reprooue others: &amp; euery man delyteth to heare them, and in what place or company so euer they come, they are always reuerenced &amp; honored aboue others: euery man desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth their knowledge and acquaintaunce, and are glad to ask them councel. And that, that is yet of greater credyt to them is, that they are not few in nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that trusteth them with their body and goods. And moreouer I say, that the wise and learned man which professeth study, shall know very well how
<pb n="107" facs="290"/>
to councel his frend, and to comfort him self at all tymes when neede dooth serue, which the foolysh ignoraunt person can not doo, for hee can not onely tell how to comfort the afflycted in aduersity, but also hee can not help hym self in hys own proper affaires, nor take councell of him self what is best to doo. But retorning agayn to our purpose, wee say, beecause wee woold not bee reprooued of that wee rebuke others of, wee haue beene very cyrcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and aduised, and taken great care and payns in our studdy, that al our bookes and workes wee haue publyshed and compiled, should bee so exactly doone, that the readers might not fynd any ill doctrine, nor also any thyng woorthy reproofe. For the vnhonest bookes made by lasciuious persons doo geeue (deseruedly) euident token to the readers to suspect the autors, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the iudgements of those that geeue attentyue eare vnto them. And the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore I councell, and admonish him that will enterprise and take vppon him to bee a writer, and setter foorth of bookes, that hee bee wise in his matter hee sheweth, and compēdious in the woords hee writeth: and not to bee ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to dyuers wryters, whose woorks are of such a frase and style, as wee shal read many times to the midst of the booke, ere wee fynd one good and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sentence, so that a man may say, that all the frute those reap for their pain, watches, and trauayl, is no other, but onely a meere toy and mockry, they beeing derided of euery man that seeth their woorks. That autor that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaketh to write, and afterwards prostrateth to common iudgement the thing hee wryteth, may bee assured that hee setteth hys wittes to great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyl and study, and hasardeth his honor to present peryll. For the iudgement of men beeing varyable, and dyuers (as they are in deede) many times they doo meddle and enter into iudgement of those things, whereof they are not onely not capable to vnderstand, but also lesse skylfull to read them. Now in the booke wee haue set out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dyal of prynces, &amp; in that other wee haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated of the life of the romayn emperors, and in this wee haue now set foorth of the fauored courtier, the readers may bee assured they shal fynd in thē good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and graue sentences, whereby they may greatly profyt, and they shall not read any woords superfluous, to comber or weery them at all. For wee dyd not once licence our penne to dare to write any woord, that was not first wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in trew balance, and meat by iust measure. And God can testify wyth vs, that without doubt wee haue had more payn to bee brief in the woords of our bookes wee haue hytherto made, then wee haue had to gather out the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention and graue sentences thereof. For to speak good woords, and to haue good matter and wise purposes, is the poperty of one that naturally is modest, and graue in his actions: but to write breefely, hee must haue a deepe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. When at the font of the printers foorme wee first baptised the booke of <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> wee there intituled it the Dyal of princes, and this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that wee haue now made &amp; added to yt, wee will call yt (for more breefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) the fauored courtier: which portendeth the whetstone and instructyon of a courtier. For if they will vouchsafe to read, and take the frutefull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells they fynd written herein, they may assure them selues they shall awake out of the vanyties they haue long slept in, and shall also open their eyes, to see the better that thyng wherein they lyue so long deceyued. And allbeeyt
<pb facs="291"/>
in deede this present woork sheweth to you but a few contriued lines, yet god him self dooth know, the payns wee haue taken herein hath been exceedyng great, and this for two causes: thone for that the matter is very straunge and dyuers from others, thother, to thynk that assuredly it should bee hated of those, that want the taste of good discypline. And therefore wee haue taken great care, it should come out of our hands well refoormed, and corrected: to the end that courtiers might fynd out many sentences in yt profitable for thē, and not one woord to trouble them. Those noble men or gentlemen that wil from hencefoorth haue their children brought vp in princes courts, shall fynd in this kooke all things they shall neede to prouide them of, those also that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue been long courtiers, shall fynd all that they ought to doo in court, And such also as are the best fauored of princes, and cary greatest reputacion of honor with them, shall fynd likewise excellent good councells, by meane whereof they may always maynteyn, and continue them selues, in the cheefest great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their credit and fauor: so that it may wel bee called a mitridatical elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary, recuering and healing all malignaunt opilations. Of all the bookes I haue hitherto compyled, I haue dedicated some of them to the Imperiall maiesty, &amp; others to those of best fauor &amp; credit w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> him: where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> readers may see, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I rather glory to bee a satire, then a flatterer, for that in al my sentences they can not fynd one cloked woord, to enlarge and imbetter my credit and estate. But to the contrary, they may read an infynyt number of others, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I doo exhort them to gouern their persons discreetly and honorably, and to amend their lyues thencefoorth. Whan I imprinted the Dyal of princes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> and brought them to lyght, I wanted not back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters and detracters that beeganne foorthwith to teare mee in peeces, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shal I want at this present (as I beeleeue) such as will not spare wyth venomus tongues to poyson my woork. But lyke as then I litle wayd their sclaunderous speaches of mee, euen so much lesse doo I now force what they can say against mee, beeing assured they shal fynd in the end, they haue yl spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of mee, and my poore woorks, proceedyng from them rather of a certayn enuy that gnaweth their hart, then of any default they fynd in my doctryne: comforting my self yet in the assuraunce I haue, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al their spight shal one day haue an end, and my woorks shal euer bee found good and perdurable.</p>
      <trailer>Here endeth the Argument.</trailer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>