<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A FAMILIAR Admonition to the Christi∣an Reader, touching the most comfortable exercise of Diuine Prayer.</title>
           <author>Norden, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120793_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18628</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120793</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A FAMILIAR Admonition to the Christi∣an Reader, touching the most comfortable exercise of Diuine Prayer.</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pensiue soules delight. Or, The deuout mans helpe. Consisting of motiues, meditations and prayers, for all persons and purposes, vpon what occasion so euer, either priuate or publike. By Iohn Norden</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Busby, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 339, 9 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>A FAMILIAR Admonition to the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Reader, touching the most comfortable exercise of</hi> Diuine Prayer.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Seeke the Lord while hee may bee found, call vpon him while he is neere.</q>
      <bibl>Esai. 55. 6.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three things, especially to be considered in the true seeking &amp; calling vpon God: The first is <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> before we call vpon God in prayer: The second is <hi>Attention</hi> in Prayer: The third and last is, <hi>Thanksgiuing</hi> after prayer.</p>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Preparation to Prayer.</head>
      <p>As touching the first, namely, <hi>preparation,</hi> we may obserue and
<pb facs="15"/>
vse a kinde of imitation of men, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned to comunicate with <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Princes,</hi> who are obserued to to preponder with themselues, first how to shape their behauiour, and externall <hi>gesture:</hi> Secondly, how to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> frame their speech to gaine <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> of him, to whom they speake: and how to auoide the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of <hi>indiscretion,</hi> in the deliuery of what they affirme, or defend. If such curiositie and carefulnesse be necessarily obserued, in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with men, whose breath is in their nosthrels: how much more obseruant and carefull ought we to bee, when wee addresse our selues to speake vnto the <hi>Maiestie of the immortal God?</hi> To intrude abruptly into the presence of this great God, &amp; vnaduisedly to speake vnto him, becommeth not a petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, but bewrayeth an vnsan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and an vnprepared heart; rather tempting and dishonouring,
<pb facs="15"/>
then glorifying of the name of God. And therefore, before we presume to present our petitions to God, in hope to be heard; we must prepare ourselues, not in our outwardge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, onely in eloquence of words, and Pharisaicall outward holines: But in rightly ordering, and dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the affections of the inner man; which, if they be set on carnall, or earthly <hi>vanities,</hi> if our hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in <hi>the fruits of the flesh,</hi> and <hi>the vnprofitable works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse:</hi> (though our words be neuer so good of themselues) we may feare the reward of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> his wife, who brought a <hi>part of their substance</hi> (hypocritically conceiling the rest) and layd that part at the <hi>Apostles</hi> feet. So, if we come vnto God, giuing him good words, keeping backe our hearts, to serue our owne carnall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane appetites: Shall we thinke that God will be content with the
<pb facs="16"/>
leaues of our good words, when we giue the fruits of our hearts to the world? will God take such <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> by the hand? we must know, that vnlesse we can truely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feinedly cast off our <hi>carnall thoughts, corrupt desires,</hi> and <hi>sinnefull affections,</hi> it cannot be that God, who <hi>loueth holinesse and truth, in the inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> can looke vpon vs, as vpon his <hi>children,</hi> who speake vnto him, as to a <hi>father,</hi> with counterfeit words, proceeding from vnsanctified hearts. When wee come therefore vnto God in prayer, <hi>we must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from all iniquitie,</hi> knowing that <hi>he heareth not sinners,</hi> such as the <hi>promises</hi> of God cannot win to obedience; nor his threates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force to <hi>forsake their sinnes;</hi> who yet will aduenture to rush rashly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the presence of God, in a formall kind of praying with the lips, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any premeditation preparation,
<pb facs="16"/>
or reformation of the heart, at all. These offer <hi>wordes</hi> for <hi>deedes: Leaues</hi> for <hi>Fruit: Wolues</hi> for <hi>Lambes;</hi> and all maner, halt, lame, blinde, and blemished <hi>sacrifices,</hi> and yet would seeme holy: And so, instead of a blessing, procure a curse vnto themselues for their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie. Wee must consider that <hi>God is a iealous God, &amp; holdeth none guiltlesse, that taketh his name in vaine,</hi> as they manifestly doe, <hi>that come neere him with their lips, when their hearts are farre from him.</hi> It is a kind of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall adultery, outwardly to seeme wholy to be gods, and yet inwardly to be meere worldlings. Before we open our mouthes therefore, to God, we must cast out of the Temple of God, (which is our heart) <hi>all buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and sellers,</hi> as <hi>Christ</hi> did out of <hi>the Temple of Ierusalem:</hi> for as long as our hearts doe harbour the desires of worldly profits, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="17"/>
pleasures, aboue the sincere seruice of God, our heart, the Temple of the liuing God, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a den of theeues, that steales away all our godly affections, to settle them on <hi>Belial.</hi> Let vs looke vnto <hi>the man Christ Iesus cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> by whose blood wee are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, by whose mediation wee are sure to haue our prayers heard of God, and granted; especially, if for our further and more perfect preparation, we can truely obserue the rule of <hi>Christ,</hi> to <hi>forgiue our enemies,</hi> knowing that <hi>if we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue not our brother that offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs, God will not forgiue vs, that farre more grieuously offend him.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Christ</hi> counselleth vs, that <hi>if we bring our sacrifice to the Altar,</hi> namely, if we intend to pray; and <hi>there remember that a brother hath ought against vs, we ought to leaue our offering before the</hi>
         <pb facs="17"/>
         <hi>Altar,</hi> that is, forbear for the time to pray, yet to continue our holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to pray; and <hi>to goe first, and bee reconciled to our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>then to come to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our gift;</hi> namely, our prayers, freely vnto <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Christ:</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we be vnburthened of all <hi>ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor, malice, enuie hatred,</hi> and all other <hi>prophane desires;</hi> it is not only not auaileable, but lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that so many will (as doe) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to come before God, with hearts so fearefully fraught with these vnholy affections; and stag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger no more to presse into Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, nay, not so much, as some that come vnto God, with most prepared, peacefull, and most san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified consciences. Let such <hi>cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the bond woman with her sonne;</hi> namely, <hi>the old man, the works and lusts of the flesh:</hi> and giue entertainment vnto the <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, and her sonne, the new</hi>
         <pb facs="18"/>
         <hi>man, which, after God is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto righteousnes, and true holines:</hi> And so recommend our prayers vnto God, the <hi>obiect</hi> of our prayers, in <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of our prayers, by <hi>the holy Ghost,</hi> the Author of all holy prayers.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Attention in Prayer.</head>
      <p>Being thus prepared, let vs ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to yeeld due and true <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in our prayers, that is, to giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eed to what we pray, to whom we pray, for what we pray, and with what zeale we pray: which are the truest tokens, and greatest argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that our prayers are liuely, powerfull, effectuall, and of faith; which properties can neuer be in lip-labour: for there cannot be a more apparent discouery of a rancke Hypocrite, then to make outward showes of <hi>Deuotion,</hi> with the gesture and lippes, and yet the heart to be busied, in the cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="18"/>
of idle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>arthly, and prophane things. And nothing more disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth an idle heart outwardly, then the wandering of the eye in the time of diuine prayer: for it is probable, and often found by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that the eye withdraweth the heart: and if the eye be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, the prayer hath not, nor can haue the due <hi>attention</hi> of the heart: yet it doth not follow, that although the eye bee fixed on any certaine obiect, or be shut, that therefore the heart is rightly set on God, for oftentimes the eye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the heart, the cogitation of the heart making the eye to forget it obiect: as when the heart is wandring in the fields of corne, viewing the herdes of cattle, and flockes of sheepe, when it is in the ware-house, in the shoppe, in the chest, minding bands &amp; payments, ouercome with pride, plotting reuenge, oppressed with feare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sotted
<pb facs="19"/>
with pleasure, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tangled with cares, or otherwise peruerted by any prophane and vngodly cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Prayers made witls such an extra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>agant heart, be they in words neuer so holy, they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto vs as sin: for shall wee thinke, that God will heare our prayers, to our profit or comfort, when the thoughts of our hearts, in the meane time, dishonor him? Many pray in their owne familiar language, and yet consider no more what they speake (for want of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention) then if they spake in an vnknowne tongue: and yet such men will hold themselues very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout, and to haue power in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to pray when they list: as if true prayer wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of that facilitie and ease, to vtter, as is an idle tale, and as it seemes by <hi>beggers,</hi> that tumble out <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> with one breath at a doore, and yet minde nothing but their almes.
<pb facs="19"/>
Such men are to be pitied, and to be wished better to aduise them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, before they attempt this seruice of God most holy; for <hi>Prayer</hi> is not an easie worke, it is of a deeper straine then a tale, that is but from the tongue to the teeth, from the teeth to the lips, and so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ayre. <hi>True prayer</hi> is cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and of that force and efficacie, as it constraineth the heart to <hi>sighes, groanes</hi> and <hi>teares,</hi> with such <hi>inward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>uencie</hi> of holy zeale, as tenters the heart with such internall gripes, as may bee truly said, <hi>the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ting of the hart.</hi> And the more we feele our hearts thus inwardly sharply touched: so much the more comfort it yeeldeth to the soule of the faithfull petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yea such, and so great conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as he that feeles it, cannot expresse it with his tongue, be he neuer so eloquent; neither can any conceiue or apprehend the sweetnes
<pb facs="20"/>
of it, that is not exercised and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in the same; for nature apprehendeth it not. <hi>No man can say that Iesus is Christ, but by the holy Ghost:</hi> and, none can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> but by <hi>the Spirit of God. Flesh and bloud</hi> cannot as much as desire <hi>spirituall things,</hi> spiritually; for <hi>spirituall things are to be compared with spirituall things,</hi> and <hi>spirituall gifts</hi> are obtained by <hi>spirituall meanes:</hi> And therefore are <hi>words</hi> without the <hi>spirit,</hi> as naked and bare incense without fire: but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inkindled in the heart, and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the holy spirit of God, who is promised to assist our spirits, they are as a <hi>liuely and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sacrifice to God,</hi> working so powerfully with him, through <hi>Christs</hi> medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tion, as they neuer returne empty of what soeuer bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing we desire. Prayer can neuer be effectuall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> there be s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me
<pb facs="20"/>
certaine spirituall obiect of the mind, to moue the attention of the heart, which obiect is God: and we must consider, that when we pray vnto him, or yeeld him any other worship, that we are not to conceiue him, in the forme of any earthly or heauenly, bodily, or spirituall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatsoeuer: for <hi>in that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, not to conceiue him, is a degree of cōceiuing him a right, according to Master</hi> Perkins. God must be conceiued of vs in our prayers, as subsisting in the whole three <hi>persons, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost. The vnitie in Trinitie, and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>initie in vnitie</hi> is to be worshipped, retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in mind, the distinction, and order of all the three <hi>persons,</hi> without seuering or sundring them: for, as they are conioyned in nature; so are they to be conioyned in worship. And therefore, he that prayeth vnto God <hi>the Father,</hi> for
<pb facs="21"/>
the forgiuenesse of his sinnes, must aske it of him, for the merits of <hi>the Sonne,</hi> and by the assurance of <hi>the holy Ghost:</hi> and he that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the remission of sinnes to <hi>God the Sonne,</hi> must pray that he would procure <hi>the Father,</hi> to graunt him pardon, and to assure it by <hi>his Spirit.</hi> He also that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the same to God the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> must pray that he would assure vnto him the remission of his sinnes, from <hi>the Father,</hi> for and by the merits of <hi>his Sonne.</hi> Thus must we apprehend the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> in our prayers: so shall we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide that idolatrous conceiuing of him, imbraced of some, who cannot pray, vnlesse they haue the figure of a humane creature, to represent vnto their bodily eyes, the shape of God <hi>the Father,</hi> in likenesse of an olde man, and a <hi>crucifixe,</hi> figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Christ,</hi> suffring on the Crosse, and the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> by a Doue,
<pb facs="21"/>
whose worship cannot bee reputed spirituall, but carnall, and their prayers, not heauenly, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane. Prayer is a spirituall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proper onely to the <hi>children of God, who are Saints by calling, sanctified in Christ:</hi> And they, and none other truely <hi>call vpon the name of the Lord Iesus:</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane persons pray not, though they seeme to pray. But most happie is that man, that commeth vnto God, <hi>Father, Sonne, and holy Ghost,</hi> truely prepared, and duely atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue; he may boldly aske, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently assure himselfe, to receiue <hi>grace for grace,</hi> and all <hi>blessings spirituall,</hi> without limitation, and all <hi>benefits corporall</hi> needfull. If▪ our prayers bee made in vs, by him, who hath promised, and hath power to giue what we aske, <hi>shall wee thinke hee will faile to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme?</hi> The <hi>hope of hypocrites</hi> in deed <hi>shall perish,</hi> and their
<pb facs="22"/>
         <hi>prayers</hi> vanish as the smoake: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they wait vpon <hi>lying vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and desire <hi>carnall pleasures,</hi> and <hi>worldly profits.</hi> But <hi>the Lord will surely fulfill the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of them that feare him,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their prayers tend to the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of <hi>Gods glory,</hi> to the good of the <hi>Church,</hi> to the remissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their owne sinnes, and other mens, to the obtaining of <hi>Gods graces,</hi> to the increase of the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of heauenly things,</hi> that they may <hi>walke before God, and be vpright,</hi> that they may doe <hi>the workes, and bring sorth the fruits of the spirit.</hi> These are the prayers that are the <hi>PENSIVE SOVLES DELIGHT.</hi> These are the <hi>prayers</hi> that wound the <hi>Serpent,</hi> &amp; that please God, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>peace</hi> to the <hi>conscience af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</hi> But, (which is to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented) all men are dull by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And <hi>the very elect,</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb facs="22"/>
weakely disposed to pray. And therefore is euery godly man to vse all holy meanes, to inkindle their hearts, to the right perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this heauenly dutie: And nothing more preuaileth therein, then <hi>Meditation:</hi> whereunto wee are also very vnapt by nature, and know not how, nor vpon what ground to lay the foundation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: yet, if we can truly frame our hearts to a holy <hi>Meditation,</hi> wee shal find, that it is the very key, that openeth our <hi>dull hearts,</hi> lockt vp vnder <hi>griefe,</hi> vnder <hi>feare,</hi> vnder <hi>trouble,</hi> vnder <hi>persecutiō</hi> &amp; <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery;</hi> and sendeth forth by litle and litle, <hi>the fire of true zeale,</hi> which at length becommeth a <hi>great</hi> flame <hi>of preuailing prayers,</hi> which thing they easily find, that are conuersant in this sacred exercise of <hi>Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Prayer:</hi> who yet, many times finde themselues most dull, and most vnapt to pray, hauing yet
<pb facs="23"/>
an inward desire thereunto, which <hi>desire</hi> they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: but labouring a while in silence, speaking inwardly to God, in <hi>sighes</hi> and <hi>groanes,</hi> at length they speake effectually with their <hi>tongues.</hi> Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that all men need motiues to stirre them vp to prayer: let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man addresse himselfe to the word of God, or peruse some godly worke of religious men. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vocally he cannot reade, by reason of his naturall dulnes; yet, if his heart can be but conuersant, and duely attend the sence, as the eye obserues the letter, his minde by little and little shall mount it selfe from <hi>earth</hi> to <hi>heauen,</hi> fixed on the <hi>Trinitie,</hi> whence shall arise such spirituall fruits of <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>feruencie of spirit,</hi> as shall fill the soule with more sweet consolation byinkindled praier, then the tongue can vtter. And to this end (gentle
<pb facs="23"/>
Reader) according to the small measure of mine vnderstanding, I haue prefixed before euery prayer, a <hi>Motiue</hi> or <hi>Meditation,</hi> touching the substance and matter of the Prayer following.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Thankesgiuing after Prayer.</head>
      <p>The third and last duty in this holy exercise is <hi>Thankesgiuing,</hi> which cannot but follow sanctified praiers, &amp; that with such ioy in <hi>the holy Ghost,</hi> as it cannot but break forth into most vnspeakeable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thākfulnes to God, who hath beene so graciously pleased, not only to forgiue our sins, but to helpe our infirmities by his <hi>holy spirit,</hi> by whom wee haue had accesse vnto the throne of grace, &amp; found such fauour with <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> as we haue obtained by the holy Ghost, both the will and the power to pray. Also we ought <hi>in all things to giue thankes to God,</hi> for euery <hi>blessing</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> wee receiue
<pb facs="24"/>
at his hands, according to the counsell and precept of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, who commands vs to <hi>giue thankes alwayes for all things vnto God, euen the Father, in the name of our Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> Ephes. 5. 20. Thus much touching the admonition.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Great Britaines happines, in regard of the free vse of the Gospell, in respect of other Nations.</head>
      <p>FInally, I thinke it not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent altogether, by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison, to consider of our happines, in being partakers of the free vse of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> in respect of the most vnhappie condition of many <hi>Nations,</hi> and infinite people, that either know not God at all, or knowing him, honour him not as God.</p>
      <p>The <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Testaments</hi>
         <pb facs="24"/>
haue beene freely opened vnto vs, neere threescore yeares without <hi>Persecution:</hi> and so it hath not been in any one Kingdom we reade of. Some <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>Free States,</hi> in their <hi>Iurisdictions,</hi> haue and doe in a sort, permit the <hi>Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell;</hi> but with the same, tolerate <hi>contrary religions</hi> &amp; professions. Where doth the freedome of the Gospell appeare, as in <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</hi> In what Kingdome is it so publikely receiued, so plentifully preached, and so freely professed, without danger or contradiction? We haue heard, and seene the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and the <hi>Massacres</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutiōs in other territories for the <hi>profession of the Gospell:</hi> and we all this while haue quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed that, for the profession wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many haue perished. May wee not therefore truely say with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
         <pb facs="25"/>
         <hi>The Lord hath not dealt so with euery Nation?</hi> Queene <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> restored <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> almost smothered by Queen <hi>MARIES</hi> persecution, which <hi>was maruailous in euery mans eyes.</hi> But which is more maruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, the same <hi>Religion</hi> is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by the meere loue and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, in raising vnto vs a <hi>Prince of most admired learning, of sincerest pietie:</hi> And that when it was vniuersally either expected, or suspected to haue bin vtterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished and rooted out, vpon the dissolution of the precedent <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernesse:</hi> we hauing then the free vse of the meanes of our <hi>Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> vnder God, by our <hi>worthiest of Kings,</hi> wee should shew our selues most vnworthie both of it and him, if we should not most lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly embrace him, vnfainedly honor him, cheerefully obey him,
<pb facs="25"/>
willingly aide him, and zealous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray for him. Many other Princes tyrannously suppresse, what hee religiously maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>the sincere seruice of God.</hi> In so much as in regard of the time that wee haue had <hi>true Religion</hi> in free vse, wee might haue beene all <hi>teachers of the Truth,</hi> yea, the meanest amongst vs, of competent age, might haue beene as <hi>Doctors,</hi> and all our <hi>Diuine Doctors,</hi> as the Angels of God. But (which is lamentable to be considered) the most of vs are not only not able to instruct them of our owne housholds, but haue nee de that the principles of <hi>Christian Religion</hi> should be taught vs anew. How shall we then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere the Master of this great Family, that hath giuen vs many talents to vse to our
<pb facs="26"/>
soules profit; who, when he shall come to take our account, and finde that we haue not only not profited by them, but to haue wasted them vpon our vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: will hee allow our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite hearing of his Word, our idle prayers, our workes of darknesse? Hee hath giuen vs the light of truth, and hidden it from <hi>many millions of soules</hi> (altogether) in <hi>Asia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> and dazeled the eyes of many in <hi>Europe,</hi> that onely see a glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering of <hi>that light, which lighteneth the world,</hi> and yet many in their pretended light comprehended it not. To passe ouer such as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in <hi>Europe:</hi> let vs looke into some of the territories of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West Indies:</hi> Into <hi>Brasill, Callicut, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi>
         <pb facs="26"/>
and many other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in those parts, who know no other GOD, but the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,</hi> to whom they pray, whom they worshippe, and to whom they doe sacrifice; offering their <hi>dearest children</hi> vnto him. The <hi>Guyneans</hi> adore for their god, the <hi>Creature</hi> which they first meet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in the morning, <hi>Beast, Bird,</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> The <hi>Angolans</hi> honour the <hi>Sunne,</hi> as the <hi>greatest god,</hi> and the <hi>Moone</hi> as the lesse: Besides which, euery man hath his peculiar god, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne priuate fansie. In the Kingdome of <hi>Loaugo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> are a people called <hi>Anziques,</hi> hauing in vse the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ale of the <hi>first Couenant, Circumcision:</hi> yet hath God left them to that, more then bestiall condition, as they will
<pb facs="27"/>
cut their owne flesh, and <hi>but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher themselues,</hi> for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing <hi>Mahomets</hi> sake yet doe they eate one the other, fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their slaues like hogs, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a <hi>Shamble Market,</hi> and <hi>Cookeries</hi> of mans flesh: and the neerest of kin, is killed and eaten for the greatest and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest daintie. Many other like <hi>Canibals</hi> are in those partes, visibly seene to eate men real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: But in some other more neere territories, they deuoure men aliue: <hi>Couert Canibals.</hi> It were much to remember all the nations (infinite) vnder the apparant captiuitie of <hi>Sathan,</hi> who, how hee bewitched the olde world with false gods, the <hi>Canonicall Scriptures</hi> doe declare. The <hi>Sidonians</hi> ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Ashteroth:</hi> The <hi>Ammonites, Moloch:</hi> The
<pb facs="27"/>
         <hi>Moabites, Chamos:</hi> The <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians, Bel,</hi> the father of <hi>Ninus:</hi> To whose counterfeit, that great king <hi>Cyrus</hi> did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and allowed a dayly dyet, of <hi>twelue measures of fine flowre,</hi> containing of our sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute measure, <hi>thirteene bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shels and a halfe, fortie sheepe,</hi> and <hi>sixe great potts of wine;</hi> of our measure, three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score gallons. This was a <hi>glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonous god,</hi> a <hi>beso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ted king,</hi> a <hi>bewitched people,</hi> and most <hi>accursed priestes,</hi> that coozoned their god of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, whom, by this meanes, the deuill robbed of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Besides these, whom God hath shut vp vnder dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the dispersed runnagate <hi>Iewes,</hi> are most of all the rest to bee condemned, who wilfully abandoned their <hi>Messias,</hi> whom
<pb facs="28"/>
they knew and crucified; And according to their owne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation, are helde still in most palpable blindnesse, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>auerie, both in bodies and soules: hauing neither Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, gouernour, nor gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor any certaine place of commorance. Insomuch, as if all the <hi>people, nations,</hi> and tongues in <hi>Asia, Africa, America,</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> were truely calculated, and their Religions discouered, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>PVRCHACE</hi> hath most worthily begunne: there would not bee found vpon the earths vniuersall Globe, one of two hundred parts, truely profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Christ; without whome <hi>there is no promise of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:</hi> which discouereth the most miserable condition of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite millions of people vnder
<pb facs="28"/>
the slauery of Sathan, and our most happy, and most blessed estate vnder <hi>Christ,</hi> whose Gospell we enioy, whose promises we haue, whose me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are ours, whose mercies we find, the aide and helpe of whose spirit wee feele. Greater blessings God could neuer haue bestowed on man: for these in earth are but pledges of our saluation in Heauen: which being well weighed and compared to the former forlorne Nations, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (in reason) but mooue vs to loue, and to serue this so mercifull a GOD with such sincere and intire affection, as should swallow vp in vs all worldly and carnall desires, and (as it were) rauish vs with most spirituall contemplations. But, if wee
<pb facs="29"/>
that haue receiued so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and sure tokens of our blessednesse in Christ; and hauing promised and vowed obedience to GOD in him▪ If we (I say) that haue the name of <hi>Christians,</hi> should liue like these <hi>Pagans:</hi> It had beene better for vs, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue knowne the truth: for it shall bee easier in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>daie of iudgement,</hi> for <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> that neuer knew GOD, then for vs that know his will, and doe it not. And it is probable, that if the blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of these <hi>blinde Nations,</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ad had the time of the learning of <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> as wee haue had, they had beene <hi>Christians,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded our present <hi>sinceritie, sanctitie, zeale, obedience,</hi> and <hi>true seruice of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi>
         <pb facs="29"/>
         <hi>God,</hi> in <hi>CHRIST, by the Holy Ghost.</hi> Let vs therefore well weigh our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, in respect of theirs, that are in a most cursed condition, and let vs consider, that there is with GOD <hi>Mercie</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> hee can call them in his free mercie, as he called vs, and reiect vs in his Iustice, for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his Word. And therefore as <hi>wee haue the light, let vs walke in the light, as children of the light.</hi> Let euery one, as hee professeth, practise the truth, and depart euery one from his euill way, and cheerefully call vpon the <hi>Lord Iesus:</hi> Let vs abandon all our carnall affections: our <hi>moderate libertie,</hi> our too much <hi>securitie,</hi> and our <hi>cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in our Religion:</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="30"/>
that most vnsauourie <hi>ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude</hi> followes these at the heeles. For <hi>GOD</hi> hath his <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> his <hi>Nabucadnezer,</hi> and manie other like <hi>Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ts,</hi> alwayes readily prepared, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides infinite other plagues, to afflict and confound a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious and thanklesse people. Hee hath often and fearefully threatned vs, and yet he hath still put vp his rodde againe in mercie. But did hee not see manie thinges amisse in vs, he would forbeare to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he hath done. And who so seeth not manie things out of course, in the carriage of men in their vngodly acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wilfully shuts the <hi>eyes of reason,</hi> and seeth nothing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> all with the <hi>eyes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let vs therefore be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb facs="30"/>
watchfull in prayer, that, when the Lord commeth to Iudgement, we may be so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with our Lamps in our hands, to attend his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as becommeth the children of God.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Thine in Christian goodwill, IO. NORDEN.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>