<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST NO∣ble Prince Lodwick Duke of Lenox, Earle of Darnely, Baron of Torbolton, Metheuen, and Aubig∣ny, Lord high Admerall and Chamberlein of Scotland, Knight of the most noble order of the garter, and one of the Kings Maiesties most honorable priuie councell, and his Highnesse Alneger generall for the Realme of England and the Dominion of Wales.</title>
           <author>May, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120174_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07323</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17710</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120174</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST NO∣ble Prince Lodwick Duke of Lenox, Earle of Darnely, Baron of Torbolton, Metheuen, and Aubig∣ny, Lord high Admerall and Chamberlein of Scotland, Knight of the most noble order of the garter, and one of the Kings Maiesties most honorable priuie councell, and his Highnesse Alneger generall for the Realme of England and the Dominion of Wales.</title>
                 <author>May, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of the estate of clothing now vsed within this realme of England : 1 The royaltie and benefit of wooll and woollen cloth. 2 The condition of the makers, being two sorts. 3 The antiquitie and power of the alneger. 4 The manner of search and searchers, now vsed. 5 The seuerall faults and abuses practised in cloth. 6 The inconuenience and hurt by the abuses. 7 The remedie to be made by the alnegers prouision. VVith an apologie for the alneger, shewing the necessarie vse of his office. Written by Iohn May, a deputie alneger</title>
                 <author>May, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 51, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MOST NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince Lodwick Duke of Lenox, Earle</hi> of Darnely, Baron of Torbolton, Metheuen, and Aubig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Lord high Admerall and Chamberlein of Scotland, Knight of the most noble order of the garter, and one of the Kings Maiesties most honorable priuie councell, and his Highnesse Alneger generall for the Realme of England and the Dominion of Wales.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eeing for a time restrained from that seruice, which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to performe vpon some occasion well knowne to your grace, My loue and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which no cause can obscure, presents it selfe with a subiect of your gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, often by your Graces cost and consent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by mee; whose condition shall bee truely reuealed, leauing the censure thereof to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and wise consideration, my selfe standing by to accuse it of many defects, who might bee
<pb facs="3"/>drawne backe in bashfull manner when I looke into myne owne impefection in wanting suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie to deliuer this cause in the right nature, but knowing that truth seemes beautifull al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though naked, and presuming on your honourable disposition, which is euer more readie to forgiue than sharply to reproue harmeles simplicitie, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldens me to goe forward although in rude sort; wherin your grace may not epect an exquisit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but like a plaine mans tale before a Judge, which will more sauour of trueth than elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, nor doe I take the helpe of any other to prompt mee, but onely seuen yeares experience, which I haue imploied in this subiects acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and now compiled the same into seuen howers studie, for one howers relation, and so made it my first fruits for this manner of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing, which I humbly intreat to bee shrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder your gratious fauour. The cause which procures mee to this taske is two fould: First, (according to my dutie) to acquaint your grace with the estate of the businesse: And se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to stirre your aide in the redresse, your power beeing able to reforme, and your place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it, still in all humblenesse desiring to haue
<pb facs="3"/>all imperfections ouerpassed with your graces fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and not called into a strict examination. The widowes mite was small, but acceptable in regard it was all shee had; let not the abilitie, but the affection be called in question, which wisheth his power farre greater, onely to shew it all in your graces seruice to whom he is so perpetuall and irreuocable bound vnto, as all is too little he can performe, wishing your grace all worldlie content, and after this life all heauenlie ioyes, to guerdon your happie and honorable deeds.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces mest humble and deuoted seruant. <hi>IOHN MAY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>