<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO AL THAT desire with faith and reuerence to call vpon the name of the Lord, by the me∣diation of Iesus Christ: Gods most holy Spirit be giuen for their inward consolation in this life, and their eternall peace and glory in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Euans, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120845_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00452</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10586</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120845</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO AL THAT desire with faith and reuerence to call vpon the name of the Lord, by the me∣diation of Iesus Christ: Gods most holy Spirit be giuen for their inward consolation in this life, and their eternall peace and glory in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Euans, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sacrifice of a contrite heart : in teares, meditations, and prayers. Penned by Iohn Euans minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Evans, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Coles (Coules, Cowles), Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hammond (Hamon), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 354 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO AL THAT desire with faith and reuerence to call vpon the name of the Lord, by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Iesus Christ: Gods <hi>most holy Spirit be giuen for their inward consolation in this</hi> life, and their eternall <hi>peace and glory in the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> in a thankfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of the in▪ numerable blessings, hee had receiued from the hands of God, said, <hi>Quid retribuam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino?</hi> what reward shall I giue vnto the Lord, for all the
<pb facs="5"/>
benefits hee hath done vnto me, and apprehending that God was not so well pleased with ceremoniall sacrifices, as thousands of oblations, or whole streames of the blood of young bullockes or goates, or with riuers of oyle; as with <note place="margin">Psal. 51.</note> a troubled Spirit, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and a broken heart; resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth therefore to humble his soule with fasting, with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and with mourning, to seeke the face and fauour of the Lord, to pay his vowes, to pray vnto the Lord, to cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his holy name, &amp; to praise him for euermore, assuring himselfe that the Lord would neither reiect nor despise such a sacrifice.</p>
   <p>Good Christian Reader doe thou the like, which art
<pb facs="5"/>
as farre indebted as euer <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was. And seeing that Iesus Christ himselfe calleth vnto thee, saying. <hi>Come vnto mee all you that labour and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy laden with the burden of your sinnes, and I will refresh you:</hi> Oh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et thy resolution be as ready as <hi>Dauids</hi> was when the Lord called, seeke my face, hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, thy face O Lord will I seeke, euen with my whole heart: so let thy answere bee to the Sonne of God, I come Lord Iesus, I come, I will pay my vowes promised to thee in the presence of thy people, and confirmed vnder the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall Seale of Baptisme, thy couenant of grace and mercy; I will come and offer vnto thee my heart, I will come and praise thee for all
<pb facs="6"/>
thy benefits, I will come and hearken to thy voyce in thy most holy and blessed word, I will abandon all secure, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious, and voluptuous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and wholly delight in thy Testimonies and in thy Commandements which are not grieuous to thy children, but more pleasing then ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or the honey combe, and more inualuable then all earthly treasure. I will come with reuerence, repentance, Charitie and Faith to receiue the cuppe of saluation at thy holy table in remembrance of thy most precious (and for my sinnes sake ignominious) death.</p>
   <p>And forasmuch as the <note place="margin">Math. 26</note> Spirit is willing, but the flesh fraile and weake, pray
<pb facs="6"/>
therefore for mortification of the flesh, and that Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and strengthening of thine owne inward Spirit: oh pray for the presence and assistance of Gods most holy Spirit to <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> helpe and strengthen thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: whereby the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent sighes &amp; inward groanes of thy heart may cheerefully ascend and pierce the heauens for a blessing: oh stirre vp thy <note place="margin">Math. 5. Acts 10.</note> heart and soule to pray ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly, offer vp thyteares with watching, with almes-deedes, with abstinence and fasting, as the repentant Niniuites: as <note place="margin">Iona. 3.</note>
      <hi>Dauid,</hi> as <hi>Daniel;</hi> oh breath out powerful sighes with <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> oh streame out riuers of teares with penitent <hi>Mary Magdalen.</hi> As some kinde of deuils could not bee cast out
<pb facs="7"/>
but by prayer and fasting; so some sins are not eiected, nor pardon for them procured without prayer and fasting, and also bitter teares with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting <hi>Peter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Oh pray effectually and cheerefully, and giue thy selfe <note place="margin">1. Thess. 5</note> continually to this diuine and holy exercise, (for this is the alone meanes to haue heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conference with thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God) oh pray without ceasing as the widow, and as the importunate woman of <hi>Canaan:</hi> pray euery where, though it be in the vppenpart of thy house with <hi>Peter,</hi> or in thy chamber alone with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liseus;</hi> whether in the Kings <note place="margin">Actes 10.</note> chamber, or in the Lyons den with <hi>Daniel,</hi> or with <hi>Moses</hi> in <note place="margin">Daniel. 6.</note> the wildernesse: the blessed
<pb facs="7"/>
children prayed in the fiery furnace, King <hi>Hezekias</hi> in his bed, <hi>Ionahs</hi> in the whales bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and our Sauiour Christ in the fields, in the gardens, on the mountaine; euen vpon the Crosse at the time of his vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious passion: pray with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> either seauen times a day, and in the night let thine eyes (like his) gush out riuers of teares, or with <hi>Daniel</hi> thrice in the day, or with <hi>Paul</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually be exercised with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sighes and sacred medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: let not, oh let not the dulnesse of thine heart, nor the greatnesse or grieuousnesse of thy sinnes hinder thee from this holy exercise, suffer not the Spirit of God to bee quenched in thee. To thee that art heauy laden with sin,
<pb facs="8"/>
and pressed with afflictions for sinne, doth thy sweet Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our call, to thee doth his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise most properly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, none asketh but he that wanteth, none seeketh but he that hath lost, remember that our Sauiour came to call sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to repentance, and to heale the sicke, and to cure the wounded, to ease and refresh all such as are laden with the insupportable burthen of their sinnes! oh bee of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, striue against thy dulnes, heare what is written for thy consolation; whosoeuer shall faithfully call vpon the Lord, shall be saued.</p>
   <p>Let not thy afflictions hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee, but rather follow the exhortation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle; if any bee afflicted let
<pb facs="8"/>
him pray, let thine afflictions encourage thee, and enflame thine heart to call vpon thy mercifull God who promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth by his Prophet to heare thee, and to deliuer thee. You shall seeke mee saith the Lord and finde mee, because you shall seeke mee with all your heart, and I will bee found of you &amp; will deliuer you from captiuity; Aske therefore and you shall haue, seeke and you shall finde, knocke and it shall bee opened vnto you: oh marke &amp; firmely beleeue the gracious promise of him that is the truth and the life, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer you shall aske the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it: who was euer denied that faithfully called vpon the Lord? The Lord is true and
<pb facs="9"/>
faithfull of his promise, both able and willing to performe, and will regard the supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and accept the prayers of his children; did not the Lord heare the prayers of the Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, and did not hee with a mighty arme plague their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and deliuer them out of captiuity and bondage: did not the red sea recoyle backe at the prayer of <hi>Moses;</hi> yea the waters saw thee ô Lord and were afraid, and at thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment made a way for the safety and deliuerance of thy people: was not the plague in the wildernesse stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the prayer of <hi>Moses,</hi> was not <hi>Miriam</hi> by prayer clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from his leprosie, was not <hi>Hanna</hi> by prayer of a barren woman made fruitfull, did not
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Dauid</hi> by his faithfull prayer and repentance obtaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission and forgiuenesse for man-slaughter and adulterie, did not <hi>Elias</hi> by prayer open the windowes of heauen and brought downe plentie of raine, was it not by prayer that <hi>Sennacherib</hi> &amp; his innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hoast were slaine &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited, by the Angel of the Lord. By prayer <hi>Susanna</hi> was deliuered frō death, the blessed children from the scorching heat of the Ouen, Queen <hi>Hester</hi> and her people were deliuered from death, <hi>Ionas</hi> out of the belley of the Whale; by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Leapers were cleansed, the blind were restored to sight, the Palsies were cured, many men &amp; womē obtained health fortheir children &amp; seruants.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
By prayer the lame haue beene restored to their limbs, the deafe to hearing, the blind to their sight, and the dumbe to their speech, by prayer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of sinnes was obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the holy Ghost was sent downe vpon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles.</p>
   <p>What should I saye more, by prayer Kingdomes haue beene subdued, miracles haue beene wrought, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises were obtained, the mouthes of Lyons were stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, the violence of fire hath beene quenched, the heauens haue beene shut and opened, the dead hath beene raised to life, the Sunne and Moone haue beene commanded and stood still. O faithfull mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger, oh diuine prayer, thou
<pb facs="10"/>
wilt striue and preuaile euen with the Lord of heauen, and obtaine the blessing.</p>
   <p>Wherefore good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and faithfull Reader, be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and constant in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exercise. Remember that when <hi>Moses</hi> hands failed, the enemies of Gods children preuailed; and that <hi>Sampson</hi> lost his strength and glory, when he lost his haire by the treachery of <hi>Dalilah:</hi> so when thou sufferest Gods Spirit to be quenched, thou art depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of thy spirituall strength and heauenly glory, and her soule despoiled of her beauty and comelinesse, and thou exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the protection of the most glorious Angels, which are ready with all chearefull willingnesse to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minister
<pb facs="11"/>
their aide and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto thee, and to beare thee safe from all thy enemies and dangers, while thou by faithfull prayer doest in the name of the Angel of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant that doeth sweetely and acceptably incense all thy oblations, call vpon the name of the most mighty and most glorious God of all Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men.</p>
   <p>And for that experience of my long afflictions and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes haue made mee appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensiue of the hardnes of our hearts, and our dulnesse and vnaptnesse to call vpon God in the time of our troubles. I haue composed these sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sighes, prayers and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which I may well call the exercises of my sad affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb facs="11"/>
to the end that if through Sathans buffets, the distempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature or weakenes of my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, or the snares of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill men my poore heart should be ouerwhelmed; yet I might haue alwayes presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mine eye how to make my moane vnto my God.</p>
   <p>And intending to publicke my labour herein, I haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured by varietie of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and prayers to make it profitably vsefull for all men. Most humbly beseech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the God of mercy to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and blesse my endeauoure herein: and grant that some glory to his holy name, and some benefite to his ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ldren, and comfort and consolation to all that groane vnder the burden of sinne, may redound
<pb facs="12"/>
hereby, and that for the alone merits and mediation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ the righteous. To whom with the father and the most holy Spirit, as by the most glorious Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, so by vs men, be rendred <hi>Halleluiah:</hi> all the glory, the praise, and the honour for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more. Amen. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>John Euans.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>