<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CATHOLICKS OF ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, AND IRELAND.</title>
           <author>Wilson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120085_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15506</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25771</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120085</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CATHOLICKS OF ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, AND IRELAND.</title>
                 <author>Wilson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English martyrologe : conteyning a summary of the liues of the glorious and renowned saintes of the three kingdomes, England, Scotland, and Ireland. Collected and distributed into moneths, after the forme of a calendar, according to euery saintes festiuity. VVherunto i annexed in the end a catalogue of those, who haue suffered death in England for defence of the Catholicke cause, since King Henry the 8. his breach with the Sea Apostolicke, vnto this day. By a Catholicke priest</title>
                 <author>Wilson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 356, 30 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CATHOLICKS OF <hi>ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, AND IRELAND.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had almost brought this little worke to an end, (deare Catholicke Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen) I began to thinke with my selfe, to whome, among many so dearely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, I might make bold to dedicate the same, therby the better to patronize that, which ouer bold presumption had cōceyued. And though the thing it selfe needed none other Patrons or Protectors then the glorious Saintes themselues, of whome we are now to treat: yet because I might not seeme, in a manner, to defraude any heerin of their right &amp; interest, which I imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; at last I thought it most conuenient, that YOW, whose hartes and myndes are firmely fixed in the honour and veneration of so glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and elected wightes, and for the imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb facs="3"/>
wherof yow daily suffer so great and many persecutions, should take vpon yow this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, for whose comfort and consolation principally (next after the honour of the Saintes themselues) the same is published. I do not heere offer vnto yow any new thing (which is alwayes commonly the custome of such to do who dedicate their workes to others) but that which so many ages since, hath by a certaine inheritance, as it were, of your forfathers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended still, by good right and title, vnto yow, and shall heerafter vnto your, and all posterity. Only this, that I haue heere gathered togeather, and restored vnto yow againe, that which the iniury of tymes had violently taken from yow, and sought to abolish all memory therof: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly presenting the same, as a duty of my loue towards yow, &amp; my dearest Countrey. Wishing yow to take in good part, what my poore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours haue byn able to produce heerin for your spirituall consolation, in these your so great affictions and pressures: with desyre to be made partaker of your good prayers.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>This first of October. 1608.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours wholy deuoted. I. W. Priest.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>