<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>VPON THE HAPPY TRANSLATI∣on of the most difficult Satirist, performed by his deare friend Mr. B. H.</title>
           <author>White, A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120195_Fr1_4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09495</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19778.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120195</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>VPON THE HAPPY TRANSLATI∣on of the most difficult Satirist, performed by his deare friend Mr. B. H.</title>
                 <author>White, A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Aulus Persius Flaccus his Satires translated into English, by Barten Holyday Mr of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Persius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>
      <hi>VPON THE HAPPY TRANSLATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the most difficult <hi>Satirist,</hi> performed by <hi>his deare friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. B. H.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>
      <hi>I</hi> Sing the Conquest, which an <hi>English</hi> rime,</l>
   <l>With all its force ne're wonne before This Time.</l>
   <l>Who thought that there would extant be the Man</l>
   <l>That such stiffe, sullen, hardy <hi>Romans can</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Subdue, and with an hand, learnedly fierce,</l>
   <l>Bind in the fetters of a <hi>Britane</hi> verse?</l>
   <l>Yet here is one that doth: But not as those</l>
   <l>That <note n="*" place="margin">Ovid: Met. Virg: Aeneid.</note>
      <hi>changed shapes,</hi> and <hi>wandring Trojans</hi> chose</l>
   <l>For to translate, with lines a mile in length,</l>
   <l>Or Paraphrase that tires. Such is His strength</l>
   <l>And strictnesse, he his Author without wrong</l>
   <l>Lodges in prisons but of fiue foot long.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Some</hi> I haue knowne, that did Attempt the same</l>
   <l>Which that they Durst, it was their Greatest fame,</l>
   <l>But it was He, that could disdaine to stay</l>
   <l>At this praise Margent, only to Assay:</l>
   <l>He with impetuous and all-conquering wit</l>
   <l>That only had the power to finish it.</l>
   <l>For had They don't, J know they must haue left</l>
   <l>Their graver studies, and haue filcht with theft</l>
   <l>Guiltie of too much sacriledge, more howres,</l>
   <l>Then time would loose; or else those sister powers</l>
   <l>Jnvoke to lend them <hi>Others liues,</hi> to plucke</l>
   <l>A vessell with such <hi>Remora's</hi> bestucke</l>
   <l>To wished shoare. But as for Him, with strange</l>
   <l>And easie hast, he did his <hi>Roman</hi> change</l>
   <l>Without complaint of time: No serious part</l>
   <l>Of learning murmur'd, that he did impart</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>Howres to the worke. For all this was begot</l>
   <l>
      <hi>(I speake my conscience)</hi> when it was his lot</l>
   <l>To be at Truce with studie. Then iudge you</l>
   <l>That shall vpon his happy paines, a vew</l>
   <l>Bestow, that nere the <hi>Muses Holydaies</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Or times of leasure, were with greater Praise,</l>
   <l>Or Thrift, or Businesse spent: and likewise since</l>
   <l>He conquer'd hath so fierce a <hi>Latin</hi> Prince</l>
   <l>Vnto the Rimes and Phrases of Our tongue:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Decree that bayes vnto his brow belong.</hi>
   </l>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. WHITE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>