<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120864_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68163</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13102</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120864</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comparison of the English and Spanish nation: composed by a French gentleman against those of the League in Fraunce, which went about to perswade the king to breake his alliance with England, and to confirme it with Spaine. By occasion whereof, the nature of both nations is liuely decyphered. Faithfully translated, out of French, by R.A</title>
                 <author>Gentil-homme francois</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 41, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I was constrained by some
friendes, to breake of a worke of some greater
importance and larger discourse, to vndertake
the translation of this briefe and pithie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.
Ere I had fully finished it, there came into my hands
another translation thereof, done by an Italian, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
vnder the title of <hi>A Politike Discourse most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
for the time present.</hi> On sight whereof though
I had perfected mine, I purposed to suppresse it, or at least
to reserue it to my selfe, and such friendes as seemed to
like it.</p>
   <p>But some being not satisfied with this former
translation, done by a stranger, and in some places (as
they thought) estraunged from our English phrase, were
desirous of my copie; which (being but one) could not well
content so manie. By occasion whereof: I was willing to
publish it, seeking their satisfaction. And the rather was I
thereto induce, because I found the treatise to bee so well
liked, that the former copies were for the most part alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
distracted.</p>
   <p>The former title of a <hi>Politike Discourse,</hi> because
it seemed too Generall, I haue chaunged into <hi>A compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison
betweene England and Spaine,</hi> which seemes
more neerely, &amp; particularly to expresse the substance of
the treatise.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
The paines which the other hath taken (howsoeuer
some mislike) I doe not condemne; neither would I wish
him to be discontented, that he being a straunger to both
countries, cannot satisfie all, in both languages; for hee
which is borne in the one, and brought vp in both, is not
able to performe it. But though he misse of his marke,
yet thinke well of his endeuors: and where I want of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
there I craue the like construction.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Some errors in printing haue escaped vs: but such as
the discrete Reader may correct with iudgement.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>