<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable, the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, the Knights, Cittizens and Burgesses of the high Court of Parliament.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120763_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09880</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20142</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable, the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, the Knights, Cittizens and Burgesses of the high Court of Parliament.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A consideration of the depriued and silenced ministers arguments, for their restitution to the vse and libertie of their ministerie : exhibited in their late supplication, vnto the honorable states assembled in this present Parliament. By Gabriel Powel</title>
                 <author>Powel, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable, the <hi>Lords Spirituall and Temporall,</hi> the Knights, Cittizens and Burgesses <hi>of the high Court of Parliament.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the <hi>Solon,</hi> or rather the <hi>Salomon</hi> of this age and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, our most gracious and peerelesse Soueraigne, hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto his singular wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and sinceritie of heart, by all good means, laboured the Reformation, as of all his Subiects in generall, which refuse to serue GOD with vs, in such holy exercises of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as are already established amongst vs, so especially of such our Brethren in the Ministerie, as emulating forraine Noveltie, refuse to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themselues vnto the ancient approued dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and ceremonies of our Church: whom therefore his Highnesse sought the more earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to reclaime, (as he loued them dearliest) by some correction of their obstinacie, by Silence and Deprivation, according to the laudable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and sanctions of the Ecclesiasticall Courts in this behalfe.</p>
   <p>Now (Right Reuerend and Honorable) there are which greatly complaine of this moderate Severitie, and both vnfitly and vndutifully terme it by the most hatefull and odious names of <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression</hi> and
<hi>Crueltie;</hi> which they do as well in their private talke, in their publike Sermons and
<pb facs="3"/>writings, as also in a late Supplicatorie Pamphlet directed vnto your graue Wisdomes, wherin the Auctor is not affraide <hi>to perswade and prouoke</hi> your Honourable Court (these are his owne words) to intercede with his Maiestie, that he would compell the Reverend Prelates of this Church, to surcease their rigorous and cruell dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, who haue soberly and temperately carried themselues in the execution of such Decrees and Sentences vpon them, as their obstinate Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had worthily made them subiect vnto. By which boldnesse he taketh occasion so to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine and crie out, as if the Gospell of CHRIST IESVS were banished out of this Kingdome, GODS worship prophanely adulterated, and our whole Ministerie strangely corrupted, to the eternall perdition and destruction of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Soules. Which grieuous complainte, seeing it cannot be vnknowne to any that liue within these Dominions, to be vtterly vniust &amp; vntrue, I can but wonder with what face he could once dare to present it to the most Reuerend Senate of your most Honorable and iudicious Court. For howsoeuer hee might perswade himselfe, that some preiudicate persons would affect his cause, and embrace his accusations; yet could he never have the least hope, so to abuse your Wisdomes, who of your owne knowledge are able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of malepert Sycophancie, and manifest vntruth. Notwithstanding all which, this Auctor fearing no rebuke or shame for his vnconsciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing (as speaking from Cimmerian darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="3"/>by concealing his name) is enboldened to offer it even vnto your Honors, <hi>to prouoke</hi> you to become suppliants and Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ters vnto his excellent Maiesty in behalfe of their cause, or else (at lēgth) to Determine of it your selues, <hi>before you dissolue your meeting.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Discourse (such as it is) I was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (by some in auctoritie) to peruse, &amp; briefly to refute, which I confesse at first I was very vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take vpon me; notwithstanding, I saw the great aduantage I should haue of my Bretherē, in the defence and maintenance of a most iust and holy Quarell. For (besides that I was exceeding loath to intermedle in these domesticall Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies, and indeed as
<hi>Abram</hi> said vnto <hi>Lot;</hi> (<hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8.) Why should there be strife betweene them and vs, <hi>for we are Brethren?</hi>) I saw many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent witts sit quietly at their studies, being better furnished and more able to deale in these cases then my selfe, who come so farre behinde them in all sufficiencie for this purposse. And specially, waighing my owne weaknesse, I iustly feared to practise this kinde of pleading in so high a Court, and before such Iudges, whose wisedomes can so easily discerne any which come before them. But on the other side, when I had throughly weighed the equitie of the Cause, the quality of my Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the necessitie of the Church, and the dutie of obeying the Auctoritie, whereby I haue beene enioyned this taske, I presently resolued with my selfe, to stand in the gap and breach betweene our Bretheren and vs, and according to my poore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>abilitie, to performe a seruice so iust, holy, dutifull and necessarie; albeit I knew my Brethrens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to be somewhat vnkinde, and their pens foule and shamelesse. But seeing it lieth not in our power to make them modest and peaceable, and that we are called to serue God and his Church, which we are bound to do in good and euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, in honour and dishonour, in wealth &amp; wo, in life and death, I willingly forgiue them any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie that may be done vnto me for this cause, and pray our Heauenly Father, that of his infinite mercie and loue in Iesus Christ, he will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it vnto them.</p>
   <p>So being satisfied of all scruples concerning this matter, and knowing no sufficient cause to the contrary, or other impediment to stay my course, I haue not withdrawne my selfe, no not for the estimation and reuerence I must needs haue of the grave iudgement of your Honours, which I saw I could not escape, but haue deemed this Defence to be my most bounden dutie to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, to his excellent Maiestie, to your honourable Court, and to this whole Church &amp; State. Wherefore I haue presumed by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable leaue and fauour, to maintaine against this Plaintiffe, to my small power, the glory of God, in the iust defence of his Church, and the honour of the reuerend Prelates in their most lawfull proceedings, against such, as by their schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and faction, disturbe the quietnesse both of our Church and common-weale.</p>
   <p>Thus having in all submission and humilitie,
<pb facs="4"/>rendred some reason of this my doing vnto your high and Honorable Court, I come now to ioine issue with my Antagonist, not doubting but that your Honors, according vnto your rare Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and speciall loue vnto Iustice, as you do in all other Causes depending among brethren, so in this, will giue equall hearing vnto both parties, and (without partiality and preiudicate affection) will iudge <hi>righteous Iudgment,</hi> that is, simplie &amp; absolutely according vnto the trueth.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The Title of the Supplication.</head>
      <p>❧ Certaine Arguments to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade and prouoke the most honorable and high court</hi> of Parliament now assembled, and also all other in any high authority, or in any grace, and credit with them that are in high authority, to promote and aduance the sincere Ministery of the Gospell; as also Zealously to speake for the Ministers thereof now Degraded, Deprived, Silenced, or Admonished, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward like to be called into question, for Subscription, Ceremonies, strict observation of the booke of common prayer, or for other conformity.</p>
      <q>
         <p>Them that honor me I will honor: and they that despise me, shall be despised.</p>
         <bibl>1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</bibl>
      </q>
      <q>
         <p>He that is not with me, is against me: and he that gathereth not with me, scattereth.</p>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Math.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>0.</bibl>
      </q>
      <p>
         <hi>Therefore,</hi>
      </p>
      <q>
         <p>Watch yee: stand fast in the faith; quit you like men, and be strong.</p>
         <bibl>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13.</bibl>
      </q>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>