<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR WILLIAM TVRPIN knight, &amp;c. his approued good friend and Patron, the increase of all Gods blessings and graces with the sound ioy and peace of a good consci∣ence be multiplied conti∣nually through Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Moore, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120561_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120561</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR WILLIAM TVRPIN knight, &amp;c. his approued good friend and Patron, the increase of all Gods blessings and graces with the sound ioy and peace of a good consci∣ence be multiplied conti∣nually through Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Moore, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A target for tillage : briefly containing the most necessary, pretious, and profitable vse thereof both for king and state. By Iohn Moore Minister of Gods word, and Parson of Knaptoft in Leicestershire. Anno 1611</title>
                 <author>Moore, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones, William 3</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, SIR WILLIAM TVRPIN knight, &amp;c. his approued good friend and Patron, the increase of all Gods blessings and graces with the sound ioy and peace of a good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be multiplied <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually through Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erusing my paper notes, and finding some heads of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine touching this argumēt of tillage, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpō occasion of my calling to the publike place: &amp; withall considering, and vnfainedly


<pb facs="3"/>
bewailing the hard hap of the generall expected hope, for the necessarie redresse of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous decay thereof; as a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willer of the common good of my coūtry, I haue added these my second thoughts to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer meditations, to be (if may be) as a further spurre for the more speedy reforming of this grosse abuse, or at least a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian warning to preuent a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mischiefe. VVhich my best endeauour I present to you (right worshipfull) not onely as a pawne of greater duties purposed for your kind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts, but for that I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded


<pb facs="3"/>
of your innocencie and harmelesnesse herin, as also of the honestie and vprightnesse of your hart for your countries good. For howsoeuer some in secret may vncharitably cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you, and put you in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the iustly accused: and so nibble at your credite, as one not altogether free from this great offence: Yet dare I be bold to ingage my poore credite, that whatsoeuer action of yours hath but a shew of any hinderance, you would be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to redresse, and most willing to redeeme with any tolerable priuate losse for the publicke


<pb facs="4"/>
gaine. And so beseeching the almighty to increase your loue to our Church and common-wealth, that still you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the profite and welfare of them both, by all possible pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and practise; I commend you to Gods grace, with the good successe of this needfull businesse. From my poore stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in Sheas by this of Aprill. 1611.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships throughly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted in the Lord Iesus, IOHN MOORE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>