<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, AND MVCH HO∣NOURED, THE LADY MARGARET GARVVAY.</title>
           <author>Woodward, Ezekias</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120251_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15695</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25971</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120251</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, AND MVCH HO∣NOURED, THE LADY MARGARET GARVVAY.</title>
                 <author>Woodward, Ezekias</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A childes patrimony laid out upon the good culture or tilling over his whole man : The first part, respecting a childe in his first and second age</title>
                 <author>Woodward, Ezekias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meredith, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stephens, Philemon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 47, 9, 182, 16, 14, 6, 207, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="107"/>
   <pb facs="107"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, AND MVCH HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOURED, THE LADY MARGARET GARVVAY.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I Know you are <hi>troubled about many things;</hi> nor can it bee otherwise, such is the trouble of <hi>entertainement.</hi> I shall call off your minde but a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and to very good purpose; though yet I shall not minde you of that you so well know; that but <hi>one thing</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many <hi>is necessary:</hi> nor yet will I be your <hi>Monitor,</hi> sith you are so well instructed that way, remembring you to make sure of that <hi>one thing</hi>
      <pb facs="108"/>
      <hi>necessary,</hi> because it is the <hi>better part,</hi> beyond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison the <hi>better.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This only, I will tell you; Herein, though it be <hi>specially</hi> intended for a Childes use, yet you may read <hi>your selfe</hi> first, and that is a very great lesson; then your <hi>graces,</hi> and <hi>wants</hi> too (all have them, even the best of all) your <hi>duty</hi> also. And towards the end you may read mighty words (they are not mine) which will minde <hi>Martha</hi> of <hi>Maries</hi> part, and, which is the Crowne of all, minde her to make choicetherof in <hi>season,</hi> and that is the only meanes to make our <hi>end</hi> joyfull. I have no more to say, when I have told you, I am your friend; This is true, but I am not so familiar, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for so low I am.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships Servant, EZEKIAS WOODVVARD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>