<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The occasion and contents of this Apology.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120316_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15655</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25919</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120316</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The occasion and contents of this Apology.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The schollers purgatory : discouered in the Stationers common-wealth, and discribed in a discourse apologeticall, asvvell for the publike aduantage of the Church, the state &amp; vvhole common-vvealth of England, as for the remedy of priuate iniuryes. By Geo: VVither</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wood, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Stationers’ Company, London</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 131, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                    <term>Book industry, catalogues and inventories</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The occasion and contents of this Apology.</head>
   <p>THe Author of this ensuing Apology haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings Grant, concerning his booke (called the <hi>Hymnes &amp; Songes of the Church</hi>) vniustly &amp; malitiously oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Stationers, who vnchristianly vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy &amp; scandalize alsoe, the said Booke, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his Maiesties powre, the hinderance of deuotion, the preiudice of the Authors estate, &amp; the disparagment of his best endeauors: He doth here Apologize both for his Booke &amp; Priueledge, shewing the true grounds of their spightfull oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition▪ discouering the Progresse of it, answearing such friuelous obiections as they haue dispersed, &amp; discouering how iniurious alsoe, they are euen to the whole Common-wealth in many other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers. It hath bene offred to the Presse, because it was otherwise impossible to divulge the same so vniuersally as they haue spread their scandalls; And it was directed alsoe to the most reuerend Conuocatiō, that the said Booke might be corrected or approoued of as the wisdome of that graue As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly shall finde cause: &amp; that the representatiue body of the Church of England, beholding a glimpse of the Stationers harbarous dispositions in misvsing this Author, might from thence take occasion to be informed, What other insolencyes &amp; abuses they are guilty of, both to the disturbance of Christian vnity, &amp; to the Common preiudice.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="2"/>If the Printers hast, shall occasion any slipps, he desires that if his worke be legible he may be ex▪ cused▪ Soe, doth our Author likewise, if in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode or language, any ouer sight be committed. For, haueing many other employments, and being constrayned to write it in hast (that it might bee imprinted before this present Session of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were expired) there may be somewhat ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seene perhapps, which needeth pardon. But as it is, he humbly offers to consideration▪ the said Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy; whose perticulers are these that follow.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1. First, an Induction; after which the Author haueing breefly touched vpon those troubles, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonments &amp; expences, which compelled him to make some benifite of his owne books, sheweth why he gott his Hymnes confirmed vnto him by his Maiesties Letters Patents, &amp; what honest Course he tooke in procuring his Grant: Pag. 1, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>2. He sheweth how vniustly &amp; ingratfully the Stationers therevpon opposed him; how vncivel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they abused him; how vnchristianly they vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his Hymnes, rather as Censurers then sellers of Bookes: And a little toucheth vpon the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer vsur pations, In sinuations, Insolencyes, Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, &amp; abuses of Bookesellers, Pag. 6, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>3. He declareth why he exercised his Muse in Diuinity: What reason he had to translate the Canonicall Hymnes into Lyrick verse; &amp; that some of the Cleargy mooned him therevnto▪ He sheweth
<pb facs="3"/>
alsoe, to what end he composed the Spirituall Songs for the obseruable tymes: Of what nature that Booke is, which the Stationers oppose: And what they doe in particuler, rayle &amp; obiect against the said Booke. Pag. 11, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>4. He proueth by diuerse Arguments that the said Hymnes are necessary, &amp; not impertinent as the Stationers obiect: Then toucheth againe vpon the abuses &amp; grosse partiality of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, acquiteth himselfe of seeking his owne profitt (to the publike preiudice,) as his Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries vntruly affyrme: and demonstrateth his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be neither Monopoly, as the Stationers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage (&amp; as some of their Patēts are) but rather a benifite. Pag. 24, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>5. He setteth downe the Stationers peremptery claime to all Authors labors: refuting a Lawyers foolish judgment passed on their behalfes. Instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in what particulers they vsurpe larger Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues then they will allow the King: And then (haueing iust occasion) pointeth at their fraudulent &amp; vnsufferable abusing of the people in their My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of Booke selling. Pag. 29, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>6. He particularizeth în what vnciuell termes the Stationers vilifie his Hymnes: How vniustly they disparage his expressions: And how impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently they vsually preferr &amp; divulge those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious &amp; impertinent things, whereby they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues may receaue profitt. Pag. 33, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="3"/>7. He iustifies his expressions: Protesteth with what mind, what preparation, and with what Caueats he proceeded in that worke. And there withall mētioneth some of those difficulties which are in such a taske &amp; speaketh somwhat cōcerning the metricall version of Dauids Psalmes now in vse. Pag. 35, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>8. He maintaines the lawfulnesse of vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a worke of that nature, notwithstanding he is no profest Diuine, against those who obiect he hath intruded vpon the Diuine calling; &amp; glanceth at the ignorance and envy of those Obiectors. P: 39,</item>
      <item>9. He discouereth how presumptuously they haue countenanced their detraction and opposition, by pretending that the Lo: Archb: of Cant: and<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others are all affected to the said Hymnes &amp; Grant. And it is made euident that they haue impudently abused the Lo: Archb: therein. Pag. 45▪ &amp;c.</item>
      <item>10. He giueth reason; for his translating and publishing the sōg of Salomō▪ in Lyrick verse. Setts downe the Stationers impious and scurrilous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of traducing it. Expresseth somewhat of that Songs comfortable vse, with what may be said in answeare to them who think it ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained, for feare of being misapplyed. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueing spoken somewhat concerning his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, submitteth all to censure. Pag 49, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>11. He displaies the Stationers demeanor to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward those who come to aske for his Booke. Setts
<pb facs="4"/>
forth the quality of those whom they haue drawne to passe their censures against it. Shewes how wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the Kings iniunction, &amp; his pious intent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hath bene reiected: And what inconueniences are likly to follow their insolencyes, if order be not taken. Pag 63, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>12. He vpholds his Hymnes for the obseruable tymes, against the Stationers &amp; those whom they haue stirred vp to oppose them: Offers them to strictest examination▪ Shewes his Christian sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity in cōposing thē; that they tend to the glory of God, and the furtherance of vniformity: That they were lawfully Authorized: That they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanant to the word of God, the Doctrine of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, and to all the lawes and ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Ordinances of this Realme. Pag. 66, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>13. He intimates that it is probable his Hymnes are scandalized by none but such as are ill affected to the gouernment of our Church. Shewes that his prefaces hath vindicated all our Solemnities from those imputations of popery, Schismaticks hath cast vpon them: Toucheth vpon the pious vseful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Churches Discipline: Illustrateth their impiety who seeke to disparage or abolish it, And specifieth in what places, &amp; in what ridiculous manner the Stationers passe their virdicts vpon his booke. Pag. 69, &amp;c:</item>
      <item>14. He setteth downe how barbarously the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners seeke to disparage all his Hymnes by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb facs="4"/>
of that for S. Georges day: How vnchristianly they misinterpreted his pious &amp; warrantable intētion in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing that Hymne; &amp; therevpon taketh occasiō to speake somewhat of the pious vse of that solemnity; of the most noble &amp; most Christian order of S. George &amp; the Patron thereof; to the honor of that institutiō, &amp; in reproofe of the vulger &amp; ignorant misconceits of his Reproouers. Pa. 76.</item>
      <item>15. He humbly intreats that neither his youth, his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, nor the vniust scandalls of his Aduersaries may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice what he hath well done: She wes why his writings &amp; Actions are exposed to more scandalls then vaniest inventions bring on their Authors; protesteth what it is that made him thus endeauor to maintain his reputation; &amp; professeth some what of his hopes &amp; Resolutiōs. p: 84.</item>
      <item>16. He displaies the true condition of his aduersaries▪ by shewing how nere they paralell Dauids enimies, &amp; that they haue giuen him iust occasiō to take vp in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral sēce almost euery bitter cōplaine wherby the Psalmist hath expressed the cruelty of a malitious multitude. P. 87</item>
      <item>17. He expostulatheth concerning that vnequall dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the world hath hitherto vsed towards him: And (taking it a little vnkindly that any of those who ought to cherish men in good employements, should do him iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by a rash censure) Toucheth vpon some others who to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Stationers haue iniuriously &amp; causelesly detracted from his labors. Pag. 89.</item>
      <item>18. He nominateth many of those perticuler iniuries offred him by the Stationers. He describeth alsoe the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre, policy, &amp; true condition of his opposers, with many of those dāgers, disadvātages, &amp; incōueniences which their malice portend▪ And then shewes both how much he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth all they can bring to passe, &amp; how he hopeth to conuert all their hate, mischeefes, &amp; slanders; to his future profitt &amp; commendation in their despight▪ Pag. 94.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="5"/>19. He giues the reason of his hopes of preuailing; cōcicture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Gods good purpose in suffring him to be afflicted by these Adversaries, &amp; his other troubles; apologizeth for that ouermuch sharpnesse▪ which he hath seemed to vse; &amp; makes it probable, that he hath no vncharitable intentiō in any thing which he hath expressed in this booke. p. 103.</item>
      <item>20. He renounceth to haue any purpose to Disparage or defame either the whole Corporation of Stationers, or any particuler member thereof, &amp; that no other may abuse this Discourse to that end; he shewes alsoe, how all the reprehensions therein expressed, may be applyed to those only who are guilty, &amp; how euery man that is innocent, or sorry for his ouersight, may, if he himselfe please, be freed from all personall blame or scandall. Pag. 108.</item>
      <item>21. To prevent their malice likwise, who would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happs apply this Discourse to the generall disparagment of the Stationers Mystery; he hath added the definition of an honest Stationer; &amp; the true Character of his contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whom he calleth a meere Stationer, &amp; against whom, only, this booke is intended. Pag. 116.</item>
      <item>22. He reconeth vp, some of those many inconueniences which the Vniuersities, the State, the whole Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, &amp; the Church of God suffers, by the Disorders among those whom hee calleth meere Stationers; but reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth their amplification to another Discourse, which he intendeth to publish if there be cause. Page 127.</item>
      <item>23. And lastly (to shew he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h not aymed at the shame or ruine of any, but at their reformatiō only) he offers to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer a profitable remedy for what he hath foūd to be ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e; to the glory of God, the content of the King, the quiet of the State, the honor of learning, &amp; to the credit &amp; profit of the Stationers themselues. And these, amōg some other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall passages, are the cōtents of this Apology, p. 130.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>