<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, SIR CHRI∣STOPHER HATTON, Knight, one of the Queenes Maiesties most Honourable priuy Coun∣sell, and Captayne of her Graces Garde.</title>
           <author>Maplet, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120741_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06859</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17295</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120741</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, SIR CHRI∣STOPHER HATTON, Knight, one of the Queenes Maiesties most Honourable priuy Coun∣sell, and Captayne of her Graces Garde.</title>
                 <author>Maplet, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diall of destiny : A booke very delectable and pleasaunt: wherein may be seene the continuall and customable course, disposition, qualities, effectes, and influence of the seuen planets ouer all kyndes of creatures here belowe: also the seuerall and sundry situation o countryes and kingdomes. Compiled and discussed briefly, aswell astrologically, as poetically, and philosophically by Iohn Maplet Maister of Arte</title>
                 <author>Maplet, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 73, 3 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HONORABLE, SIR</hi> CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOPHER HATTON, Knight,</hi> one of the <hi>Queenes Maiesties</hi> most Honourable priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, and Captayne of her Graces Garde.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>ENOPIDES</hi> Chius (most honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Syr) dedicated at the Tryumphes holde in Greece to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Iupiter Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus (or as others write) to Hercules, a Booke of his owne framing and make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of Brasse: the Methode and matter whereof was nothing else but a summary Discourse collected oute of Plato as concerning the continuance, circuite, and course of the seuen Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets. VVhich busines so carefully, and costly perfourmed by the aforesayd Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, is here peraduēture in another sort with other necessary sequell thereof, &amp; with lesse a doe also and lesse cost scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="3"/>&amp; debated. VVhich small treatise of myne, neyther crauing Iupiter, nor Hercules, but requireth rather youre honors present Patrocynie, and fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable protection: Your Honour being now in these dayes to our most renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Prince, &amp; the VVeale Publike euē the same that PHOCION a moste renowmed Captayne was to the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians: And as EPAMINON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAS was to the Thebanes. Three rare &amp; royall vertues there are which AGESILAVS (speaking it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good tryall and proofe thereof) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth to bee in a Captayne set ouer the Prynces Garde: the first hee sayth, is fidelity to his Soueraygne, whose per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son hee is moste carefully to safegarde and defend: the second (he sayth) is an hawty heart and valiancy of Mynde, friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y affected towards his friendes, and litle esteming the force of his foes: and the last he reposeth in ripenesse of Iudgement &amp; dexterity of VVisdome
<pb facs="3"/>in geuing of common wealth councell. All which three Ormamēts &amp; Iewels, and the same three (I dare vtter it) thrise doubled and trebled, shyne and shewe forth in your Honor very resplē dishingly. Insomuch that if I were (as I am nothing fit thereto) to determyn as the Orator DEMADES did, of Noble Personages and moste worthy VVyghtes euen eyes of the Realme, as hee calleth them: the consideration of your honors so Infinite and inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues, euen of very right deseru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same, required (I shoulde say very worthely) your Honors accoumpt (as it also hath already) among y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Senators and Sages of this Land. And whereas many other Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gouerned onely as it were Cyclopy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, (that is to say) wyth myght &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely force, therewith onely defeng thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, being wythout theyr wyse Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, as it were without their Eyes (as the Poets say the great Gyaunte CY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLOPS
<pb facs="4"/>is) doe yet neuerthelesse for want of the same runne oftentimes to much ruyne, subiection, and subuersion. This our Countrey and Nation (the Lord bee hyghly thanked therefore) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing such theyr Eyes and eysight, as it hath in deede very cleare, perfite, and pretious, whereby aswell all the whole body of the Realme: as also euery parte thereof is most happely dyrected in all kinde of safety: howe greatly wee and the same is to glorifie GOD therefore, though I should say nothing thereof but be silent therein, the very force of such a ryche blessinge and Benefite, it selfe would burst forth and speake it. Now the cause that only mooued me at this time, to craue your Honores Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauncinge of this Litle Treatise, was chiefly, the hearesay of your Honoures accustomed Clemency, and Curtesy in like behalfe towardes others. VVhich being any thinge accepted at your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors hands, shall encourage me hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="4"/>to other Trauayles and endeuours. In the meane tyme I shall not cease to pray to the gouernor of all, the Lord of Lordes, for the prosperous &amp; long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of your Honour, and for the continuance of your honors estate &amp; good lyking, to the glory of GOD, the contentation of the Prynce, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of the Countrey.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Northall <date>The last of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember. 1581.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honors humble and dayly Orator. Iohn Maplet.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>