<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Argument of the seue∣rall Chapters.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120922_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12880</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120922</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Argument of the seue∣rall Chapters.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of egregious popish impostures : to with-draw the harts of her Maiesties subiects from their allegeance, and from the truth of Christian religion professed in England, vnder the pretence of casting out deuils. Practised by Edmunds, alias Weston a Iesuit, and diuers Romish priests his wicked associates. Where-vnto are annexed the copies of the confessions, and examinations of the parties themselues, which were pretended to be possessed, and dispossessed, taken vpon oath before her Maiesties commissioners, for causes ecclesiasticall</title>
                 <author>Harsnett, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 284 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ The Argument of the seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Chapters.</hi>
   </head>
   <p n="1">1 THE occasion of publishing these wonders, by the comming into light of the penned booke of Miracles.</p>
   <p n="2">2 The fit time that the Popish Exorcists chose to act these mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in.</p>
   <p n="3">3 The places wherein these Miracles were played.</p>
   <p n="4">4 More speciall considerations touching their choyse of places.</p>
   <p n="5">5 The persons, their Disciples pretended to be possessed, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possessed.</p>
   <p n="6">6 Their wayes of catching, and inueigling their Disciples.</p>
   <p n="7">7 Their holy pretences to make their Disciples sure vnto them.</p>
   <p n="8">8 Their meanes, and manner of instructing their Schollers.</p>
   <p n="9">9 Of the secrets, and strange operation of the holy chayre, and holy potion.</p>
   <p n="10">10 Touching the strange names of their deuils.</p>
   <p n="11">11 The reasons why somtime one deuil alone, somtimes an 100, sometimes a thousand are cast out at a clap.</p>
   <p n="12">12 Of the secret of lodging, and couching the deuill in any part of the body that the Exorcist please.</p>
   <p n="13">13 Of dislodging, rowsing, and hunting the deuil by the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full power of the presence, approach, &amp; bodily touch of a priest.</p>
   <p n="14">14 Of the strange power of a Catholique Priests breath, and of the admirable fire that is in a Priests hands to burne the deuill.</p>
   <p n="15">15 Of the admirable power in a Priests gloues, his hose, his gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, his shirts, to scorch the deuill.</p>
   <p n="16">16 Of the wonderfull power in a Priests albe, his amice, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niple, his stole, to whip, and plague the deuil.</p>
   <p n="17">17 Certaine questions aunswered, concerning the Church of Rome, her making, and accumulating yet more dreadfull tooles, and Engines for the deuill.</p>
   <p n="18">18 Of the dreadfull power of holy water, hallowed candell, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincense, Brimstone, the booke of Exorcismes, and the holy potion, to scald, broyle, and to sizle the deuill.</p>
   <p n="19">19 Of the astonishable power of Nicknames, Reliques, &amp; Asses eares, in afflicting, and tormenting the deuill.</p>
   <p n="20">20 Of the dreadfull power of the Crosse, and Sacrament of the Altar to torment the deuil, and to make him roare.</p>
   <p n="21">21 Of the strange formes, shapes, &amp; apparitions of the deuils.</p>
   <p n="22">22 Of the admirable finall act of expelling the deuils, and of their formes in the departing.</p>
   <p n="23">23 Of the ayme, end, &amp; mark of all this pestilent tragaedie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>