<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120443_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13168</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23463</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120443</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The examination of M. Thomas Cartvvrights late apologie : wherein his vaine and vniust challenge concerning certaine supposed slanders pretended to haue bene published in print against him, is answered and refuted, By Matthevv Sutcliffe</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher, Deputies of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>1, 58 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="6" facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be, gentle Reader, that either thou mayest thinke mee contentious, that haue entred into this quarrell with <hi>M. Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> being a matter very friuolous, &amp; no way to any good purpose: or els very idle and at great laisure, that haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els to busie my selfe withall, vnlesse I doe dispute and talke of <hi>Hackets</hi> &amp; <hi>Penries</hi> matters, and <hi>M. Cartwrights</hi> landes and liuings, and also of his domesticall and inward affaires, and his priuate conceits and opinions. But yet, if thou wilt be pleased to consider either the great credite and fame, which <hi>M. Cartwright</hi> hath amōg his followers, that admire all his vanities; or els the importunitie of him, that made the preface to his booke, that would haue all my writings mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured by this false and deceiuable line of <hi>M. Cartwrights</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologeticall challenge, by the which hee supposeth him to bee cleared, and mee to be quite disgraced, and therefore seeketh to discredite all that I haue written in the common cause by the supposed vntruethes and slanders vttered against him, of which he taketh me as conuicted: I trust thou wilt pardon mee, although I doe examine euen these fond toyes, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, not worth a straw; and grant, that it is to some good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, if I doe cleare my selfe of those fonde and ridiculous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, which hee would so willingly, and yet doeth so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handsomely fasten vpon me.</p>
   <p>I was not ignorant, that wise men doe well perceiue this to bee an vncertaine, and deceitfull rule, considering that such as write best are not voyde of errours, and very learned men doe often slip: yet such is the iustice and clearenesse of my cause in this controuersie betwixt <hi>M. Cartwright</hi> and me, that I would not feare for once to allowe this rule, and to make the most simple iudge of my dealings herein. the which helpe seeing my cause doth afford me, I thought it not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
<pb facs="8"/>to leaue to such clamorous aduersaries any pretense of aduantage.</p>
   <p>I am therefore to pray thee not to accompt mee for this cause either contentious and quarrelsome, or els vnwilling to accept of conditions of peace; but rather to pitie mee, whom such contentious fellowes with their vaine iangling, and clamarous complayning will not suffer to rest. I did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer challenge any as yet; but still wrote against those, that had first entred into voluntary quarrels against this Church and state. such was my discourse against <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and the Papists: such also were those two bookes which I wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the whole fraternitie of the disciplinarians, and their extrauagant fancies. neither had I to doe either with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the petition, or with M. <hi>Iob Throk.</hi> before they did challenge me. seeing then this my answere to <hi>M. Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> is of the same nature, why should the same bee more blamed, then my other doings?</p>
   <p>As for my leisure, I assure thee, it was neuer lesse. for yet there are not many dayes passed since the Fleete returned, wherein I was with others in her Maiesties seruice in the iourney of <hi>Guadix:</hi> and to set my things in order, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh my selfe of my former trauailes, some time is required. as for idlenesse, I doe detest it, and <hi>M. Cartwright</hi> and his friendes (I thinke) will thereof discharge me. yet if his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory dealing, and his proloquutors insolencie would haue suffered mee to rest; I could nowe haue bene content to put o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>M. Cartwrights</hi> briefe vntill the next returne. but being prouoked by both, either to yeelde my selfe to haue done notorious wrong, or els to make answere; although my other busines was great, and my ease none at all, yet haue I thought good to sende them both away with a quicke dispatch to rake vp some new accusation or rather calumniation against me at some other time.</p>
   <pb n="7" facs="8"/>
   <p>This, certes, is the cause that specially mooued me to looke into this newe matter, although both for the basenesse of the subiect, and vnsufficiencie of the handling of the cause most vnworthy to bee answered, read, or regarded. for (I pray) what doeth it concerne, but <hi>M. Cartwrights</hi> priuate causes, with which, were I not drawne to it, I am most vnwilling to meddle? yea, and in this cause of his owne, how doeth he be haue himselfe? doeth hee not forbeare to answere the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test and most of those questions which are demaunded of him? the examination of particulers, and the reading of this treatise will declare it. To come to the argument of this pamphlet, let vs see how he handleth it. he saith and in great wordes giueth out, <hi>that I haue slaundred him,</hi> and that, forsooth, <hi>in two diuers pointes,</hi> whereof the first (as hee saith) <hi>concerneth common maners,</hi> the second <hi>toucheth his owne estate.</hi> but when hee descendeth from the toppe of his high stile to talke of particulers, either hee doeth not rightly alledge my wordes, and so faileth in his ground; or els frankly confesseth as much as I say; or els the matters where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he taketh himselfe to be charged, are not criminall. but suppose I had spoken somewhat, that might offend him; yet I trust his estate is not so high, but that it may be touched. I doe not thinke hee desireth any royallestate, as some haue done; neither any priuiledged place, such as licencious persons seeke. for mine owne part, I must needes say, that I haue not read a more fond and friuolous dispute.</p>
   <p>Like to <hi>M. Cartwrights</hi> booke is that preface which bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a great roume in this small treatise. like lippes like let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise: both vaine, both deuoyde of wit and learning. yet of the two the preface is more fond, aduancing <hi>M. Cartwright</hi> to the state of innocencie; and more odious, being fraught with diuers rayling reproches. the authour seemeth to Master <hi>Iob Throkmorton</hi> an olde friend of mine, who by commending
<pb facs="9"/>of M. <hi>Cartwright</hi> sought to be reuenged on mee. And what he could not winne by commending him, that he seeketh <hi>by rayling and</hi>
      <note n="1" place="margin">Inter hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas faceros san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niones faceti trendentes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra me dentibus suis. Psalm. 35.</note>
      <hi>gnashing his teeth vpon me.</hi> such mery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious fellowes well doeth the Prophete describe in his <hi>35.</hi> Psalme. and such dealing is not strange in that gentleman, to whom I wish no other paine, then that for his scorning and rayling, for which his owne friendes call him <hi>gibing Iob,</hi> he doe not in the ende weepe full bitterly. I had thought the euill speede and successe hee had in his last letter would haue admonished him to surcease writing either of letters, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces. But he is of the number of those whom no harme will make wise, and percase is content especially for M. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrights</hi> sake, to suffer some fewe gentle blowes in deduction of those paines, which otherwise he hath deserued.</p>
   <p>Against both the preface, and M. <hi>Cartwrights</hi> briefe challenge I haue published this briefe answere. by which I trust (by Gods grace) to defend my rightfull cause. thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by shalt reape this profite. thou shalt see, that these men, so they could reteine their old credit, could be content to see the cause of their discipline deserted, yea, and M. <hi>Cartwright</hi> and M. <hi>Throkmorton</hi> will I trust make so good vse of it, as to learne to master their affections, and to tame their hauty minde, and to rest when they are in the wrong, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to drawe men into quarrels that wisheth them all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and meekenesse that should bee in men of their sort. I woulde to God, that these that so eagerly pursue mee for sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed matter against themselues, would in the ende come home, and make an amends for that publike slaunder and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace they haue offered to the state. But what do I wish that, which will not bee had? such men as are settled in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked purposes and courses, wil not lightly giue ouer, that which once though vnaduisedly they haue begun. I would therefore if their heades will not bee aduised, yet wish their followers to
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>take heed, how they be abused by them, and to looke for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ground, then such froward leaders strange conceits.</p>
   <p>This answere I pray thee read with patience, and looke not for any great learning in it. for it was deuised on the sudden, and beside that, it is framed vpon a base subiect, and a light matter of fact, and very needlesse, if M. <hi>Carwright</hi> could so haue bene contented. Is it possible to draw water out of flint, or likely that wee shall gather grapes on thistles? M. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> doeth not boast of miracles as hee saith, and I neuer professed that I could worke them. what fruite then is to bee expected out of this rockie soile? Well, such as it is, I pray thee accept this discourse. and I would it were better for thy sake. The best is, it shall not be long, nor I hope tedious: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leauing all other preambles, I come now to the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the booke it selfe. But first a few wordes concerning the two diuers titles, that this petit pamphlet hath in two se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all places put before it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>