<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, Grace and peace from GOD our Father, and from the Lord IESVS CHRIST.</title>
           <author>W., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120396_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15144</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25441</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120396</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, Grace and peace from GOD our Father, and from the Lord IESVS CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>W., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvay to the celestiall paradise : Declaring how a sinner may be saued, and come to life euerlasting. Contained in three bookes.The first second third sheweth that a sinner may be saued, &amp; come to life euerlasting. By faith, apprehending Christ for his iustification, &amp; applying to himselfe the promises of the Gospell made in Iesus Christ. Repentance, hauing his sins washed away in the bloud of the lambe Iesus Christ. Prayer, calling vpon God in the name of Iesus Christ. By Robert Whittell, minister of the Gospell</title>
                 <author>Whittle, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rounthwait, Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>58, 398 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE CHRISTIAN</hi> READER, <hi>Grace and peace from GOD our Father, and from the Lord IESVS CHRIST.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, this Booke, in my first thoughts, was intended to be but a Manuall: but my meditations enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselues, it is growne to this bignesse. And now being come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy hands, I craue of thy courtesie, two things▪ to read it, and to practise it. First, to read it: and in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> reading it; first, to reade it wholly, and throughout: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> not heere a leafe, and there a leafe: to read by snatches and peeces, is vnprofitable. Secondly, to read it delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> both for the better vnderstanding of it, as also for the auoyding of rash censure: things hastily read,
<pb facs="6"/> and not well vnderstood, easily beget vniust censure. Thirdly, in reading it, despise not my plaine and humile <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> stile: for I put not my selfe forth to this open view, to humor thee with pleasing words, nor to tickle thine eare with affected eloquence; but to saue thy soule; and to bring thee to the Celestiall Paradise: which cannot bee performed, with <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 1, 4.</note>
      <hi>excellency of speech, nor with enticing words of mans wisdome, but in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of the Spirit, and of power.</hi> And last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> reiect it not, because others haue formerly written of the same subiects: for I haue not drawen much water out of any of their fountaines: neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r haue I trodden farre in any of their steps, for <hi>Matter:</hi> if I haue some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lighted my darke candle at the cleere light of the graue Fathers, or any of their Sonnes of later times; that's none other thing, then the Fathers themselues, and after them, all learned men, which haue written, almost of any subiect, haue formerly vsed. And for my <hi>Methode</hi> and manner of handling these Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, of <hi>Faith, Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> I haue, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, consulted with many Authours; but directly followed none: my <hi>Methode</hi> is mine owne: for which, I acknowledge my selfe bound, first to God; next, to my <note n="b" place="margin">D. Downame B. of Derry.</note> Tutor, then to Art. How many learned men haue beene exercised in <hi>Controuersies,</hi> and haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested the diuersities of gifts vpon the same subiects? How many <hi>Commentaries, Expositions</hi> and <hi>Postills</hi> are now extant, the later still sucking moisture and fatnesse from those which haue gone before? whether men exercise themselues in Controuersies, Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or Treatises; that saying of the Apostle is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in all: <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 4.</note>
      <hi>There are diuersities of gifts, but the</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>same Spirit.</hi> Hauing read it; in the second place, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whosoeuer thou art that readest, to <hi>practise</hi> it: The reading of good bookes, and not practising what thou readest, as it may augment thy knowledge, so will it adde to thy punishment. Good Reader, I shew vnto thee here, <hi>The way to the Celestiall Paradise:</hi> walke in the same; that at thy last end, thou mayest enter into that Heauenly Paradise. Heere is the path of life, which will bring thee into the presence of God, where there is <note n="d" place="margin">Psal. 16. 11.</note>
      <hi>fulnesse of ioy, and at whose right hand there are pleasures for euermore.</hi> I declare vnto thee how thou mayest be <hi>saued,</hi> and come to <hi>life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting:</hi> O then, I beseech thee by the mercies of God, whiles thou hast time, vse meanes to saue thy soule; and suffer not thy soule to perish, for which Christ died. If thou hast read this Booke, and findest thy selfe no whit bettered, neither for information, nor reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor consolation; then thou hast read in vaine, and vnderstood in vaine, and I haue bestowed on thee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vaine: But if thou hast so read it, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood it, as that therby thy vnderstanding is inlightned, thy iudgement informed, thy life amended, thy faith stablished, thy zeale enflamed, thy conscience pacified, and thy soule comforted; then, not vnto me, but vnto the LORD ascribe the glory: and this I pray thee doe; Praise thou the LORD, and pray for me.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus. R. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>