<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREMONITION, OF THE TITLE AND VSE of Characters.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr9_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREMONITION, OF THE TITLE AND VSE of Characters.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice">
   <pb facs="88"/>
   <pb n="165" facs="88"/>
   <head>A PREMONITION, OF THE TITLE AND VSE of Characters.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Diuines of the old Heathens were their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Philosophers: These receiued the <hi>Acts</hi> of an inbred law, in the <hi>Sinai</hi> of Nature, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them with many expositions to the multitude: These were the Ouerseers of manners, Correctors of vices, Directors of liues, Doctors of vertue, which yet taught their people the body of their naturall Diuinitie, not after one manner: while some spent themselues in deepe discourses of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane felicitie, and the way to it in common; others thought it best to apply the generall precepts of goodnesse or decency, to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conditions and persons. A third sort in a meane course betwixt the two other, and compounded of them both, bestowed their time in drawing out the true lineaments of euerie vertue and vice, so liuely, that who saw the medals, might know the face: which Art they significantly tearmed <hi>Charactery.</hi> Their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were so many tables, their writings so many speaking pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, or liuing images, whereby the ruder multitude might euen by their sense learne to know vertue, and discerne what to detest. J am deceiued if any course could be more likely to preuaile; for herein the grosse conceit is led on with pleasure, and informed while it feeles nothing but delight: And if pictures haue beene accounted the bookes of Jdiots, behold here the benefit of an image
<pb n="166" facs="89"/> without the offence. It is no shame for vs to learne wit of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; neither is it materiall, in whose Schoole we take out a good lesson: yea, it is more shame not to follow their good, than not to lead them better. As one therefore that in worthy examples hold imitation better than inuention, J haue trod in their paths, but with an higher and wider steppe; and out of their <hi>Tablets</hi> haue drawne these larger portraitures of both sorts. More might be said, I deny not, of euery Ʋertue, of euery Ʋice: J desired not to say all, but enough. Jf thou doe but reade or like these, J haue spent good houres ill; but if thou shalt hence ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure those Vices, which before thou thoughtest not ill-fauoured, or fall in loue with any of these goodly faces of Vertue; or shalt hence finde where thou hast any little touch of these euils, to cleare thy selfe, or where any defect in these graces to supply it, neither of vs shall need to repent of our labour.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>