<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVL Sr. THOMAS HYRNE Knight; Maior of the Citie of Norwich: Health on earth; in heauen happinesse.</title>
           <author>Younger, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120582_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15834</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120582</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVL Sr. THOMAS HYRNE Knight; Maior of the Citie of Norwich: Health on earth; in heauen happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Younger, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nurses bosome· : A sermon vvithin the Greene-yard in Norwich. On the guild-day when their maior takes his oath. On Tuesday Iune 18. 1616. Preached by the parson of Southwalsham. Hereunto is added, Iudahs penance, the sermon preached at Thetford before the iudges in Lent. Mar. 10. 1616</title>
                 <author>Younger, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. THOMAS HYRNE Knight; Maior of the Citie of Norwich: Health on earth; in heauen happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, to giue you some Testimonie of my good will, I shall hazard to doe I know not what. Infinite are the books in this age: and of the greater number, we may say with <hi>Socrates, I he paper is more worth then the matter.</hi> Of Sermons, how many are extant? For who almost preacheth, that printeth not: In so much as the <hi>Presse</hi> may say vnto the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> in the words of <hi>Esau</hi> to his brother <hi>Iacob; Plurima habeo, sint tua tibi:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 32.9.</note> Keepe that which thou hast, I haue enough. Yet haply, it may be the will of God, in these last and sinfull times, that <hi>our visions should bee written,
<note place="margin">Hab. 2.2.</note> and made plaine vpon Tables.</hi> In so great a multitude, mine, I confesse, might haue well stood out. But when I considered, it was not so much mine, as yours, for whom it was preached: nor so much yours as theirs, before whom it was deliuered, I was at length, not vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, (if it got forth in the crowde,)
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.16.</note> that it might be a <hi>Booke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> vnto <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>the rest</hi> who shall succeede: wherein you may be admonished how <hi>weighty</hi> that office is which you beare; and what <hi>affections</hi> ought to possesse you in the course of your Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let me say therefore in the words of the Prophet: <hi>This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is for you,</hi> and <hi>for those</hi> that come after you,
<note place="margin">Mal. 2.1.</note> in that place of Magistracie, euen this <hi>Precept</hi> of God to <hi>Moses; Carry them in thy Bosome.</hi> I once sent it to the <hi>care,</hi> now I present it to the <hi>eye,</hi> that one way or other it may get to the <hi>heart.</hi> Ʋnto this, I haue added one more, to beare it company: that these two, as the Twinnes of Hippocrates, may fare alike abroad in the world, either to laugh or mourne together. Both these I send and commend vnto you, and you vnto the <hi>word of his grace,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> who is able to build you further, and to giue you an inheritance amongst them which are sanctified.</hi> Southwalsham, Iune <hi>1. 1617.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships wel-willer, <hi>W. YONGER.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>