<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE
PRINTER TO
THE READER.</title>
           <author>Mylbourne, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120658_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00594</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10731</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120658</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE
PRINTER TO
THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Mylbourne, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cygnea cantio: or, Learned decisions, and most prudent and pious directions for students in divinitie; delivered by our late soveraigne of happie memorie, King Iames, at White Hall a few weekes before his death</title>
                 <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 41, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb n="39" facs="24"/>
   <head>THE
PRINTER TO
THE READER.</head>
   <p>COurteous Reader, this Relation inclosed
in a Letter to the D. of W. was shewed to
King <hi>Iames</hi> our late Soveraigne of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
memorie and order was given by his Majesty
for the present printing thereof: it was licenced
for the Presse, and entred for my Copie, Ian. 19.
1625. with an Epistle Dedicatory prefixed to his
most excellent Majestie that now is, shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
his Coronation. Since which time (the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
not urging the printing thereof) I let it lye
by me, and imployed my selfe in printing divers
other bookes which were then more sought after;
whereby I hoped in some measure to repaire that
exceeding great losse which I sustained by <hi>Fire,</hi>
in the burning of M. <hi>Elton</hi> his booke on the ten
Commandements, and Lords Prayer, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
losse (in that kinde) that ever any Stationer
received: for I had taken from me almost nine
hundred bookes, bound and in quires. which
(with my<note n="*" place="margin">Albeit for my releasement I was and will acknowledge my selfe much obliged to a great and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Prelate in this Church.</note> Imprisonment, and other charges)
cost me above threescore and ten pounds.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="40" facs="25"/>
And though I have since beene beholding to
my good friends for some good Copies, that would
have helped to make me whole againe, (if they
might have passed freely without checke or rub)
yet I found, to my great disadvantage, that the
Informer, who so persecuted M. <hi>Elton</hi> after his
death, held on his course to calumniate the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
of my friends living, and to procure them
either to be altogether suppressed or to be so gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
and mangled, that the sale of them thereby
was very much hindred: Neither was hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
to doe me and my friends this wrong while
he hovered here about London for such preyes,
but since his flight into the <hi>North,</hi> he triumphed
and boasted at the table of a great personage, that
<hi>he had procured</hi> Pelagius Redivivus <hi>to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
in, and utterly suppressed; and that 300.
of them were taken from the Printer.</hi> But
herein hee was not his crafts-master, but was
<hi>Cousened</hi> himselfe: for though a great number
of the Copies of that Worke were taken from me,
upon his clamor, and delivered to the Bishop of
London that then was, yet they were all given me
backe againe: and by the stirre hee made about
them, they were much more inquired after and
sold the better, being called for even from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motest
parts of Scotland.</p>
   <p>As for this Relation, I feare not his, nor any
others mis information, which had (three yeeres
agoe) not onely the approbation of divers reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
Divines▪ but also of the most learned Prince
King <hi>Iames;</hi> there being nothing contained in
<pb n="41" facs="25"/>
it, but that which tendeth to the glory of God,
and the honor of that religious King; who shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
his constancie in the true Religion established,
and his Zeale for it, as well against the Papists,
as other Heterodox Opiners even to the death.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Mylbourne.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>