<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Preface of Maister Iohn Auenar, Doctor of Di∣uinitie, and Publike Professor of the Hebrue tongue in the Vniuersitie of Witeberge, taken out of his Epistle before his Booke of daily Praiers, dedicated to the most mightie Prince, and Duke, Au∣gustus, High marshal of the Romane Empire, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120167_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12582.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120167</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Preface of Maister Iohn Auenar, Doctor of Di∣uinitie, and Publike Professor of the Hebrue tongue in the Vniuersitie of Witeberge, taken out of his Epistle before his Booke of daily Praiers, dedicated to the most mightie Prince, and Duke, Au∣gustus, High marshal of the Romane Empire, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The enimie of securitie or A dailie exercise of godly meditations : drawne out of the pure fountaines of the holie Scriptures, and published for the profite of al persons of any state or calling, in the German and Latine tonges, by the right reuerende Maister Iohn Auenar, publike professor of the Hebrue tonge, in the famous Vniuersitie of VViteberge; In Englishe by Thomas Rogers Maister of Artes and student in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Habermann, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 359, 7 + pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>¶ A Preface of Maister <hi>Iohn Auenar, Doctor of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie,</hi> and Publike Professor <hi>of the Hebrue tongue in the Vniuersitie of</hi> Witeberge, taken out of his Epistle <hi>before his Booke of daily Praiers, dedicated to the most mightie Prince, and Duke, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus, High marshal of the Romane Empire, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chosen vessel of God, Saint Paule in his former Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vnto Timothie, doth exhort, <note n="a" place="margin">1. Timo. 2, verse. 1. &amp;c.</note> that first of al, deprecations, supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, intercessions, and giuing of thankes be made for al men: For Kings, and for al that are in aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that we may leade a quiet and peaceable life, in al godlines and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie. Likewise vnto the Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans he saith <note n="b" place="margin">Philip. 4. verse. 6.</note>, be careful for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in al things let your peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be manifest vnto God in praier


<pb facs="13"/>
and supplication, with giuing of thankes.</p>
   <p>By which words we are not onely<note place="margin">Kindes of praier.</note> pricked forward vnto the Godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of praier, but admonished be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, that there be foure kinds ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, al necessary to be vsed euery day. The first are Deprecations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<note place="margin">1. Deprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what;</note> we beg at the hands of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, either altogither to turne away his heauie displeasure concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued through our sinnes, or at the least to mitigate the punishments due for our offences. Supplications<note place="margin">2 Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what;</note> are called requestes, wherby we craue such things as are necessarie either for the sustentation of this present life, or for our euerlasting comfort in the worlde to come. Intercessions<note place="margin">3. Intercessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what;</note> are praiers made in the behalfe of others. By thankesgiuing we praise<note place="margin">4. Thankesgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing what;</note> God, and celebrate his holie name for al benefites conferred both vpon our soules and bodies.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>In this my Booke I haue had spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial<note place="margin">Th'order of this Booke.</note> regarde vnto these foure kinds of praier. For first, for euery day of<note place="margin">1</note> the weeke I haue made a morning praier, containing both a thankesgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for the blessed rest receaued, and a deprecation for the escaping of al euils which may happen in the day time. Afterwarde followeth a<note place="margin">2▪</note> thankesgiuing for some singular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite receaued. Then two supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note place="margin">3, 4.</note> or petitions, for blessinges as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel eternal as temporal. Next vnto<note place="margin">5, 6.</note> them are placed two intercessions for men of euerie state or degree. After them ensueth a praier a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst<note place="margin">7</note> the sondrie enimies of Christs Church. And last of al, an euening<note place="margin">8</note> praier, containing a thankesgiuing vnto God for his preseruing of vs in the day time, a deprecation that no euil hurt vs in the night, and a petition of his fatherlie protection, is annexed.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="14"/>And this manner I haue obserued<note place="margin">Daily prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is inioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs.</note> in distinguishing the praiers for euerie day. For it is our partes daily in al our necessities to cry vnto God, as our Sauior teacheth to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 18, 1.</note> Praie alwaies, &amp; be not wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, And Saint Paule willeth the same, saieng, Praie <note n="d" place="margin">1. Thes. 5, verse. 17.</note> continually, in al things giuing thanks. For this is the wil of God through Iesu Christ toward you. Againe, <note n="e" place="margin">Eccles. 18, verse. 21.</note> be not let to praie alwaies, and be not let vnto the death to exercise thy selfe in righteousnes. Thus did the kingly prophet Dauid, which of himselfe saieth, <note n="f" place="margin">Psal. 119, verse. 164.</note> seauen times a day doe I praise thee, because of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgements.</p>
   <p>And certes it is a goodly worke to<note place="margin">A noble exercise to praie.</note> cal vpon God in praier, and to enioy his familiar speech: The which also Saint Ambrose witnesseth, saieng,<note place="margin">Ambrose.</note> To praie much and often is a worke grateful to God. Howe excellent a


<pb facs="14"/>
thing it is for man to intermingle<note place="margin">Praier ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs to the blessed company of the Angels in heauen.</note> his talke with God, no man is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and that excellencie is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by praier onely, which ioineth vs to the societie of Angels, through ascribing due praise and glorie vnto Almighty God, as their office doth binde them. Hence doth the Psalmist say: <note n="g" place="margin">Psal. 138. verse. 1.</note> In the sight of Angels wil <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sing praise vnto thee, I wil worship toward thy holy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and extol thy name. For in other<note place="margin">To praie, &amp; to praise God, a thing common to men with Angels.</note> things there is much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene their condition and ours, whether we respect their nature, or their kinde of life; their wisedome, or their vnderstanding, but to praie is a worke common both to Angels and men. For praier doth seperate vs from brute beastes, and associate vs with Angels, Yea, an easie matter is it, for one to attaine to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, dignitie, wisedome, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, if al his life time, he giue


<pb facs="15"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="16"/>
himselfe wholy vnto praier, and the<note place="margin">The como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie which the dailie exercise of praier doth bring.</note> seruice of God. For if they which frequent the companie of wise men, by reason of their continual mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, in short space are so changed, that they represent the wisedome of such as they company withal: what shal we saie of them which dailie talke with God in praier? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behooueth vs, obeieng the wil of our Heauenlie Father, to spende our life time in the lauding of God, and in deuout meditations. But he which neither wil praie, nor<note place="margin">The state of him which vseth not to praie.</note> praise God, neither yet delight in this diuine communication, surelie liuing he is dead without life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ense or vnderstanding, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth Saint Chrysostome.</p>
   <p>The frute and profite coming by<note place="margin">The frute and profit of faithful praier.</note> godly praiers doth Saint Iames ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse on this manner: The praier of faith <note n="h" place="margin">Iam. 5, 15.</note> shal saue the sicke, and the Lord shal raise him vp, and if he


<pb facs="16"/>
haue committed sinnes they shal be forgiuen him, &amp;c. Againe, <note n="i" place="margin">Iames. 5, vers. 16. &amp;c.</note> The feruent praier, of a righteous man auaileth much, Elias was a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<note place="margin">1. Kings. 17. verse. 1. Eccle, 48, 1. Luke. 4, 25.</note> infirmities, euen as we are, and he praied in his praier that it might not raine, and it rained not on the earth, by the space of three yeres and sixe moneths. And he praied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and the heauen gaue raine, &amp; the earth brought forth hir frute.</p>
   <p>By these words it appeareth that<note place="margin">The force of faithful praier.</note> the praier of faith can obtaine, and bring to passe al things, belonging either to the safetie of the bodie, or saluatiō of the soule. As <note n="k" place="margin">1. Sam. 30, verse. 4. 2. Sam. 5, 19</note> that king and Prophet Dauid by praier repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the horrible crewe of his mortal enimies. So in like maner <note n="l" place="margin">4. kings. 19 verse. 15.</note> Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the King of Iuda, Ierusalem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing besieged by Sennacherib King of<note place="margin">2. Chro. 32, verse. 20.</note> the Assirians, gathered not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of soldiours, but onely went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst<note place="margin">Eccles. 48, verse. 20.</note> his enimies in praier, preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led


<pb facs="17"/>
against them, and preserued the<note place="margin">2. Kings. 20 vers. 3, &amp; 5. Esaie. 38, vers. 2, &amp; 5. 2. Chro. 32, verse. 24.</note> Cittie with the vtter ouerthrow of his aduersaries: Likewise by his humble praier he escaped death, and faithful supplication prolonged his daies. This made Saint Augustine to saie, <note n="m" place="margin">Augustin. Nothing should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maie a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian from praieng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</note> The praier of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is the keie of heauen, The praier of the godlie doth ascende, and the mercie of God doth come downe.</p>
   <p>So that knowing the dignitie of<note place="margin">Though of our selues we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie to open our mouthes in the presēce of God▪ yet through the grace of Gods holie Spirite, wee are embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened so to doe.</note> this familiar talke with God, and considering the commoditie which cometh thereby, me thinkes nothing should dismay a Christian from cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon God. For notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it exceede the power of man to reason with God: yet doth the holy spirit dwelling in the faithful helpe our weakenes, and not onely embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth vs to approche before his Maiestie, but also maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession for vs <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 8, verse. 26.</note> with groanes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakeable. As we reade that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men


<pb facs="17"/>
being of nature weake vessels, oftentimes by praier haue apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, &amp; detained him, <note n="o" place="margin">Matt. 15, vers. 22. &amp;c.</note> as may appere in the woman of Canaan.</p>
   <p>Finally so many occasions are<note place="margin">The necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of dailie and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual praier.</note> there to mooue, and stir vs daily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to praier, that sufficiently they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expressed. And if at any<note place="margin">Other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses mouing vnto prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you shal finde in the Epistle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatorie.</note> time often praier were needeful, I perswade my selfe, that nowe in this last and olde age of this doting worlde, wherein as more grieuous and wofull wickednes doth raigne than at any time: so it is to be feared that in the Church more horrible punishments, and in common weales more miserable confusion wil ensue, than euer did, it should be practised; which euils can by no other meanes be auoided, but onely by dailie, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, and faithfull praier.</p>
   <p>The fountaine of al true wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and learning God almightie, continue among vs for his Sonnes


<pb facs="18"/>
sake the puritie of his worde toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the studie of good letters, maintaine peace and concorde in his Church, and make vs al continually to addict our selues to aduance his glorie both in deede and worde, and to benefite his Church to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of our power, that liuing alwaies in his feare, we may die in his fauor, and rise againe to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes.</p>
   <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>