<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120908_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09551</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19830</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120908</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere made by one of our brethren, a secular priest, now in prison, to a fraudulent letter of M. George Blackwels, written to Cardinall Caietane, 1596, in commendation of the Iesuits in England</title>
                 <author>Philalethes, Andreas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here commend vnto you, (good Catholicke Reader) this Treatise following, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a Catholick Priest, in answere of a letter written by M. <hi>Blackwell,</hi> about fiue years since, to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Caietane.</hi> In which treatise, the authour amidst many of his greefes, a little to sollace himselfe, doth play with the said M. <hi>Blackwel;</hi> but vvith such modestie as well becommeth his calling, the vanitie and falshood of the partie he dealeth vvith, considered. Which two qualities, together vvith his rude pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous Epistolizing to <hi>Graces,</hi> doe so anatomize the man, as I could not let him passe vncoated vvith a Preface, agreeing to the treatise: as not knowing, neither hauing euer been taught, to call a tree by any other name than a tree; a gull, a gull; a Coridon, a Coridon, <hi>Et sic per omnies casus cum stulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>plena sunt omnia.</hi> I can say no more, but that of Iesuitisme there is too great plentie in England, the more is the pittie, and the greater is like to be our miserie. For as I hear say, <hi>Tom Long</hi> Carier is comming on his ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney (in the vvide vvay to perdition) vvith Antichrist: and it is further reported, That the Iesuits, Puritanes, Iews, Turks, Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans, &amp; others of that rable, striue for the supremacie, vvhich of them should first own him, to make him the great Muster-maister vnder <hi>Damp-Sathanas,</hi> in his dismall march to make the conquest ouer the kingdom of Iesus: which is the mark al these do shoot at.</p>
   <p>Well, it is a strange case, that the Iesuits should bee such fellowes; but much more strange, that good M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> is become so rude ruricall courtly, insalutatiue scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to princes: or rather <hi>Caesar</hi>-like take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him vvith <hi>Vene, vide, vici,</hi> to send abrupt apostrophall congratulations to Cardinals: but most strange of all, is this, That a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densed multitude of populorums, vvil not or cannot see vvood for trees; but vvill still call chalke, cheese; beasts, men; moldhils, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines: and so backward againe, and all by
<pb facs="3"/>
contraries. But seeing it is so, <hi>Pian piano,</hi> I haue here laid down before your eyes the <hi>Crow Black well</hi> suited in sables, set vpon a stake, in pale proper, pinyoned, as it vvere the vvhile, vntill you may blazon the Cras croaking foule in her owne pure naturals.</p>
   <p>And to complie a little more formally with the text, you shall (gentle Reader) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that this <hi>Black-wel-mand</hi>-Statist in comporting of Cardinals vvith vncourtly complements, was (as it seemeth) in such a sweuen vpon the suddain, of an odde cōcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Monarchie, as he imagined himselfe to be Monos; though in very deed hee is but a Iesuits Spanified Monopolos: that is in plain English (abstract from all Hyperboles and Rhetoricall figures) the extortionall tythes and imposts, or rather the very dregs, or a grosse Chaos, <hi>Rudis indigestaque moles, non bene iunctarum discordia semina rerum</hi> of all the Iesuits Machiauelian drifts, Prothenian plots, and Catelinian countermined con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies, for a conquest. Which vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of that matter in these men, is now made so apparent, as a very Ninnie cannot but perceiue it, and the blind tankerd-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, with helpe of his dogge and his bell,
<pb facs="4"/>
may smell it out at midnight. For otherwise why doe they of the Spanish faction gape so much after newes out of Ireland? Why doe they linger and dally off the time in the Low countries, without comming to any se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious parle, or consent to make satisfaction for their misdeeds, and restitution of Priests and Princes good names, and other wrongs done by them? Why doe they band it out with Spanish souldiors at Kinsale and other places, new fleets stil flocking afresh thither? yea, and giue it out in plaine tearmes both by vvord and vvriting, That they vvill neuer come to anie agreement, peace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, vntill they heare an end of the Irish vvarres? Why should they bend all their vvits to these desperate traiterous courses, vnlesse their stratagemicall instigators, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding that M. <hi>George Blackwell</hi> is of late summoned to appeare vvhere he vvould not; they thereby saw their Arche readie to fall, and their Top-gallants in daunger to break their necks from off their loftie stand: the verie imaginarie opinion vvhereof, hath amated them with so desperat amazements; on the one side, their guiltie conscience tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting them, for banding a bad cause; and
<pb facs="4"/>
on the other side an enuious feare of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie successe to the secular cleargie, in their appeale to the supreme Patriote of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolick See, and mother citie; causing them in defence of the Catholick Roman church and Common-wealth of Christendome in generall, and of Englands little church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, and vveale publicke, in speciall: as that hereupon, and for and through their many other practises their heads are stuffed vvith so many quiddits, as they quarter and braue it out euery where (but especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the seas) with the great hopes they haue of making England a Iaponian Island by conquest of Ireland, according to the old prophecie, <hi>He that England will win, through Ireland he must come in.</hi> What man, Ireland? Yea, I say Ireland. What, Ireland woon from her Maiestie? yea, and from <hi>Teron</hi> too? Tush man, it is a ieast. Well, a ieast it may be tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in respect of the Iesuits fantasticall assurance: but they goe about it in such sad earnest, as all the vvorld may now dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne them to bee ranke traitours: and they so persuade their fautors, as all the Iesuited faction stand so much vpon their puntoes, in hope of these Lucian tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that they vvill neuer yeeld to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellants
<pb facs="5"/>
(as some of thē haue alreadie blabd it abroad) vntill Ireland be vvholly theirs, or else all the poore Spaniards haue an Irish tricke plaied them in a triple turne betwixt their heads and their shoulders. But vvhat said I, will they be desperate? Yes verily, for they haue no other meanes in the vvorld to feed their faction with, but the hope of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land onely, as their case now stands. O huge! be these religious Iesuits? Well, well, I see all is not gold that glisters, nor all pure Saints that haue Puritanes faces: but, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there leauing these martiall Iesuits to their pikes, let me returne my pen vpon good Maister <hi>George</hi> his Epistle to Cardinall <hi>Caietane;</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which, according to the ensuing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, I haue made a Preface as you see, from point to point vnlacing it in forme following.</p>
   <p>I haue deducted, or rather reducted, all the lines of this spruze <hi>Black-well</hi>-beseene-Oratours Letter, <hi>gradatim;</hi> not oblique, but direct, comformable to the Epistle it selfe▪ euen from the circumference thereof, to the centre: that by the exenterating of it, you may peruse and see (as it were in hearing the Anatomie lecture of this new Legifer, read vnto you, brought forth to be vncased and
<pb facs="5"/>
bowelled before your eyes, in open sight) from vvhat manner of braine and vaine the stately stile of this vvorthie <hi>Vlisses</hi> dooth proceed; as also the <hi>Longum, Latum,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundum</hi> of this tropicall Rhetoricians ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, and by consequent the <hi>Quantum</hi> of the whole <hi>Compositum,</hi> I meane good master <hi>Blackwel</hi> the protonotorious Arche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. The <hi>Longum</hi> doth consist in this, <hi>viz.</hi> That he thinketh it long, long, long, &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry minute a summers day long, vntill he be such another State, as to whom he writeth: the <hi>Latum</hi> is limited to this, <hi>viz.</hi> That al must thinke him worthy of so princely a dignitie, far and neere ouer the whole latitude of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion: the <hi>Profundum</hi> is the ditch that <hi>Thales</hi> slid into by gazing too much vpō the stars: Into this ditch his admirators are suncke downe dead like stones, by staring on <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dusaes</hi> head too too profoundly: and by consequent (as a man might say by meere chance) they there haue foūd out the <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> of the man, in, <hi>O quanta est inscitia viro.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But will you know the <hi>Quantum</hi> of the man indeed: or rather, his <hi>Tantum</hi> by his <hi>Quantum:</hi> or his <hi>Tantillū</hi> by his <hi>Quantillum:</hi> at a word, he is a <hi>quilibet</hi> to a Iesuits <hi>quodlibet,</hi> vvherein he doth so quadrate with them, as
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Tantum deest quantum est:</hi> and so shall you see the <hi>Tantillum</hi> of his mind, in the <hi>Tantum</hi> of his fellow-like tearmes to so great a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificall <hi>Mecaenas</hi> and princely Prelate in the church, as is a Cardinall. And by inference of corolaries, himselfe being no better than a Pewterers son, and but the Apostolick No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie or Scriuener (of matters from England to Rome; or els, where the great Emperors, <hi>Parsons, Creswel,</hi> and other <hi>Presbiter-Iohns</hi> or great <hi>Chams</hi> or <hi>Mogors</hi> do soiourne &amp; abide) besides his Priesthood, you shall onely find the Iesuits sauors extended towards him, to consist in this, <hi>scil.</hi> in erecting to his function a goodly new glorious-seeming Arche; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they meane to set a stately Pyramis of <hi>Pan,</hi> with a dedication, not to that <hi>Paxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> god (as I imagine) but to their owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular societie with the Ariopagians inscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Ignoto deo;</hi> or vvith this Imprese, <hi>Sic pro Iesuitis.</hi> And last of all, you may hereby see, the <hi>Quantum</hi> of the Iesuits pride; the <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillum</hi> of the Archpriests vvit; and the <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunculum</hi> of both their drifts, practises, and deuises. Now read on, and Iesus blesse you from Iesuits and Arches.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>