<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120489_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00614</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1075</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120489</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The maner to dye well : An introduction most compendiouslie shewinge the fruytfull remembrance of the last fowre things: that is to say, death, hel, iudgement, and the ioyes of heauen. Gathered out of manye good authors, both comfortable and profitable to the dilligent reader. Learnedly instructing howe to prouide for death</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 <publisher>Bamford, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 64, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O stirre vp a more diligence of the inwarden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in vs, our Lorde Iesus putteth foorth this similitud: <hi>knowe you that if the houshold Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew at what time the Theefe would inuade his house, he would surely watche, and woulde not suffer his house to bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi> By this Household is vnderstanded the thoughtes of man, and also the invvarde and outward motions and deedes. VVhich hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde vvoulde be to lasciuious and vvanton, if by the diligence of the Father they vvere not corrected and repressed. For if the father be vvearie of his care, vvho coulde be able to shevve hovve proude and insolent the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes, eyes, tongue, eares, and other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers vvoulde become. This house is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, vvherein this Father dvvelleth, and gathereth together the treasure of vertues, for vvhich he doth vvatche diligentlie, least the house should be broken vp▪ And it is not one, but many Theeues that vvould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this buglary and robbery. For euery ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ice incident vnto it. The cheefe
<pb facs="2"/>Theefe is taken to bee the Deuell, againste whom and all his atmie the saide father (if he be not negligent) doth watche and warde his house: appointing <hi>Prudence</hi> in the firste warde, who vnderstandeth what is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and what is to be kept out. Next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her is placed <hi>Fortitude,</hi> to withstand suche enemies as by her warning he seeth to come neere. And <hi>Iustice</hi> sitteth in the middest, to geue to euerie one his owne. And euerie houre is to bee feared, for it is not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in what houre the theefe wil come. VVe oughte alvvaies to watche, least the sleepe of sinne do vnwares creepe vpon vs. Now these thinges beeing thus ordered, the <hi>Memorie</hi> of <hi>death</hi> desireth to come, in and is suffered to enter, who being demaunded to say what he was, and from whence he commeth. Hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered that he would say nothing except all were commaunded to silence. VVho obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his request, began in this order: <hi>My</hi> name (saith he) is <hi>Memorie of death,</hi> and I foretel you that death is comming. <hi>Prudence</hi> speaking for al, putteth the question, saying, VVher is death? <hi>Memory</hi> ansvvereth, I know where he is, for he draweth very nere, but the houre of his comming <hi>I</hi> knowe not. <hi>Prud.</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>VVho commeth with him? <hi>Mem.</hi> A num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Deuilles bringing with them greate bookes, in which are written the offences of man, and they claime those whose sinnes are written therein, and they will violentlie draw with them both their soules and bodies to hel. <hi>Prudence.</hi> VVhat thing is hell? <hi>Mem.</hi> Hel is a place of vnmesurable sorowes, mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and darknes, there is eternal horror, there is no hope of goodnes nor seperation from euyl. Euery man that is there hateth himselfe and al others. There is weping and gnashing of teeth. There is no voyce there heard but Alas, Alas, Alas, they haue no vvord but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las. The deuelishe tormentors doo tormente and are tormented, and of them there shall neuer be ende nor remedie. Suche a place is Hel, and a thousande times worse. <hi>Prudence.</hi> O God what shall wee doo? My brethren, heare mine aduise, and geue me yours. Be ye faithful, watche and pray, doo good, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the sighte of men, but in the sighte of God. <hi>Temperaunce.</hi> Let vs goo before his face with harty repentaunce, and let vs prayse him in Psalmes. Bee you sober and watche. <hi>Fortitud.</hi> Vpō whom do you stay? Be strong in fayth, Comfort your selues in our Lorde,
<pb facs="3"/>Arme your selues with the armour of God, Take vppon you the harneys of Iustice, the target of Faith, and the sworde of the holie Ghost, which is the word of God. <hi>Iustice.</hi> Let vs lyue sober, iust, and godlie. Sober to our selues, iust to our neighbours, and godlie to God. Let vs not do that to others, vvhich vve vvould not haue done vnto our selues. <hi>Prud.</hi> Behold another Messenger verie comelie and pleasaunt, vvho seemeth to bring some good newes. <hi>Iustice.</hi> Let him come in, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he wyl make vs mery: for this first mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger hath terrified vs. <hi>Prudence.</hi> I vvill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him. Come in. VVho art thour <hi>Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> I am called, <hi>The loue of eternal lyfe.</hi> Keepe silence, for I can not be heard vvhere tumult is. <hi>Iustice.</hi> Yf vve did keepe silence vvhilst the <hi>Memory of death</hi> spake, of iustice we ought to be silent when thou speakest. <hi>Desire of eternal lyfe.</hi> I haue seene such thinges as no man is vvorthy to speake of. I sawe God, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie of the vndeuided Trinitie, but yet as it vvere through a glasse: that brightnes vvas so cleare, that mine eyes dasled to beholde that clearenes vvhich passeth all vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Yet notwithstanding I behelde a litle vvhyle our Lorde Iesus sitting on the right
<pb facs="4"/>hande of his father, who did so farre excel all creaturs, that the Angels themselues desire to beholde and looke vpon him. And I sawe vppon his bodye the woundes of his passion, wherewith he redeemed vs. But not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any long time to looke vpon this bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the sonne of God, I turned mine eyes vpon the orders of Angels, that stand before God. I behelde also the Prophets, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and Martirs, and an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of blessed Soules, from whose eyes God hath wasshed awaie all teares: they doo see the king in his Maiestie, and were all appareled in long white garmentes, lyuing a lyfe without ende.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>