<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVE, SOVND, AND HOLY CHVRCH OF GOD; wheresoeuer warfaring vpon Earth.</title>
           <author>H., J.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr37_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVE, SOVND, AND HOLY CHVRCH OF GOD; wheresoeuer warfaring vpon Earth.</title>
                 <author>H., J.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="330"/>
   <pb n="627" facs="330"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVE, SOVND, AND HOLY CHVRCH OF GOD; <hi>wheresoeuer warfaring vpon Earth.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present vnto thee (deare, and holy Mother) this poore vnworthy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of my loue and loialtie; the not so pleasing, as true report of thy fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture broiles. How much gladder should I haue beene (if thy Spouse had so thought good) to haue beene the messenger of thy Peace and securitie! But since the great, and wise Moderator of all things, hath thought a Palme fitter for thee, than an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue; it is for thee to thinke of victory, not of rest: Thou shalt once triumph in heauen, and rest for all; but in the meane time, here is nothing to bee lookt for, but ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes, skirmishes, tumults: And how cheerefully must thou needs both beare and ouercome all oppositions, that art not more sure of the necessitie of thy warfare, than of the happinesse of thy successe, whilest thou seest thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious husband, not onely the leader of this field, but a most iust, and mercifull crowner of thy Conquest. Certainly, it is as vnpossible for thee to miscarry, as to sit still, and
<pb n="628" facs="331"/> not fight: Behold, all the forces of heauen and earth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spire, and reioyce to come voluntaries vnto this holy warre of thine, and promise thee a most happy issue: ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse thy selfe therefore (as thou art wont) couragiously to this worke of God: But remember, first, to inquire (as thou dost) of ABEL: Spare no teares to thy desperate Sister, (now thine enemie) and calling heauen and earth to witnesse, vpon thy knees beseech and intreat her, by her owne soule, and by the deare bowels of CHRIST, by those precious drops of his bloudy sweat, by that common price of our eternall redemption, that she would at the last returne to her selfe, and that good disposition, which she hath now too long abandoned; that she would forbeare, any more (as I feare shee hath hitherto wilfully done) to fight against God: but if shee shall still persist to stop her eares against thee, and to harden her selfe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against her God; forget (if thou canst) who shee once was; and flie mercilesly vpon this daughter of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall,</hi> that vaunts her selfe proudly in the glory of her mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; Goe, smite, destroy, conquer, and reigne, as the worthy partner of thine husbands Throne: For mee, I shall in the meane time be as one of thy rude Trumpets, whose noise shall both awaken thy courage vnto this spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall battell, and whose ioyfull gratulations shall, after thy rich spoiles, applaud thine happy returne in the day of thy victory.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>J. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>