<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN God, IOHN, Lord Bishop of Saint Asaph, and to the Right VVorshipfull, the truly Honoured Sir IOHN WYNNE Knight and Baronet; all grace and hap∣pinesse in this life, and eternall hap∣pinesse in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120026_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15447</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25719</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN God, IOHN, Lord Bishop of Saint Asaph, and to the Right VVorshipfull, the truly Honoured Sir IOHN WYNNE Knight and Baronet; all grace and hap∣pinesse in this life, and eternall hap∣pinesse in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seuen goulden candlestickes houlding the seauen greatest lights of Christian religion : shewing vnto all men what they should beleeue, &amp; how they ought to walke in this life, that they may attayne vnto eternall life by Gr: Williams Doctor of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gryffith</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 468, 471-617, pages 596, pages 609, 618-744, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN God, IOHN, Lord Bishop of Saint <hi>Asaph,</hi> and to the Right VVorshipfull, the truly Honoured Sir IOHN WYNNE Knight and Baronet; all grace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse in this life, and eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Reuerend Father:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Write not this vnto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship by base flattery, to beg any thing of you; for I doe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour alwayes to support my meane estate by meditating on the Apostles lesson, <hi>in any state to be contented;</hi> and I know, that as we came naked into this world, so we shall all returne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hence againe: but I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to affixe these few lines vnto these my poore labours, to assure the world of mine vnfained ioy to see your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship placed in that seate of gouernment wherein you are, in a certaine hope, that (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> said of <hi>Timothy</hi>) according to the prophesies that went afore of you; that is,
<pb facs="8"/> the Propheticall expectation that all men conceiued of you; and the faire promises that your Religious and alwayes vpright carriage hath made vnto vs; your Lordship will be a great comfort, and a Diuine blessing vnto that whole Diocesse wherein you liue. I know it is the practise of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I dare not say of any Bishop, either basely to sell their spirituall promotions, or sinisterly to bestow them on their friends, their kinsmen and alliances; and yet I say not the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth imitate that painted Harlot of <hi>Babylon,</hi> nor that <hi>Ierusalem</hi> iustifieth <hi>Samaria;</hi> but as <hi>Demodocus</hi> said of the <hi>Milesians,</hi> they were no fooles, and yet they did the same things that fooles did; so I feare that we may say of many in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> we are no Pagans, no Popes, no Papists, no worldlings, no carnall men; and yet though I say not that any man doth ill, yet I doubt wee doe not all well, not much better then they vse to doe herein. I confesse the Apostle noteth it as a vice of the latter times, to be without naturall affection; but if gifts blinde the eyes of the wise, that they peruert iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I doubt not but this carnall loue of flesh and bloud will sometimes with <hi>Mydas,</hi> preferre <hi>Pan</hi> before <hi>Apollo:</hi> and this naturall affection to kinred, being vnworthiest, will not onely deiect the mindes of painefull men, and cause men rather to seeke to be allied to others, then to attaine vnto any worth in themselues; but it must also turne to the hurt and detriment of the whole Church of God, and doth apparantly shew such spirituall Patrons to be indeed car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded; for <hi>do not the Publicans and Sinners euen the same?</hi> and therefore though I wish all men to abound in loue and affection vnto their Kins-folkes, yet in this case, I would to God that all of vs,<note place="margin">Deut. 33 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>8.</note> wold imitate <hi>Leui,</hi> who saide vnto his father, and to his mother, I haue not seene him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he acknowledge his brethren, nor knew his owne children, but obserued Gods word, and kept his couenant,
<pb facs="8"/> that we would set God alwayes before our eyes;<note place="margin">Neither doe I say this to deny that men should doe for their kinsfolke being worthy men, but that they should not doe this, neglecting others farre more worthy.</note> and laying aside all sinister respects, would doe onely what should be most for Gods glory, for the encouragement of painfull Preachers, and for the best benefit vnto the people of God: for if Christ being lost by <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Ioseph</hi> could not bee found among his owne friends and kins-folkes, these men should take heed they finde him not among theirs. I could say more of this point, and yet not so much as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> saith vnto <hi>Eugenius,</hi> of many other points like to this: but this will serue to be a witnesse against some at the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, and perhaps to stirre vp as much rage against my selfe, as the Iewes had against Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> for speaking this truth against them that vse such dealing against God: If it doth, I say as Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> said of the rage of that cruell Empresse: If they keepe me poore, I know Christ had not an house to put his head in; if they silence me and thrust me out of their Sinagogue; so was that poore man that confessed Christ, and the Apostles inioyned not to speake in the Name of Christ; if they cast me into prison, so was <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and many more; If I be forced to flie my Countrey, I haue that beloued <hi>Iohn,</hi> and that <hi>Atlas</hi>-like <hi>Athanasius</hi> for presidents of the like vsage, or whatsoeuer else should be done vnto mee, I haue the holy Martyres for my fellow sufferers, and I will neuer count my life deere vnto me, so I may finish my course with ioy; but I will by Gods helpe, be euer ready, with all my heart, to suffer any thing for the Name of Iesus Christ, and for the least iot of his truth. But I doe much reioyce in that assured confidence which I haue, that your Lordship will herein, as well as in all other points of true piety, be an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly shining light and president vnto all other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and succeeding Bishops, and other Patrons whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer; and to that end my prayers shall euer continue for your Lordship.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>And for you my most worthy friend, and neuer to be forgotten Benefactor, Sir <hi>Iohn Wynne,</hi> I must, because I may truely say of you with the Poet, <hi>Ego te intus &amp; in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te noui,</hi> I am so intimately and inwardly acquainted with your very heart &amp; affections, most earnestly pray to God for your long continuance amongst vs: not onely because of your continuall loue and fauours vnto me and mine, but especially to be, as you haue beene hitherto, the chiefest pillar of ciuill gouernment, the best relieuer of our poore and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the most apparant patterne of all good workes of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and charity in all these parts wherein you liue: and you haue not lost your reward; for God hath blessed you and your Lady with many blessed children, all fearing God; I said enough, though I could truely say much more hereof; such a comfort, that not many men haue the like; and God renueth your yeares as the Eagles, and I hope yet will adde vnto your dayes, as he did vnto the dayes of <hi>Ezechias:</hi> and yet this is nothing; <hi>Quia merces tua apud Deum;</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of that great reward which you shall haue of God; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that by continuance in well doing, you shall be sure to haue glory, and honour, and immortality; and therefore most worthy Knight, as I beare witnesse of this truth which I haue seene and know of your Religious heart, fearing God, full of good, so I say vnto you, as Christ saith vnto the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> Goe on in your course of godlinesse, and be faithfull vnto the death, and you shall haue the Crowne of life, when the Lord shall say vnto you, <hi>Euge serue bone, Well done thou good and faithfull seruant, enter thou into thy Masters ioy.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships, and your Worships in all Christian seruice, to be commanded, GR. WILLIAMS</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>