<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120314_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15736</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26005</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120314</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Runne from Rome. Or, A treatise shevving the necessitie of separating from the Church of Rome : Disputed in these termes: euerie man is bound vpon paine of damnation to refuse the faith of the Church of Rome. By Antony Wotton. B.D</title>
                 <author>Wotton, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Councell of Trent confirmed by the Pope, is the chiefe Oracle of the Church of Rome: from it she receiues all doctrines necessarie to be beleeued vnto saluation; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Catholikes hold it for a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that whatsoeuer is deliuered therein for doctrine, is an article of faith, and must stedfastly be beleeued vpon paine of damnation: he that doth not, is pronounced an Hereticke, and is made lyable to a (supposed) heauy curse. What little reason there is that Papists should yeeld such blind obedience to the Canons of that Councell, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by a plaine (but true) testimonie which was giuen thereunto by a Bishop, a member of that Church and Councell, who was present thereat; This testimonie I haue thought good to prefixe to this my Treatise, because in it I dispute against the doctrine of faith deliuered in the said Councell.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Andraeas Dudithius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Quinquecclesiae,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Quinquecclesiae, is acitty in Lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in German <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>rchin in Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nden or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and Embassadour in the Councell of Trent for Maximilan the second Emperour: in an Epistle to the said Emperour, (wherein he deliuereth his iudgement about granting the Cup to the
<pb facs="4"/> Laitie, and the marriage of Priests,) writes thus of the Councell of Trent.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>WHat good could be done in that Councell where voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were taken by number, not by weight? If argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if reason might haue preuailed, if we had had some and those not many to take part with vs, though we should haue bin but a few: yet had vve ouerthrowne the grēat forces of our aduersaries: but when all stood vpon number, wherein we were much inferiour, we could not get the better, though our cause were the better. The Pope was able to set an hundreth of his against euery one of ours: and if an hundreth were not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, he could vpon a sundaine haue created a thousand to succour them that were readie to faint and perish. Therefore we might see euery day hungrie and needie Bishops, and these for the most part beardlesse younkers, and wastfully ryotous, come in flocks to Trent, hired to giue their voices according to the Popes humour, vnlearned indeed and foolish, but of good vse to him for their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciousnesse and impudencie. When these fellowes were ioyued to the Popes old slatterers, then iniquitie got the vpper hand and triumphed: neither could any thing be decreed but according to their liking, who thought it the highest point of religion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the power and royot of the Pope. There was in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell a graue and learned man who could not endure this indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but the Councell by terrour threatning and bayting him as one that was no good Catholike, drew him to yeeld to that which he did no way like of. In a word, things are brought to that passe by their dishonesty who came prepared and made for the nonce, that it seemed to be a Councell not of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, but of puppies: not of men, but of images, who (as it is reported of</hi> Daedalus <hi>Statues) were moued not by their owne but by other mens nerues, and muscles. Those hireling Bishops most of them were like Countrey Bagpipes, which must haue breath blowne into them before they can sound. The holy Ghost had nothing to doe with that Couenticle, all things were argued by human pollicy, which was wholly employed in maintaining the immoderate, &amp; indeed most shamelesse Lordship &amp; Domination
<pb facs="5"/>
         <hi>of the Popet. From thence were answers looked and wayted for, as it were from the Oracles of</hi> Delphos <hi>or</hi> Dodona: <hi>from thence the holy Ghost, who (as they brag) is President of their Councell, was sent shut vp in the Carriers budgets and packes, who (a thing worthy to be laught at) when the waters were vp as it falls out many times, was faine to stay till they were downe againe before he could repaire to the Councell. By this it came to passe that the Spirit was not carried vpon the waters as in</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis, but along besides the waters. O monstrous and incredible madnes! Nothing that the Bishops as it were the Bodie of the Church resolued of, could be of any force, vnlesse it came first from the Pope as the head of the bodie.</hi>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <head>
         <hi>Epigramma</hi> G. B. <hi>de Rome et papa.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>Non ego Romulea miror quod Pastor in vrbe</l>
      <l>Sceptra gerat, Pasto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> conditor vrbis erat,</l>
      <l>Quumque lupae gentis nutritus lacte sit Autor,</l>
      <l>Non ego Romulea miror in vrbo lupos.</l>
      <l>Haectantum superat nostrum admiratio captum,</l>
      <l>Quomodo securum praestet ovile lupus.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>The same translated.</head>
      <l>
         <hi>It is not strange a Shepheard raignes in Rome.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For he that built it, was a Shepheards Groome.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Nor is it strange that wolues in Rome abound.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He suckt a wolse, that did the Cittie found.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But this is strange, and farre aboue my skill,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>How wolues should keepe the flocke secure from ill.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>