<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND EXCELLENT PRINCE, HENRY, PRINCE of WALES, All happinesse.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120194_Fr22_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12635b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120194</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND EXCELLENT PRINCE, HENRY, PRINCE of WALES, All happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorks of Ioseph Hall Doctor in Diuinitie, and Deane of Worcester : With a table newly added to the whole worke</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 468, 6, 13, 3, 471-960, 3, 894-967, 7, 1043-1208, 6, 1231-1397, 29 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="185"/>
   <pb n="357" facs="185"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND EXCELLENT PRINCE, <hi>HENRY,</hi> PRINCE of WALES, All happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MOst Gratious Prince:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et me not (whiles I desire to be dutifull) seeme importunate, in my dedications. J now bring to your Highnesse these my last, and perhaps most materiall Letters: wherein, if J mistake not, (as, how easily are wee deceiued in our owne?) the pleasure of the variety shall striue with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of matter. There is no worldly thing, I confesse, whereof I am more ambitious, then of your Highnesses contentment; which that you place in goodnesse, is not more your glory, then our ioy. Doe so still, and heauen and earth shall agree to blesse you, and vs in you. For me, after this my officious boldnesse, I shall betake my selfe in silence, to some greater worke, wherein J may approue my seruice to the Church, and to your Highnesse, as her second ioy and care. My heart shall be alwayes, and vpon all opportunities, my tongue and pen shall no lesse gladly be deuoted to my gratious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, as one</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Who reioyce to be your Highnesses (though vnworthy, yet) faithfull and obsequious Seruant, IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>