<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Satyre to the meere Courtiers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120366_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68914</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25911</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Satyre to the meere Courtiers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iuuenilia. A collection of those poemes which were heretofore imprinted, and written by George wither</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 308, 313-387, 209 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_hostile_courtiers">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Satyre to the meere Courtiers.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Irs; I doe know your mindes; You looke for fees,</l>
   <l>For more respect then needes, for caps and knees.</l>
   <l>But be content, I haue not for you now;</l>
   <l>Nor will I haue at all to doe with you.</l>
   <l>For, though I seeme opprest, and you suppose</l>
   <l>I must be faine to crouch to Vertues foes;</l>
   <l>Yet know, your fauours I doe sleight them more</l>
   <l>In this distresse, then ere I did before.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Here to my <hi>Liege</hi> a message I must tell;</l>
   <l>If you will let me passe, you shall doe well;</l>
   <l>If you denie admittance, why then know,</l>
   <l>I meane to haue it where you will or no,</l>
   <l>Your formall wisedome which hath neuer beene</l>
   <l>In ought but in some fond inuention seene,</l>
   <l>And you that thinke men borne to no intent,</l>
   <l>But to be train'd in Apish complement;</l>
   <l>Doth now (perhaps) suppose mee indiscreet,</l>
   <l>And such vnused messages vnmeet.</l>
   <l>But what of that? Shall I goe sute my matter</l>
   <l>Vnto your wits, that haue but wit to flatter?</l>
   <l>Shall I, of your opinions so much prize</l>
   <l>To lose my will that you may thinke me wise,</l>
   <l>Who neuer yet to any liking had,</l>
   <l>Vnlesse he were a <hi>Knaue,</hi> a <hi>Foole,</hi> or <hi>mad?</hi>
   </l>
   <l>You <hi>Mushroms</hi> know, so much I weigh your powers,</l>
   <l>I neither value <hi>you,</hi> nor what is yours.</l>
   <l>Nay, though my crosses had me quite out-worne,</l>
   <l>Spirit enough <hi>I'de</hi> finde your spight to scorne:</l>
   <l>Of which resolu'd, to further my aduenture,</l>
   <l>Vnto my <hi>King,</hi> without your leaues I enter.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>