<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults escaped in Printing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120643_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04847</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1498</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120643</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults escaped in Printing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The spirituall architecture. Or, the balance of Gods sanctuary to discerne the weight and solidity of a true and sincere, from the leuitie, and vanitie of a false and counterfeit profession of Christianity. Wherein also the sandy foundations of the papisticall faith are briefely discouered. A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 16. of Nouember, 1623. by Robert Barrell, Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word at Maidstone in Kent</title>
                 <author>Barrell, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 68, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Faults escaped in Printing.</head>
   <p>PAge 2. line 33 for imploy read imply. page 3. line 22. for walles read waters: page 4. line 14, for man read Mammon, page 5 line 30, for certifying reade rectifying, page 6, line 13, read, I wish that my words, &amp;c. &amp; page ead. line 28, for conneyed, reade conueyed: page 8 line 22, for <hi>usullarum vnita,</hi> read <hi>multa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vnitas</hi> &amp; page ead. line 28, for startling, read starting: page 9, line 13, leaue out thereof page 10. line 6. read acknowledge him, &amp;c. page ead. line 28. for Epitom read Epitome &amp; line 29, for section, reade perfection. &amp; line 37. between see, and smell, insert but: page 12, line 6, for Loe reade Hoe, &amp;c &amp; page ead. line 26, for <hi>Solius</hi> read <hi>solus.</hi> page 13, line 2, for mine, reade ruine page 14, line 2, for way, reade wander. page 15, line 2, for phrases, read praises: ibid. line 18, for criri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, aeade criticall. ibid. line 19, for word, read words, page 23, line 27, for till, read while page 30, line 1, for verity, read vnity, &amp; line 23, for vnitie, read vnite. page 31, line 6, for Catholikes, read Cacolikes, &amp; page ead. line 35, for supply, read supple. page 33, line 26, for <hi>sectuntur,</hi> read <hi>secta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tur,</hi> ibid. line 30, for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> reade <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. page 34, line 38, for <hi>Costerius,</hi> reade <hi>Costerus.</hi> &amp; page 36, line 28, ibid. line 26, for sunne read sonne. page 40. line 14, for <hi>vt,</hi> read <hi>vel.</hi> page 41. in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</hi> marg. for Anno 3033, read 303, ibid. page 35, for whhle, read whole, page 45, line 21, for <hi>flaida,</hi> read <hi>fluida.</hi> ibid line 35, for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, page 48. line 9, read <hi>Si restitui potest,</hi> ibid. line 14, for <hi>Colloguintida,</hi> read <hi>Colloquintida,</hi> ibid. line 27, for mind, conscience, reade my conscience Page 50 line vlt, for ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, reade ouerflow, page 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, line 15, for thee read them, page 61, line 18. for irrecouerable. read irreuocable. ibid line 33, for <hi>Sancte,</hi> read <hi>Sancta,</hi> ibid. line 38, for wasted, read roasted, page 64, line 5, for right, read righteousnes, ibid. in marg for <hi>Cypr.</hi> read <hi>Opus,</hi> page 65. line 25, for mine, read ruine, page 67, line 27, for me read one, page 68, line 2, for <hi>malorum,</hi> read <hi>magorum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If thou finde (Gentle Reader) any other faults, either in Orthography or otherwise, I pray thee correct them with thy pen: and let not the Printers errors be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Authour.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>