<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Brian, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120701_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07793</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18170</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120701</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Brian, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology for schoole-masters : tending to the aduauncement of learning, and to the vertuous education of children. By Thomas Morrice, Master of Artes</title>
                 <author>Morrice, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fleming, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing that (gentle Reader) all men are naturally desirous of knowledge: and that many haue bin aduaunced thereby, to Nobilitie, Principality, Regall and Imperiall authoritie. And considering that this knowledge, whether it be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniscentia,</hi> as the <hi>Platonistes,</hi> or <hi>de nouo,</hi> as the <hi>Peripatetikes</hi> doe more truely maintaine: is instilled, and deriued vnto vs originally, &amp; ordinarily by Schoole-masters,
<pb facs="5"/>which are the instrumentall causes thereof, ordayned by Almighty God to that intent and purpose.</p>
   <p>I thought it not amisse, in this short treatise, to incite and stirre vp some, which in this age are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant herein, to a due conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to a more religious respect, to a more requisite vsage, and to a more gratefull remembrance of Schoolemasters. Albeit there be faults in all professions, and in all fortes of people; yet some imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections wee ought rather with <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Iaphet</hi> to couer, then with cursed <hi>Cham</hi> to scoffe at. The swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test rose hath a prickle; and the finest cloth a bracke. I request thee to be aduertised, that I treate here of learned and honest Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, not of vnlearned and disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest intruders into that function.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Abel</hi> will offer sacrifice, <hi>Cain</hi> will
<pb facs="5"/>sacrifice too: <hi>Iacob</hi> will haue a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, <hi>Esau</hi> would haue a blessing: too: <hi>Simon Petter</hi> will worke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> wold do so too: <hi>Constantine</hi> the great wil be a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, <hi>Thraso</hi> will be one to: <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> will be a Schoolemaster, <hi>Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> will be one too. The impes of Sathan, sometimes wil be the apes of the Children of God. I doe not defend irregular, vnlearned, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit persons, which intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and vsurpe the office of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: but approued, learned, &amp; discreete Schoolemasters: which for the benefit of publique-weales are not a little to be regarded. Thus wishing thee increase of vertuous knowledge, I rest euer thy Well-willer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T.M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>