<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH Mighty, Iust, and Clement
Prince, CHARLES King of Great-Brittaine, France, and Ireland,
&amp;c.</title>
           <author>H., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120087_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120087</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH Mighty, Iust, and Clement
Prince, CHARLES King of Great-Brittaine, France, and Ireland,
&amp;c.</title>
                 <author>H., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mercy &amp; truth. Or Charity maintayned by Catholiques : By way of reply vpon an answere lately framed by D. Potter to a treatise which had formerly proued, that charity was mistaken by Protestants: with the want whereof Catholiques are vniustly charged for affirming, that Protestancy vnrepented destroyes saluation. Deuided into tvvo parts</title>
                 <author>Knott, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 299, 1, 206, 6, pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH <hi>Mighty, Iust,</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi>
Prince, CHARLES King of <hi>Great-Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,
&amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Titles (most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne) part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flovving
from your Royall Authority, and partly appropriated to your Sacred Person,
haue by their happy coniunction emboldened me to lay at your Princely Feet, 
<pb facs="3"/>vvith most humble respects, and profound submission, this
REPLY of mine to a Booke, lately vvritten in obedience, as the Author therof
affirmes, to your Maiesties particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Commaund.</p>
   <p>For, though your Regal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may seeme to be an Obiect of
only Dread and Avve; yet doth it not so much auert, as inuite men to a
confident approach, vvhen it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares so svvetly tempered, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned
vvith such rare Personall Qualities as your Maiesties are;
<hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> to all; <hi>Clemency</hi> to euery one of your meanest
Subiects; <hi>ƲƲis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> to discerne vvith quicknes &amp; depth,
and to determine vvith great maturity of Iudgment, betvvene right and vvrong; A
Princely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and iust indignation against <pb facs="3"/>the least
dissimulation, vvhich may be repugnant to the secret testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of
Conscience; An heroicall Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and euen as it vvere a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall kind of
sympathy vvith all Sincerity, and Truth.</p>
   <p>So that, vvhen your Maiesty thought fit to impose a
Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of vvriting vpon one; I could not but conceiue it to be also
your gracious Pleasure and Will, that in Vertue of the same Royal Commaund,
others vvho are of contrary Iudgment, vvere suffered at least, if not
obliged, to ansvvere for themselues; but yet vvith all due respect, and
Christian moderation: Which, I haue as carefully endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to obserue,
as if I had vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the expresse Commaund, &amp; spoken in the
Hearing, and acted <pb facs="4"/>the part of <hi>Truth,</hi> in the presence of
so <hi>Great,</hi> so <hi>Modest,</hi> and so <hi>Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> a
Monarch, as your Maiesty is.</p>
   <p>I vvas therfore supported by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of these your rare
En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovvments of Mind: vvhich, as they are the <hi>Happines</hi> of all your
Subiects; so vvere they no lesse a <hi>Hope</hi> to me, that your
Maiesty vvould not disdaine to cast an eie of Grace vpon this REPLY, not
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the face of present times, but vvith regard to the Plea's of
<hi>Truth,</hi> appearing in times more ancient, and in places more
diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, by the allegation of one, vvho doth so cordially professe
himselfe your Maiesties most humble sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as that from the depth of
a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere hart, and vvith all the povvers of his soule, he vvishes that
God be <pb facs="4"/>no longer mercifull, and good to him, and all your other
Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques Subiects, then they, and he shall both in desire, and deed,
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue themselues vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, sincerely Loyall to the most
Excellent Person, and thrice hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Issue of your Sacred
Maiesty.</p>
   <p>This our Catholique Religion teaches vs to professe and
perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: and heervvith I lay this poore Worke, and prostrate the Author
thereof, at the Throne of your Royall Feet.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble and most loyall
Subiect. <hi>I. H.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>