<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE Most, High, and Mighty Princesse, ELIZABETH, by the grace of God, QVEENE of Bohemia, Countesse Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Wing, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S120119_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15580</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25847</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S120119</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE Most, High, and Mighty Princesse, ELIZABETH, by the grace of God, QVEENE of Bohemia, Countesse Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Wing, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The saints aduantage or The welfare of the faithfull, in the worst times : A sermon, preached at the Hage the 18. of May, 1623. before the most high, and mighty princesse, Elizabeth, by the grace of God, Queene of Bohemia, Countesse Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c. By Iohn Wing an vnworthy minister of the gospel and pastor to the English Church at Flishing in Zealand</title>
                 <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nolck (Nolick), Marten Abrahamsz van der</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Flushing</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE Most, High, and Mighty Princesse, <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> by the grace of God, <hi>QVEENE</hi> of Bohemia, Countesse Palatine of the Rhene, &amp;c.</head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>IOHN WING,</hi> Pastor of the <hi>English</hi> Church at <hi>Flushing,</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> wisheth all encrease of grace, and peace, &amp; whatsoever may enlarge all present hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines <hi>on earth,</hi> and assure that which is eternall, <hi>in heaven.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MOST GRACIOVS PRINCESSE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>nasmuch <hi>as it pleased your most</hi> excellent <hi>Majesty,</hi> to vouchsafe a <hi>Gracious eare</hi> to the weake vtterance of these medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I am comfortablely encouraged to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent a more compleate discovery of them, to your <hi>Princely eyes,</hi> not that I account them worthy (as they are myne) of the <hi>least looke of Majesty;</hi> but trusting <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to that clemency &amp; favour, which I humbly entreate, may thyne from you, vpon this my poore endeavour; it having (next to the honour of the most high God) her only respect, and ayme, at your Majesties present, and furture condition; a true <hi>type</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is here tendered by him, whose soule doth daily sue vnto the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> that as he hath measured vnto, (and you haue shared with,) <hi>Moses,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> many tribulations in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of their honour, and renowne, and after made them so much the more <hi>famous, admired,</hi> &amp; <hi>victorious:</hi> So it, might please the same Lord to alott you the sweete happines of <hi>their</hi> issue, which was most blessed and glorious; to alay the distaste of that bitter beginning, which (vnto nature) seemeth somewhat tarte, and greivous; and together with that peerelesse greatnes
<pb facs="3"/> which they enjoyed on earth, the same glory and joy, which they posesse in heaven. The <hi>Great God</hi> of heaven and earth blesse, with the richest <hi>abundance,</hi> &amp; <hi>combination</hi> of his <hi>rarest,</hi> and <hi>best</hi> blessings, your <hi>Royall Head, &amp; Husband;</hi> your <hi>Highnes,</hi> all your hopefull <hi>Plants,</hi> &amp; <hi>Princely posterity,</hi> that your <hi>Crowne</hi> may yet flourish, your enemyes may ever pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and you all, may be made <hi>mirrours</hi> of <hi>Majesty,</hi> and <hi>Royalty,</hi> to all generations.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your</hi> Majesties <hi>in all duty to be commanded.</hi> IOHN WING.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>