<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The right Honorable my very good Lord the Earle of Southampton.</title>
           <author>Wright, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121118_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15775</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26040</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121118</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The right Honorable my very good Lord the Earle of Southampton.</title>
                 <author>Wright, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The passions of the minde in generall. Corrected, enlarged, and with sundry new discourses augmented. By Thomas Wright. With a treatise thereto adioyning of the clymatericall yeare, occasioned by the death of Queene Elizabeth</title>
                 <author>Wright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                            <distributor>Burre, Walter</distributor>
                            <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 352, 4, 17, 3 pages, folded leaf, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO <hi>The right Honorable my very good Lord</hi> the Earle of Southampton.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome seaven yeares ago (right Honorable) I was requested by divers worthy Gentlemē, to write briefly some pithie discourse about the passions of the minde: because (as they sayd) they were things ever in vse, and seldome without abuse: they were dayly, yea and almost hourely felt no lesse craftie, then dangerous, much talkt of, and as yet never well taught. Their demaund seemed to me so rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, honest, profitable, and delightfull, as I deemed it discourtesie, and incivilitie, not to condescend to satisfie their sute. A treatise hereupon I penned, but I know not how in the inundation of my crosses it suffered ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack with the rest of my writings: and at what time I supposed it had bin lying rotting in the bottome of the sea, a favorable gale brought it ashoare, where being found (belike by some that liked it well) was taken vp, entertayned, and dispersed abroad. When I beheld it, I wondred, and could not tell whether to reioyce to see mine aborted infant revived, or feare whether it had bin maymed and corrupted: for I doubted it had passed by some hands, which might have cavsed me speake in a language I never vnderstood. At last I fell a perusing of
<pb facs="3"/> it, and in deede found, it had not bin hardly vsed, but kindly dealt withall, &amp; what escapes were overslipped, proceeded rather from the vncorrected copie (for of three this was most vnpersit) then from any vncivill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaynement. After that the whole impression was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed, the Printer made meanes to have me adde what I thought wanting, and to amend that I iudged amisse. And so I have augmented this edition with as much more as the first copie conteyned. The which after I had absolved, it seemed of it selfe by a connaturall sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathie to present it selfe vnto your Honour. For literall labours are vsually offered to such personages, with whom they particularly consort: and how could any passions finde out a person more proportionate then your Honour? They concerne Gentlemen and Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to guide them in the way of civill conversation: Your Gentrie is well knowne: they appertayne to souldiours to stirre them vp to courage, and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie: your martiall prowesse are patent at home, and famous abroad. They belong to Magistrates and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, for discovery and manage of subiects: your place, and evident hopes of further preserment presage, that this part cannot but agree to you. For me thinks as often as I consider your presence about his Maiestie, it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me, with mine eyes to behold an other match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse <hi>Parmenio,</hi> for trust and fidelitie about our invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible <hi>Alexander</hi> of the North. Wherefore my passions being provided for Courts, Fields, and Senates, finde in you vnited, that they sought for dispersed: for as it is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>icill to determine which of them hath chiefest part in you, so it is easie for me to resolve how fit this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course is for you, which levelleth at all three. I doubt
<pb facs="3"/> not but I might say to you as <hi>Plotinus</hi> a famous Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher in <hi>Rome</hi> sayd to <hi>Origen,</hi> when he entred into his Schoole to heare him reade, who presently at <hi>Origens</hi> aspect <hi>rubore suffusus,</hi> blushing, ceased to speake: <hi>Origen</hi>
      <note place="margin">Porphyr. in vita Plot.</note> requested him to proceede, <hi>Plotinus</hi> replied, that it was time for a professour to hold his peace, when his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors before-hand knew what he intended to teach. You need not learne of me those things, which both by stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and practise you have attayned vnto: yet it is no small comfort for a man to see, either that he knoweth, confirmed, or that he doeth, approved. If these sillie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours shall content your Honour, I wish no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence: for that which liketh you in this kinde, I know will not dislike the best: and that which pleaseth the best, by right reason, should be a good inducement, to content all. If these blasted leaves be acceptable to your Lordship, when the fruites are ripe, you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a fatter crop: in the meane time Christ Iesus preserve you in his grace, protect you from your enemies, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you from inordinate Passions.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours devoted servant, Thomas Wright.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>