<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The copie of the said Letter, written as touching the Translation of Plinie.</title>
           <author>F., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121936_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20030</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121936</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The copie of the said Letter, written as touching the Translation of Plinie.</title>
                 <author>F., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the vvorld: commonly called, The naturall historie of C. Plinius Secundus. Translated into English by Philemon Holland Doctor of Physicke. The first tome</title>
                 <author>Pliny, the Elder</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 614, 54, 632, 88 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The copie of the said Letter, written as touching the Translation of <hi>Plinie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y beloued, in twentie yeeres and better, so many tokens of our mutuall loue passing betweene vs, I need not now to professe my affection to your selfe; and my daily conuersing with you, hath yeelded my approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your tedious labor in translating</hi> Plinie. <hi>These few lines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shall onely serue to witnesse vnto others the deserued account which for your learning I haue alwaies made of you, and my conceit of this your travaile in opening to your countrymen the treasurie of Nature: therein to see and to admire the wisedome, power, and the goodnesse of the onely true God, the Framer of Nature. I am not of their minds, who desire that all humane learning in Arts and Naturall Philosophie should be reserued vnder locke and key of strange language, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which no other man should haue accesse vnto it: For as such knowledge is a branch of that excellencie wherein man was formed, so the repaire thereof (though it bee not the chiefe) is yet a thing vnworthily neglected, as well in regard of our owne comfort therein gained, as for the glory of God thereby promoted. And it was the wisdome and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hand of the All-sufficient, so to guide the wise heathen in Arts and Nature, that they should publish such their skill vnto their countrimen in mother tongue: partly to correct the rudenesse which is in ignorance, and in part to leaue them the more inexcusable: In</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note>
      <hi>which regard, they may in some sort be called, The Prophets and Teachers of the heathen. And though</hi> Plinie <hi>and the rest were not able by Natures light to search so far as to find out the God of Nature, who sitteth in the glorie of light which none attaineth, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwise</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note>
      <hi>in the vanitie of their imagination bewrayed the ignorance of foolish hearts, some doting vpon Nature her selfe, and others vpon speciall creatures as their God: yet feare we not that Christians in so cleare light should be so farre bewitched by such blind teachers, as to fall before those heathen Idols. Yea, though some of them (as namely</hi> Plinie) <hi>haue spoken dishonourably of the onely true God and of his prouidence, because they knew him not; which speeches (if it might stand with the lawes of Translation) I could wish were vtterly omitted; yet may we hope that Christian men so long taught by the light of grace out of the holy word of God, will no lesse therefore giue him his deserued honour, than when they doe in like sort heare the blasphemie of</hi> Sanneherib <hi>king of Ashur, who sent to</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Reg. 11.</note>
      <hi>raile vpon the liuing God. I feare not the corrupting of vnstable minds any thing so much by these foolish Gentiles which are without, as by the deceitfull spirit of error speaking in the mouth of men within: such I meane as are within the bosome of the Church. These are the foxes by whom we feare the spoile of the Lords vines when as the grapes first begin to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note>
      <hi>cluster; for whose taking I desire that all Gods husbandmen would be more carefull. As for the speeches of these blind heathen, the true Christian may well thereby be provoked to extoll the mercie of God, who sitteth in so glorious a light as hath dasled the sharpest sight of Nature; but for our comfort hath put a vaile vpon his glorie, and by his grace hath so
<pb facs="3"/>
cleared the eye of our vnderstanding, that we might see his face in his beloued, and know him to be the onely true God, and his blessed prouidence vpon all his creatures. And when they shall perceiue that the wisest clearke in naturall skill could not learne by the booke of heauen and earth to know their Maker, whose glorie they declare, and handiworkes set</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>l. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>om. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>out; nor who it was that framed Nature, when by his word he first created them in such</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>excellencie, and then, by his blessing gaue, and by his prouidence working all in all, doth yet maintaine such an operatiue power, as by the which they are still coutinued in their kindes: nor how it came to passe that Nature lost her excellencie in all creatures, and</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen 3. Rom. 8.</note>
      <hi>her power vnto good was not onely weakened (whence we see her faile in many of her purposes) but also peruerted vnto euill; then (I say) they will the more be stirred vp by</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 119. &amp; 147.</note>
      <hi>Gods grace to make reuerent account of the holy Scriptures, which God in rich mercie hath giuen to them to be a light in all things for to direct them through the errors in Natures blindnesse, and to bring them to the heauenly Ierusalem and happie world of all the holie where he dwelleth, whom they worship in vnitie and trinitie. Proceed then my beloued friend to bring vnto the birth your second labour; whereof I pray that God may haue honour in the praise of his works throughout nature, and wish you comfort in good acceptance with the reader, and your countrie vse and pleasure in the skill thereof. Vnto him which onely hath immortalitie and dwelleth in that light which none attaineth, to God only wise be all honour and glorie.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Iunij xij. 1601.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your louing friend in the Lord,
H. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>