<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>T. M. Q. in prayse of this booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121817_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14021</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24328</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121817</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>T. M. Q. in prayse of this booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The noble arte of venerie or hvnting : VVherein is handled and set out the vertues, nature, and properties of fiutene sundrie chaces togither, with the order and maner how to hunte and kill euery one of them. Translated and collected for the pleasure of all noblemen and gentlemen, out of the best approued authors, which haue written any thing concerning the same: and reduced into such order and proper termes as are vsed here, in this noble realme of England. The contentes vvhereof shall more playnely appeare in the page next followyng</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 202, 359-362, 205-248, 4 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>T. M. Q. in prayse of this booke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WHo list to learne, the properties of hounds,</l>
      <l>To breede them first, and then to make them good,</l>
      <l>To teach them know, both voice and horne, by sounds,</l>
      <l>To cure them eke, from all that hurts their blood:</l>
      <l>Let him but buye this booke: So shall he finde,</l>
      <l>As much as may, (for hounds) content his minde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVho list to viewe, what vertues do remaine,</l>
      <l>In euery beast, which Man doth hunt and chase,</l>
      <l>VVhat cures they beare, for many an ache and paine,</l>
      <l>VVhat seasons serue, to finde them best in case:</l>
      <l>VVithin this booke he may the same finde out,</l>
      <l>And so be well resolvde of euerie doubt.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And to be short, as much as <hi>Latine, Greeke,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Italyans, Frencb, High Dutch, or English skill,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Can teach, <hi>to Hunt, to Herbor, lodge, or seeke,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To force, to take, to conquer, or to kill,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>All games of chase: So much this booke descries,</l>
      <l>In proper termes, as wit can (well) deuise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVherefore my Muse, must recommend the same,</l>
      <l>As worthy prayse, and better worth the price,</l>
      <l>A pleasant booke, for peeres of noble name,</l>
      <l>An honest booke to recreate the wise:</l>
      <l>A Booke well bought, God graunt it so be solde,</l>
      <l>For sure such Bookes, are better worth than golde.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tet, quod non patet.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>