<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Forsyth, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121939_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01077</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11191</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121939</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bitter vvaters of Babylon, or The miserable estate of the citizens of Sion : considered by the confusion of all things in this world</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aruell not <hi>(gentle Reader)</hi> that I haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulged these my mean meditations; being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in that Place from whence daily doth drop most sweet honny of diuine eloquence: since that most of the learned that repaire thither, are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to publish their workes; by reason of the multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of printed sermons, that proceed from thence. There be two reasons that induce me heereunto: The one is, the encouragement I had by the <hi>Audience,</hi> that day whereon it was deliuered: And secondly, the vrgent entreaty of many of my especiall friends; vnto whom I owe my selfe and all seruice. Looke not for eloquence, according to thine expectation; proceeding from such an eminent place: <hi>For I came not with eloquence of words; but eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the spirit:</hi> to perswade men and women to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their lewd-led-life, that by their vnfain dcontriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they may preuent Gods visitation in Iustice, for their transgressions, by the example of these <hi>Israelites</hi> beeing captiuated for their offences. If any thing heerein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in thy iudgement, bee too <hi>tart</hi> and <hi>bitter:</hi> Consider with what weapons, I, and all Gods faithfull Ministers, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> come into the field to fight against Gods enemies; the two-edged sword of Gods <hi>Spirit</hi> doth diuide betweene the Carnall and Spirituall man: the stone that <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke
<pb facs="5"/>
vp against <hi>Goliah</hi> did sinke suddenly into his temples. The diseases of these times wherein we liue, require such <hi>corrasiues</hi> and bitter <hi>potions:</hi> for we are like vnto <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> that will not be cured. When thou readest those things; gadde not abroad, nor aime thou not at other men: descend into thine owne Conscience, and feeling thy selfe wounded, apply these warily vnto thine own soule: and so shalt thou be healed of thine infirmity. That this consideration may work some zeale of Gods glory in thee; and that thou mayst daily encrease more &amp; more in the knowledge of his waies, I shall (as by duty bound, vnto all faithfull Christians) daily pray for thy happinesse in this life, and eternall glory in the life to come with Iesus Christ, and his holy Angels. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord<lb/>
IAMES FORSYTH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>