<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir IVLIVS CAESAR Master of the Rolles, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell: Encrease of grace in this life, and eternall happinesse in the life to come:</title>
           <author>R., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121051_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10738</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21017</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121051</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir IVLIVS CAESAR Master of the Rolles, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell: Encrease of grace in this life, and eternall happinesse in the life to come:</title>
                 <author>R., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon against oppression and fraudulent dealing: preached at Paules Crosse, the eleuenth of December, by Charles Richardson, preacher at Saint Katherines neare the Tower of London</title>
                 <author>Richardson, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 38, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir IVLIVS CAESAR</hi> Master of the Rolles, <hi>and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell:</hi> Encrease of grace in this life, and eternall happinesse in the life to come:</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it pleased God to giue better approbation to this poore Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering of it, then I expected: I haue beene
<pb facs="3"/>
earnestly intreated since, by some of my good friends, to giue way that it might bee printed. And though I am not ignorant of mine own inability: yet because I know that God can, and doth worke, as well by weake, as by greater meanes; I haue yeelded to their request. I confesse it is written in a rude &amp; homely stile, and I doubt not, but the curious censurers of this age, who like nothing but that which is for their owne humors, will carpe &amp; cauill at the plainenesse of it: but my desire was to make it appear, that as <hi>Barnard</hi> sayeth, in the like case, I rather sought <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> then <hi>Ostentation.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the meanes of that mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb facs="3"/>
which I haue, is chiefly by your honourable fauour, I haue therefore presumed to publish it vnder your Honours name. And howsoeuer there be nothing in it worthy your Honours contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation: yet I beseech you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it as a poore testimony of that dutiful affection which most deseruedly I owe vnto you. The Lord blesse your Honour with increase of all sauing graces, that you may long be a profitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of his glory, both in the Church, and in the common wealth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all humble duety and seruice, <hi>C. R.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>