<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE SVMMARIE OF THE CHRI∣stian exercise, as it is intended.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121958_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19353</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121958</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE SVMMARIE OF THE CHRI∣stian exercise, as it is intended.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the Christian exercise : appertayning to resolution. VVherein are layed downe the causes &amp; reasons that should moue a man to resolue hym selfe to the seruice of God: and all the impedimentes remoued, which may lett the same</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 431, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE SVMMARIE OF THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian exercise, as it is intended.</head>
   <p>FOR THAT three thyngs are necessarie to a man in this lyfe, for the attayning of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: that is, to resolue hym selfe to serue God in deed: to begynne a right: and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuere vnto the ende: therfore this whole treatise shalbe deuided into three bookes.</p>
   <p>THE FIRST booke shalbe of resolutiō, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two partes. And in the first parte shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be layed downe all the principall reasōs that ought to moue a man to this resolutiō. In the second shalbe remoued all impedimētes that commonlie doe hynder men from the same.</p>
   <p>THE SECONDE booke shall treate of the waye how to begynne well, and shall lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse be deuided into two partes: wherof the fyrst shall shew the waye how to delyuer our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues from sinne, and from the custome, bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage or delectation therof. The second shall open the meanes, how to ioyne our selues perfectlie to God, and to make a right entrā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce into his seruice.</p>
   <p>THE THIRDE booke shall hādle the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of perseuerance, so farre forthe as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth our habilitie, for though this gyft be onelie of god: yet are there two thinges left by his grace to be performed of vs: the one, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke his ayde: the other, to ioyne our endeuour with the same. According to which two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, this booke shalbe deuided also into two partes: The first wherof shall intreate of all kynde of prayer, bothe mētall and vocall. The secōd shall declare the wayes &amp; meanes, how (by help of gods grace) we may resist &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all sortes of sinne, &amp; the tēptatiōs therof.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>