<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all courteous Readers, and lo∣vers of good Horses.</title>
           <author>M., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121248_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06911</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17341</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121248</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all courteous Readers, and lo∣vers of good Horses.</title>
                 <author>M., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The complete farriar, or The kings high-way to horsmanship : Experimentally unfolding 1. The dyeting and governing of the running horse. 2. How to order, feed, and keep any horse for war, pleasure, hunting, or travell. 3. How to know the age of any horse. Lastly, certaine rare and approved secrets for the cure of the worst infirmities in horses. By G. Markam</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Young (Junius), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fisher, Benjamin.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Nevill, Philip</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 170, that is 172, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all courteous Readers, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of good Horses.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His my ensuing Book (which I have stiled, <hi>The complete Farriar,</hi> or the Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to Horsemanship) was some yeares since collected for my own private benefit, and now, by the request of many friends, sent to the view of the World: It being the last of all my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, I will not commend it; yet so far I will allow of it, that it is not inferiour, if not equall to any of my former Bookes. For my bosome receipts, which I practised daily, not knowne to any but my selfe, (and being now aged) I was willing to impart to the benefit of
<pb facs="3"/>
all well-wishers and lovers of Horses, to their posteritie: for these will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive my memorie, when time hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most raz'd out the remembrance of me. And so wishing you all good successe in your experiments, I heartily take leave, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours G. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>