<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121027_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20986</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7361</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121027</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The principall points of the faith of the Catholike Church : Defended against a writing sent to the King by the 4. ministers of Charenton. By the most eminent. Armand Ihon de Plessis Cardinal Duke de Richelieu. Englished by M.C. confessor to the English nuns at Paris</title>
                 <author>Richelieu, Armand Jean de plessis, duc de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cramoisy, Sebastien</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 114 pages, 115-120 leaves, 121-124 pages, 125-126 leaves, 127-335, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing learned of S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine that it is à meere follie to speake without proofe in matter of religion;<note place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>2.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra lit. Piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liani cap. <hi>29.</hi>
      </note> and seeing that the writing, which moued me to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this <hi>defence of the principale points of Faith,</hi> touched all questions, without prouing any one, I was long tyme of opinion, that it rather me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited to be despised then answered.</p>
   <p>But hauing vnderstoode (as it is the custome of the weake to tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe at smale matters, and by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of faigned aduātages, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish victories which they obtayned not) that the pretended Reformers of these parts, sent abroad this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with à florishing vogue, and diuulged
<pb facs="6"/>euery where, that it was an Arsenall, which within à litle cōpasse comprised all the engines requisite vtterly to ruine the truth of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion; and considering with S. Hilaire by how many guiles,<note place="margin">Hilar. in Psal. <hi>64.</hi>
      </note> and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties heresie striues to peruerte faith, I iudged it better to replie, then passe it ouer in silence, and here vpon I resolued to vndertake this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
   <p>My purpose is to discouer.</p>
   <p>That the Ministers of Charenton. are ill grounded in all their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
   <p>That they haue all the reason in the world to commend our Kings, and no occasion at all to complayne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as they doe.</p>
   <p>That their Beleife is not hared for the reasons they alleadge, though worthy of hatred, for many others,
<pb facs="6"/>which cuningly they conceale.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, that the Catholike Church, her Ministers, and all those whom they accuse, remayne free from the crimes which they impose vpon them.</p>
   <p>To effect this, I haue diuided this booke into 19. chap. in the first 14. I satisfie the Ministers writing from point to point. The other fiue are spent in deducing the reasons for which their doctrine ought to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of all the world.</p>
   <p>The Reader may please to know, that studying breuitie in this my answere, I haue no intent, to heape together all that might be said vpon euery point, and yet say enough too to make it impossible for our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, to shake or moue what I shal establish.</p>
   <p>Further let him know, that as often
<pb facs="7"/>as I can possibly, I make vse of their confession of Faith with whom I deale, and of the testimonie of their owne Authours, so that, without blushing and Lying both at once, they shall not be able to call in question the truth which I publish.</p>
   <p>I had tyed my selfe to the onely confession of their Faith, if I had found it as compleate and intire as full of defectes. But wheras they cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne not halfe the points which are in controuersie betwixt vs and those too which they cōtayne being expressed in an obscure, and reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued manner, I was forced to haue recourse to their Authours; to Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin and Luther amongst the rest, whose authoritie they cannot reiect. Not Caluins, because they make thēselues his followers in à peculiar manner; gathering out of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<pb facs="7"/>their confession, their Church-prayers, their Catechisme, and the forme of administring, their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Nor Luthers,<note place="margin">Coelum lib. de Arb nōt Pigkiū. Witak. ad ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians.</note> since they esteeme him the Apostle who reesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished the puritie of the Gospell, and accnowlegde that those who imbrace his doctrine, doe but make vp one Church together with them.</p>
   <p>I beseech the Ministers that if they answere me, they doe it inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously, and giue satisfaction to each point of this booke, so that I may take as confessed all which they doe not contest. I coniure, them that in their answere, they doe ether ingenuously confesse what we hold, or at least, that they make their owne defence without ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie in words. If they giue vs clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vnderstand what their beleife
<pb facs="8"/>is, we shall be greatly obliged vnto them, since we haue ordinarily more difficultie to fish it out then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it:<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Cte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siph. cont. Pelag. Ecclesiae victoria est vos apertè dicere quod senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> which thing S. Hierome had experienced in his tyme speaking to Heretikes in these tearmes. <hi>It is à victorie to the Church, for you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse in cleare tearmes what you hold.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To conclude, the Ministers may please not to esteeme they haue answered sufficiently, if, when I haue alleadged à passage of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours for à thing, they produce another of them who affirmes the contrarie; because they cannot thence cōclude, that they taught not that which I pretend, but onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that it is the customarie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of Heretikes to contradict one another.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>