<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To any that will read it.</title>
           <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121634_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20849</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7229</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121634</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To any that will read it.</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part, or a continuance of Poly-Olbion from the eighteenth song : Containing all the tracts, riuers, mountaines, and forrests: intermixed with the most remarkable stories, antiquities, wonders, rarities, pleasures, and commodities of the east, and northerne part of this isle, lying betwixt the two famous riuers of Thames, and Tweed. By Michael Drayton, Esq</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <distributor>Dewe, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 168 pages, 12 folded plates, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="202"/>
   <pb facs="202"/>
   <head>To any that will read it.</head>
   <p>WHen I first vndertooke this Poeme, or as some very skilfull in this kind, haue pleased to tearme it, this Herculean labour. I was by some vertuous friends perswaded, that I should receiue much comfort and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement therein; and for these Reasons: First, that it was a new, cleere way, neuer before gone by any; then, that it contained all the Delicacies, Delights, and Rarities of this renowned Isle, interwouen with the Histories of the Britanes, Saxons, Normans, and the later English: And further that there is scarcely any of the Nobilitie, or Gentry of this land, but that he is some way or other, by his Blood interressed therein. But it hath fallen out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; for instead of that comfort, which my noble friends (from the freedome of their Spirits) proposed as my due, I haue met with barbarous Ignorance, and base De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction; such a cloud hath the Deuill drawne ouer the Worlds Iudgement, whose opinion is in few yeares fallen so farre below all Ballatry, that the Lethargy is incurable; nay some of the Stationers, that had the Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the first part of this Poeme, because it went not so fast away in the Sale, as some of their beastly and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Trash, (a shame both to our Language and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) haue either despightfully left out, or at least care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lessely neglected the Epistles to the Readers, and so haue cousoned the Buyers with vnperfected Bookes; which these that haue vndertaken the second Part, haue beene forced to amend in the first, for the small number that are yet remaining in their hands. And some of our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landish, vnnaturall English, (I know not how other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb facs="203"/>
to expresse them) sticke not to say, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this Island worthy studying for, and take a great pride to bee ignorant in any thing thereof; for these, since they delight in their folly, I wish it may be heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary from them to their posteritie, that their children may bee beg'd for Fooles to the fift Generation, vntill it may be beyond the memory of man to know that there was euer any other of their Families: neither can this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre mee from going on with Scotland, if Meanes and Time doe not hinder me, to performe as much as I haue promised in my first Song:</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Till to the sleepy Maine, to <hi>Thuly</hi> I haue gone,</l>
      <l>And seene the Frozen Isles, the cold <hi>Deucalidon,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Amongst whose Iron Rocks, grim <hi>Saturne</hi> yet remaines,</l>
      <l>Bound in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> gloomy Caues with Adamantine Chaines.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>And as for those Cattell whereof I spake before, <hi>Odi profanum vulgus &amp; arceo,</hi> of which I account them, bee they neuer so great, and so I leaue them. To my friends, and the louers of my Labors, I wish all happinesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Michael Drayton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>