<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE vnto the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121118_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15775</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26040</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121118</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE vnto the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The passions of the minde in generall. Corrected, enlarged, and with sundry new discourses augmented. By Thomas Wright. With a treatise thereto adioyning of the clymatericall yeare, occasioned by the death of Queene Elizabeth</title>
                 <author>Wright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                            <distributor>Burre, Walter</distributor>
                            <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 352, 4, 17, 3 pages, folded leaf, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE <hi>vnto the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Have divers times weighed with my selfe, whence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from it should proceed that Italians, and Spaniardes, with other inhabitants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eyond the Alpes, should ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lemings, Englishmen, Scots, and other Nations,<note place="margin">Tramontani sem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> dwelling on this side, simple, vncircumspect, vnwarie, easie to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyved, and circumvented by them. And the cause of my doubting was, for that I had perceived, by long experience in Schooles, both in Spaine, Italie, France, and Flaunders; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>emings, Scots, and Englishmen were ever equall, and rather deeper Schollers, than ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Italians or Spaniards, so many for so many: Whereunto we may adde the proofe of former ages, wherein all the worlde will confesse, that our Nation hath yeelded as profound and learned Schoole-men as any Nation vnder the Sunne, in like quantity and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>portion. For, what Countrie in any age did ever represent vnto the world, such venerable w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ttes, as England, by yeelding our venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> who, borne in a corner of the world, comprehended the whole world in his boundiesse apprehension &amp; iudgement▪ what age ever see before our <hi>Alexander de Hales,</hi> a Divine more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rrefragable in all his doctrine and opinions, the chiefe master of Schoole-men, before that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land sent him into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rance? In what Countrie ever appeared such a mirrour of learning, of subtilitie, of brevitie, of perspicuitie, (in deepest matters, and vnto worthy spirites) as when <hi>Scotus</hi> shewed himselfe in the chayre at Oxford? whom, for his worth, some other Countries with no lesse vntrueth, than ambition, have challenged for theirs, and would have bereaved England of one of the worthies of the world, What might I not say of <hi>O cams,</hi> of <hi>Bacons,</hi> of <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,</hi> in forraine Nations more accounted of, than prized at home,
<pb facs="4"/> whose doctrine, the best highly esteeme, whose wittes the wisest ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and whose opinions innumerable Doctors doe follow? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may well glory in this, that our Countrie hath affoorded most of the masters, &amp; of the chiefest Wits, which at this time both Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, Reals, and Nominals do follow, eyther in Philosophie, or Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. And yet for all this, our Nation is accounted simple and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, among divers others.</p>
   <p>Moreover, let vs cast our eyes vpon all sortes of Artes and Trades, from the very shooe vnto the hatte, from the shirte to the cloake, from the kitchin to the Court, and we shall see our Nation as well furnished, as compleate, and artificiall as any other: and as all tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers can well affirme, farre superior to the Spantards, and nothing inferior vnto the Italians. I must confesse, that in some one or other trade, the Italians surpasse vs, but they be such, as eyther England regardeth not at all, or prizeth not very much: but, in such as our Countrie esteemeth, wee may, eyther equall or preferre our selves before them. And yet for all this, a hie-minded companion doubted not, within these few yeeres, to call our Nation, vncivill, and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous▪ and others, to repute vs as simple and vnwarie. After some consideration and reflexion vpon our selves, with reference vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, I found out three causes, why those which inhabit these Northerne Climates, are accounted simple and vnwise.</p>
   <p>The first is, a naturall inclination to Ʋertue and honestie, much more palpable and easie to be perceyved in these colder Countries, than in those hotter Climates: this we may proove by common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, for both Spamards and Italians, if they can have a I lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or an Englishman for their servant, if he be alike qualified with those Country-men, they will preferre him before their owne, for fidelitie, sinceritie and diligence. The very blushing also of our people, sheweth a better ground, wherevpon Vertue may build, than certaine brazen faces, who never change themselves, although they committe, yea, and be deprehended in enormious crimes; for the shame of vice, is a good commencement of Vertue, because it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from a iudgement disliking of evill, which is an apt beginning of good. Wherefore <hi>Aristotle</hi> calleth shamefastnesse a vertue, not<note place="margin">Arist. 3. mora. Nico. cap. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> for that it is a true vertue indeed, (for it most of all raigneth in
<pb facs="5"/> children, who are not capable subiects of morall Vertues) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is the seede of Vertue, or a spurre to Ʋertue, or a bridle from vice: or a way, preparation or disposition vnto an honest vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life. And therefore <hi>Plato</hi> said that iustice &amp; shame fastnes were<note place="margin">Plato in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagor.</note> the giftes of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> This naturall foundation of honestie, other Nations baptize with the Name of Simplicitie, which they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, not in such sort as it resembleth a Vertue, and bordereth vpon sinceritie and vpright dealing, but rather as a vice bending to stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, &amp; lacke of knowledge. The common sort of Spaniards and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talians, censuring our inclinations, with an erroneous iudgement, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that a passion of ignorance, which in very deed, is the first step vnto prudence, esteeming them foolishly vnwary, whom they ought to have reputed rather vertuously wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e.</p>
   <p>The second cause is, Education, for prudence and policie are wonne by experience, experience by practise, practise by conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conversation by communication with people, the which in Citties is better attained vnto then in Villages, and in Citties of greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and resort, than in Cities of lesser repayre. This wee trie by common consent of all men, who acknowledge the inhabitants of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>townes to be more craftie than the rurall colonies, and therefore I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers are iudged most craftie of all, yet my meaning is alwayes, <hi>cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris paribus,</hi> because, as some Ilanders have little trade, so some Citties no great resort. The nature of mens wittes is such, that one whetteth and pollisheth greatly another, for as their faces are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, so their inventions setches, sleights and iudgements are diverse.</p>
   <p>Wherefore those that have great commerce with men, either they themselves; or else see the various dealings and practises of others, cannot but in time greatly perfite their owne iudgements and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings: this we may dayly perceyve in our owne Countrie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Northerne and Welchmen, when they come to London, are very simple, and vnwarie, but afterwards, by conversing a while, and by the experience of other mens behaviours, they become won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull wise and iudicious. The Italians therefore and Spaniards, disdayning greatly to dwell long in the Countrey, and betaking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves almost wholly vnto Cities, by a continuall conversation, even from their youth, become very nimble in the managing all affaires,
<pb facs="5"/> and consequently, very politique and craeftie. For great Citties (spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Emporiall) affoord vnto them all sorts of positique prudenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, eyther for vniversall governement of the State, or particular regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Cittie, or private oeconomie for a family, or common conversation with men: all which Citties, as open Schooles, teach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly; villages and townes, eyther nothing, or very sparingly. The most of our Englishmen contrariwise, eyther dwell in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, or in Citties not so populous, wherein they may enioy such meanes, as enable other Nations vnto the attainement of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t▪ po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, and prudence, wherefore this defect of conversation impeacheth greatly the warines of our Countriemen with other Nations: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by sundry of our rurall Gentlemen, are aswell acquainted with the civill dealing, conversing, and practise of Citties, as many Kockneis, with the manuring of lands, and affayres of the countrey. Our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish youth also, for most part, are brought vp, with too much feare and terrour: for eyther their Parents or Schoole-masters passe the borders of mediocritie in this part: because they eyther punish them too extreamely, or threaten them too severely: whereby th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of pusillanimitie &amp; feare specially when any matter of moment is to be attempted, so distract their present attention, that they cannot almost possibly vpon a sudden consider the circumstances, weigh the matter, and resolve aright: for these restraining Passions witharaw a great part of their soules consideration. The Italians and Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards contrariwise, by bringing vp their children with more libertie, enlarge their hearts with boldnesse and audacitie, in such sort, as v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually you shall see them at sixteene or seventeene yeeres of age, as bold and audacious as ours at thirtie: and contrariwise ours at sixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene or seventeene, drooping with feare and timiditie, as if they were so many chickens drawne out of a Well.</p>
   <p>The third cause is, a certaine naturall complexion and constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of body, the which in very deed inclineth and bendeth them of hotter Countries more vnto craftinesse and warinesse, than them of colder Climates; This we may perceyve in Italy it selfe, where the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mbards are more simple than the Romanes, and these not so craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as the Neapolitanes, not these comparable to the Sicilians. The like we finde in Spaine, where the Biskains are not so subtle as the
<pb facs="6"/> Castilians, nor these so craftie as the Andalusians. Wherefore, as we proove in beasts, that some, by their naturall instinct, are more wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e than others, as Foxes, Monckies, and Apes, so we finde in men, that some surpasse others in aptnes to deceyve, and in craftinesse to circumvent. And in this we may confesse that Spaniards and Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians goe before vs, for commonly they can better conceale their owne Passions, and discover others, than we. Our people, for most part, reveale and disclose themselves very familiarly and easily; the Spaniard and Italian demurreth much, and selleth his secrets and his friendship by drammes, you shall converse very long with him, before you shall know what is in him: he will shew a countenance of friendship, although he intendeth revenge: he can trayne his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses afarre off, to vndermine where hee pleaseth: hee will praise where he spiteth, and disprayse where he loveth for a further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: hee can observe his times better than we for his plots, and marke fitter occasions to effectuate his i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tent: he can winne ground in a mans affection by some small conversation, and after prevaile in what he list, when he hath got the advantage. In sine, he can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble better his owne passions, and vse himselfe therein more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspectly, than we can doe. Wherefore I thought good to trie if a little direction would helpe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur Countriemen to counterpoise their native warinesse, and open the way, not to become craftie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, which is vitious, but how to discover other mens passions, and how to behave our selves when such affections extraordinarily pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse vs, the which is the chiefest poynt of prudence, and fittest mean▪ to attayne vnto religious, civil, &amp; gentlemanlike conversation, which is vertuous. Whereunto especially this discourse of Affections ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, albeit for more compleate doctrine, I have handled almost all those questions, which concerne the Passions in generall.</p>
   <p>But for all this, I would not have any man to thinke that I am of opinion, that all Italians and Spaniards go beyond all Englishmen in subtiltie and warinesse, for I have found divers of our Nation, whom I beleeve, neyther Italian, nor Spanyard c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uld over-reach, in what negotiation soever: but onely I meane that for the most part, those Nations surpasse ours in a certaine politique craftinesse, the which Nature first bred in them, Education per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ited, Vertue amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
<pb facs="6"/> and Art discovereth. The which I have endevoured first of all (as I thinke) to draw into forme and method, according to the principles of Sciences, hoping that some other will hereby take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, eyther to perfite mine, or to attempt a better; my desire is, the good of my Countrie; the effect, every mans prudent carriage; the last end, the glory of God; whereunto all our labours must tend, and all our actions be directect: and therefore, to him let these little sparkes be consecrated, to kindle the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ire in his most holy Temple.</p>
   <closer>&amp; in tremore. sperando.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>