<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE, CHARLES Prince of WALES.</title>
           <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121634_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20849</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7229</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121634</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE, CHARLES Prince of WALES.</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part, or a continuance of Poly-Olbion from the eighteenth song : Containing all the tracts, riuers, mountaines, and forrests: intermixed with the most remarkable stories, antiquities, wonders, rarities, pleasures, and commodities of the east, and northerne part of this isle, lying betwixt the two famous riuers of Thames, and Tweed. By Michael Drayton, Esq</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <distributor>Dewe, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 168 pages, 12 folded plates, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="201"/>
   <pb facs="201"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE, <hi>CHARLES</hi> Prince of WALES.</head>
   <p>THE first Part of this Poeme (most Jllustrious Prince) I dedicated to your deceased Brother of most famous Memorie, whose princely Bountie, and vsage of mee, gaue me much encouragement to goe on with this second Part, or Continuance thereof; which now as his Successor, J owe to your Highnesse. If meanes and time faile me not, being now ariued at <hi>Scotland,</hi> I trust you shall see mee crowne her with no worse Flowers, then J haue done her two Sisters, <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales:</hi> and without any partialitie, as I dare bee bold, to make the Poets of that Kingdom my Iudges therin. If I ariue at the <hi>Orcades,</hi> without sinking in my flight, your Highnesse cannot but say, that I had no ill Perspectiue that gaue mee things so cleerely, when I stood so farre off.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>To your Highnesse 
most humbly deuoted. MICHAEL DRAYTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>