<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his worthy and learned friend Mr THO. FULLER, upon his excellently com∣posed Historie of the HOLY WARRE.</title>
           <author>C., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121250_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121250</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his worthy and learned friend Mr THO. FULLER, upon his excellently com∣posed Historie of the HOLY WARRE.</title>
                 <author>C., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the holy vvarre : by Thomas Fuller, B.D. prebendarie of Sarum, late of Sidney Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Fuller, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Williams, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 286, 30 pages, 2 leaves of plates (1 folded), illustrations, map, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To his worthy and learned friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> THO. FULLER, upon his excellently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed Historie of the HOLY WARRE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>CAptain of Arts, in this thy Holy warre</l>
      <l>My Muse desires to be thy Trumpeter,</l>
      <l>In thy just praise to spend a blast or two:</l>
      <l>For this is all that she (poore thing) can do.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Peter</hi> the Hermite, like an angry owl,</l>
      <l>Would needs go fight all armed in his cowl.</l>
      <l>What, had the Holy man nought else to do,</l>
      <l>But thus to lose his bloud and credit too?</l>
      <l>Seeking to winne Christs Sepulchre, God wot,</l>
      <l>He found his own: This was the ground he got.</l>
      <l>Except he got more ground, when he one day</l>
      <l>Besieging Antioch fiercely ran away.</l>
      <l>Much wiser was the Pope: At home he stay'd,</l>
      <l>And made the world beleeve he wept and pray'd.</l>
      <l>Mean while (behold the fruit of feigned tears)</l>
      <l>He sets the world together by the cares.</l>
      <l>His head serves him, whil'st others use their hands:</l>
      <l>Whil'st Princes lose their lives, he gets their lands.</l>
      <l>To winne the Holy land what need Kings roam?</l>
      <l>The Pope can make an Holy land at home</l>
      <l>By making it his own: Then for a fashion,</l>
      <l>'Tis said to come by Constantines donation.</l>
      <l>For all this Fox-craft, I have leave (I hope)</l>
      <l>To think my friend farre wiser then the Pope</l>
      <l>And Hermite both: He deals in Holy warres</l>
      <l>Not as a stickler in those fruitlesse jarres,</l>
      <l>But a composer rather. Hence this book;</l>
      <l>Whereon whil'st I with greedie eyes do look,</l>
      <l>Me thinks I travel through the Holy land,</l>
      <l>Viewing the sacred objects on each hand.</l>
      <l>Here mounts (me thinks) like Olivet, brave sense;</l>
      <l>There flows a Iordan of pure eloquence:</l>
      <l>A Temple rich in ornament I find</l>
      <l>Presented here to my admiring mind.</l>
      <l>Strange force of Art! The ruin'd Holy citie</l>
      <l>Breeds admiration in me now, not pitie.</l>
      <l>To testifie her liking, here my Muse</l>
      <l>Makes solemn Vows, as Holy Pilgrimes use.</l>
      <l>I vow, deare friend, the Holy warre is here</l>
      <l>Farre better writ then ever fought elsewhere.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>Thousands have fought and died: But all this while,</l>
      <l>I vow, there nothing triumphs but thy style.</l>
      <l>Thy wit hath vanquisht Barbarisme more</l>
      <l>Then ever <hi>Godfrey's</hi> valour did before.</l>
      <l>Might I but choose, I rather would be farre</l>
      <l>Be authour of thy Book then of that Warre.</l>
      <l>Let others fight; I vow to reade thy works,</l>
      <l>Prizing thy ink before the bloud of Turks.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>J. BOOTH, B. D. C. C. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>