<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121937_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10228</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20505</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121937</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Purchas his pilgrimage. Or Relations of the vvorld and the religions obserued in all ages and places discouered, from the Creation vnto this present : In foure partes. This first containeth a theologicall and geographicall historie of Asia, Africa, and America, with the ilands adiacent. Declaring the ancient religions before the Floud ... With briefe descriptions of the countries, nations, states, discoueries, priuate and publike customes, and the most remarkable rarities of nature, or humane industrie, in the same. By Samuel Purchas, minister at Estwood in Essex</title>
                 <author>Purchas, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 467, that is 473, 470-674, 677-752, 22 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND now, Reader, I come vnto thee, with
whom I dare bee somewhat bolder. Being, I
know not by what naturall inclination, addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
to the studie of Historie, my heart would
sometimes obiect a selfe-loue, in following my
priuate delights in that kind. At last, I resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
to turne the pleasures of my studies into
studious paines, that others might againe, by
delightfull studie, turne my paines into their
pleasure. I here bring <hi>Religion</hi> from <hi>Paradise</hi> to
the <hi>Arke,</hi> and thence follow her round about
the World, and (for her sake) obserue the World it selfe, with the seuerall
Countries and peoples therein; the cheife Empires and States; their priuate
and publique Customes; their manifold chances and changes; also the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
and most remarkeable effects of Nature; Euents of Diuine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
Prouidence, Rarities of Art; and whatsoeuer I find by relations of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians,
as I passe, most worthie the writing. <hi>Religion</hi> is my more proper
aime, and therefore I insist longer on the description of whatsoeuer I finde
belonging thereto; declaring the Religion of the first men; the corrupting of
it before, and after the Floud; the lewish obseruations; the Idols, Idolatries,
Temples, Priestes, Feastes, Fastes, Opinions, Sects, Orders and Sacred Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes
of the Heathens; with the Alterations and Successions that haue
therein happened, from the beginning of the World hitherto.</p>
   <p>This Worke I diuide into foure partes. This first exhibiteth, Relations
and Theologicall discouerie of ASIA, AFRICA, and AMERICA: The
second, when God will, shall doe the same for EVROPE: The third and
fourth, in a second visitation, shall obserue such things in the same places, as I
hold most remarkeable in the Christian and Ecclesiasticall Historie; and that
according to the same method, which is squared in the <hi>Whole</hi> by order of
<hi>Place:</hi> going still out of one Countrie into the next, in each particular part
and seuerall Countrie, by the order of <hi>Time;</hi> deducing our Relations, so farre
as wee haue others foot-prints to guide vs, (though not exactly naming the
day and yeare, and determining questions in Chronologicall controuerfies,
yet in some conuenient sort) from the Ancient times, and by degrees descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the present. If thou demaundest what profit may bèe hereof; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere,
That here Students of all sorts may find matter fitting there Studies:
The naturall Philosophers may obserue the different constitution and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtion
of the Elements, their diuerse working in diuerse places, the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of heauenly influence, of the yearely seasons, of the Creatures in the

<pb facs="5"/>
      
Aire, Water, Earth: They which delight in State-affaires, may obserue the
varietie of States and Kingdomes, with their differing Lawes, Politics, and
Customes, their Beginnings and Endings. The Diuine, besides the former,
may here contemplate the workes of God, not in Creation alone, but in his
Iustice and Prouidence, pursuing sinne euery were with such dreadfull
plagues; both bodily, in rooting vp and pulling downe the mightiest Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires;
and especially in spirituall Iudgments, giuing vp so great a part of the
World vnto <hi>the efficacie of Errour in strong delusions, that hauing forsaken
the fountaine of liuing waters, they should digge vnto themselues these broken pittes
that can hold no water;</hi> deuout in their superstitions, and superstitiuous in their
deuotions; agreeing all in this, that there should bee a Religion; disagreeing
from each other, and the <hi>TRVTH,</hi> in the practise thereof.</p>
   <p>Likewise our Ministers may bee incited vnto all godly labours in their
function of preaching the Gospell, seeing otherwise, for outward and bodily
ceremonies, the Turkes and Iewes in their manifold deuotions in their Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories
euery day, and other Heathen would conuince vs of Idlenesse. And
let mee haue leaue to speake it for the glorie of God, and the good of our
Church; I cannot find any Priestes in all this my Pilgrimage, of whom wee
haue any exact Historie, but take more bodily paines in their deuotions, than
is performed by not-preaching Ministers, especially in Countrie-villages,
where on the weeke daies they cannot haue occasion, or companie, for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
prayers: and therefore if they onely read the seruice then, and neuer
studie for more (which I would it were not the idle practise of some) euen
the Heathen shall rise vp in judgment against them. I subscribe with hand
and practise to our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> but not to such <hi>Lethargie:</hi> whose darknesse is so
much the more intolerable, in this Sun-shine of the Gospell, wherein wee
haue a gratious <hi>King,</hi> so diligent a frequenter of Sermons; and <hi>Reuerend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi>
(notwithstanding other their weightie Ecclesiasticall employments) yet
diligent Preachers.</p>
   <p>The studious of Geographie may somewhat be helped in that kind: not
that wee intend an exact Geographie, in mentioning euery Citie with the
degrees of longitude and latitude, but yet limiting euerie Countrie in his
true situation and bounds; and performing happily more then some, which
take vpon them the title of Geographers, as their chiefe profession: and more
then any, which I know, hath done in our language.</p>
   <p>He which admireth and almost adoreth the Capuchine Iesuite, or other
Romanists for selfe-inflicted whippings, fastings, watchings, vowes of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
pouertie, and single life, and their not sparing their limmes and liues
for their <hi>wil-worships,</hi> may see, in all these, the Romanists equalled by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,
if not out-stripped euen by the reports of the Iesuites and other their
Catholiques.

<note place="margin">I. Tim. 4.8.</note>
      <hi>Bodily exercise profiteth little, but Godlinesse is profitable vnto all,
and hath the promise of this life and that which is to come.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Here also the Reader may see most of their Popish Rites, deriued out of
Chaldaean, Aegyptian, and other fountaines of Paganisme; as in the later
taske we shall haue more occasion to shew. Here euerie Englishman may see
cause to praise God continually for the light of his truth, communicated to
vs: whereas it is (in comparison) but a small part of the world, that soundeth

<pb facs="5"/>
      
      <hi>the sacred name of</hi> IESVS; and of those that professe it, how infinite are the
sectes and superstitions? <hi>God hath shewed his Word vnto our</hi> IACOB (THE
DEFENDER OF HIS FAITH) <hi>his Statutes and his iudgments vnto this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>srael</hi>
      
of Great Britaine. <hi>He hath not dealt so with euery Nation, neither haue
the Heathen,</hi> nor scarsely, if sarcely any other Christian Nation, so much
<hi>knowledge of his iudgments.</hi> And yet how seditious are some? how prophane
are other? how vnthankfull the most? That beastly Sinne of Drunkennesse,
that biting Sinne of Vsurie, that Deuilish Sinne of Swaggering, ruffling in
deformitie of clothes, like monstrous <hi>Chimaeras,</hi> and barking out a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie
of oathes, like hellish <hi>Cerberi,</hi> as if men could not be <hi>Gallants,</hi> vnlesse
they turned <hi>Deuils:</hi> These are the payments we returne vnto the Lord, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead
of prayers for, and loialtie to his Maiestie; peaceablenesse and charitie
to each others; modestie and sobrietie in our selues.</p>
   <p>For the forme, I haue sought in some places, with varietie of phrase, in
all, with varietie of matter, to draw thee along with mee in this tedious Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage.
Some names are written diuersely, according to the differing Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies
which I followed, which thy discretion will easily conceiu.e I doe
not in euerie question set downe my censure; sometimes, because it were
more then needes; sometimes because of the difficultie. I mention Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours
sometimes, of meane qualitie, for the meanest haue sense to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
that which themselues see, more certainly then the contemplations
and <hi>Theorie</hi> of the more learned. I would also acknowledge the labour of
the meanest. I haue laboured to reduce relations to their first Authours, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
their names to their allegations: the want where of hath much troubled
me, whilst the most leaue out their Authors, as if their own assertion were suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
authoritie in things borrowed. I haue (to my great paines) contracted
and epitomized whole volumes (and some very large) into one chapter; a
thing vsuall through these relations. Where I haue found plentifull dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
for Religion (my chiefe aime) I am shorter in other relations; and
where I haue had lesse helpes for that discouerie, I insift more on the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
of Nature, and discoueries by Sea and Land, with other remarkeable
accidents. These Rarities of Nature I haue sometimes suted in a differing
phrase and figure of speech; not that I affect a fantasticall singularitie; but
that these diuine workes might appeare in Robes, if not fitting their Maiestie,
yet such as our Word-Robe did willingly without any great affectation or
studie, afford: not without example of the Scripture, which vseth to bring in
the mute creatures, speaking and performing, (as it were) other personall
offices; nor without this effect, to make the Reader staie a while with obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
and wonder; besides that varietie, of it selfe, is delightsome.</p>
   <p>If any mislike the fulnesse in some places, and the barrennesse of wordes
in others; let them consider, wee handle a World, where are mountaines and
vallies, fertile habitations, and sandie desarts: and others steps, whom I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
hold me sometimes in a narrower way, which elsewhere take more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.
I touch sometimes a <hi>Controuersie;</hi> both for illustration of Historie; and
in season, and out of season, to shew my affection to the truth.</p>
   <p>Now if any man thinke, that it were better these rotten bones of the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
and stinking bodies of the present Superstitions were buried, then thus

<pb facs="6"/>
      
raked out of their graues; besides that which hath beene said, I answere,
That I haue sufficient example in the Scriptures, <hi>which were written for our
learning to the ends of the World,</hi> and yet depaint vnto vs the vgly face of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie
in so many Countries of the Heathens, with the Apoitasies, Sects, and
Heresies of the Iewes, as in our first and second booke is shewed: and the
Ancient Fathers also, <hi>Iustin, Tertullian, Clemens, Irenaeus, Origen,</hi> and more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<hi>Eusebius, Epiphanius,</hi> and <hi>Augustine,</hi> haue gone before vs in their large
Catalogues of Heresies and false Opinions. And what doth more set forth
the glorie of Gods grace, then in pardoning; his power, then in reforming;
his justice, then in giuing men vp to such delusions? Are not these the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees
and glorious victories of THE CROSSE OF CHRIST, that hath
subuerted the Temples, Oracles, Sacrifices, and Seruices of the Deuill?
And maist not thou see herein, what <hi>Man</hi> is, and thou thy selfe maist be,
if God leaue thee to thy selfe? Reade therefore, with praises vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
God, <hi>the father of thy light;</hi> and prayers, for these Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,
that GOD may bring them out of the
<hi>snare of the Deuill,</hi> and that <hi>Christ</hi> may
be <hi>his saluation to the ends
of the World.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And let me also obtaine thy prayers in this my <hi>Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi>
      
to be therein directed, to the glorie of
God, and good of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.
Euen so Lord
IESVS. ({inverted ⁂})</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>