<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Vincent, P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121128_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24760.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Vincent, P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentations of Germany : Wherein, as in a glasse, we may behold her miserable condition, and reade the woefull effects of sinne. Composed by Dr Vincent Theol. an eye-witnesse thereof; and illustrated by pictures, the more to affect the reader. Hereunto are added thre letters, one whereof was sent to the Dutch consistory in London, under the hand and seales of 14. distressed ministers of Swyburggen in Germany</title>
                 <author>Vincent, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 20, 2, 25-33, 32-63, 1 page, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>BEhold here, as in a Glasse, the mournefull face of a sister Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, now drunke with misery; according to what God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy.</hi> Should I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all the memorable particulars, which might be accumulated, to amplifie this sad theme, the third part would bee sufficient to weary thee or blinde thy eyes with reares, if thy heart were not adaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. I record but a small portion of what I have seene, what I have had from sufficient testimonies. Gall and Wormewood are tasted in a drop, and so may the great Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Onely the thing I desire, is to move thy Christian heart to compassionate the estate of thy poore brethren, so lamentable, and almost desperate, that thou mayest (at least)
<pb facs="3"/>
by the vials of thy prayers poured out in their behalfe helpe to appeale this wrath of Heaven which is upon them. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring withall, that as wee know not what hangeth over our owne heads, so we are not ignorant of our owne indeserts. Our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrey did sometimes suffer in like manner, if not measure, as in the civill wars and other times. Now we are free, and live in peace, every man under his owne Vine, under his owne big-tree; Let us not forget to bee thankfull for this unto the God of peace, and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ithall to shunne those provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, for which hee maketh a fertile land barren, a populous Land desolate, even the iniquity of them that dwell therein.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine <hi>P. Vincent.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>