<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, TO BIE, BY THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD, Archbishop of Yorke, Primate of England, and Metropolitane.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121083_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04031</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14088.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, TO BIE, BY THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD, Archbishop of Yorke, Primate of England, and Metropolitane.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon vpon the vvords of Saint Paul : Let euerie soule be subiect vnto the higher powers. Wherein the Popes soueraigntie ouer princes, amongst other errors, is briefly but sufficiently refuted; and the supremacie of the King, by cleare euidence and strong proofe auerred; to the silencing of the aduersarie, and satisfaction of the indifferent Christian, not blinded with partialitie and preiudicate opinion: by Thomas Ingmethorpe</title>
                 <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, <hi>TO BIE,</hi> BY THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD, Archbishop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Primate of <hi>England, and Metropolitane.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present vnto your Grace this short Sermon, not for any Synopticall skill to be seene in it, (for how should a Minstrell pipe artificially, wanting his ouerlip?) but onely for the good I am perswaded may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound by it to the people of this Land, my brethren and kinsmen according to the flesh. For, whereas they are borne in hand, and some, for want of better grace, are made ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleeue, that the Regiment of the Church peculiarly belongeth to the Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the prerogatiue of his office; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb facs="3"/>admit no coine for currant money, but that which cometh from his Mint, and hath his Image and superscription on it: here they may see the ground of that leud opinion sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at least, if not razed; and, as it were, a Trophee of the Kings supreame power ouer his subiects, as well in matters Spirituall as Temporal, by force of Gods word, as by dint of sword, established. So as there is likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that such, who haue any sparke of the good Spirit, which leadeth into truth, resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in them, vpon so euident a manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their error, will be won at length to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it, and leaue banding themselues in the Popes quarrell against the Lord and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: the onely <hi>Helena,</hi> in a manner, that this day troubleth the state of our <hi>Greece.</hi> For (to appeale to all that be acquainted, either with the present constitution of our bodie politique, or with the true complexion of our Church) what other maligne humour, to speake of, doth attaint the health of the one; or blemish, disfigure the beautie of the other? If this cloud were scattered, Lord, how bright would our Hemisphere shine? If this mud <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>