<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR IOHN SWINNERTON KNIGHT, ONE of the Aldermen of the honorable Citie of London.</title>
           <author>Nyxon, Anthe.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121754_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08252</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18588</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121754</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR IOHN SWINNERTON KNIGHT, ONE of the Aldermen of the honorable Citie of London.</title>
                 <author>Nyxon, Anthe.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons doue: or A memoriall of the life and death of Maister Robert Doue, citizen and marchant-taylor of London : and of his seuerall almesdeeds and large bountie to the poore, in his life time. He departed this life, on Saterday the 2. day of this instant moneth of May, 1612</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hunt, Joseph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR IOHN SWINNERTON KNIGHT, ONE of the Aldermen of the honorable Citie of London.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing drawne certaine particular remembrances, of the bountie and charitable Almes-deedes of Maister <hi>Robert Doue,</hi> lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased (done all for the most part in his life time.) And they being digested into a volume (although little for quantitie, yet not vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be committed to memorie) I thought they could not be better bestowed then vpon such as held commerce with that company, or were Heads of that body, whereof he continued a long time a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy member.</p>
   <p>Amongst which, I haue selected you from a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of others, and am bold to present this little la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vnto you, as a brother of that Societie, and one that can well iudge both of the Relation, and the truth thereof.</p>
   <p>The chiefe and farthest point that my intention seekes to arriue at in this, is but to leaue to Posteritie
<pb facs="3"/>
a deserued Testimonie, and commemoration of his s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>erall liberalities, to the intent that the hand of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rcy which Heauen (in him) hath stretcht forth ouer distressed people, being duly considered: Others (to whom God hath plentifully giuen his blessings) may be stirred vp to trace him in the like steppes of true Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie, and be encouraged to looke into their owne Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es betimes, and to imitate him in the works of pietie.</p>
   <p>It is my Loue that makes tender of this vnto you, which I pray receiue with such good acceptation: As with my best affection, it comes and is bestowed vpon you: Thus humbly referring my selfe to your censure, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Deuoted vnto your worship, <hi>Anthe: Nyxon.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>