<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A true Copy of a Letter writ∣ten by a worthy Minister, Andreas Pilger sometimes Minister of Heydelberg. From Wormbs the 10th. of Febr. 1637.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121128_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24760.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A true Copy of a Letter writ∣ten by a worthy Minister, Andreas Pilger sometimes Minister of Heydelberg. From Wormbs the 10th. of Febr. 1637.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentations of Germany : Wherein, as in a glasse, we may behold her miserable condition, and reade the woefull effects of sinne. Composed by Dr Vincent Theol. an eye-witnesse thereof; and illustrated by pictures, the more to affect the reader. Hereunto are added thre letters, one whereof was sent to the Dutch consistory in London, under the hand and seales of 14. distressed ministers of Swyburggen in Germany</title>
                 <author>Vincent, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 20, 2, 25-33, 32-63, 1 page, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>A true Copy of a Letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a worthy Minister, <hi>Andreas Pilger</hi> sometimes Minister of <hi>Heydelberg.</hi> From <hi>Wormbs</hi> the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1637.</head>
   <p>ALas! What stormes and tempests doe now beat upon the ship of Jesus Christ in our Countrey? What punishments and plagues doe now oppresse us? God is just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angry with us for our manifold sinnes, and seemes in his indignation utterly to destroy us, and all that is round about us. The heavie curses of <hi>Moses,</hi> the bitter lamentations of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and all the horrible threatnings of the holy Prophets, wee see daily here accomplished. With this new Winter-quarter, beginnes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of our miseries; oppression and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, we being utterly destitute of all helpe and meanes to support us. The chiefest of our Countrey are forced to leave their houses and lands, and to goe a wandring in strange Countries; yea, many of them end their lives most miserably. It is impossible to expresse either the greatnesse of our wants, or the fury of Famine amongst us. Mothers forgetting
<pb facs="15"/>
their naturall affections towards their owne children become butchers of them, and eate them up in stead of food. Wee do heare dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly children crying about the streets, and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that they dare not goe home, for feare of being killed. It is kept upon record by the Magistrates of this City, how that men have digged out of the graves dead bodies, and have eaten them. A woman was found dead, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a mans head rosted by her, and the rib of a man in her mouth, holding it betweene her teeth, and of this horrible spectacle all sorts of men can give testimony. Such and many more signes of Gods heavie wrath wee could write unto you of, but this shall suffice to give you a touch of the extremities wee are in. O how seasonable are those almes, which are sent hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to keepe some of us alive! That faithfull God, who hath made so many promises to the liberall heart, will undoubtedly consider those, that consider our poore Countrey-men in these extremities, and keep them from famishing.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Andreas Pilger, Pastor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>