<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY VERY LOVING FRIEND, Master THOMAS VVHYTE, a Citizen of BRISTOVV.</title>
           <author>G., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121104_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01743</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11878</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121104</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY VERY LOVING FRIEND, Master THOMAS VVHYTE, a Citizen of BRISTOVV.</title>
                 <author>G., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sacred philosophie of the Holy Scripture, laid downe as conclusions on the articles of our faith, commonly called the Apostles Creed : Proved by the principles or rules taught and received in the light of understanding. Written by Alexander Gil, Master of Pauls Schole</title>
                 <author>Gill, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Anne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <distributor>Norton, Joyce (Jocosa)</distributor>
                            <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 196, 232 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="227"/>
   <pb n="211" facs="227"/>
   <head>TO MY VERY LOVING FRIEND, Master THOMAS VVHYTE, a Citizen of BRISTOVV.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hile I was at <hi>Norwich,</hi> in the yeere <hi>1597,</hi> I writ this Treatise vpon such oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion as appeares therein, and delivered it unto that Hereticke, that by himselfe, if <hi>God</hi> would, he might consider and be perswaded. Since which time I have kept it by me: and though some of my private friends desired copies; yet allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wisedome of <hi>Solon,</hi> who would make no law against Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricide, lest the mention of the fact might give occasion to commit it: and withall considering that it is too simple and poore for the publike view, I refused to make it common. Yet after perceiving a present necessitie, because that some began to wander in this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth: and withall remembring, that if any weakling shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after entertaine this opinion, he may, before he be wholly posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed therewith, find the absurdity of it and be reformed; that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a novice in Christianity, who therefore doubts of the truenesse of his Religion, because he finds no familiar reason to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade,
<pb n="212" facs="228"/> but onely the racke of authorities to constraine him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it; may perhaps bee hereby satisfied and finde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: and that they who are already strong, may by this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus, triumph in the goodnesse of <hi>God,</hi> who requires them to beleeve no more, then they may by that understanding, which hee hath given them, bee perswaded of: I have for their sakes who may reape benefit thereby, neglected all froward Censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, not guilty unto my selfe of any offence which I can commit in making it publike. Such as it is, accept (kinde Sir) as a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of that assertion, which may hereafter follow, of every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Christian faith; if <hi>God</hi> shall vouchsafe me understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, leisure, and maintenance thereto. I therefore offer it unto you, both because I know you are diligent in reading of bookes of good argument; and because I have none other meanes, whereby to shew my selfe thankefull for your manifold kindnesses and your love.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your loving and assured friend, <hi>A. G.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London,</hi>
         <date>this <hi>20.</hi> of <hi>April 1601.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>