<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>D., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121690_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20762</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7143</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121690</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>D., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A guide to godlynesse or a Treatise of a Christian life : shewing the duties wherein it consisteth, the helpes inabling &amp; the reasons parswading vnto it ye impediments hindering ye practise of it, and the best meanes to remoue them whereunto are added diuers prayers and a treatise of carnall securitie by Iohn Douname Batcheler in Diuinitie and minister of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Downame, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bladen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 734, 733-925, 956-961, 3, 16, 103, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the duty (Christian Reader) of all who desire to approoue themselues faithfull subiects and seruants to our great Lord and Soueraigne, that they consecrate themselues wholly vnto his seruice, not only in the spirituall Warfare, by fighting his battels, euen vnto the death, against the many and mighty enemies of his glory and our saluation; but also in the time of peace, by doing his will, and performing all holy duties of his seruice, which in his Word he requireth of them. And therefore as I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured heretofore (according to the measure of grace receiued) to prepare and fit all those who vouchsafe to peruse my poore labours, that they may performe the duties of valiant Souldiers, in my Bookes of the Christian Warfare: so perceiuing that those my paines haue much aboue their worth found good acceptance with all those that feare God; I haue now also beene incouraged to vndertake the other, and not only to describe the duties of a godly life, in which we ought to serue our Lord and Master, but also to shew the meanes wherby we may be inabled hereunto, and how we may remoue the impediments which otherwise might hinder vs from entring into, or proceeding in the wayes of godlinesse. The which my labours, if they prooue as profitable to those that reade them, as they haue beene painefull vnto me in framing and composing them, I shall thinke my selfe abundantly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced, and much more reioyce when I see the haruest of my hopes, then euer I had cause to sigh and grone, through wearinesse in my laborious seed-time. Of which, though I should faile (as I hope I shall not) yet, as it is said of Vertue, that it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bringeth a reward with it, so may I truely say of these my labours; out of which, so much profit, comfort, and contentment haue accrewed vnto my selfe, that I should haue no iust cause to repent for the scantnesse of my reward, although no other fruit should spring from them. But if I be not deceiued (as we are apt to be no lesse blinded in iudging of our spirituall and mentall, then of our naturall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall births) these my present labours will proue no lesse profitable vnto all that peruse them, then any of the former. Yea, if my affection corrupting my iudgment, doth not cause me to looke vpon them (like Fathers, vpon the children of their old age) with an ouer-partiall eye, they are in some respects to be preferred before any of the other, both because the subiect on which they intreate, hath the priuiledge of excellency and necessity, as being the maine duties of Christianity, which are to be performed thorowout the whole course of our liues; and also because they generally concerne all sorts of men, who thinke themselues bound to doe God any seruice, or to carry themselues so, as that their works and wayes may be accepted of him. If any man shall thinke that I haue described the duties of a godly life with more strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and in greater perfection, then any can attaine vnto in this state of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and so haue required more of others, then I can any wayes be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my selfe; let him know, that the worke must be fitted to the rule, and not the rule to the worke, and that this must be straight and perfect, although by reason
<pb facs="6"/> of the crookednesse of the matter or stuffe, no worke-man is able to frame it so, but that it will in many places decline and swarue from it. And though the marke of perfection be so small, and so farre out of our reach, that none in this life can hit it; yet must it be set before vs, and we must striue to shoot at it, as neere as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>; seeing they are more likely to haue the prize of the best game, who aime at it, then those who looke another way. For my selfe, none can accuse me of so many and great imperfections in my course and practice of these duties, as I am ready to charge my selfe within the court of mine own conscience; &amp; yet if I would not belie the grace of God in me, I must professe, that I doe labour to performe that my selfe which I propound vnto others; and though I cannot attaine to the goale of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as I haue here described it out of Gods Word, yet bewayling my stiffenesse and lamenesse in running the Race, I indeuour and presse (in some measure) <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 13, 14.</note>
      <hi>the marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Iesus Christ;</hi> and no more then this doe I require of others. Now, because wee cannot grow in grace and godlinesse, without the assistance of Gods Spirit, and this cannot be had, vnlesse we sue and seeke for it; and because also godlinesse in a great part consisteth in powring forth our soules before God in humble and hearty, frequent and feruent prayers, therefore lest any thing which is necessary, should be wanting to this Treatise, I haue in the end of it set downe diuers formes, which may serue either for the vse of weake Christians, who cannot fit themselues with better, or for some direction to guide them in composing or conceiuing others, according to their owne particular occasions. If any man thinke them ouer-long and tedious, to him, I confesse, they are so, (though there is scarce two amongst them that may not be treatably vttered in a quarter of an houre) and therefore I would not torture his deuotion, by perswading him to racke and stretch it aboue its due length and strength; but rather I would aduise, if hee meet not with shorter Prayers, which better please him, that hee deuide both the Confessions and Petitions, with some marke of a Pen, so as he may vse one halfe at one time, and the rest at another. And so (Christian Reader) I leaue thee to the Lord, and his good blessing vpon all thy studies and indeuours, only requesting these two things at thine hands; First, that as I haue laboured much in giuing thee directions for the leading of a Christian life; so thou wilt also striue with all thine indeuour, to walke in this way reuealed vnto thee. And secondly, that if thou reape any fruit of my paines (as I doubt not thou wilt, if thou reade to profit by them, constantly vnto the end, and not heere and there, by fits and snatches) thou wilt be pleased to affoord me the benefit of thy Prayers, that together with thy selfe, I may continue and hold out vnto the end, in the profession and practice of all Christian and holy duties; vntill hauing finished our course with ioy, we doe both of vs receiue the Crowne of righteousnesse, which God of his free grace hath laid vp for vs, and for all those who loue his appearing.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>Octob. the</hi> 16. 1622.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus our Head and Sauiour, I. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>