<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
A BRIEFE DIS∣COVRSE OF PRODI∣GIES, by way of Preface to the Treatise following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121731_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16857</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3758</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121731</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
A BRIEFE DIS∣COVRSE OF PRODI∣GIES, by way of Preface to the Treatise following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvarnings of Germany : By wonderfull signes, and strange prodigies seene in divers parts of that countrey of Germany, betweene the yeare 1618. and 1638. Together with a briefe relation of the miserable events which ensued. All faithfully collected out of credible High Dutch chronicles, and other histories by L. Brinckmair Captaine. As also a learned &amp; godly sermon preached before the lords the States at Norrimberg. Anno 1638</title>
                 <author>Brinckmair, L.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Norton, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Overton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 69, 11, 72 pages, folded plates, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="2"/>
A BRIEFE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE OF <hi>PRODI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIES,</hi> by way of <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Treatise</hi> following.</head>
   <div n="1" type="section">
      <head>Section 1.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost divine is that <hi>Axiome, God</hi>
         <note place="margin">Beda inter axiome. Philos. ex Arist.</note>
         <hi>and nature do nothing in vaine.</hi> Nature is that constant order of being and working, which God hath appointed for the creatures. Where there is <hi>order,</hi> and that order <hi>constant,</hi> and both <hi>determined by an infinite wisdome,</hi> there must necessarily be some good end propounded by the <hi>Ordainer,</hi> and all motions effectuall for accomplishment. Yet the course of Nature is sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to many alterations, because there is a <hi>God above nature,</hi> who hath set bounds for the
<pb facs="3"/>
creatures, but none for him save <hi>the counsell of his will. Whatsoever the Lord pleases, that doth hee in Heaven above, and in the Earth beneath.</hi>
         <note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 135▪ 6</note>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="section">
      <head>§ 2</head>
      <p>Hereupon it followes, That even those things which come to passe according to the course of nature, are very considerable: because they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ffected according to Gods ordination. <hi>His invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible power and Godhead</hi>
         <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1. 20.</note>
         <hi>may be seene in them.</hi> Nothing is so small, but his providence extends to it. <hi>Praes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ntemque refert quaelibet herba Deum.</hi>
      </p>
      <q>
         <l>In every tender grasse</l>
         <l>God may be seen as in a glasse.</l>
      </q>
      <p>Divine praescience were far from being, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>is est maxima, pert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>e quem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> it is, <hi>all Infinite,</hi> did it not extend it selfe to every accident. Nothing is or <hi>moves,</hi> or <hi>suffers</hi> in any kinde, but in subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Gods eternall decrees, that his wise pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose may be effected. And what is it which we see or heare of in any of the creatures, which affords not some morall and divine use? The world is Gods great booke <hi>in Folio.</hi> Every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a severall page, in which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e may reade some instruction to further us in heavenly wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The <hi>Occasional Meditations</hi> of such as are
<pb facs="3"/>
piously devoted, give us sensible demonstration of this. Prophane then, and irreligious are they that looke on the ordinary course of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but never looke up to God in holy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereas everything wee see is like <hi>Iacobs Ladder.</hi> The foote of it is in earth, but the top is in Heaven. We should therefore looke beyond our senses, and use them as a prospective glasse, to see God through, that he may be brought nigh our hearts, though wee be farre from his glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence. That Philosopher seemés to have had some secret inspiration from the almighty, who being as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked<note place="margin">Apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Arist. de an.</note> wherfore man was made, answered, <hi>coeli con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templandi gratiâ.</hi> For God indeede made us to study himselfe, and minde things above. Why was <hi>Adam</hi> put in <hi>Paradise?</hi> Onely to till the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den without taking other care, or pleasure? rather, that by imploying himselfe about the creatures, he might more distinctly meditate of every one to inflame his affections toward God. And what is it which affords no instruction? Toades, and such like, seeing man fly from them presently. A live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Emblem of lapsed mankinde, which cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Gods presence, we being conscious to our selves that we are worthy of his hatred. Seeing poore wormes made by God in such a condition, that every foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e may tread on them, and them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meanes to revenge or resist that hurt, we should
<pb facs="4"/>
hence learne humilitie, patience, and all subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the will of God. Every Cocke crowing is a lesson of Repentance. Every sound of a trumpet an Alarum to the last Iudgement. And every puffe<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> Pind.</note> of breath a <hi>Memento mori.</hi> For <hi>what is our life? it is even a Vapour, appearing for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, then vanishing.</hi> I am. <hi>4. 14.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="section">
      <head>§ 3</head>
      <p>This supposed, it followes further. Those things which are more rare in the course of nature, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi>
         <note place="margin">A min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>i ad mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>es.</note>
         <hi>contrary,</hi> or <hi>above,</hi> are more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be thought upon. For of every such thing it may be said, <hi>Digitus Deiesthic,</hi> God hath an immediate hand in them, they are for speciall use. Having therefore in the Treatise following<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
         <hi>the wonderfull things of God</hi> reflicted to us as in a glasse, by an historicall gleaning together of some remarkable Prodigies which of late Yeares have happened in <hi>Germany,</hi> with the Events which followed them, it will not bee su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ous to take something along with us in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them, touching the nature, ends, and use which is to be made of such like, according to the Scripture. The rather because they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves like the writing on the Wall in <hi>Beshazzars</hi> Palace,<note n="a" place="margin">Dan 5. 8.</note> which <hi>Sooth-fayers, Astrologians,</hi> and <hi>Chald<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ns</hi> could neither understand nor
<pb facs="4"/>
reade. Who can reade Gods riddle, but they who plough with his Heifer? None know what use to make of his workes, but they who meditate of them, according to his word, with the helpe of his spirit. Hence it is though some are carefull in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving them, yet few have the happinesse to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by them. Most men profanely disregard them, being of <hi>Gallio's</hi> temper, carelesse of such mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Some su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>itiously abuse them. Many onely gaze, and wonder. Few know what they meane, and therefore skip them over as unskilfull readers use to doe sentences of <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> which they understand not. To remedy this in some part, Here is my indeavour in hope of Gods blessing. <hi>The worke of the Lord is great, sought out of all them that have pleasure therein</hi> Psalm. <hi>111. 2.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="section">
      <head>§ 4.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>If the question be what Prodigies are, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer may be,</hi> Signes and wonders wrought by God immediately, or by others at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, to signifie his pleasure aforehand touching some speciall mercy or judgement ensuing.</p>
      <p>The Treatise cals them Prodigies, that is <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions</hi> or foremarnings. So much the word implyes <seg rend="sup">a</seg>. In Scripture phrase they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb facs="5"/>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> signes and wonders, Joel (chap. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>38.)</hi> calls them wonders, St. Luke, chap. <hi>21. 11)</hi> calls them <hi>fearefull sights, and great</hi>
         <note place="margin">Prodigia, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>orro dicant, dest, sut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rrap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicant. Au. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Civ. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>i. lib. <hi>21</hi> cap. <hi>8</hi> Omnia qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>pe por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nta contra nauram di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> csse: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>dn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n sunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>dem. c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>nch de ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ih. Dei. lib <hi>3.</hi> Cap <hi>13.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>signes.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> tearmes them, <hi>wonders in Heaven, and signes in Earth.</hi> Acts. <hi>2. 21.</hi> Of signes some are to represent, Some for commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Some to assure, Others to prognosticate, whereof some be ordinary, others extraordinary. <hi>Prodigies be extraordinary prognosticating signes.</hi> They are also called wonders, not because they are all <hi>miracles in propriety;</hi> but because they seeme to bee, unto such as know not the causes and effects of them, and therefore cause wondring. <hi>A miracle is that which happens besides the order of all nature, particular, and generall,</hi> For a stone to moove upward when it is throwne, is contrary to the particular nature of a stone, yet no miracle, because all things give way to violence. The hanging of Mahomets iron tombe in the Ayre (if it bee, as it is reported) is no miracle, because it may be drawne up by vertue of some Loadstone above it. But every thing is a wonder, whose cause we know not, or at least which wise men know not. Admiration alwaies rises out of<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>um &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> some degree of Ignorance. There is therefore a difference betwixt a miracle and a marvell: <seg rend="sup">d</seg> under the tearme of wonder; <hi>3</hi> Severall things be comprehended.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="5"/>
1 Speciall rarities in the course of nature, and<note place="margin">Quae sunt rara <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>psa sunt mira Augu.</note> in the actions and affaires of men <seg rend="sup">e</seg>▪ Secondly, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles properly so called. Thirdly, whatsoever it is which makes the wiser or greater part of men to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, as wel as fooles, however it be called. Alwhich are here included under the name of prodigies.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="section">
      <head>§ 5</head>
      <p>Having briefly notified the meaning both of the name and thing in hand, the next thing most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary<note place="margin">Novis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia plena virg.</note> is to consider of the author, who gives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to things prodigious, and appoints their use. That must needs bee God, who is the onely Alpha and Omega; The center from which all lines are drawne, and the circumference wherein they are terminated. All predictions, whether they bee naturall or supernaturall, must needs originally issue from him, that decrees things from eternity, and causes them to exist in time in all circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces according to his appointment. This hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been out of controversie, not onely among Christians, but also among the Philosophers, yea even amvng the very Vulgar heathen. But though all have reference to God, yet not all alike. Some things hee either doth immediately, or at least wise seemes to doe, for both <hi>God, and nature are often clouded.</hi> Many things are effected by the Ministery of the Angells. Some proceed
<pb facs="6"/>
from me, and the course of nature, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God. Those things which are most common in the course of nature, are to bee counted Gods<note place="margin">
            <hi>a</hi> Iob. 38. 28. 29.</note> workes, and therefore much more those which are strange. God puts these Questions to Iob. <hi>Hath the raine a Father? or who hath begotten the drops of dew? Out of whose wombe came the yce? and the hoary frost of heaven, who hath gendred it?</hi> The answer to bee made is this, God giveth being to al these things according to his pleasure, what then shall be thought of raining bloud, Fire, and such like? No otherwise then according to that, The Lord rained upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> fire and Brimstone from the Lord out of Heaven <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 19. 24.</note>. He threatens such afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and he alone hath power to effect them. Therefore when we see or heare of any such thing, we can doe no lesse then acknowledge in the <hi>Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists</hi> words, This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes. Psal. <hi>118. 23.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="section">
      <head>§ 6</head>
      <p>But how is it that signes and wonders are said to be wrought by false Prophets? for so Moses inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates<note n="a" place="margin">Deut 13. 1.</note> And our Saviour sayes expresly, <hi>There</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>b</hi> Mat. 24. 24.</note>
         <hi>shall arise false Prophets, and false Christs, and shall shew great signes and wonders</hi> And to like effect Paul speakes of Antichrist▪
<pb facs="6"/>
         <hi>2.</hi> Thess. <hi>2. 9.</hi> We read also that many signes done before <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by <hi>Moses,</hi> were also done before him by the Magitians of <hi>Aegypt</hi>
         <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 7. 11.</note>.</p>
      <p>No doubt but Satan and his Instruments are permitted to doe great things for the triall of Gods Church and children, but in all they doe they are no more but instruments. Therefore that Fire wherewith Jobs sheepe and servants were consumed, is fuly called the <hi>Fire of God,</hi> though the <hi>Prince</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>d</hi> Iob. 1. 16.</note>
         <hi>of the Ayre</hi> was in that the Incendiary and the bellowes, and added oyle to the flame. But Gods wonders and Satans differs very much▪ Oftentimes in the thing it selfe.<note n="*" place="margin">Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>nus Biermanus, de Magicis Actiombus</note> Satan seemes to worke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but God workes miracles indsed.</p>
      <p>Satan also makes a shew of doing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things which indeed hee doth not, deluding the outward senses and the the Phantasie. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes lies against God or nature. Therefore well saith <hi>Moses, Who is like unto thee O Lord among the Gods? who is like unto thee? glorious in holinesse, fearefull in praise, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders.</hi>
         <note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 15. 11.</note> But in the ground and end there is alwayes a vast and manifest difference betwixt the one and the other. All that Satan does, is out of hatred, envy and malice, to God and man. But all that God doth is in mercyor Iustice. The plot which the Devill prosecutes in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, is to rob God of his glory, to make his
<pb facs="7"/>
word of none effect, and to frustrate the salvation intended for the Elect. Gods immutable purpose is to glorifie himselfe, to fulfill his word in all the promises and threatnings, and to save those whom he hath chosen in Christ. The one intends nothing but fraud and mischiefe, the other to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his goodnesse even to them that wilfully pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish. Satan labours to bring men into Heresie, superstition, and Idolatry, to blind their eyes, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their hearts, and wholly to corrupt them in all their wayes. God would have all men come to the knowledge of the truth that they might be saved<seg rend="sup">a</seg>,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 4.</note> if any desire to know how it may be knowne, which wonders be wrought by God especially, and which by Satan, let them consider, This is needlesse for us curiously to inquire after, and fruitlesse to bee knowne. Our duty is to looke upon all good and evill as coming from God, as Iob did, saying, <hi>The Lord, hath given, and the Lord hath taken, &amp;c. Shall wee receive good from the hand of the Lord, and not evill?</hi> And though some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies be but rarities in nature, yet are wee to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe all to God, in as much as nature is his handmaid, and even of naturall things there is more to be made then a naturall use.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="section">
      <head>§ 7</head>
      <p>As for the matter wherof Prodigies consist, that is worthy to be considered of, but warily to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb facs="7"/>
A confused Notion that some things are prodigious, without knowledge of the particulars, and whether it be good or evill that is portended, hath bred and nourished much curiositie and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition, needlesse feares in some, fond hopes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, there have anciently beene a sort of men who have made it their study and profession to teach what is ominous, and of what: such were the Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayers, <hi>Astrologians, Chaldeans,</hi> and the like. But the light of the Gospell hath made all these see ming starres to vanish. And yet still pride, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riositie, infidelity, like bitter rootes growing in the heart of mankinde naturally, leade them much what in the same way. Hence it is that almost every accident is by some counted a signe of good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill lucke, according to our common phrase. To reckon up particulars in this kinde, would be both tedious and ridiculous.</p>
      <p>But it must be granted that some things are <hi>Prodigious:</hi> true. And that some things are so in reference to particular persons, and families. Some to Countries, Nations, and whole States. This also cannot be denied, Whatis then the rule to know them by? No vulgar conceit, no nor every pretended reason. Nor yet all manner of experience, so far as wee are to regard <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies.</hi> The Scripture is a sufficient rule. Therein we have multitude and varietie of examples that
<pb facs="8"/>
teaches us to count of sinne as a certaine forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of divine vengeance, unlesse repentance intercept. And to take Repentance, Faith, Obedience, Piety, Justice, and Charity for assured pledge of Gods love and purpose of blessednes in every kinde. According unto these we are to regulate our hopes and feares. <hi>Humility is a speciall token of honor ensuing, and pride a forerunner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi>
         <note n="a" place="margin">Pro.</note> He that goes on in an evill way shall not prosper at the last, <hi>though the Sun, Moon</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>b</hi> Gen. 27. 9.</note>
         <hi>and Starres should seeme to fall downe and worship him,</hi> as they did sometime to <hi>Ioseph.</hi> And he that feareth God, and escheweth evill may be confident that all shall worke together for the best, though Hell were for the present let loose upon him. Yea, though God himselfe should make a but of him to empty his quiver in. Foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Prophets may say to <hi>Ahab, Goe up to Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth Gilead and prosper.</hi> Yet <hi>Ahab</hi> falls there, for he had sold himselfe to worke wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. <hi>Romes</hi> merchants will not believe her fall, but they shall certainly see and lament it<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 19.</note>
         <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> sayes <hi>I am, and none else besides me. I shall not sit as a widdow, neither shall I know the losse of children. But these two things (saith God) shall come to thee in a moment</hi>
         <note place="margin">Isa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. 8. and 9.</note>
         <hi>in one day, the losse of children and widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, they shall come upon thee in their perfection,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="8"/>
In sinning there be some circumstances which are more immediate harbingers of judgement, and so likewise many particular sinnes. Backsliding, as in <hi>Solomon.</hi> Presently hereupon God stirred him up adversaries. Raeshnesse in things which require a waighty consultation, as in <hi>Rehoboam.</hi> Selfe-will, as in <hi>Iosias.</hi> Impudency, as in <hi>Absolon.</hi> But I had rather leave particulars to the studious Readers observation.</p>
      <p>So on the other side humility, wisedome, patience, importunity in prayer, diligence in well doing doe more especially demonstrate Gods purpose to manifest his especiall mercy. But those praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which we have now especially to consider, are of another sort.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="section">
      <head>§ 8.</head>
      <p>To speake more fully of the <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> in generall▪ I conceive it is some speciall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident happening by the providence of God. The things about which such accidents happen are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse, and according to the difference thereof wee may count of <hi>3.</hi> kinds of <hi>Prodigies, Naturall, Morall</hi> and <hi>Divine,</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</p>
      <p>Naturall are those speciall accidents which fall out in the particular or generall course of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Of which some are <hi>Celestiall,</hi> some <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ntarie. Celestiall</hi> I call those which happen
<pb facs="9"/>
about the heavenly bodies. As about the Sunne, Moone or other Starrs. By Elementary I meane those which happen in the Elements themselves, or those things which are compounded of them. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Prodigies</hi> are those which consist in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, passions, words, or actions of men. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> I call those wherein (<gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>) some divine<note place="margin">* Qui por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentorum numerat multitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem que historia gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur. Aug.</note> impression is more conspicuous or necessarily to be acknowledged. For each of these kinds there is mutiplicity of Instances to be had almost in all <hi>Histories,</hi> but it shall suffice me to particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ise in some few out of Scripture.</p>
      <p>That extraordinary Eclipse which happened at our Saviours passion <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 27. 45.</note>, at which the greatest <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers,</hi> that then were, much admired. The plague of darknesse in <hi>Aegypt</hi>
         <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 10 21.</note>, and the appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Angells and heavenly visions, whereof we often read in Scripture, were <hi>Prodigies</hi> Celestiall. Of Elementary we have more variety of examples, The Fire which consumed <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
         <note n="c" place="bottom">
            <hi>Levit▪</hi> 10. 2.</note>, <note place="margin">Fitry Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies.</note>That which fell from heaven on the Captaines and their companies, sent by <hi>Ahaziah</hi> to <hi>Elijah,</hi>
         <note n="d" place="bottom">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1. 10.</note> The pillar of Fire which was for safe conduct to the Israelites in the night time <note n="e" place="bottom">
            <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 21. 22.</note>. The fire &amp; vrimstone which fell on <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> The <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims</hi> and flaming Sword which God placed before paradice.<note place="bottom">
            <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 24.</note>
         <note place="bottom">
            <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 24.</note>
      </p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="9"/>
         <note place="margin">Airy.</note> The cloudy pillar which was Israels guide by day. The <hi>Manna</hi> wherewith they were fed in the wildernesse. The plague of Haile in <hi>Egypt.</hi> That on the army of the Five <hi>Canaanitish</hi> Kings in<note place="margin">
            <hi>Iosh.</hi> 101<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note>
         <hi>Ioshua's</hi> time.</p>
      <lg>
         <l>The dividing of the red Sea.</l>
         <l>
            <note place="margin">Watery.</note> And of <hi>Iordan.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Christs walking on the water.</l>
         <l>Water issuing out of the rocke,</l>
         <l>And out of the Jaw bone of an Asse.</l>
         <l>Bitter Water becomming sweet by casting in Salt.</l>
      </lg>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Earthy.</note>
         <hi>Earthquakes, Famine, Extraordinary fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnesse, Excessive multitude of Birds, as of Quailes,</hi> among the <hi>Israelites,</hi> or of <hi>Flyes, Beasts, or creeping things,</hi> as among the Plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> The strange peregrination of Creatures, from their wonted habitation, as the comming of the creatures into the <hi>Arke.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>These and many such like particulars are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prodigies, and for distinction sake naturall, because some thing in it selfe naturall, is the subject of them.</p>
      <p>As for morall <hi>Prodigies</hi> that which is passed in the former <hi>Section</hi> shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>suffice, because it is but a schedule that I have to write, and not a volume: for divine prodigies, so called in a more
<pb facs="10"/>
especiall manner, these following are most ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Isa. 38. 8.</note> The <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moone</hi> standing still as in <hi>Ioshua's</hi> time. The shadowes going backe 10 degrees on <hi>Ahaz</hi> his Diall in <hi>Hezechiahs</hi> time. The new starres appearing at our <hi>Saviours</hi> birth. The rending of the vaile of the Temple, and the resurrection of dead bodies, at the time of his crucifying. &amp;c.</p>
      <p>These are sufficient to shew us what is to bee counted prodigious, and what not. For all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars we have no instance. Things new and strange may daily happen as God sees cause to conclude this part of the matter in hand, let this note suffice. Whatsoever happens extraordinarily and rarely to us or to any of the creatures, hath more or lesse of the nature of a Prodigie in it. Such was the strange fighting in the nombe of <hi>Rebekah, Nebuchadnezzars, Pharaohs,</hi> and <hi>Pilates</hi> wives dreames. The carriage and speech of <hi>Baalams</hi> Asse. The falling off of the Chariot Wheeles of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> as they drave in the red <hi>Sea. Dagons</hi> prostrating before the <hi>Arke.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="section">
      <head>§ 9</head>
      <p>Sufficient being spoken of the <hi>Matter,</hi> the next
<pb facs="10"/>
thing necessary to be touched is the forme, to shew what makes any speciall accident to be a Prodigie, that is (as I conceive) the aptitude which such ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents have in themselues, or by divine institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to portend the futurition or manifestation of something as yet not existent, or not knowne. As for example, Bloud happening extraordinarily in raine, in sweate, or in the use of bread or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, doth fitly betokenwarre, murther, execution of malefactors, or persecution. But how comes the <hi>Rainebow</hi> to be a signe the world shall never be overflowne againe by an Vniversall Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas naturally it signifies raine. This it could not doe if God had not appointed it for such an use. It may be demanded what I thinke of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. If it be found by observation from time to time that after such an accident in one kind, such an event in another followes, may not that accident thenceforth be taken for a certaine signe of such an event to ensue? <hi>I answer,</hi> God is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>searchable in his wayes. No observation whatsoever will inable us to trace him. <hi>As the way of a ship in the Sea, or a Bird in the Ayre, so are Gods waies.</hi> Experience therefore is but an uncertaine guide, because the course of Gods providence is a perfect maze or Labyrinth. There is indeed no variance nor shadow of turning betwixt his will at one time, and
<pb facs="11"/>
his will at another. <hi>(I speake of his absolute will)</hi> Neither is there any difference betwixt his <hi>will in decree, and his will in deed,</hi> and hee often doth the same things over againe, <hi>for kind.</hi> Yet there is so much variety for circumstances, that its impossible by al observation to conclude for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, from that which doth happen in one kind, to that which shallhappen in another. This notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the argument from existence of the signe, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>utu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ition of the thing signified, concluding onely probably and indefinitely, cannot justly bee gainesaid: for instance, Thus to reason is very use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. After a Comet or blazing starres appearing and vanishing, some great personages doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly expire.</p>
      <p>This experienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> out of many Histories confirms,<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> Therefore such a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> now appearing, its likely some of the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> of the Earth shall dye like men, and all of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> just cavse more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>or death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ecially such as <hi>Herod.</hi> Bat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>her matter calls me to it.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="10" type="section">
      <head>§ 10</head>
      <p>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nall cause of prodigies, that is divers in divers re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s. The common end is that Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> may beglorified by us in beholding his works,
<pb facs="11"/>
and spelling out of them his infinite wisedome,<note place="margin">I psa nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nt indict <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m rei. Monster sane dicta pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>hi bentà. monsirando. &amp;c. Aug quo supra.</note> power, and goodnesse, whereunto prodigies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce no little, because they minister master for an invincible argument against an Atheist or Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; and strongly prove both God and providence. The proper end of them is either <hi>neare</hi> or <hi>remote;</hi> That which they serve for more immediately is in generall, to intimate some change in the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, to whom they have reference: But sometimes they serve to bring to light that which was hid, or to make that knowne which was secret; as when <hi>Satan</hi> appeares for a time where some body lies buried in secret, and then vanishes, or when extraordinary trouble of minde falls on some, that thereby they may be brought to disclose some secret sin, the revealing whereof may tend to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Some of them doe more especially serve for comfort, some for terror.<note n="*" place="margin">Cum Deus puuitur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> est gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ens vel orben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> prod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> id <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> Herod.</note> Some serve to terrifye for a while, as the burning Bush, but leave comfort in the issue, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that did. And the Angells wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full behaviour in the presence of <hi>Sampsons</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: some serve to streng then the faith of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> children in time of great discouragement; orwhen the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to some special service: some serve to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite and call all, of all sorts, to repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life.</p>
      <p>Those which serve to this end are in a more peculiar manner The <hi>Prodigies,</hi>
         <pb facs="12"/>
and such are those which are instanced in, in the following History▪ Comfortable ones may happen to the wicked, and terrible to the godly, to harden the one, and humble the other. That the one may prepare for correction and profit by it, the other in Gods just judgement perish everlastingly. If the Question be when fearefull Prodigies happen in a Countrey where there be two contrary sides of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent professions in religion, how it may be knowne whether of them they concerne. I answer, the only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssary thing is, for each private person of what sort soever, whose abode is in such place, to take it to himself, and to examine his heart, wayes, and spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al estate, that he may reforme himselfe according to the word of God, lest hee also perish. Many are too prone to cry woe unto others, but at last are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to say (with him mentioned by <hi>Iosephus,</hi> where be speakes of the lass destruction of <hi>Ierusalem.) woe unto mee also.</hi> God is not wont to send ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall judgements, till all flesh more or lesse have corrupted their way: and therefore it behoues all of all sorts▪ howsoever different in the profession of religion to humble themselve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, and study refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation really▪ not inpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tence.<note n="*" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> 16.</note> If they of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> doe so, and then send out a dove from their Arke, she is likely to return with an Olive branch in her mouth. In the meane while so long as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one looking on his neighbour saies, Truth is on
<pb facs="12"/>
my side, Thou art an hereticke, and therefore the destruction threatned is to thee, but I shall escape: God that is no respecter of Persons findes just mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of offence in both, and on which side peace and Victory will rest, as touching sence is yet uncertaine. But wee know who they are that cry peace, peace, to themselves: that for temporall things dreame of a <hi>fifth Monarchie,</hi> and for Church affaires would faine force all to doe as they doe, that is, to put their Noses under the Popes girdle. And though here I digresse a little, I hope it will be pardoned.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="11" type="section">
      <head>§ 11</head>
      <p>As for those particular <hi>Prodigies</hi> which the History at hand makes mention of▪ the Reader may well admire at them, and happily revolve these questions in his minde. Whether there were such things as are here related▪ Whether they are truly Prodigious or no. Whether those Events here adopted to them were portended. Whether the like things have not happened elseywhere without like effects or consequences, with more of likenature, if hee bee either cautious, or scrupulous, to alwhich I have onely this to answere. If any credit may be given to such Histories of <hi>Germane</hi> affaires, as commonly fall into the hands of the learned, from <hi>Mercurius Gallo-Belgicus;</hi> it is certaine that <hi>Africa</hi> was not antiently more famous for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
<pb facs="13"/>
then <hi>Germany</hi> hath for many yeares been of <hi>Prodigies.</hi> The particulars hereafter mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned make not a fourth part of what might be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in like kinde. And if <hi>Prodigies</hi> be taken in a large sense, as they are here to be understood, the matter doth well answer the title. But this must needs be granted, this or that single prodigie may happen, and yet no remarkable judgement follow. For God may shake his rod often, before he strike once. And many times he threatens, but to try. But when Heaven and Earth, Sea, and Land did all make one outery, and strike up an <hi>Alarum,</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could be expected, but that God should march on apace in fury after. It is but a gentrall intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this or that Iudgement, that Prodigies doe make necessarily. But what else could bee expected but shedding bloud on earth, when it rained bloud from heaven. Battailes in the Ayre were most lively pictures of the same to bee on earth. So that wee may truly say, God wrote his minde in most lively Characters, and hath punctually fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led what hee threatned. It seemes they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of longer peace, or else God needed not to have reade them so many Lectures of bloud: what particular Iudgements are signified by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Prodigies</hi> may wel be guessed by the Prodigies themselves: for my owne part <hi>I beleeve, admire,</hi> and <hi>adore,</hi> and shal wonder at him that can doe
<pb facs="13"/>
lesse. I doe every day expect the like and greater, because our Saviour hath so largely prophesied in this kinde in reference to ourtimes, which all the Evangelists have recorded. The latter dayes shal bee short beyond expectation, and Christ come soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then we are aware, and therefore the signes of his comming must needs bee expected, whereof strange Prodigies are one.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="12" type="section">
      <head>§ 12</head>
      <p>Aud now hopeing this may satisfie such as have anycandor; its high time to draw the Arrow to the head, and hit the marke I shoote at, which is to point out the Christian use which godly feare and reverence teaches us to make upon the knowledge of these dreadfull things. To which end there are some cautions to be premised.</p>
      <p>I Seeing God is the author of Prodigies, wee must religiously observe them, and by prayer seeke from him instruction and grace, to fit us for a holy improvement of them to his glory and our own benefit; Saying as <hi>Paul,</hi> when Christ spake to him in a vision out of Heaven, <hi>Lord what wilt thou</hi>
         <note place="margin">Acte. 9. 6.</note>
         <hi>have mee to doe?</hi> And with prayer wee must joyne all diligence in studying of his holy word, for thence it is that al necessary instruction is dertved. Be we sure to make use of Prodigies according to this rule, and light will come out of darkenesse, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort out of feare.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="14"/>
Secondly we may not bee too curious in searching after the particular evills which Prodigies fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shew, much lesse to know their circumstances, when, where, and how they shall happen. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us, and great mercy from God, that we have, aforehand, so much as the noise of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to aflict. In the state of Israel, God was wont to threaten in the Fathers dayes those Judgements which hee purposed to their posteritie, and yet upon those threatnings, he expected present repentance. And surely that <hi>Memento</hi> given by Christ unto the Angell of <hi>Sardis,</hi> is necessary for every Church and state to apply uato themselves in these dayes: <hi>Remember how thou hast received, and heard,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Rev. 3 3.</note>
         <hi>and hold fast and repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come on thee as a thiefe, and thou shalt not know what houre I will come upon thee.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>A third caveat</hi> is that, which God himselfe<note place="margin">Ier. 10. 2.</note> gives by the Prophet Ieremy, <hi>Learne not the way of the heathen, and be not dismaied at the signes of heaven. For the heathen are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied at them.</hi> Where a things are forbidden. The one is learning the heathens way, that is, to worship the creatures themselves, or to use any part of their Idolatrous service: The other is excessive feare upon the sight of all unpleasant aspects in the heavenly bodies, without any true feare of God who
<pb facs="14"/>
causes them, and in whose hand it is to hasten or prolong, increase or diminish, or totally remove all threatned evils. The grosser sort of antient Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters<note place="margin">Ezech. 8.</note> thought the Sun, Moone, and other starres to be Gods, and Eclipses and such like to be signes of their anger, whereupon they feared exceedingly unto astonishment, and addicted themselves by divers rites and ceremonies to pacify them. Many times the <hi>Israelites</hi> were much subiect to like Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, against which God there instructs them. This place therfore does not condemne all feare upon the sight of prodigies, as unlawfull, but the abuse of feare, when it is placed on the creature, not on God, and leades not to true piety, but to will worship. Or when it so captivates, that we thinke it in vaine to seeke God by repentance, and doe hereupon despise him, and harden our hearts, and commit all int<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with greedinesse. Of all things such a feare is most to be feared. As for such whom a lively faith hath incorporated into Christ, and a true feare of God in his iudgements, made penitent and obedient according to Gods word. Prodigies should rather comfort them, then otherwise. Ioel having said in one verse, <hi>The Sunne shall bee turned into darknesse, and the Moone into blood, before the great and terrible day of the Lord come,</hi> saith immediately in the uext <hi>verse, It shall come to passe that who soever</hi>
         <pb facs="15"/>
         <hi>shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. For in Mount Sion and in Ierusalem shall be deliverance.</hi> Our Saviour speaking in<note place="margin">Luke. 21. 31.</note> like manner of the Prodigies which shall happen partly before the destruction of Ierusalem, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially before the end of the world, and of the feare which shall be in many, said to his disciples, <hi>When these things begin to come to passe, then looke up and lift up your heads, for your redemption draweth nigh,</hi> Christ the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisher &amp; finisher of it. Thus much for caution.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="13" type="section">
      <head>§ 13</head>
      <p>Now for the uses themselves, who will not hereby be assured of a generall judgement comming on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, seeing these forerunners of it. I speake both of the Prodigies, and of the things which follow and accompany. The order of the signes of the latter day is this. First false Prophets. Many shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Iniquity shall abound. Secondly, persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by meanes thereof Apostacy in some, great misery to others. Then Warres, Famine, Pestilence. <hi>Prodigies,</hi> interchangeably, till false Prophets, and al deceived by them be rootea out of the earth. And as touching warrs, judgement must begin at the house of God. Therein false Prophets arise, as<note place="margin">Acts. 20.</note>
         <hi>Paul</hi> saies, <hi>from among your selves</hi> &amp;c. Their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing is like the opening of Pandoraes box, the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of alevil. And certainly the churches negligence in not convincing them by doctrine, and suppressing them by discipline in the particular Churches wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="15"/>
they first appeared is the corner stone of all, and therefore it is fit gods churches should be first in the course of Judgement, who are first in the course of sinning. The third course of signes which are now most conspicuous shall continue till the first error be discovered and amended, and that evill which it hath brought in be removed, I meane particular Churches be rightly stated, and faithfull in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of all publicke Ordinances, &amp;c.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="14" type="section">
      <head>§ 14</head>
      <p>In the meane while▪ <hi>for a second use,</hi> let every one of us learne hence, <hi>To search and try our waies, and turne unto the Lord our God,</hi> lest our securitie prove prodigious unto us. Be we more carefull to know Gods will, and to professe that we know, and live according to our profession; in one or other of these specialties we all faile. Yea wherein is it that we faile not? see the state of the seven Churches of <hi>Asia,</hi> as St. <hi>Iohn</hi> describes it, and I feare whatsoever is reproved in all them together▪ will be found among us, but little of that which they are commended for. Were it not that God is iealous of his own honour, and (in his own phrase) <hi>feares the wrath of the enemie, lest our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries</hi>
         <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 27.</note>
         <hi>should behave themselves strangely, and say, our hand is high, the Lord hath not done this,</hi> we also ere this time had felt the effect of many prodigies which have beene among our selves. But I hope God will shortly stirre up some in a more especiall manner, to bring Gods
<pb facs="16"/>
wonders among us in remembrance. This for the present may serve something to awaken us. And if we regard neither the voyce of God on earth, by his <hi>Ministers,</hi> nor the voyce of God from heaven by his wonderous workes, <hi>though Noah, Job, and Daniel were among us, they shall deliver but their owne soules.</hi> God must deny himselfe, or we perish if we continue impenitent, The name of reformation which we have in our mouthes, will no more helpe us then the <hi>Iewes</hi> crying. <hi>The Temple of the Lord, We be Abrahams chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> In many abuses there is not so much as a colour of reformation, as in the matter of sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for one. It was after <hi>Iosiah</hi> had reformed many things, that his heart was tender, and smote him upon hearing of the Law. Perceiving thereby there were yet more abuses in the Land than he at first was ware of. Antichrist had made all places like <hi>Augean</hi> stables. They doe therefore surely neede a continuall clensing. The God of all grace fill us according to our measure with wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and zeale, that we may grow from beauty to beauty in his eyes.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="15" type="section">
      <head>§ 15.</head>
      <p>And seeing God is so gracious, as by all meanes to manifest himselfe and his intended judgements, he hath not left himselfe without witnesse, but we
<pb facs="16"/>
are altogether without excuse. Let him have the prayse which is due unto his name, who abounds to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward us in all meanes of grace, whereby we might be made wise unto salvation. Thy Word, O Lord, is sufficient of it selfe to warne all the World. Thy Workes are the utmost that we can aske or thinke: what shall we say of thy wonderous Workes from day to day! Oh thou holy one of <hi>Israel.</hi> All this is <hi>that thou mightest be justified in thy sayings,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Rom 3. 4.</note>
         <hi>and overcome when thou art judged.</hi> It will be thy glory that thou ast shewed us signes in Heaven above, and wonders in Earth beneath, But it will be our misery if we regard them not, or if regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we doe not blesse thee the Almighty, or if blessing thee in words we repent not and amend. Of our selves we are able to doe none of all this. Let it not alwayes be said of us as it was sometime of thy<note place="margin">Deut. 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> people <hi>Israel, Yet the Lord hath not given you a heart to perceive, and eyes to see, and eares to heare unto this day.</hi> For thy Annoyiteds sake powre upon us thy spirit, give us hearts according to thine owne heart, and cause us to walke in thy wayes. Truth Lord, thou mayst leave us to our selves, and let us perish: if thy Grace were not free for thee, to besto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>r not, it were no grace. If thou sayest, I have no pleasure in you, doe to us as seemeth good in thy sight. Yet be pleased to remember thy Covenant. And for his sake who hath sealed it
<pb facs="17"/>
with his bloud poure out his spirit among us. Worke knowledge in our minds, submission in our wills. Yea sanctify us we beseech thee throughout. Oh love us, and cause us to love thee, and then wee know assuredly that all things shall worke together for the best, Amen.</p>
      <p>If any thing offend thee Christian Reader in this Prologue, consider herein I tread an unbeaten path, wherein it is easie to erre. The way it selfe is rough, my spare houres for such imployment few. Importunity of others, and arguments drawne from the publicke good, have stollen mee from my selfe to doe others service in this businesse. If it seeme strange I make so much a doe to usher in a small Pamphlet, consider not the book, but the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. In Prodigies God comes in, as <hi>riding on a Cherub, and flying on the wings of the wind.</hi> How then can just exceptions be taken at one for cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before to cry<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 44. 43.</note>
         <hi>Bow the knee?</hi> my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse pardoned I am content to beare all other blame.</p>
      <epigraph>
         <q>In Magnis est volxisse Satis.</q>
      </epigraph>
   </div>
   <div type="errata">
      <head type="sub">Errors in the Preface.</head>
      <p>In the first Sect. r. Axiona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a. for him r. himself. In 2. Sect. them r. him for fooler foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e. 3. Sect. for suspitiously r. superstitiously, for paedicant r p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rdica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. 5. Sect. for No is in mar. 1. Iovis so, mer men▪ in 7 Sect. so pledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> pledges in mat-tom r. revel. for prediens r. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>edict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ors in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t r. which ate adapted.</p>
      <pb facs="17"/>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>