<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the discreet and true searchers of the secrets of Na∣ture, leading a solitary life.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121240_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05040</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15184</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121240</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the discreet and true searchers of the secrets of Na∣ture, leading a solitary life.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reuelation of the secret spirit : Declaring the most concealed secret of alchymie. Written first in Latine by an vnknowne author, but explained in Italian, by Iohn Baptista Lambye, Venetian. Lately translated into English, by R.N.E. gentleman</title>
                 <author>Agnello, Giovan Battista</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Skelton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 80, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the discreet and true searchers of the secrets of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, leading a solitary life.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>Iohn Baptista Lambye,</hi> Venetian,
wisheth health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing spent many yeeres, and inestimable labours, about that Science, which by all the wisest Philosophers is called diuine and secret; according to the experience which I haue had in my selfe, I cannot choose but haue compassion of those noble Spirits, who are turmoiled in the difficulty thereof; and therefore as it hath beene a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto me, to finde him who in any thing could haue helped my study; euen so will I
<pb facs="7"/>
freely (so farre as I can) helpe others; insomuch as by long trauell and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I could attaine: Neuerthelesse with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out departing any waies from the custome of our wisest Masters, who in writing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer addressed themselues to the vulgar, but to the onely children of truth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing in my hands a little Treatise of an vncertaine Author, intituled, <hi>A Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the secret Spirit,</hi> short in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of leaues, but according to my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in sentences and learning most graue: and to my knowledge no more Copies seene in light, I thought good to set it forth vnto the benefit of you all, who are inamoured of this diuine Science. And that it might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come so much the more profitable and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, I haue purposed yet to adorne the same with a short Exposition and allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of sentences of the best Philosophers. Not perhaps in such manner as you could haue wished, or the matter hath required, but at least as my weaknesse could, and the custome of our Masters doth permit to doe. Therefore I pray you accept cheerefully this
<pb facs="7"/>
so much as a courteous minde desirous to helpe and to further, could for the present giue; praying our Lord God, without whose fauour so excellent a science cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that he would both giue vnto me the grace to be able to shew some thing profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vnto you to vnderstand and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, no otherwise than to the honour and glory of his glorious and blessed name.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>