<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>I pray thee (gentle Reader) to haue an eye to the Marginall notes, and referre them to their right places: and also to correcte thy booke from these faults following, and afterwardes to reade with iudgement too thy profite and comfort.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121928_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17727</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121928</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>I pray thee (gentle Reader) to haue an eye to the Marginall notes, and referre them to their right places: and also to correcte thy booke from these faults following, and afterwardes to reade with iudgement too thy profite and comfort.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three propositions or speeches, which that excellent man M. Iohn Caluin, one of the pastors of the Church of God in Geneua had there : To which also is added, an exposition vpon that parte of the catechisme, which is appointed for the three and fortieth Sunday in number. Translated into Englishe, by T.VV</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 82, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="99"/>
   <head>I pray thee (gentle Reader) to haue an eye to the Marginall notes, and referre them to their right places: and also to correcte thy booke from these faults following, and afterwardes to reade with iudgement too thy profite and comfort.</head>
   <p>Follio <hi>6.</hi> Pag. <hi>2.</hi> Line <hi>12.</hi> For abroade, reade aboade. Fol. <hi>9.</hi> b. line <hi>22.</hi> For vve thē, reade vve must not then. Fol. <hi>13.</hi> b in the margent, for de sacro Basil, reade de sacro Baptist. Fol. <hi>18.</hi> b line <hi>6.</hi> for it said, reade it vvas said. Fol. <hi>20.</hi> b. line <hi>22.</hi> for accept, reade except. Fol. <hi>23</hi> a. line <hi>19.</hi> for imperfection, reade perfection. Fol. <hi>24.</hi> b. line <hi>3</hi> for vvinne, reade conuince. Fol. <hi>29.</hi> b. line <hi>18</hi> for confirme, reade conforme. Fol. <hi>31.</hi> b line <hi>8</hi> for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, reade nation. Fol. <hi>34.</hi> a laste line, for sufficiently, reade stifly. Fol. <hi>39.</hi> a. line <hi>25.</hi> for sinnes, reade sinnner. Fol. <hi>39.</hi> b. line <hi>9.</hi> for vvorde, reade, corde, Fol. <hi>40.</hi> b line <hi>19.</hi> for debated, reade cast dovvne. Fol. <hi>41.</hi> a. line <hi>3.</hi> for makers, reade vvoorkes. Fol. <hi>41.</hi> a. line <hi>12.</hi> for one, ceade do one. Fol. <hi>42.</hi> b. line <hi>24.</hi> for beastly, reade beasts. Fol. <hi>50.</hi> b. line <hi>10.</hi> for at time, at that time. Fol. <hi>59.</hi> a line first, for dead, reade death. Fol. <hi>63.</hi> a. lin <hi>22.</hi> for his reade this, and b. line <hi>23.</hi> for in it, reade in vs.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>