<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all such, as through weakenesse of judgement, with some supersti∣tious feare, and not by any malevolent spirit of opposition and schisme, are offended at the Decency of our Churches, and the Reverend demeanure of our out∣ward expressions in Gods publique Worship.</title>
           <author>Robartes, Foulke</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121261_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10795</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21068</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121261</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all such, as through weakenesse of judgement, with some supersti∣tious feare, and not by any malevolent spirit of opposition and schisme, are offended at the Decency of our Churches, and the Reverend demeanure of our out∣ward expressions in Gods publique Worship.</title>
                 <author>Robartes, Foulke</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods holy house and service : according to the primitive and most Christian forme thereof, described by Foulke Robarts, Batchelor of Divinity, and prebendary of Norvvich</title>
                 <author>Robartes, Foulke</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergier, Richard 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 98, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all such, as through weakenesse of judgement, with some supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious feare, and not by any malevolent spirit of opposition and schisme, are offended at the Decency of our Churches, and the Reverend demeanure of our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward expressions in Gods publique Worship.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Loving Brethren,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worship of God hath of late yeares beene so carried in many places among us, as if therein men were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any businesse relating unto God. The places of meetings being so ruinous and sordid, the people in the act of prayers and praises de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning themselves so, as if they sate in counsell with God: (a gesture, of which <hi>Tertulian</hi> saith, that in prayer, it is <hi>irreligiosissimum,</hi> a most irreligious <note place="margin">L. de orat.</note> thing,) rather than devoute and humble worships. Much irreverence was in administring and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="3"/>
the holy Communion. I have often conceived hereupon, that either Papist, Turke, or Pagan, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our fashion, would thinke that either our Churches were not the houses of the holy God, or that the people in them were not about Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. Our present most reverend Metropolian hath in his Metropoliticall visitation, layd those grounds, which have already reformed much, and I trust will (by Gods mercy) soone reduce all things in Gods worship, to due decency, and reverence, all England over; Not doubting of the like successe in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which we finde in the Diocesse of <hi>Norwich:</hi> For while the right reverend Father now Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Elie,</hi> for the time his Lordship was our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocesan (as an other <hi>Elishaeus,</hi> in the spirit of <hi>Elias)</hi> his Lordship so proceeded in this pious worke, as that <hi>the worke of the Lord prospered in his hands.</hi> The house and service of God shineth among us in the primitive splendor, to the great good liking of all sober Christians. But as when S. <hi>Paul</hi> preached of the resurrection, <hi>Some beleeved, others mocked,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 17.</note> So upon sight of this good worke, so happily begunne, and so effectually followed; some joyfully confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; others frowardly opposed. The one encouraged, the other exasperated my poore zeale; first by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and private communications, &amp; now by prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this slender treatise, to put forth my selfe a weak labourer, under such <hi>Aholiabs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bezaliels,</hi> master workemen.</p>
   <p>I doe not in all this little treatise frame any one proposition, which I doe not in my conscience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb facs="3"/>
to be the truth of God. Nor doe Iuse any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument or reason, but such as I apprehend naturally to inferre the conclusion. My desire herein (God knoweth) is your satisfaction and right informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in that, which not a little concerneth Gods glory, and your good. Thinke not that I would reduce all Gods worship, to bodily gestures; Neither imagine, that it belongeth to the soule alone: The soule is the most excellent part, whose intentions recommend the expressions of the body unto God. But the body is a part, and an essentiall part of the man; and must beare his part with the soule in Gods worship. If the body act alone, then doth God say, Man, where is thy soule? If the soule alone take all upon it; then saith God, where is, or what doth thy body? Where are thine eyes, thy hands, thy knees, thy legges, to declare and accompany the lifting up, the humility, and the confidence of thy soule? Thy whole man is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in my worship: It is for God and for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that I do pleade thus earnestly with my bretheren. How decent a thing is it in the eye of man, to behold bodies and soules accord and joyne together, in the holy worke? How doth the visible and expressive devotion of one Christian, beget and encrease the same in an other? And how powerfully shall the reverend behaviours and gestures of an whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation together worke one upon an other? Is not God the more glorified when our devotion is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and advanced. O my bretheren; be not froward, but meeke and tractable. Boy strous men, in a spirit of error or opposition or both, have made too much
<pb facs="4"/>
stirre, troubled and affrighted honest hearts. On the other side, some men expressing devotion outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, give too much scandall through want of probity. But I beseech you turne away your eyes from men; turne them upon God, and then turne them home upon your selves: And then, tell me; doe you not perceive the Majesty of God to be so great, as that it becommeth the whole man, soule and body to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane himselfe, in all points of humility and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, inward and outward, when he is in Gods speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all presence? Is not the excellent goodnesse of God such, as drawes all mens eyes upon him, and feedes them all with expectation? Is not his bounty such as filleth every living thing with plenty of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? Shall not the eye then looke up towards God, in admiration and hope? Shall not the hand be lifted up, shewing the heart ready to receive the blessing, and to reach out thankes? Speake to God with the intention, judgement and fervency of the soule. Speake also by the expressions of the members of thy body. Speake by thy tongue; Speake by thine eyes; Speake by thine hands and by thy knees. The tongue interpreteth the meaning of the soule, by words. The eyes and hands interpret the confident expectation of the soule, by their elevation. The knees interpret the humilitie of the soule by bowing. And so the rest of our decent gestures doe interpret the soule, every one in its owne language, which God intendeth, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth and accepteth; when they truly declare out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, what the soule conceiveth inwardly. But I am asked what neede these gestures and postures
<pb facs="4"/>
more now, than heretofore? Whereto I answer, that there is no more neede to use these decent and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend gestures and expressions, in the worship of God now, than heretofore. And that if heretofore wee have been defective in what was requisite, it is time that now we be reformed. Againe, if by heretofore, yee understand the space of 40. or 50. yeares last passed: I confesse that what we performe now, may seeme a novelty. But if by heretofore you meane the best and primitive times, of the ages next the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and before the dayes superstition crept on: then I say that there is no more required now, than what was in use in the practise of Christians hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. God therefore give us grace to discerne truth from error, and light from darkenesse, and not to bee put out of the way of true devotion, through a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nike feare of a supposed superstition; heartily prayeth</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At my Study in Norwich,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>March.</hi> 4. 1638.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your loving brother, <hi>Fowlke Robarts.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>