<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE VN∣TO THE CHRISTIAN REA∣DER, TOVCHING THE causes
and the maner of our publish∣ing this Treatise.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121934_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05190</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15324</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121934</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE VN∣TO THE CHRISTIAN REA∣DER, TOVCHING THE causes
and the maner of our publish∣ing this Treatise.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The prophane schisme of the Brovvnists or separatists : With the impietie, dissensions, levvd, and abhominable vices of that impure sect. Discouered by Christopher Lavvne, Iohn Fovvler, Clement Sanders, Robert Bulvvard. Lately returned from the companie of M. Iohnson, tha wicked brother, into the bosome of the Church of England, their true mother</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burre, Walter</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO THE CHRISTIAN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER, TOVCHING THE causes
and the maner of our publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Treatise.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that hideth his sins shall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper; but hee
that confesseth and forsaketh them, shall haue mercie,</hi> Prou.
28.13. Our sin of separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereby we haue reiected the communion of all
true Churches, being now made manifest vnto vs vpon such occasion as is
hereafter declared in this Treatise, and we desiring to receiue mercie from
the Father of mercies, haue therefore resolued and thought in our selues,
according to the counsell of the holy Ghost, that we will not hide our
iniquitie, but confesse against our selues our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto the
Lord, that the punishmēt of our sin may be forgiuen vs. Our owne
ignorance, and the deceit fulnes of others had drawne vs into the depth of this
error; and in the middest of this deepe Schisme, when the Lord might
iustly haue iudged and rebuked vs in wrath, euen then were wee bold to iudge
and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne <pb facs="3"/> others that were better than our selues, and farre
excelling vs in all the gifts and graces of Gods Spirit; wee condemned them and
slandered our whole nation as a false Church, false Christians, a
Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Satan, and a people according to their publike profession in
a damnable estate; we exempted none, neither the learnedest and godliest
Ministers, nor zealousest people, but condemned all, and auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all in
the seruice of God: And therefore to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish our repentance for this
scandalous Separation, we hold it in the first place a iust and
necessarie cause for the publishing of this Treatise.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>He that is first in his owne cause is iust; then commeth
his neighbour and maketh enquirie of him;</hi> Prou. 18.17. Master
<hi>Iohnson</hi> and his confederates being parties accused by vs, and
being iudges also in their owne cause, haue first condemned vs with their
censure; when we complained of their sinne, they could find no way to
cleare themselues but by accusing vs, so that when wee renounced their
Schisme, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced their curse against vs, and thus declared vs to
be their enemies, when wee told them the truth. In this case the holy Ghost
alloweth vs to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie for our selues, in enquiring into, and
refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting those slanders which they lay vpon vs, and make the ground of
their sentence against vs. They haue condemned vs first in their owne
Church. Wee do now in the second place by a publike appeale bring the matter
before the Churches of Christ, to iudge thereof. This is also another
cause of our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at this time.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>When thou art conuerted, strengthen thy
brethren;</hi> Luke 22.32. Being our selues deliuered from this snare of
the Separation, our desire is to stretch out a hand of helpe and comfort
vnto those, that yet lie in that ditch: and wee are not without hope of
some fruit of our endeuours this way; but especially our hope is to stay
and strengthen some weake Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that are inclining and looking that
way, whom we admonish and desire them in the Lord that they would bee
warned by our harmes, and by our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing astray, to walke the more
circumspectly in the middest of all offences and scandals wherewith they
shall meete. As for those that are alreadie separate and caught in the
briars of that Schisme, although we do assure our selues vpon good
ground, that sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie of them do wish they had neuer met with the
Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paration, and would also much reioyce if they were well quit and freed
from the same, yea and haue wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed some of them that there might be a
dissolution of their schismaticall bodie, that so they might escape
without excommunication; yet are they in the meane time kept vnder in such
bondage by the terror, tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, &amp; subtiltie of their guides, which they
shew both in their doctrine and in their gouernment, that they dare not
easily whisper or muffe against the separatiō. As for those whose
feet are almost gone, &amp; their steps wel neere slipt, we desire thē
to pause a while; it is not so easie a matter to come out of that snare
when they are fallen therein, as it is to keepe out at first, &amp; for the
stay of such we haue thought it needfull to publish this Treatise for
their further information touching <pb facs="4"/> the estate of
<hi>Brownisme,</hi> as also to warne all such as haue bin the occasion
of those Heresies and Schismes to conforme themselues to the Church of
God, that these Caterpillers may no more rise out of them.</p>
   <p>And although we be vnlearned men which haue composed this booke,
yet we hope it will not be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked therefore, seeing we speake of nothing
but which our owne knowledge and experience hath taught vs; and the admonition
may take better place, because that the most which are taken in the net of
<hi>Brownisme</hi> are men of our condition.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>