<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my worthy and much honou∣red friends, M aster William Hackwill Es∣quire, one of his Maiesties Iustices of Peace for the Countie of Buckingham, with his truely ver∣tuous and religious Bedfellow, Mistris Elizabeth Hackwill, the dew of Heauen, and fatnesse of the Earth, Grace and Peace bee multiplied in Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Crompton, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121236_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19626</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6061</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121236</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my worthy and much honou∣red friends, M aster William Hackwill Es∣quire, one of his Maiesties Iustices of Peace for the Countie of Buckingham, with his truely ver∣tuous and religious Bedfellow, Mistris Elizabeth Hackwill, the dew of Heauen, and fatnesse of the Earth, Grace and Peace bee multiplied in Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Crompton, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vvedding-ring, fitted to the finger of euery paire that haue or shall meete in the feare of God: or, That diuine circle of heauenly loue, wherein man and wife should walke all their dayes : The posie whereof is an expression of a good husbands kindnesse toward his vertuous wife, with her retaliacion of like affection</title>
                 <author>Crompton, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 36, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my worthy and much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red friends, M aster <hi>William Hackwill</hi> Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, one of his Maiesties Iustices of Peace for the Countie of Buckingham, with his truely ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and religious Bedfellow, Mistris <hi>Elizabeth Hackwill,</hi> the dew of Heauen, and fatnesse of the Earth, Grace and Peace bee multiplied in Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipfull, and right dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued: I haue often sought oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to salute you ioyntly; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging my selfe your deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor many wayes, &amp; which is more; vnable to satisfie any: it was the griefe of <hi>Darius,</hi> that he should die indebted to his friend, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting he bewayled, as his last, not his least mis-hap, hauing receiued a courtesie, hee should not liue to requite it. if such an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement
<pb facs="3"/> may not goe in part of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I might despaire; hauing receiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from you, both while J liued neere you, as since my remouall at your motion, into these parts (distance of place hath not stopt the current of affection, nor absence begot obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion) and yet find my selfe able to doe no more: onely this is my comfort, Good-will hath not beene wanting; if abilitie answered desire, you should find me as readie to pay, as to confesse: J would not faigne a debt; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease it, the propertie of insinuating flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; neither would I denie it, where it is due, the guise of seruile basenesse; iudging it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thus to publish my owne pouertie, then to be censured as vngratefull, or of my friends forgetfull.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Preaching at the Marriage of Mr. <hi>Iohn Berrie.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Occasion</hi> lately directed my meditations vpon this subiect: wherein the mutuall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse of your choyce, did often present it selfe vnto my thoughts; the matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of handling;</p>
   <p>(If the testimonie of an experienst friend
<pb facs="3"/> may be thought impartiall) applying it selfe most fully &amp; fitly to you both; that I could not forbeare to impart it as a messenger of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, no worke of worth; except you bee pleased by acceptation, to make it worth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>using: here you may read your selues, and be stir'd vp to blesse God, the maker of Marriages, for his good prouidence in your meeting; here you may see that Wedding-ring, which you both put on, in conceit and resolution, at the Marriage-day; that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Circle or heauenly round of heartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting-loue, wherein you doe, and all mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried persons should moue during life; to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their owne vertuous mates, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling others; am I deceiued? or experience hath taught mee what I haue written: no more: neither may I speake; what I haue seene and obserued, of your happinesse in this kind: liue long more happy; it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to pray, as <hi>Ioab</hi> for <hi>Dauid:</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.3.</note> The Lord your God adde vnto it an hundred-fold, that your eyes may see it: the Lord increase
<pb facs="4"/> your content daily, and double the portion of the sauing graces of his Spirit vpon you both: otherwise I cannot steed you; prayers you shall not want, while I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my studie in</hi> Barstaple, <date>Ianuary 1. 1630.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>W. CROMPTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>