<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE R. HONOVRABLE LORD ROBERT EARLE OF ANCRAM.</title>
           <author>Tozer, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121020_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13851</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24159</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121020</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE R. HONOVRABLE LORD ROBERT EARLE OF ANCRAM.</title>
                 <author>Tozer, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christian wisdome, or The excellency fame and right meanes of true wisdome : As it was briefly delivered in a sermon in St Maries Church in Oxford. Novemb: 11. 1638. By H. Tozer B. D. Fellow of Exeter Colledge</title>
                 <author>Tozer, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 107, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE</hi> R. HONOVRABLE LORD <hi>ROBERT</hi> EARLE OF ANCRAM.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>R. HONOVRABLE.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HERE adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to present to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>of the Praise and Worth of Wisdome.</hi> Were the Discourse answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Subject, it were
<pb facs="3"/> a Treasure indeed and well worth the keeping, but the emptinesse of that may well giue the World just cause to think it to be, as it is, too far below the acceptance of so great a Personage, and my selfe so much the more unadvisedly bold in presenting the same unto You. However, it will not bee very seasonable to enlarge a Preface with variety of studied words and elaborate expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="3"/> for the obtaining of Your <hi>Lordship's</hi> favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptation, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed to adventure on a second incongruous boldnesse in trespassing on Your wonted <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> and dayly serious <hi>Imployment:</hi> whereof the One, as the world knows well, respecteth not so much a verball obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance as plaine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty and Truth; and the Other, which duly is discharged in waiting on
<pb facs="4"/> the service of GOD and Your KING, doth sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome give leave to spend much time in the reading of long Epistles and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dedications.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, to say all that is needfull in a litle, if any by reading this plaine Discourse shall be occasioned to entertaine one Thought of seeking after VVisdome more than before hee had, 'tis that which, God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, was my ayme in the
<pb facs="4"/> Publication thereof: and if, for this purpose, Your <hi>Lordship</hi> shall please to let it goe forth under Your Honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and accept the Dedication of it as a true acknowledgment of that service, wherein I have stood long engaged, 'tis more than I deserve, and all that I doe or can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire.</p>
   <p>God direct the hearts of all men to seek after that wisdome, which is
<pb facs="5"/> acceptable and makes them such, who love it: and may the Gift there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be ever multiplied on Your Honourable Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the magnifying of God's glory here, and Your's hereafter: which is the true desire and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned Prayer of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships Humble Servant <hi>HENRY TOZER.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>