<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE LIFE OF DOROTHEVS GATHERED by the Translator.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121374_Fr5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00440</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121374</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE LIFE OF DOROTHEVS GATHERED by the Translator.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The auncient ecclesiasticall histories of the first six hundred yeares after Christ : wrytten in the Greeke tongue by three learned historiographers, Eusebius, Socrates, and Euagrius. Eusebius Pamphilus Bishop of Cæsarea in Palæstina vvrote 10 bookes. Socrates Scholasticu of Constantinople vvrote 7 bookes. Euagrius Scholasticus of Antioch vvrote 6 bookes. VVhereunto is annexed Dorotheus Bishop of Tyrus, of the liues of the prophetes, apostles and 70 disciples. All which authors are faithfully translated out of the Greeke tongue by Meredith Hanmer, Maister of Arte and student in diuinitie. Last of all herein is contayned a profitable chronographie collected by the sayd translator, the title whereof is to be seene in the ende of this volume, with a copious index of the principall matters throughout all the histories</title>
                 <author>Eusebius, of Caesarea, Bishop of Caesarea</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 176, that is 190, 201-402, 4, 403-538, 2, 56, 18 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb n="514" facs="260"/>
   <head>THE LIFE OF DOROTHEVS GATHERED by the Translator.</head>
   <p>DOrotheus vvas a rare and singular man, vvell seene in the Latine, Greeke and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brevv tongues. He flourished in the time of Diocletian, Constantinus Magnus, Constā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius &amp; Iulian the Apostata. Eusebius Pamphilus one that knevve him very vvell &amp; heard<note place="margin">Euseb. eccles. hist. li. 7. ca. 31</note> his gift of vtterance, vvryteth thus of him: Dorotheus minister of the Church of Antioch vvas a very eloquent and singular man. He applied holye Scripture diligentlye, he studied the Hebrevve tongue so that he reade vvith great skill the holy Scriptures in Hebrevve. This man came of a noble race. He vvas expert in the chiefe discipline of the Grecians, by nature an Eunuche, so disposed from his natiuitye. For vvhich cause the Emperour for rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse thereof appropriated him, placing and preferringe him to be magistrate in the citie of Tyrus, and to ouersee the dieing of purple. VVe heard him our selues expounding holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">Democh. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. Christ. religi.</note> vvith greate commendation in the Church of God. So farre Eusebius. Antonius De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mochares saith of him, that he vvas exiled in the persecution vnder Diocletian, and that he returned from banishment after the death of Diocletian and Licinius, and recouered his Bishopricke againe, vvhere he continevved vnto the raygne of Iulian, about the yeare of our Lord 365. And because Iulian persecuted not the Christians openly him selfe, but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly by his gouernours and Magistrates, Dorotheus vvas faine againe to flie vnto the city of Odissus, vvhere (as Petrus de Natalibus vvriteth) the officers of Iulian apprehended<note place="margin">Petrus de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus lib. 6. de Sanctis.</note> him and tormented him to death for his testimony of Christ Iesus. There he died and vvas crovvned Martyr being a hundred and seuen yere old. An. Dom. 366. Of his vvorkes there is none extant saue this treatise contayning the liues and endes of the Prophetes, Apostles, and seuenty Disciples of our sauiour mentioned in the Gospell after Luke, the vvhich he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, by translation a compendium or briefe tract.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>