<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader</title>
           <author>S., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121081_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25786</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader</title>
                 <author>S., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian dictionarie : opening the signification of the chiefe wordes dispersed generally through Holie Scriptures of the Old and New Testament, tending to increase Christian knowledge. Whereunto is annexed: a perticular dictionary for the Reuelation of S. Iohn. For th Canticles, or Song of Salomon. For the Epistle to the Hebrues. By Tho: Wilson minister of the Word, at Saint Georges in Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 240, 243-577, 1, 234, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader</head>
   <p>ALthough words be the significations of things, yet as <hi>Aug. de doct. Christ. lib. 4. and cap. 11.</hi> saith verie well: It is a note of the best &amp; wisest men, <hi>In verbis, verum amare, non verba, quid enim prodest clauis aurea si ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rire quod volumus non potest? Aut quid obestlignea, si hoc potest, &amp;c.</hi> In words, to loue the truth more then the wordes; For what anayleth a Key of Gold, if it cannot open the Treasure that we would faine enioy? Or what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth a Key of Wood, if it can open it, &amp;c. <hi>Lewes Viues</hi> hath fitly obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of <hi>Augustin de ciu: dei lib. 13. cap. 24. Quanti sit momenti ad omnes artes disciplinas{que} intelligendas vera &amp; Germana vocabularum cognitio.</hi> The true and proper signification and knowledge of words, is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great moment and consequence to the vnderstanding of all Artes. It is verie fit therefore (good Reader) thou shouldst imitate the wise Traueller, he will be carefull to attaine to as much skill as may bee in the Languages of all those parts and Countries through which he is to passe, that he may with the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer inconueniences, be interrupted in the way, and with greater expedition may runne his intended race and iourney: So thou, in thine intended iourney to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, if thou be ignorant of the Language, Customes, Wordes, Phrases, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and Orders of the place and Countrey, wilt meete with a World of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences, to interrupt thine intention, and discourage thee in thy course, so as thou wilt either leaue off, or verie faintly and vncomfortably go forward. For as the same <hi>Augustine</hi> saith again verie truly, <hi>Nam aut ignotum verbū, facit haerere lectorē, antignota locutio;</hi> Either an vnknown word causeth the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to sticke, or an vnknowne Phrase and manner of speaking. Vse therefore this Booke, which God hath affoorded for thy good, and for thy guide, reade it diligently, and be much conuersant therein, it will be a faithfull guide and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter vnto thee; It will bring thee acquainted with the Language, Phrase, and Customes of <hi>Canaan;</hi> It will open vnto thee the hidden Treasures of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Wisedome, and it will tell thee in plaine <hi>English</hi> and easie tearmes, the minde and meaning of thy good God towards thee. Entertaine it kindly, and take it vp vnto thee, as that Noble <hi>Eunuch</hi> did his guide Phillip. Acts 8, 31, 39. and it will make thee (as he did) go thy iourney with ioy and chearefulnesse. As the Sea-men and Marriners in their Uoyages, bee carefull to bring <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> so be thou in thine, as carefull to bring <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and sincere minde; and I doubt not, but thou shalt find it <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, euen according to thy hearts desire, and answereable to thine expectation. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>B. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>