<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface before the Table.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121081_Fr1_18</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25786</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface before the Table.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian dictionarie : opening the signification of the chiefe wordes dispersed generally through Holie Scriptures of the Old and New Testament, tending to increase Christian knowledge. Whereunto is annexed: a perticular dictionary for the Reuelation of S. Iohn. For th Canticles, or Song of Salomon. For the Epistle to the Hebrues. By Tho: Wilson minister of the Word, at Saint Georges in Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 240, 243-577, 1, 234, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>A Preface before the Table.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, in this vast Ocean, and large Forrest of words contained in this Dictiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I doe find that there be three sorts most materiall; where of I desire that thou sholdst take more especiall notice and knowledge, as being of more worth and waight. The first I call an Ecclesiasticall word, which being translated from common vse of speech, is by the Church appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to signifie holy and diuine things. A word of this kind, though it be not in the Scripture for Letter and Sillables: yet is to be found there for matter and substance; as Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, &amp;c. Sacrament, Indifferent, Satisfaction, Merit, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>A word of the second rancke, I doe tearme <hi>Polemicall;</hi> because it pertaines to Controuersie, &amp; hath in it a ground of difference betweene the true Christian, which thinketh, speaketh, and writeth <hi>Orthodoxally,</hi> and soundly; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which loue and embrace errors, in fauour where of they wrest, and peruert the pure wordes of Scripture: as <hi>Iustification, Assurance, of Faith, Hope of Glory, Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scence, Antichrist,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>A word of the third sort, is called <hi>Fundamentall,</hi> of which kind, I doe take such wordes to be, as doe containe in them things, which beeing denyed, Religion it selfe is ouerthrowne; euen as an house is ouer-turned, by taking away the foundation or ground-worke whereuppon it stands; as <hi>Grace, Fayth, God, Christ,</hi> &amp;c. for the descer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of these words from other, I iudge this to be a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary rule.</p>
   <p>A word, containing in it anything, which being deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">A Rule whereby to iudge a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall word.</note> either God himselfe, any person of the God-head, the decrees of God, his properties, his workes of Creation and prouidence, his word of Law and Gospell: or Christ Iesus the Mediator, his Person, Natures, Offices, benefits,
<pb facs="15"/>
Church, and people be denied; either directly, or by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary and immediate consequence. Any such word is <hi>Fundamentall,</hi> for that must needs be the foundation of an House, which being remooued, the house cannot but fall. Of this Nature be the wordes, vpon deniall whereof, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the ruine of the whole Fabricke of Religion.</p>
   <p>Of these three kindes of words, I haue heere drawne a Table after the order of the Alphabet, setting a Starre * before an <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> word, to know it by. I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed this sillable [<hi>Con</hi>] aboue a Polemical word, and haue placed an [<hi>F</hi>] ouer the head of a fundamentall word: where it happeneth, that any one word is both an <hi>Ecclesiasticall,</hi> &amp; a word of <hi>Controuersie,</hi> I haue written vpon the top of it, both a Star, and this sillable [<hi>Con.</hi>] Also, you shall find this sillable [<hi>Con</hi>] and an [<hi>F</hi>] ouer euery word, which is both <hi>Polemicall,</hi> and a word of <hi>Foundation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Moreouer, whereas I haue with the explication of words, sometimes ioyned the definition of the thing expressed by such a word, ye shall finde this sillable [<hi>Def.</hi>] put vnder the foote of such a word. And those words in this Table that doe admit distinctions, they are noted out by this sillable [<hi>Dist.</hi>] directly put vnder the word.</p>
   <p>Finally, if in the draught, either of this Table, or of this whole Dictionary, I haue failed in any thing (as no doubt but I haue, being but a man; and therefore subiect to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, from which no Booke is priuiledged, sauing the book of Bookes,) I do earnestly entreate thee to couer my slips by loue, eyther amending them, or admonishing mee of them: doing vnto me, as in the like case thy selfe wouldest bee done vnto: euer remembring, that it is much easier to dislike, then to doe the like. The former, will cost thee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but the latter (trust me) will cost thee paines, vnto sweate and wearinesse, if thou wilt but endeuour to doe what I haue done before thee.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>