<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Abbay, T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121887_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12466</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22791</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121887</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Abbay, T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A map of Virginia : VVith a description of the countrey, the commodities, people, government and religion. VVritten by Captaine Smith, sometimes governour of the countrey. Whereunto is annexed the proceedings of those colonies, since their first departure from England, with the discourses, orations, and relations of the salvages, and the accidents that befell them in all their iournies and discoveries. Taken faithfully as they were written out of the writings of Doctor Russell. Tho. Studley. Anas Todkill. Ieffra Abot. Richard Wiefin. Will. Phettiplace. Nathaniel Povvell. Richard Pots. And the relations of divers other diligent observers there present then, and now many of them in England. By VV.S</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 39, 1, 4, 110, 2 pages, folded plates, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="27"/>
   <pb facs="27"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong hath the world longed, but to be truely satisfied what Virginia is, with the truth of those proceedings, from whence hath flowne so manie reports of worth, &amp; yet few good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the charge, which hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed suspition in many well willers that desire yet but to be truely satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied therein. If any can resolue this doubt it is those that haue lived residents in the land: not salers, or passengers, nor such mercinary contemplators, that only bedeck them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with others plumes. This discourse is not from such, neither am I the author, for they are many, whose particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar discourses are signed by their names. This solid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, first was compiled by <hi>Richard Pots,</hi> since passing the hands of many to pervse, chācing into my hands, (for that I know them honest men, and can partly well witnesse their relations true) I could do no lesse in charity to the world thē reveale; nor in cōscience, but approue. By the advise of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graue and vnderstanding gentlemen, that haue pressed it, to the presse, it was thought fit to publish it, rather in it owne rude phrase then other waies. For that nothing can so purge that famous action from the infamous scandal some ignorantly haue conceited, as the plaine simple and naked truth. For defect whereof the businesse is still suspected, the truth vnknowne, and the best deservers discouraged, and neglected, some by false reports, others by coniecture, and such power hath flattry to ingender of those, hatred and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that one is sufficent to beguile more, then 500 can
<pb facs="28"/>
keepe from being deceiued.</p>
   <p>But this discourse is no Iudge of mens manners, nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of their former courses; only a reporter of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Virginia, not to disgrace any, accuse any, excuse any, nor flatter any; for which cause there is no wrong done but this, shortnesse in complaining, &amp; so sparing in cōmending as only the reader may perceiue the truth for his paines, &amp; the action purged of foule slander; it can detract from none that intendeth there to adventure their fortunes; and to speake truly of the first planters, that brake the yee &amp; beate the path, howsoeuer many difficulties obscured their inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, he were worse then the worst of Ingrates, that would not spare them memory that haue buried themselues in those forrain regions. From whose first adventures may spring more good blessings then are yet conceived. So I rest thine, that will read, pervse, &amp; vnderstand me. If you finde false orthography or broken English, they are small faultes in souldiers, that not being able to write learnedly, onlie striue to speake truely, and be vnderstood without an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. ABBAY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>