<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull, sir Thomas Cauerden knight, Robert Bur∣rant wisheth moche prosperous healthe and wealthe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121116_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18234</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4854</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull, sir Thomas Cauerden knight, Robert Bur∣rant wisheth moche prosperous healthe and wealthe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Preceptes of Cato : with annotacions of D. Erasmus of Roterodame vere profitable for all [...]</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>352 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right worshipfull, sir Thomas</hi> Cauerden knight, Robert Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant wisheth moche prosperous healthe and wealthe.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull sir, all</hi> questions set a parte, the onely fame &amp; good reporte, whiche ye doe right worthely deserue of your so very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent giftes and qualities, and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally your vpright iudgemente, with moste prudent and sage wisedome in Marciall affaires annexed, seme not vnworthy the patronship of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of the antique &amp; wittie Cato Forasmoche as ye dooe not onely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate and folowe like circumspecte grauitie and pollicie, but also dooe with your like factes and propreties reuest and newly garnishe the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Cato. I suppose that if the fates and destinies would suffre Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to reuiue again, and were certified into whose tniciō and saufe defence
<pb facs="3"/>
he were dedicate, he would either coumpt himself the moste fortunate of all other, or els would willingly surrender his right and title, that he could claime or demaūde in this his preceptes, vnto your discrecion. Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideryng that ye were hable to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase vnto him a more ample inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of fame immortall, whom he would finde so legitimate &amp; naturall a soonne, and heire of his politique wisedome, who for his merueilous inuencions and wittie coneighaunce in warrefare, is not onely of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Capitaines to bee folowed, and of young warriers to bee practised, but also of children to bee learned. And finally, for this his excellencie deserueth not onely of the Grecians, and Latinistes to bee read and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, but also to bee translated into the Oulgare toungue of all nacions.
<q>
         <p>Receiue therefore here your father Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons inheritaunce.</p>
         <p>And with your like wisedome, caufe kept his substaunce.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>