<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121926_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19675</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three conformities. Or The harmony and agreement of the Romish Church with gentilisme, Iudaisme and auncient heresies. VVritten in French by Francis de Croy G. Arth. and newly translated into English. Seene, perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Cro, François de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 130, 6, 131-177, 25, 179-258 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="110"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Masters, the chiefe weapon that the Diuell hath vsed against the Church, is Heresie, which the Apostle <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.</note> placeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the workes of the flesh. It is not to day, that this contagion of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar chusing of opinions, hath corrupted a great number of men. The Churches, both of Israell and primitiue, haue tasted of this cruell poyson. Those wits that made too great account of Philosophie, and are borne among Sophismes, puft vp with pride, pale and deformed through ennie, haue hatched this generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and brought forth this Hydra of all mischiefes. No age hath beene free thereof. The histories doe set before our eyes and our eares some lamentable examples, and namely in these latter dayes: which being most fertile in all vices, are likewise fruitfull in producing those
<pb facs="111"/>
detestable heresies, the effects whereof are to draw away men from the way of truth, to make them become <note place="margin">Effects of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies.</note> enemies thereof, as did in old times <hi>Iamnes,</hi> and <hi>Mambres</hi> the aduersaries of <hi>Moyses,</hi> to corrupt them in their vnderstanding, to ioyne them with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, and at length to debarre them from the Kingdome of God. We and you are ordained to be contraries. You call vs Hereticks, and wee <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Iuuen. Satyr.</hi> 2 <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione querentes?</hi>
      </note> returne againe this title vnto you, like a ball in the Tennis-court. Who will beleeue you? Who will beleeue vs? There is no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty here: let vs examine the doctrines: let vs search diligently for that which is true. That is true saith a certaine Father <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Tertul. aduer. Marcion. lib.</hi> 4.</note>, which is the first, that is first which is from the beginning: and that is from the beginning which is from the Apostles. Wee haue this true, this first, this beginning, the doctrine of the Apostles, which is the Anchor of our Faith. There will nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for you therefore, but the last and false, to wit, the dregges of heresie. Yet doe you not cease to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vnto vs, that we haue renued, and as it were drawne out of hell many old Heresies, which (as you exclaime) we haue broached in these latter times, and haue insinuated them into the beleefe of men for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall doctrines. And to the end that none should thinke that you had spoken idlely and without reason, you set downe their number: and if you might be trusted, there is no scab or sore of the auncient He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, whereon we haue not rubbed our selues. It is after this manner that you tickle your selues to make you laugh, and when you haue spent all your force, whether it be in sleight, or eloquence, to rouse <note n="d" place="margin">Lib. cont. heres.</note> vp the implicite faith of your flockes, you thinke it is enough,
<pb facs="111"/>
and that we haue nothing to reply thereto. Wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the heresies, and haue the register thereof in our memorie, to the intent that we may beware of the same. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> gathereth to the number of <hi>80.</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Ad quod vult Deum.</note> reckoneth eight more. <hi>Philastrius</hi> more yet. And before these <hi>Ireneus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> made some catalogues. In reading of them we haue found matter enough against you, because we haue learned (and bee not offended) that you are fellowes and fauourers, of those who through their Heresies sought to destroy the Church. How then can it be possible that we are their companions? Thereupon you pay those of your side, not with reason, or with any likelyhood, but with false calumnies against such as withstand you, and to this end you picke out certaine Heresies at your pleasure, which, you say, haue beene as it were renued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored againe by those great Heralds, the restorers of true piety, which haue gone before vs in the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church. This little Preface shall declare the contrary, and such Christian soules as are mildely disposed, shall be iudges of our right, and of your wrong. <hi>Ireneus</hi> saith of the <hi>Simonians</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>de haeres.</hi>
      </note>, that they taught that <note place="margin">Simonians.</note> men were saued through the mercy of <hi>Simon,</hi> and that workes were not necessary vnto saluation: from <note place="margin">Eunomius. <hi>de haeres. ad quod vult Deum.</hi>
      </note> whom <hi>Eunomius</hi> hath not gone farre, who (witnesse S. <hi>Austin<seg rend="sup">g</seg>)</hi> did hold the opinion; that men could take no harme by sinne, how great soeuer it were, prouided that their faith had not fayled. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> accuseth <hi>Luther</hi> for consenting to these follies, being followed by <hi>Caluin, Brencius</hi> and others: who verily confessed that good workes were the effects of Faith, but denyed that they could merit life euerlasting. The learned
<pb facs="112"/>
treatises which haue beene compiled by our writers on this subject, should haue serued for phisicke vnto your eye-sight, and should haue taken the moate out of your eyes, that you might behold the truth against your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate doctrine? Wee will not doe you so much wrong as to debauch them from your companie, that we may draw them to our side. Then let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine still there in a good time, we denounce them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed. Those infamous persons wallowed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in all manner of crimes. No thing, as they thought, could hurt them, if they had acknowledged <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to bee the chiefe way vnto saluation. Haue you found any thing in our Churches like vnto this? <hi>Simon</hi> reiected all manner of vertuous and iust workes as superfluous, wee, acknowledge them as necessary, but not as meritorious: for grace can get no entry there where merits haue taken place already. We abhorre <hi>Eumenius</hi> likewise. We confesse <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Bernard. sup. cant. serm.</hi> 67.</note> the <note place="margin">Eumenius.</note> separation of faith from good workes, to bee more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, then to separate the beames and light from the Sunne. And what doe you finde worthy to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, whiles we teach that sinne cannot hurt him that hath the act of Faith? You couer your selues with the ambiguity of this word Faith, whereby you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand nothing but a simple knowledge of the doctrine, and a naked insight in Religion, and not this certaine perswasiou that the iust man liues by his Faith. Truth it is that the sinnes, which make vs guilty before God, doe astonish vs: but we say in like manner that they are not imputed vnto vs, and that they are couered through the iustice of the sonne of God and mediator Christ Iesus. Also you would haue vs to bee fellowes
<pb facs="112"/>
withone <hi>Florinus</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Ireneus. apud Eusebium. liber</hi> 5. <hi>Histor. cap.</hi> 20.</note>, and to say with him that God is <note place="margin">Florinus.</note> the author of sinne: an heresie which <hi>Vincent</hi> de <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> did likewise attribute <note n="k" place="margin">In suo commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitorio.</note> vnto <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> For an answere hereunto, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is your oracle, it sufficeth if he hath said so to you. This assertion, saith <hi>Ireneus,</hi> is more then heresie. Shall we therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the same? Truely all things moue vnder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God. The wicked and their sinnes are not exempted from this celestiall power and gouernement. Is God therefore the cause of sinne? Fie on this blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie. It is not he that inspireth man with: wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: this worke is of the Diuell. The Butt that wee ayme at discerneth the actions. The scope of mens e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill actions is nothing but rebellion and contempt of the Creator: and by the contrarie, God aymeth onely at the execution of his immoueable and eternall decree. The good and the bad Trees, being nourished both with one manner of iuice, in the same soyle, and place, are different, notwithstanding in their fruites. Who can blame the ground? Let vs therefore exeeme God from the imputation of iniquitie, and let vs not play the Marcionists. <hi>Origen</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Epiph. haeres.</hi> 63.</note> thought that <hi>Adam</hi> through his fall had altogether lost the image of God, <note place="margin">Origene.</note> whereunto he was created in his originall vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and that <note n="n" place="margin">Hieren. epist. ad Auitum.</note> Hell was nothing else but a terror of Conscience. You doe inclose <hi>Caluin</hi> within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe of the same errors, and are not ashamed to cite those places <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Cal lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Iust. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c. vlt. sect. vlt:</hi>
      </note> which you vnderstand amisse, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret worse, that you may make him bee detested like an Hereticke. Wee abhorre both the one and the other reauing of <hi>Origine. Caluin</hi> speaketh not so grosly: he saith indeede that the image of God is not altogether
<pb facs="113"/>
defaced, that there are many remnants left vnto vs after this ship-wracke, the reason, the vnderstanding, and other naturall gifts. This wee affirme with <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin,</hi> that those supernaturall graces, wherewith God had honoured man, were quenched and lost: as the wisedome, <note n="p" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note> which made vs to know God: the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 24.</note> which pushed vs forward vnto a voluntarie obedience of his commandements: and holinesse <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Col.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</note>, which are seales and principall markes of this heauenly likenesse. Subscribe to this doctrine, or else wee will say to your face, that you are infected with Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme. The Iesuites <note n="s" place="margin">Gratensis in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert diffens.</note> hold, that <hi>Adams</hi> sinne was small, and not so outragious as it is made. Let vs say <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Ambr. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiso. August. in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chir. c.</hi> 45. <hi>Prosper. lib. de gratia Dei. Tertul. lib. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Iudaos.</hi>
      </note> better: that our <hi>protoplastes</hi> haue lost their faith: That it was an Heresie, asinne of incredulitie, an apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasie; a fault that could not be amended by any other then the Sonne of God. Like as the Moone after her coniunction with the Sunne, is replenished with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power, which she imparteth vnto all things: so al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the soule of this little world being rauished through contemplation, and as it were vnited with that great intellectuall Sunne, was inflamed with an heauenly light, and an inestimable power: and if it should bee separated from thence, what would remaine but darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and infirmitie? As touching Hell, neyther <hi>Caluin,</hi> nor we did euer speake any such thing, neyther yet any thing that commeth neere vnto that which you alledge: it is deceite and calumny.—Let vs proceede to the rest of your accusations. We rule not onely our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall actions, but also the affections of our heart. The word of God is the square. Those concupiscences that tickle and sting our soules ought to bee bridled,
<pb facs="113"/>
and for this cause we account them as sinnes, yea, euen in the persons of the regenerate: but that they liue not, that they reigne not, that they are not imputed vnto vs, through the benefit of faith. This is it which we beleeue. What haue we to doe then with the heretike <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Epiph. haeres.</hi> 64 Messalians.</note>
      <hi>Proclus?</hi> What simpathie is there betweene vs and <note place="margin">Proclus.</note> the <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de haeret. fabulis.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Messalians?</hi> You know not what concupiscence meaneth, you know not the effects thereof. And sith we are speaking thereof, doe you not falsifie the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wheras of the last commandement of God which forbiddeth concupiscence, you make two, against Saint <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. &amp; 13. <hi>v.</hi> 9. Pepuzians.</note>
      <hi>Pauls</hi> meaning, who comprehendeth the forbidding of concupiscence, all vnder one commandement? In the end we auouch, that the <note n="z" place="margin">
         <hi>August. lib. haeres. ca.</hi> 27.</note>
      <hi>Pepuzians</hi> admitted wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vnto the sacred ministrie of the Church. <hi>Luther</hi> is slaundered <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Articulo</hi> 13. <hi>ex iis quos Leo damnauit.</hi>
      </note> as if he had followed the footsteppes of this false doctrine; To say, that sinnes are remitted through Repentance, whether the Priest absolue them of the same or not, is this to follow the <hi>Pepuzians?</hi> To say, that a woman, or a child hath as much power to forgiue sinnes as the Pope hath, is this to attribute the Priesthood vnto that sexe, which the Heauenly Oracle forbiddeth to teach in the Church? We are better taught then so: and in effect this present discourse shall declare vnto you, that you can neuer be able to free your selues from Pepuzianisme. The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatians <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de haerec. fabulis Cornelius Papa apud Euseb. li.</hi> 6. <hi>hist. cap.</hi> 33.</note> acknowledged no other meanes to reconcile men to God in the Church then Baptisme, and taught <note place="margin">Nouatians.</note> that such as were baptised ought to be anointed with the Bishops Chrisme. Acknowledge your brethren here: but let vs answere. <hi>Nouatus</hi> admitted not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to repentance those that had fallen after Baptisme.
<pb facs="114"/>
Doe we teach that? It is true indeed that we deny two things: that penitence is a Sacrament: that the force of Baptisme doth not continue vnto the end of mans life. S. <hi>Hierome</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieronym. in</hi> 15. <hi>cap. Ezec.</hi>
      </note> calleth repentance the second table after shipwracke. Let vs say, that it is not the cause of the remission of sinnes (it is the merey of God purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto the faithfull through their onely Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ) but onely the signe of remission, and the remedy whereby those that are baptised do helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues among those great confusions and disorders ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing from their faults. Moreouer, who hath foughten <note place="margin">Sabellius.</note> better then we against <hi>Sabellius</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Epiph. haeres.</hi> 57</note>, who acknowledged but one person in the sacred Trinitie? Why then do you match vs with that pest? The bookes written by our men beare record of our Orthodoxall faith: and the punishment that <hi>Seruet</hi> suffered, declareth the practise thereof. Wherefore if it be sufficient to accuse, who shall be found innocent? <hi>Arrius</hi> made the Sonne to be <note place="margin">Arrius.</note> meaner then the Father. The <hi>Tritheites</hi> taught the <note place="margin">Tritheites.</note> same. You shall be contented (if it please you) that we produce a simple negatiue against a bare affirmation: and in like manner, if we send you vnto the learned writes of our men. In the meane season we will by order deny that we are in any wayes acquainted with the Manicheans <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieronym. in praefat. dialog. contra Pelagia. August. li. de hae res. cap.</hi> 49.</note>, contemners of nature, and deniers <note place="margin">Manicheans.</note> of free will. We acknowledge a free will in euill things, and remoue the same from spirituall graces. Touching sinne, we doe attribute it to the will of man, to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and not to God. And if the same Manicheans <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>August. lib.</hi> 22. <hi>contra Faustum.</hi>
      </note> haue accused the Fathers of the old Testament, to wit, <hi>Abraham, Iacob, Sampson, Sara, Rebecca,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as wicked and detestable persons: shall it be sayd
<pb facs="114"/>
likewise that <hi>Caluin</hi> hath scourged these fathers with the rod of slander? Those did so, that they might make their memorie hatefull vnto the posteritie: he had no other intent, but to declare how fraile our life is, and that our infirmitie ought to minister occasion vnto vs, to suspect our naturall forces, as in themselues incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of vertuous actions and heauenly mysteries. The former, to wit, the <hi>Manicheans,</hi> haue followed <hi>Cham:</hi> the latter sendeth vs vnto the grace of God, who vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth our right hands, that we may not fall into this puddle of sinne. Shall we be <hi>Donatists<seg rend="sup">g</seg>
      </hi> also? They closed the Church within the bounds of <hi>Africke:</hi> they <note place="margin">Donatistes. <hi>August. lib. de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Eccles. c.</hi> 12.</note> reiected sinners from the libertie and communion of the visible Church: proclaimed open wars against the Catholicke Bishops. <hi>Caluin</hi> and we (say you) doe in like manner. You speake onely by report or by dreaming. We confesse indeed, that the Catholicke Church, which consisteth of the elect onely, is inuisible. The eternall election whereupon Gods couenant is grounded, which is the essentiall forme of the Church, and maketh it to be a Church, cannot be made knowne and manifest, but through the holy Ghost, and through the word of God. The election of the visible elect is inuisible. Seeing therefore that to be in the Church, or of the Church, doth not declare the essence of man, but sheweth the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall election, whereunto Gods couenant had a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that you beleeue after this manner; why doe you slaunder vs, as if we were partakers with the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natists?</hi> Concerning the limits of the Church, we doe not diminish them, they are extended throughout all the climates of the earth: and it is you that inclose them within the walles of Rome. And if we haue a crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="115"/>
action against your Bishops, you must not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude that we are enemies to those that with the Bishops sea haue the succession of the Apostolicke doctrine. <hi>Aerius</hi> would not pray for the dead: nor <note place="margin">Aerius.</note> yet we. Are we heretickes therefore? Then let S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieronym. in</hi> 65. <hi>cap. Isa. Chrysost.</hi> 2. <hi>serm. de Lazaro. August serm.</hi> 66. <hi>de temp. Theophil. ad</hi> 25. <hi>cap. Math.</hi>
      </note>, if your consequence be true, <hi>Chrysostome, Austin,</hi> that most worthy Bishop of <hi>Hippona,</hi> and <hi>Theophilactus</hi> be Aerians and heretickes: for they affirme all after one manner, that after this life, there is neither time nor place to make satisfaction for our sinnes in this world: and the same <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Hom.</hi> 7. <hi>ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pul. Antioch.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Chrysostome</hi> sayth that those prayers were vsed as a thankes giuing to God, for that he had crowned those that were dead. The same <hi> Aerius</hi> left fasting in the free power of the faithfull: said that the Bishops and Priests differed nothing in dignitie. And what harme I beseech you, either in the first (so that it be vnderstood of priuate fasts) or in the last. Concerning fasts, there is no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion: touching the last, <hi>Aerius</hi> and we agree both with the holy writes, and with the venerable <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Cyprian. de simplie praelat. &amp; cibatur cap. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>i tur Dominus</hi> 24. <hi>quaest.</hi> 1. <hi>Item ad Corn. Hieronym. in Tit. c.</hi> 1 <hi>et in epistola ad Euge</hi> 11. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopum. &amp; cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur can. legimus dist.</hi> 93 <hi>et Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidenter.</hi> 1. <hi>quaest.</hi> 1.</note> antiquitie, which cry out with a lowd voice, that all Byshops and Ministers of the word haue alike power, in whatsoeuer place they be, whether in Naples, or in the Indies, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Tartarians. If <hi>Aerius</hi> then haue taught but these three points, he is wrongfully accounted among heretickes. And <hi>Theodoret</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Theodor. lib. de fabulis Iudaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Iouinian.</note> freeth him thereof, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing onely one <hi>Eustathius</hi> his mortall aduersarie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and S. <hi>Austin</hi> be not of the same opinion. <hi>Iouinian</hi> is not forgotten. They would make vs to agree with him in fiue heresies. The first, that man after he hath receiued Baptisme cannot sin, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>Caluin</hi> hath subscribed, say you, without shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="115"/>
the place where: who writeth that the faith that is once receiued into the heart of the faithfull, cannot make shipwracke. We graunt the second; and impugne the first, which concerneth Baptisme, and experience furnisheth vs with proofes of the contrarie, and freeth both <hi>Caluin</hi> and vs from these impostures. The second pretended heresie, imputed to <hi>Iouinian,</hi> is concerning the difference of meates and merites through fasting, which he reprooued. And thereupon you raise hue and cry after <hi>Caluin.</hi> If that which you hold concerning the difference of meats, the fish and flesh dayes be true: I know not how you shall be able to resist: and what rampart you can set before your Canons <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Can. si quis carnem dist.</hi> 30. <hi>Can. delitiae. Can. Quisquis. Can. quod dicit. dist.</hi> 41. <hi>Can. si quis pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter dist.</hi> 30.</note>: Canons (I say) which vomite forth powder and bullets to bruse all to peices. Moreouer, if <hi>Iouinian</hi> maketh marriage equall with chastitie, both in dignitie and merite, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten not your tongues against <hi>Caluin</hi> in that matter: exclame against Christ Iesus who hath sayd so, and beare ill will against S. <hi>Paul</hi> that hath written so. Your <hi>Erasmus</hi> wished to finde in S. <hi>Hierome</hi> a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie and greater mildnesse against his aduersaries: this is your desire likewise. It is true that in so farre as <hi>Iouinian</hi> withstoode the perpetuall virginitie of <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> he deserued a very seuere and rigorous punishment, yea euen the fire. And vpon this blaspemie S. <hi>Hierome</hi> had very good reason to frame his inuectiues against him. The like is not taught in our Churches; and it is without all reason that these great lights of our age <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Molineus</hi> are blamed. <hi>Esay</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Esa.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> shall be a warrant for that which we beleeue, and likewise that which <hi>Ezechiel</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Eze.</hi> 44. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> writes, which the auncient writers all with one accord haue
<pb facs="116"/>
expounded of the perpetuall virginitie of the glorious mother of Christ Iesus, shal ouerthrow those desseings, whereby you labour to make vs hatefull vnto all men. Yea, and we should be very sorrie to helpe our selues with the authoritie of S. <hi>Basill,</hi> who sayth <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>serm. de humana generat. Christi.</hi>
      </note>, that the beleife concerning the perpetuall virginitie of the holy Virgin, after the dispensation of the conception and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of the Sonne of God, cannot profit vs any thing to be sought out, and that it is curiositie to take any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof. The last heresie which S. <hi>Hierome</hi> and you doe attribute vnto <hi>Iouinian,</hi> is touching the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the reward of this life: from which (as you write) <hi>Luther</hi> goeth not farre, seeing he writes <note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Serm. de nata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. Mariae. Et in comment. in</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi>
      </note> that Christians are vnder the same paralell of righteousnes in the Kingdome of God with the virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> We could insist vpon <hi>Iouinians</hi> affirmatiue: for there is but one manner of faith amongst all the faithfull, then there is but one manner of reward. But that you may not surprise vs, let vs say, that concerning holinesse and inherent iustice, there is some inequalitie, which notwithstanding is remoued, in regard of the holinesse and iustice of Christ Iesus, which being grounded on the eternall election that he hath made of his owne, is equally distributed amongst all the faithfull and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate. Vnto faith and the excellent effects thereof, which are the gifts of God, and are crowned by him, we doe attribute diuerse rewards, according to the greater or lesser measure: this maxime neuerthelesse being <note place="margin">Vigilantius.</note> still true, that we are receiued and auouched by the heauenly Father, through the onely one meane of the obedience of Christ Iesus his onely and well-beloued sonne. <hi>Vigilantius</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Tamen Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius ab Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymo sanctus Presbiter dictus est epist.</hi> 13. <hi>ad Paulin.</hi>
      </note> shall haue his part here also, and
<pb facs="116"/>
we shall become <hi>Vigilantius</hi> or <hi>Dormitantius</hi> (chuse which of them pleaseth you best) if we would beleeue you. If he hath sayd that the reliques of Saints ought not to be worshipped: behold we are on his side: behold S. <hi>Austin</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 20. <hi>de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei, cap.</hi> 10.</note> is in like manner: <hi>we honour,</hi> sayth he, <hi>the memorie of the Saints, but we doe no seruice to the dead in their graues.</hi> Item: <hi>the Martyres are not Gods, they are named and inuoqued by the Priest.</hi> Vigilantius hath in like manner condemned the inuocation of Saints: <hi>Caluin</hi> hath done the same: we haue imitated him. Shall we all be heretickes? Then the holy Ghost shall be so also, who by his Oracle teacheth <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Esa.</hi> 63. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> vs, that the dead know nothing of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and that they medle no wayes with them. And put the case that they prayed, will it follow by good Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke that they must therefore be worshipped? <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius</hi> reproued singlenesse of life, and graunted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage vnto the Ministers of the Church. O what a great crime? O most damnable fault for that we teach the same. The holy Ghost, according to your speech, knew not what he indited to the Apostle, when he accounted the forbidding of mariage among the Doctrines of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils. What farther? <hi>Vigilantius</hi> found fault with the giuing away of their goods, the mother of the Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers pouertie. And what profit redounded hereof? Your men, such as the Capuchins, and others giue all that they haue, but to their owne kindred, and not to Christ Iesus: they enter into the Monasterie, where they haue greater plentie then vnder their owne roofe: and S. <hi>Francis</hi> his bag is at least worth a Cardinals reuenue. What are we farther? <hi>Pelagians</hi> you answere. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? <note place="margin">Pelagians.</note> Because you deny originall sinne with them: and
<pb facs="117"/>
thereafter teach that the children of the faithfull are holy, and are saued without Baptisme. We disaduouch them in so farre as they sayd, that children were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all sinne: true indeed, that we attribute holinesse vnto them, euen from their mothers wombe, because of Gods couenant, wherein they are comprehended: if this be not true, the Apostle <note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> must be a <hi>Pelagian.</hi> As touching Baptisme, condemnation proceedeth not of the want thereof, but of the contempt of that sacrament which was instituted by Christ Iesus. And how, say you farther, can you purge your selues from <hi>Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme,</hi> seeing that with the author of that sect you make all sinnes equall, and for the smallest offence that can be committed, you thinke that life euerlasting is lost. Truely the righteousnesse of the faithfull (we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere) doth not decay for euery transgression. Wee confesse indeed that all sinnes are deadly, euen the smallest, which the <hi>Pelagians</hi> would not acknowledge. We will not therefore place all manner of sinnes in one degree: we are not <hi>Stoickes:</hi> some are more hainous then others. And that inequalitie set downe by Christ Iesus <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>et</hi> 11.</note> in the paines of the reprobate, doth it not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede of the inequalitie of the offences? You thinke it strange, that we call all sinnes (saue that against the holy Ghost) veniall, that is to say pardonable. Betake your selues therefore to the mercy of God, who desireth not the death of a sinner? What farther? A certaine great person, and a seruant of God in our age, and one whom God endueth daily with more and more graces, thought once that there had beene two hypostaticall or personall vnions in Christ, the one of the soule with the bodie, the other of the diuinitie with the humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb facs="117"/>
Shall it not be lawfull for vs to recant, and cancell that which through mistaking we haue thought and written amisse, as S. <hi>Austin</hi> did very commendably? He yeelded to the admonitions that were giuen him, and declared his meaning, in his learned treatise of the hypostaticall Vnion of the two natures in Christ Iesus. Shall he therefore be accounted a <hi>Nestorian,</hi> that esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished <note place="margin">Nestorians.</note> two persons in Christ? And we shall be farre lesse of the <hi>Eutichian</hi> sect, which admitted but one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as well as one onely person in Christ, although <hi>Swenckfeldius, Smidelinus,</hi> and others haue written so, which we disaduouch. We should neuer haue done: and this Preface would exceede its bounds, if it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs by little and little to follow the footsteps of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonsus</hi> a Castro, of one <hi>Prateolus,</hi> of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and others of that kind, which haue filled vp therwith huge and great paltrie volumes, and set vp trophees of their accusations on this subiect. That which we haue sayd shall serue for a proofe, that it may be knowne to the posteritie, that with the like facilitie we are able to refute the other heresies, which we haue not set downe here, to the end that we might eschew prolixitie; (and whereof you accuse vs) wherwith we haue refuted the former. And this little discourse shall declare how vaine your proiects are, by seeking to make vs worthie to be detested among men, and that our innocencie shall be a decree of condemnation against you, in so farre as you haue shewed your selues false accusers and rebels vnto the <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Constantinus Christianam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, Catholicam &amp; sanctissimam hares: appellauit: apud Euseb. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. hist. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> truth. Those great vants of your huge and large Temples doe nothing but make an Eccho of this word heretickes, your cheekes are altogether swelled therewith. You can say no worse, taking it in that sense,
<pb facs="118"/>
wherein it is commonly spoken. It seemes that the Eccho of those vast dennes of your Temples, taketh pleasure to double and repeate seuen times ouer these iniurious words, that they may the better be distilled <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Nam haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum communione leges diuinae &amp; humanae pijs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicunt.</hi> 2. <hi>Ioan v.</hi> 10. 24. <hi>quaest.</hi> 1. <hi>ci quae dignior c.</hi> 13. <hi>extrauag. de haereticis.</hi>
      </note> into the braines of your flockes. And who would not easily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the victorie, when the enemie doth not appeare? Would God that we had libertie to answere you by and by, in the same pulpits, from which you threaten vs so much; I beleeue that within a short time you would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Curats without Parishioners. For we should haue iust cause to prescribe against you: because of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting, for that you are blind leaders, for that you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree not with the holy words of Christ Iesus, yea, and because you are <note n="z" place="margin">This is your part likewise (Sirs) to defend the Arrianisme of <hi>Liberius,</hi> for which he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate by S. <hi>Hilary:</hi> the Monothelisme of <hi>Honorius</hi> for which hee was condemned by the 6. and 7. Councels: The opinion of the soules sleeping with <hi>Iohn</hi> 23. The opinion that the soules of men dy with their bodies, like those of beasts, and that there is no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting life with <hi>Iohn</hi> 24. condemned for this cause by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Constance, Session.</hi> 11.</note> heretickes. You will iudge here that I am inciuill and iniurious, yet can I not terme a house otherwise then a house, and euery thing by the owne name. I loue your persons, I hate your heresies and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and it is against them, and not against you that I prepare this combate, for the safetie both of you and of that poore people whom you haue bewitched. This little table shall represent not in small; for it were impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but in great, the harmonie and agreement which is betweene your Poperie and old heresies. And it were as much as to enter into an Ocean, if we would make a Register of the great heapes of your errours, sith that (the decree of the blessed Trinity being excepted) there is nothing sound throughout the whole bodie of the Romish Religion. Many with good successe haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to discouer them, though to your great griefe: and haue manifested that which you would, had beene hid for euer, in the thickest of Cimmerian darkenesse. I beare you no malice, God is my witnesse, my onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="118"/>
is that it may be knowne euidently to which of vs two this loathsome epithet (hereticke) belongeth. Two things <note n="*" place="margin">August. lib. de Trinit. in Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio.</note> do support each other in errour, the presuming of the truth before it be knowne: and the defending of the presumed falshood, after that the truth hath bin manifested vnto vs. We haue accused you, yea, and haue vanquished, both of the one and the other, of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption and obstinacie. Heresie proceedeth not from the Scripture, but from that it is not rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode: it is a crime not of the words, but of the sense. You erre in both twaine: and although it be against your owne consciences, yet so it is that you chuse rather to be damned then vanquished by the truth. God of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy open your eyes, and make you see the beames of his graces in his Church, where being gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with vs, we may worship together, that Pastor and soueraigne Bishop of our soules, our Lord Iesus Christ, who in the vnitie of the Father and of the holy Ghost, liueth and reighneth God eternally.</p>
   <closer>So be it.</closer>
   <pb facs="119"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>