<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121926_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19675</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three conformities. Or The harmony and agreement of the Romish Church with gentilisme, Iudaisme and auncient heresies. VVritten in French by Francis de Croy G. Arth. and newly translated into English. Seene, perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Cro, François de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 130, 6, 131-177, 25, 179-258 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="81"/>
   <pb facs="81"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Masters, we shall be briefe in the description of the harmony, which is betweene your Church and Iudaisme. For if we would search narrowly that great heape of ceremonies, which hath beene transported from the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall law into yours, wee should neuer haue done, and the reading thereof might perhaps be tedious, for the prolixitie of the same. And truely if we search well the fountaine of all your cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, whereby the pure seruice of God hath beene made not honourable, but by little and little hath beene disguised and transfigured, and in end conuerted into Idolatry and vngodlinesse; we should finde them to be as many remnants of Iudaisme, if we adde vnto them that which hath beene taken out of the puddle of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilisme, as we haue declared in the conformitie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding. It is after this manner, that so cunningly you haue mingled together with your deuotions, rules and
<pb facs="82"/>
ceremonies, not onely the Mythologies of the Pagans, but that also which in old times was appointed for his people, at this time neuerthelesse abolished through the comming of our Sauiour Christ Iesus, who hauing fully executed the charge which the heauenly Father had committed vnto him, hath done all that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for deliuering of vs from the second death, and to purchase vnto vs life euerlasting, as it was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto the Fathers, euen when the first sinne was committed, and afterwards figured and shadowed by the Ceremonies of the whole outward seruice of the Church of Israel. Seeing therefore that he hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perfectly accomplished all whatsoeuer was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</note> and foretold, as well of his person as of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and that he hath put an end to all the shadowes of the legall ceremonies, wherefore haue you restored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the greater part of those types which were pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised vnder the Leuiticall gouernement? Those cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall lawes were eyther personall, or were appointed for the daily and ordinary seruice of the Tabernacle, or for the vse of sacrifices, purifications, expiations and such other shadowes of this auncient pedagogie, which God had ordained, as well to separate his chosen people <note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 12.</note> from the Idolatrous nations, to hinder them from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vnto themselues any new seruices at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and following their owne fancies, as to admonish them to nourish and confirme their faith, in looking for the great Messias, who was shadowed by those Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. All these things haue ceased; And that those Ceremonies are not acceptable vnto God at this time, it appeareth in this that the Iewish policie is no more, the Arke is lost, the Vrim and Thumim suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
<pb facs="82"/>
the citie of Hierusalem defaced, and the temple destroyed, so that there is not a stone left vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,: and what licence soeuer the Iewes obtained to reedifie the same, as vnder <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apostate, a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall foe vnto the Christians, who did contribute him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe thereto, yet could they neuer bring it to passe. But, as the Gentiles themselues of those dayes doe witnesse, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ammian Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. lib.</hi> 23.</note> fires comming out of the earth, and great thundrings from heauen, consumed the workemen, and scattered the workes which they had begunne, with exceeding great pride and cost. And where now is the fire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming the holocaustes, the glorie of God among the <hi>Cherubins,</hi> the manifest inspiration of the holy-Spirit vpon the Prophets, the Arke of the couenant, the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which came out of the propitiatory, the <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thumim,</hi> the Royall and Priestly annointing: in a word, all those goodly prerogatiues, wherewith God in old times did beautifie and adorne his people? The whole is no more, and it is certaine that if it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God to continue and prolong, as well these things, as the ceremonies of the Law, he had not suffered the Romane Emperour to ouerthrow Ierusalem, to destroy the sanctuary, and abolish the sacrifices throughout the whole earth. And those vtter desolations which haue happened vnto this people through his permission, and were foretold in old times by the propheticall Oracles, doe sufficiently shew the bill of diuorcement which <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.</note> God hath sent to those types and shadowes, whereof also we did not stand any more in neede: sith the truth hath beene manifested both vnto their eyes and yours. And since it is so, wherefore haue you set them vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? You haue loaded your selues with so heauy a
<pb facs="83"/>
burden of diuerse ceremonies, that you haue not beene contented with the reliques of Iudaisme, and to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise the same, yea, and you haue made no difficultie to put forth your prophane hands vnto the holy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of the miraculous workes of Christ Iesus. And what? Know you not well enough that, that which he hath said and done, wherein hee would be imitated of his owne, ought to be referred vnto the practise of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect pietie that is due to God, and to the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect charitie which he hath shewed vnto vs? But doe you not counterfeit Christ Iesus in things, which hee neuer did, to that end that he might be followed and imitated therein? For howbeit it be not borrowed from Iudaisme: yet it is an indecent imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and voide of all reason.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>