<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP-FVL,
ADAM HIL DOCTOR OF DIVINITIE,
Vicar of Westburie, person of Goosage, Prebend and
subchanter of the Cathedrall Church of our Ladie,
in the Citie of nevve Sarum.</title>
           <author>Marbury, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121138_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03833</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13948</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121138</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP-FVL,
ADAM HIL DOCTOR OF DIVINITIE,
Vicar of Westburie, person of Goosage, Prebend and
subchanter of the Cathedrall Church of our Ladie,
in the Citie of nevve Sarum.</title>
                 <author>Marbury, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reioynder to Doctor Hil concerning the descense of Christ into Hell : Wherein the answere to his sermon is iustlie defended, and the roust of his reply scraped from those arguments as cleanlie, as if they had neuer bene touched with that canker. By Alexander Hume, Maister of Artes. Heere, besides the reioynder, thou hast his paralogismes: that is, his fallacies and deceits in reason pointed out, and numbered in the margin: amounting to the nomber of 600. and aboue: and yet not half reckoned</title>
                 <author>Hume, Alexander, schoolmaster</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 157, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP-FVL,
ADAM HIL DOCTOR OF DIVINITIE,
Vicar of Westburie, person of Goosage, Prebend and
subchanter of the Cathedrall Church of our Ladie,
in the Citie of nevve Sarum.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N May before the Moneth of August, you
speake of going home to visite my naturall
friends, I left my reply to your sermon to be
delivered you. But it was kept backe vppon
the considerations, which I haue saide in my
Epistle to the Reader. What other Coppy
you receiued in August, I cannot tel: But wel
I am assured I sent you none. Howsoeuer you
came by that coppy, plaine dealing wold haue answered that which
I sent you my selfe▪ you tell me, that going vp to London, you rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
an answere to your Sermon, &amp; pervsing it at your returne, you
found it an endeavoure to answere some peece of it: and within few
lines you will me to set downe al as you do. Your simile is vnfit, for
you set not downe all, that you had of me. Neither could I set down
all your Sermon: for I had but the notes of it: and them also written
with your owne hand so confusedly, that it woulde haue troubled
your selfe, to tell which was the beginning▪ middle, or end. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
this quarrell, that I did not set downe all, seeing I had not all,
is very vnreasonable. As for your notes I answered them all, sauing
two arguments, which being forced to seek hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e one, and there an
other, I missed in that confused Chaos of <hi>non bene i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ctarum dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia
semina verum.</hi> If you had bene disposed to speake properly,
they were too small a qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>let, to make all the rest be called, but a
peece of your Sermon. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your warinesse heere is notable. Least
some might think too well of my reply: you will not vouchsafe it the
name of an answere: but an indeavoure to answere some peece of
your Sermon. Such it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eavours as this, may well blind the simple:
but amongst the wise wil never purchase much credit to your cause.
But you would haue let all alone you say, if the speeches of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
disgracing your abilitie had not set you a worke: my desire was
either to winne you to vs, or reasons from you to drawe me to you.
But nowe it appeareth that your owne estimation was more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
in your eies, than the defence of the trueth, or winning men
<pb facs="10"/>
from errours. This will be a foull blot in the face of a Doctor: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
you wash it with a bale of truth and plaine dealing, confessing
that I was in no errour at all. But then you say you resolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
your selfe, or else to recant. I thought you had bene resolute
in Chippinhames pulpit six moneths before, if you were not as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute
then as now, I will not take your word for shoe-buckles: for
I had then more witnesses to your word, than I haue now to your
hand. But me thinks it is strange, that I oppugning David, Esay, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiell,
Peter, Paul, and Christ himself, could haue escaped the
check of your pen, if it had not bene to maintaine your owne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite
amongst the people. It is without doubt, that you loued that
most, that moved you most. If you were not as jelous of their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
as your owne estimation you were not so sure a friend, as
many supposed. But it is hard for me you say, to kicke against the
prick. It were so if I did so. but looke you M. Doctor to your owne
heeles: for my part I haue the testimony of a good conscience. No
other cause, than the simple loue of the trueth set me on worke. I le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled
not at preferment. I commended not my work to great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones.
I published not my book till you opened the gate: &amp; I could
do no lesse than followe. As for Christ and his Apostles I hope to
make it clear in al indifferent eares, that I haue not opposed one
syllable against them: And that you pull my wordes, as Cacus did
Hercules his Kein into what stinking dennes, it pleseth your wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
braine to devise. I know both what, when, and where I write. I
write of an Article of our faith, in which I am so much more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest,
as the Children of God shuld be more diligent to vnderstand
their faith aright. As for these dangerous times it is you that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
them. It is you, that devide the coat of Christ: it is you that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
the Scriptures guilefully: it is you, that publish private things to
make the Papists sport, and trouble the Church. That which divers
learned Papists affirme the Scriptures, never saide you put them to
the rack to make them confesse. Scotus saith, that the discense of
Christ into hell cannot be prooued by Scriptures. And radius one
of the learnest that was in the counsel of Trent, saith it, and proues
it. Hesselius another of the same counsell construeth the place of
Peter against you. To him accordeth Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mas Aquinas. and Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius
Carthusianus agreeth with Andradius. It were easie to quote
many: If the seeking of them were not more laborious, than their
testimonies will be effectuall in this cause. I bring onely these to set
their ingenuitie against your partialitie. As for the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
it hath not alwaies fostered your opinion, as you vntruely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch.
The times of popery, we yeeld you: because you agree in the
name, and the places be but severall roomes of one dungeon. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="11"/>
can we denie you the times of King Edward, which creeping
but out of the shelles of Popery, had not shaken of the buddes of
your errour, about that time the greatest part of your favorities li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:
and in that time your opinion (for want of better) was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
by convocation. But anno 1564. in the beginning of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties
raigne, in a convocation assembled to reestablish the Acts of
King Edward, which Queene Mary had taken away, that article on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
was reformed, and your opinion defaced, no more being left, but
the naked article of the beleefe in wordes equivalent. wherevpon
I build this reason. No counsell nor convocation censuring a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
taketh that away,<note place="margin">Synod. Ed.</note> which it selfe alloweth. But this
convocation censuring the convocation of King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Quemadmodum Christus pro nobis mortuus est, &amp; sepultus: ita est etiam cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendus ad inferos descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disse. Nam corpus vs{que} ad resurrectionē in sepulchro iacuit: spiritus ab illo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missus cum spiritibus, qui in carcere, siue in inferno detinebantur fuit, illis{que} predicauit queadmodum testatur Petri locus.</note>
hath taken your opinion away. Ergo, this convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
allowed not your opinion. But contrariwise, the
same Church of England hath made our opinion her
owne, by publishing by her authoritie, Thomas Rogers
exposition of these Articles, wherein he agrees with vs:
and countenansing it with her owne name, in titeling
it the English Creede. She hath also printed and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by her authoritie many books against you. The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva
Bible, I know not how many times: The newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament
with Beza and Villerius his notes: Fulkes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere
to the Remishe Testament: Baro his Lectures vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
Ionas:<note place="margin">Synod. Eliz. <hi>principium tantum retinuit.</hi> Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum Christus pro no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis mortuus est, &amp; sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: ita est etiam creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ad inferos descendisse.</note> Calvins Institutions at large, and abridged:
Northbrooks Confession: Fulk against Gregory Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,
and the Rhemists: Whitaker against Campion and
Duraeus: Vrsinus his Catechisme: Bastingius his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme:
Andrewe Willets vewe of Popery, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
Some dedicated to the Queene her selfe, Some
to my Lord Treasurer, some to my lord of Huntington,
some to my lord of Leister, some to my lord of Bedford, some to my
lord of Warwick, some to one, some to another, all allowed, and all
against you, Lastly our opinion hath bene taught in the Pulpits, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
in Schooles, allowed in the Vniversities, so that one Doctor
Husse, his grace was denied in Cambridge aboue 20. yeares agoe
for your opinion: and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>r owne had bene denied you within this
three yeares in Oxford, if you had not promised more than you
meant to performe. Whatsoeuer other men hath done, or spoken
for their owne: you are the first that ever I heard of, that oppugned
ours in the Church of England: saving D. Husse in Leister. Against
whome the Bishop of that Diocesse did oppose himselfe, procuring
from Cambridge their Reader, countenanced with the authoritie
of their convocation, to confute that opinion, which the english
<pb facs="11"/>
name of hel did make more popular, and probable to the ignorant,
by the countenance of that famous, and worthie Vniversitie. Thus
men may see how truely you challenge the Church of England, to
haue allowed your opinion alwaies▪ your alwaies commeth short
of all that time, which you desired most to take your part: for men
of your livery, if you may get autoritie on your side, count your self
otherwaies sufficiently armed. As for me, If I handle the scriptures
deceitfully: let not onely the Papists laugh at me: but let al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians
spit at me. if I reforme it not, when I am convicted. Howe
strong my reasons are, to cary this cause cleare through the midst
of the aduersaries of it: I hope the sequell will proue: and I referre
it to the advised judgment of the indifferent Reader: I cannot tell
how to frame irrefragable reasons to you. There was a Prophecie
(as Curtius recordeth) that hee who could vndoe the knottes of
Gordius his chariot, should be Emperour of Asia. Alexander inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
that conquest, came to the temple where those knottes were
kept, to see, if hee could open them. But they beeing insoluble by
mans reason, hee tore all assunder with his sword. So you serue my
arguments, be they never so irrefragable: when you cannot open
them with reason: you teare them all assunder with violence. As for
my latine answere, which I indeed did send you, and you in trueth
should haue answered me, and not this wandring vagabound: you
haue had it these three yeares and more, wherein were successiue
houres ynough to answere two sheets of Paper: if you haue not bin
more busie about greater matters, than you would haue the world
to knowe. In the meane time I haue pervsed this, and put my friends
in hope of good successe in the other: when your long leasure will
serue you to answere it. Thus beseeching God to giue vs all one
heart and one minde, I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, Alexander
Hume.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>