<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY FRIENDS, THE CAMBRO-BRITANS.</title>
           <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121639_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A97346</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7228</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121639</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY FRIENDS, THE CAMBRO-BRITANS.</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chorographicall description of all the tracts, riuers, mountains, forests, and other parts of this renowned isle of Great Britain : with intermixture of the most remarkeable stories, antiquities, wonders, rarities, pleasures, and commodities of the same. Diuided into tw bookes; the latter containing twelue songs, neuer before imprinted. Digested into a poem by Michael Drayton. Esquire. With a table added, for direction to those occurrences of story and antiquitie, whereunto the course of the volume easily leades not</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                            <distributor>Dewe, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 303, 9 pages, 18 folded plates, maps, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>TO MY FRIENDS, THE CAMBRO-BRITANS.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>TO haue you without difficulty vnderstand, how in this my intended progresse, through these vnited kingdomes of great</hi> Britaine, <hi>I haue placed your (and I must confesse) my loued</hi> Wales, <hi>you shall perceiue, that after the three first Songs, beginning with our French Ilands,</hi> Iernsey, <hi>and</hi> Iersey, <hi>with the rest; and perfecting in those first three the suruay of these sixe our most Westerne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> Cornwall, Deuon, Dorset, Hamp, Wilt, <hi>and</hi> Summerset; <hi>I then make ouer</hi> Seuerne <hi>into</hi> Wales, <hi>not farre from the midst of her Broad side that lieth against</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>I tearme it her Broad side, because it lieth from</hi> Shrewsbury, <hi>stil along with</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerne, <hi>till she lastly turne sea. And to explaine two lines of mine (which you shall fina in the fourth Song of my Poeme; but it is the first of</hi> Wales) <hi>which are these,</hi>
      <lb/>
And ereseauen Books haue end, Ile strike so high a string,<lb/>
Thy Bards shall stand amaz'd with wonder whilst I sing.<lb/>
      <hi>Speaking of seauen Books; you shall vnderstand that I continew</hi> Wales <hi>through soma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; beginning in the fourth Song (where the nymphes of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>contena for the Ile of</hi> Lundy) <hi>and ending in the tenth; Striuing, as my much loued (the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned)</hi> Humfrey Floyd, <hi>in his description of</hi> Cambria <hi>to</hi> Abraham Ortelius, <hi>to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her auncient bounds,</hi> Seuerne, <hi>and</hi> Dee, <hi>and therefore haue included the parts of those three English Shiers of</hi> Gloster, Worster, <hi>and</hi> Sallop, <hi>that lie on the west of</hi> Seuerne, <hi>within their ancient mother</hi> Wales: <hi>In which if I haue not done her right, the want is in my ability, not in my loue. And beside my naturall inclination to lone Antiquitie (which</hi> Wales <hi>may highly boast of) I confesse, the free and gentle companie of that true louer of his Country (as of all ancient and noble things)</hi> M. Iohn Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams, <hi>his Maiesties Gold-smith, my deare and worthy friend, hath made me the more seek into the antiquities of your Country. Thus wishing your fauorable construction of these my faithfull endeuors, I bid you farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Michael Drayton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>