<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Preface Exhortatory: Touching the use which is to be made of the ensuing Narration.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121128_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24760.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Preface Exhortatory: Touching the use which is to be made of the ensuing Narration.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentations of Germany : Wherein, as in a glasse, we may behold her miserable condition, and reade the woefull effects of sinne. Composed by Dr Vincent Theol. an eye-witnesse thereof; and illustrated by pictures, the more to affect the reader. Hereunto are added thre letters, one whereof was sent to the Dutch consistory in London, under the hand and seales of 14. distressed ministers of Swyburggen in Germany</title>
                 <author>Vincent, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 20, 2, 25-33, 32-63, 1 page, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Preface Exhortatory: Touching the use which is to be made of the ensuing Narration.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Men and brethren:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>HEre followes (according to the table) <hi>A true representation of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable estate of Germany.</hi> A most grave, serious, and weighty subject, and above all other most necessary for us to peruse, and ponder. Wee for the present have <hi>Halcion dayes.</hi> Sitting as the people under <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Every man under his owne Vine, and Fig-tree; No complayning in our streets, no carrying into Captivity.</hi> For which all honour and praise be to him, whose mercy it is that wee are not consumed. And yet there may be <hi>a lengthening of our tranquility,</hi> if wee would walke worthy of those mercies which we doe inioy, and <hi>learne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse by the judgements of God, which are made manifest.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
One especiall meanes effectually tending hereunto, is to be acquainted with the passages of Gods providence abroad, and to make such use of his dreadfull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as he himselfe in Scripture directs us to. For our information in the state of things abroad, these ensuing schedules may helpe such as have no better intelligence. Wherein such passages are related, <hi>as may make both our eares <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> to heare them.</hi> The heads insisted on are <hi>the Arrowes of the Almighty;</hi> Sword, Famine, and Pestilence, together with their pale and grisly attendants. Extortion, Rapine, salvage cruelty, desolations, deaths of all kinde. A sad and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall troope.</p>
   <p>The subject on which all these evils light, is <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> a neighbouring countrey well knowne. The Throne of Europes Empire. This is now the Stage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on most direfull Tragedies are acted. And therein as well the <hi>Protestants</hi> (the more the pity) as the <hi>Papists:</hi> no difference for religious sake; nor any respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, ages, sexes, or conditions. <hi>The fowles of the ayre may therein eate the flesh of Kings, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and mighty men. The flesh of horses, and them that sit on them. Yea, the flesh of all men, both free and bond, both small and great,</hi> Rev. 19. 18.</p>
   <p>The instances and particulars which are here recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded are such as may seeme incredible, and cause wondring unto astonishment, yet is there nothing but what may well be counted probable, a few things considered. As first, what God threatens in this kinde for breach of his Law.
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 53, &amp;c. Thou shalt eate the fruite of thine owne body, the flesh of thy sonnes and daughters —. The man that is tender among you, and very delicate, his eyes shall be evill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosome, and towards the remnant of children which hee shall leave: so that he will not give to any of them the flesh of his children, whom he shall eate, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Then what particular instances we have of like things upon like occasions in Scripture, as in the siege of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, 2 King. 6. 28, 29.</hi> The certainety of the generals is beyond all exception, among those that will believe any thing more than they see with their eyes, and feele with their hands. The time, and space that the wars have endured addes much to the probability of all ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects avoucht. The current yeere making up full twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty since the beginning. During all which <hi>Germany</hi> hath beene <hi>Acheldama, a field of blood.</hi> Vnder this word <hi>(warre)</hi> more evill and mischiefe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended than can be uttered. Weigh all things duly, the severall kinds of warre, forraigne and domesticke; by invasions, by insurrections, the same persons, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being to day Conquerours, and to morrow conquered, over and over againe, and all things every day worse and worse; we may well conclude, <hi>the one halfe hath not beene told us.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I hope none among us are so prophane as to say what is this to us, be it all be true? and few so ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, as not to know what God requireth of us
<pb facs="5"/>
in this regard. Yet it's too manifest, that most are so carelesse, that they neede a Monitor to twit them by the care. I have therefore partly upon intreatie, and chiefly for affection unto the thing it selfe, endevoured briefly to speake something unto that end. <hi>The Lyon hath roared, who will not feare? The Lord hath spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, who can but prophecie,</hi> Amos <hi>3. 8. Salvian</hi> in his time, tooke great paines to prove there was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilence, when the then supposed barbarous <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandalls</hi> broke in upon the Empire, as the Sea doth sometimes over flow the banke. But mee thinkes that alone were enough to manifest the finger of <hi>God,</hi> which bred the doubt in men Atheisticall. How exceeding full is the Scripture for the proofe of this? <hi>That God is Authour of all Judgements, and therefore in all wee ought to looke up unto him.</hi> All Captaines and their armies are but Sergeants under <hi>the Lord of hosts; that man of warre, and God of battell. The Assyrian is the rod of Gods anger, the staffe in their hand is Gods indignation,</hi> Isay <hi>10. 5. There is no evill in a City but he doth it. Behold</hi> (saith the Psalmist) <hi>what desolations the Lord hath made in the earth.</hi> Psal. 46. 8. If a Sparrow fall not to the ground, but <hi>according to the will of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father,</hi> much lesse are millions of men mowed downe with the sword, but according to his righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in Iudgement.</p>
   <p>It is also cleare out of Scripture, that wee ought to lay to heart those Iudgements of God, which wee are acquainted with, and especially his greater Iudgements
<pb facs="5"/>
God sends one place to consider of another: <hi>Goe yee now unto my place, which was in</hi> Shilo, <hi>where I set my name at the beginning, and see what I did to it for the wickednesse of my people Israel,</hi> 7. 12. saith God to the men of Ierusalem.</p>
   <p>And who makes question, but that those <hi>Churches, Nations, Persons,</hi> and <hi>Places,</hi> which have speciall relation one unto another, sacred or civill, in the bonds of Religion, neighbourhood or commerce are more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially bound mutually to consider and bemoane one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conditions.</p>
   <p>This likewise is evident, that our Church and State, and every member of the same, ought upon speciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration to be cordially affected with the miseries of <hi>Germany.</hi> They are of the same Religion with us. Christians as wee are; our peace is the weaker for want of theirs; many of our owne have suffered with them. but above all is the affliction of that <hi>Royall Lady</hi> our Gracious Soveraignes onely sister, who hath suffered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in her Royall Person, and may suffer yet more in her posterity, but God forbid. But what is it that wee must doe, or learne from the state of things in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny?</hi> The particulars are severall in severall regards. In relation to God, to them and to our selves.</p>
   <p>In regard of God. Wee must acknowledge the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his Wisdome and unsearchablenesse of his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and take heede of rash assigning the cause. Some lay all the blame upon the <hi>Protestants,</hi> as if their divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion among themselves, and unnecessary separation (in their phrase) from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> were the
<pb facs="6"/>
roote of all. But is it not more likely, that <hi>Germany drinkes now of the cup of wrath, because shee hath long drunke of the cup of sundry great abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations?</hi> The generall cause, which is sinne, wee all acknowledge: It were a happinesse to know the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, according unto that, <hi>Foelix qui potuit rerum cognoscere causas.</hi> But such a spirit of discerning God gives not unto all. They themselves best know their owne waies, case and state, and therefore wee may leave it unto them to consider of the speciall causes, whom it most concernes. <hi>But who will not feare the Lord, and glorifie his Name, who onely is holy, and whose judgements are made manifest,</hi> Rev. 15. 4.</p>
   <p>In respect of them, first let us sympathize: grieve with them that grieve. Rom. <hi>12. 15. and weepe with them that weepe.</hi> We are all members of one and the same mysticall body, whereof Christ is head. Our peace and security is in a great measure bound up in theirs: their troubles may increase ours; as they have already occasioned many feares, cares and expences: Witnesse the great levie of souldiers at some times, and not a little chargeable Embassages from our King and State. Next of all, we are to pray for them, that God would restore peace, and make up all breaches. <hi>Giving the Lord no rest, untill hee make</hi> Ierusalem <hi>the praise of the earth. Abraham</hi> interceded long for <hi>Sodome,</hi> how much more ought we to do the like for them? And yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as we have ability and opportunity, we ought to help and succour them, ministring to their necessities, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of their profugates, and intertaining them into our
<pb facs="6"/>
bosomes, when they fly from their owne to us. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of ours found among them a shelter from the storme in our <hi>Marian daies,</hi> and doe still, no doubt, blesse God for our peace, notwithstanding their owne warres.</p>
   <p>In respect of our selves, there be many instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which we may learne from the <hi>Lecture</hi> of their calamities. No privileges can finally secure a sinfull people; for what have we to glory in that they had not? The seedes of all their evills are sowne in our fields. There be likewise di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers duties that wee should abound in the more: In repentance, lest we bring upon our selves the like: In prayer, that God would blesse our state and government, that by the wisedome thereof we may be led along in such waies as may propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate our peace unto posterity: In patience under those chastisements which we suffer. Though the hand of God hath long beene upon many Cities and Townes, and <hi>his Arme be stretched out still</hi> upon some of them, yet is our misery, happinesse, in comparison of theirs: If a gentle plague alone have affrighted us all, What would Sword and Famine with it doe?</p>
   <p>But what doe wee? <hi>Wee put farre away the evill day, and cause the seat of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to come neere: Wee drinke wine in bowles, and anoint our selves with the chiefe ointments, but are not grieved for the afflictions of</hi> Ioseph, Amos <hi>6. 3. &amp; 6.</hi> This
<pb facs="7"/>
is no small sinne, and if once the day of our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitation come, a small chastisement on Gods part will not be all. Oh that wee would consider, <hi>the Vials of Gods wrath are pouring forth, as well on his owne Churches for correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as on their adversaries unto destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> Who knowes how fast the cup may passe round? Gods arrowes are all fleete. <hi>The curse of God goeth forth over the face of the whole earth,</hi> Zach. <hi>5. 3.</hi> If the sinnes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> be found in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and the sinnes of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> in <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> they shall all pledge each other: for God is no respecter of persons. Are there no drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards but in <hi>Germany?</hi> Or, doth God hate sinne in them alone? What are wee, that God should alwaies spare us? Many cry, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> and I with the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> say <hi>Amen. The Lord doe so, the Lord performe the words of them which prophesie of nothing but good,</hi> Iere. <hi>28. 6.</hi> But its good to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that of the Apostle, when they cry, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gloss. ordin.</hi> in Ierem. <hi>7. 12. Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid illo populo fecit Deus, timeamus: cum nos similia faciamus.</hi> Yet no such clouds <hi>(blessed bee God)</hi> arise over our heads, as those where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with her horizon is darkned. But stormes arise suddenly. <hi>God creates good and evill,</hi> brings both when there is no appearance or cause of suspici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Not to feare is cause enough to bee affraid, if we could so reflect upon our selves: <hi>As God brings
<pb facs="7"/>
light out of darknesse, so darknesse out of light.</hi> How faire rose the Sunne upon <hi>Sodome,</hi> that day it rained fire and brimstone? How poore a thing was a cloud like a mans hand, to prognosticate abundance of raine by? But I must <hi>manum de tabula.</hi> Well then reade on, reade and spare not, reade and consider, reade and weepe, imagine the Booke to be <hi>Germany</hi> it selfe, their case ours, and <hi>our soules in their soules stead.</hi> Do as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did when he heard of the state of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> and the Temple therein <hi>He sate downe and wept, mourned and fasted certaine daies, and prayed before the Lord God of Heaven,</hi> Neh. <hi>1. 4.</hi> Would we but doe the like for our selves and them, God would assuredly restore their peace, and continue ours, for which I shall ever heartily pray, and so rest</p>
   <closer>A well-wisher to all the Churches of God.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>