<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121940_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17946</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4606</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121940</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of Cambria, now called Wales: a part of the most famous yland of Brytaine, written in the Brytish language aboue two hundreth yeares past: translated into English by H. Lhoyd Gentleman: corrected, augmented, and continued out of records and best approoued authors, by Dauid Powel Doctor in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Caradoc, of Llancarvan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 22, 2, 401, 15 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Aradoc of Lancar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan (gentle Reader) col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the successions &amp; actes of the Brytish Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces after Cadwalader, to the yeare of Christ 1156. Of the which collections there were seuerall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies afterward kept in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Abbeis of Conwey and Stratflur, which were yearelie aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented as things fell out, and conferred together or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarilie euerie third yeare, when the Beirdh which did belong to those two Abbeis went from the one to the other in the time of their Clêra,<note place="margin">Clêra <hi>is their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie visitation which they vse euerie third yeare.</hi>
      </note> wherein were contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned besides, such notable occurrences hapning within this Ile of Brytaine, as they then thought worthie the writing: which order of registring and noting conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in those Abbeis vntill the yeare 1270. which was a little before the death of the last Lhewelyn who was slaine at Buelht. These collections were copied by diuers, so that there are at this daie of the same in Wales a hundred copies at the least, whereof the most part were written two hundred yeares ago. This booke Humffrey Lhoyd gentleman (a paineful and a worthie searcher of Brytish antiquities) translated into English,
<pb facs="6"/>
and partlie augmented, chieflie out of Matthew Paris, and Nicholas Triuet: but before the booke was po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished (hauing yet manie imperfections, not onelie in the phrase, but also in the matter and substance of the historie) it pleased God to take him awaie in the floure of his time: who (if God had spared him life) would not onelie haue set out this historie absolute and perfect, but also haue opened vnto the world other antiquities of this land, which now lie hidden and vnknowen. The copie of his translation, the Right honorable Sir Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sidney Lord President of Wales (whose disposition is rather to seeke after the antiquities, and the weale pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike of those countries which he gouerneth, than to obtaine lands and reuenewes within the same, for I know not one foote of land that hee hath either in VVales or Ireland) had lieng by him a great while, and being desirous to haue the same set out in print, sent for me in September last, requesting me to peruse and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it, in such sort as it might be committed to the presse. But I (knowing my selfe to be far vnable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and accomplish those things which are requisite to the publishing of such an historie, and being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called and imploied) was verie loath anie thing to medle therein, and so excused my selfe; yet he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a better opinion of me than there was cause, would needs haue me to doo mine indeuour in that behalfe. VVhose request I was not of dutie to gainesaie or withstand, and therevpon I promised to doo my best, which trauell two things haue caused me to be the more willing to take it in hand.</p>
   <p>First, because I see the politike and martiall actes of all other inhabitants of this Iland, in the time of their gouernment to be set out to the vttermost, and that by diuers and sundrie writers: and the whole doings and
<pb facs="6"/>
gouernment of the Brytaines the first inhabitants of the land, who continued their rule longer than anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nation,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rob. Caenal. li.</hi> 2. <hi>Par.</hi> 2.</note> to be nothing spoken of nor regarded of anie, especialie sithence the reigne of Cadwalader, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing so manie monuments of antiquitie to declare and testifie the same, if anie would take the paines to open and discouer them to the vew of the world.</p>
   <p>The second thing that mooued me therevnto, is the slanderous report of such writers, as in their bookes do inforce euerie thing that is done by the Welshmen to their discredit, leauing out all the causes and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the same: which doo most commonlie not onelie eleuate or dissemble all the iniuries and wrongs offered and done to the Welshmen, but also conceale or deface all the actes worthie of commendation at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued by them. Search the common Chronicles touching the Welshmen, and commonlie thou shalt find that the King sendeth some noble man or other with an armie to Wales, to withstand the rebellious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, the proud stomachs, the presumptuous pride, stirre, trouble and rebellion of the fierce, vnquiet, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, fickle and vnconstant Welshmen, and no open fact laid downe to charge them withall, why warre should be leuied against them, nor yet they swaruing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brod out of their owne countrie to trouble other men. Now this historie dooth shew the cause and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of most of those warres, whereby the qualitie of the action may be iudged. And certeinlie no man is an indifferent witnesse against him whom he counteth his enimie or aduersarie, for euill will neuer speaketh well. The Welshmen were by the Saxons and Normans counted enimies, before the twelfth yeare of Edward the first, while they had a gouernour among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: and afterward, when king Edward had brought
<pb facs="7"/>
the countrie to his subiection, he placed English offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to keepe them vnder, to whome most common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie he gaue the forfaits and possessions of such Welsh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as disobeied his lawes, and refused to be ruled by the said officers: the like did the other Kings that came after him. The said officers were thought oftentimes to be ouer-seuere and rigorous for their owne profit &amp; commoditie: which things caused the people often to disobeie, &amp; manie times like desperate men to seeke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengement, hauing those for their iudges which were made by their ouerthrow, and also wanting indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in their causes and matters of griefes: for the Kings alwaies countenanced and beleeued their owne offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, by them preferred and put in trust, before their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers, whom they liked not of. Wherevpon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of England fauoring their countriemen and freends, reported not the best of the Welshmen. This hatred and disliking was so increased by the stirre and rebellion of Owen Glyndoure, that it brought foorth such greeuous lawes, as few Christian kings euer gaue or published the like to their subiects. These things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so, anie man may easilie perceiue the verie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of those parentheseis and briefe notes of rebellion and troubles obiected to the Welshmen, without ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of cause or declaration of circumstances.</p>
   <p>The Normans hauing conquered England, and got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all the lands of the Saxon nobilitie, would faine haue had the lands of the Welshmen also, wherevpon diuers of them entred▪ VVales with an armie, so that the VVelshmen were driuen for their owne defense to put themselues in armour: for the which fact they are by some writers accused of rebellion, wheras by the law of Nature it is lawfull for all men to withstand force by force.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Vim vi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellere licet.</hi>
      </note> They were in their owne countrie, the
<pb facs="7"/>
land was theirs by inheritance and lawfull possession: might they not therefore defend themselues from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and wrong, if they could? What right or lawfull title had the Earle of Chester to Ryuonioc &amp; Tegengl? or the Earle of Salope to Dyuet, Caerdigan, &amp; Powys? or Rob. Fitzhamon to Glamorgan? or Barnard New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march to Brechnoke? or Ralph Mortimer to Eluel? or Hugh Lacy to the land of Ewyas? or anie other of them to anie countrie in VVales? By what reason was it more lawfull for those men to dispossesse them of these countries with violence and wrong, than for them to defend and keepe their owne? Shall a man be charged with disobedience, because he seeketh to keepe his purse from him that would robbe him? I meane not by this to charge those Noble men, which wan these countries by the sword: but I speake it to note the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial dealing of the writers &amp; setters foorth of those hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, that should haue reported things indifferentlie, as they were done, and laid downe the causes and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of euerie action truelie, who being altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parciall, fauoring the one side &amp; hating the other, do pronounce of the fact according to their priuate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, condemning oftentimes the innocent, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifieng the wrong doers.</p>
   <p>These considerations I saie, besides my bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, caused me to venture to take this thing in hand. The translation of H. Lhoyd I haue conferred with the Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish booke, whereof I had two ancient copies, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the same, when there was cause so to doo. And after that the most part of the booke was printed, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued another larger copie of the same translation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better corrected, at the hands of Robert Glouer Somerset Herald, a learned and studious Gentleman in his profession, the which if I had had at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb facs="8"/>
manie things had come foorth in better plight than they now be. Againe, I got all the authors that I could come by, which haue anie thing written of the affaires of VVales, as Gildas, Asser Meneuensis, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fride, William of Newborow, Matthew Paris, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Westminster, Thomas Walsingham, Ponticus Virunnius, Polydor Virgil, Io. Leyland, Io. Bale, I. Prise, Matthew Parker, Io. Caius, VVilliam Lambert, and all the English Chronicles printed. In written hand I had Gildas Sapiens <hi>alias</hi> Nennius, Henrie Huntington, VVilliam Malmsbury, Marianus Scotus, Ralph Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall, Io. Euersden, Nicholas Triuet, Florentius Vigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niensis, Simon of Durham, Roger Houedon, and other which remaine in the custodie of I. Stowe citizen of London, who deserueth cōmendation for getting togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ancient writers of the histories of this land. I had also the Brytish books of petegrees. I. Castoreus, &amp; Syluester Giral. Cambrensis, which with diuers other rare monuments of antiquitie, I receiued at the hands of the Right Honorable the Lord Burghley high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer of England: who also directed me by his letters to all the offices where the Records of this realme are kept, out of the which I haue gathered a great part of this historie, and more would haue done, if the time had permitted. The copie I haue conferred with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed authors, and where I found them to intreat of the matters therein contained, I haue noted them in the margine, and in such authors as are printed I haue most commonlie directed thee gentle Reader to the page or chapter of the booke where thou shalt find the same historie treated of. Againe, where I found anie thing of Wales worthie the noting in the said au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors being not conteined in the copie, I haue inserted
<pb facs="8"/>
the same in a smaller letter with this marke * before it, whereby it may be discerned from the copie it selfe. Further, such things as were breefly set downe in the copie without signification of cause or declaration of circumstances, if I found the same in anie of mine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors treated of and further opened, I haue likewise in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted it in his due place. In the possession and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of families, I haue sought what I could for the time, and haue laid downe most of the noble families of England, which had lands in Wales, or descended out of that countrie. I was greatlie furthered in this worke by the painefull and studious trauell of the right worshipfull Sir Edward Stradling Knight, Thomas Powel of Whittington parke, and Richard Broughton Esquires.</p>
   <p>In the description I haue taken the lesse paines, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king dailie for the comming foorth of the painefull and studious trauell of some other, who hath labored in that behalfe, and studied all the Romane and Brytish histories concerning the ancient names of nations and places within this Iland, so that my labour were super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous in that behalfe. Herein if happilie I haue swar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or omitted anie thing, which should haue beene laid downe in this historie, I neither did it wittinglie nor willinglie: and therefore being readie vpon better information to amend that which shalbe found to be amisse, if any so shalbe, I am the rather to be born with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, because I am the first setter out in print of this histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: for things can neuer be so well doone at the first when there is but few that doo trauell therein, as they maie in processe of time, when euerie man putteth to his helping hand, which curtesie I am to desire of thee gentle Reader for the perfecting of this worke.</p>
   <p>Concerning the alteration of the estate, there was
<pb facs="9"/>
neuer anie thing so beneficiall to the common people of Wales, as the vniting of that countrie to the crowne and kingdome of England, whereby not onelie the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie and hurt of the dissention that often hapned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Princes of the countrie, while they ruled, is now taken awaie, but also an vniformitie of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment established; whereby all controuersies are exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, heard &amp; decided within the countrie: so that now the countrie of Wales (I dare boldlie affirme it) is in as good order for quietnes and obedience as anie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in Europe: for if the rulers and teachers be good and doo their duties, the people are willing to learne, readie to obeie, and loath to offend or displease. And if it please God once to send them the Bible in their owne language according to the godlie lawes alreadie established, the countrie of Wales (I doubt not) will be comparable to anie countrie in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>