<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, the Master, VVardens, and Assistants of the Honourable Cmnie of MERS in London, my worthy friends and Patrons, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Gill, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121104_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01743</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11878</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121104</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, the Master, VVardens, and Assistants of the Honourable Cmnie of MERS in London, my worthy friends and Patrons, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Gill, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sacred philosophie of the Holy Scripture, laid downe as conclusions on the articles of our faith, commonly called the Apostles Creed : Proved by the principles or rules taught and received in the light of understanding. Written by Alexander Gil, Master of Pauls Schole</title>
                 <author>Gill, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Anne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <distributor>Norton, Joyce (Jocosa)</distributor>
                            <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 196, 232 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, the Master, VVardens, and Assistants of the Honourable C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nie of MER<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>S in London, my worthy friends and Patrons, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now six and twentie yeares, since by the great love and favour of the Company, I had the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that ancient, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous foundation of <hi>Pauls</hi> Schole, committed to my trust, and care In all which time (untill Nature gave place unto extreme age and infirmitie) if my abilitie assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted with industrie hath advanced those, that were commended to my institution, in manners, and learning; I desire that they may render and attribute the sole thankes unto you. For by your courtesie and discreet libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie I was cherished, and furthered, not onely to doe you ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in my selfe, but likewise to give such education to my sonnes, as hath made them fit, in their qualities, to performe the like dutie.</p>
   <p>Now so it is, worthie Gentlemen, that Nature being not onely declined in me, but almost quite worne out, by reason of a seden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie life, much studie, and continuall paynes; I thought it fit, before I goe hence, in gratefull acknowledgment of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great obligations, which your goodnesse hath from time to time fastned upon me, ever since my entrance into your service,
<pb facs="5"/> to dedicate the best of my labours to your acceptance. This is it, which if it have the blessing to doe (as doubtlesse it will in some measure) any benefit to the Church and country, wherein I live, I shall likewise intreate them to conferre the thanks upon you, by whom I was enabled to perfect a worke of so high and necessary an argument. I shall not live to receive your thanks my selfe: and therefore I beseech you to accept of them, as the legacie of a dying man, and, with them, the dedication of this worke. Which as it was begun, and finished under your roofe: so I know none more fit to patronize the worke, than your-selves, who have been the Patrons of the author.</p>
   <p>Thus in all humility I take leave, committing you to God; my surviving sonnes to the continuance of your love and care; and this other chyld of my old age to your fostering, a more living witnesse of your favours towards me, and my thankefulnesse to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your much obliged Servant, <hi>ALEX. GIL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>