<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE my singular good Lord, Sr THOMAS FLEMYNGE Knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of England.</title>
           <author>James, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121923_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15298</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121923</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE my singular good Lord, Sr THOMAS FLEMYNGE Knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of England.</title>
                 <author>James, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo short treatises, against the orders of the begging friars : compiled by that famous doctour of the Church, and preacher of Gods word John Wickliffe, sometime fellow of Merton, and master of Ballioll Coll. in Oxford, and afterwards parson of Lutterworth in Lecestershire. Faithfully printed according to two ancient manuscript copies, extant, the one in Benet Colledge in Cambridge, the other remaining in the publike librarie at Oxford</title>
                 <author>Wycliffe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 62, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE my singular good Lord, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> THOMAS FLEMYNGE Knight, Lord Chiefe Iustice of England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable &amp; my good Lord, beeing tied vnto your Lordship with those bonds, which to recount in particular, were to exceed the bounds of an Epistle, as first for my electiō into that famous <hi>Seminarie</hi> of good learning neere <hi>VVinchester,</hi> secondly for my better promotion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that enermore iustly to be called <note n="a" place="margin">Inde value ex Equo Troiano, vi ri omni tē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te excellē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes prode ūt Polyd. Virg Hist. Angl. l. 19. p. 381.</note>
      <hi>New Colledg in Oxford</hi> (two most honorable foundatiōs of one sole <hi>Founder VVilliam of VViccham</hi>) lastly for my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great hopes and farther incouragemēts in the Ministerie; all which kind fauours, as I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg them to haue proceeded only, or espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by your Lordships meanes, so in a thankful remembrance thereof, accept I beseech you these two small Treatises ensewing, as pledges of my duty, and the meere Interest of that Honor which is due vnto your Lordship, and hath beene of a long time (Iconfesse) vnpayd, but not vnremēbred wherfore, hauing not as yet any thinge of mine
<pb facs="3"/>
owne store worthy the bestowing, I haue borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed these few lines from one, that is rich in this kinde: whose soule I trust is with God, his fame with the world, and his bones had rested in the graue, had not the restlesse malice of his cruel ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries herein exceeded, by taking, or rather raking them vp out of the <note n="b" place="margin">See the decree of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of con stance, and the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ox</note> graue, after hee had quietly slept in the Lord, for the space of 41. years; committing them to the mercy of two merciles E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, Fire and Water; And as if this crueltie had not s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>iced to aswage there bloud thirsty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, Councell must be called vpon Councell, Bishops, Archbishops, <note n="c" place="margin">See Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singham▪ pag 188. Lib. memo rabilium ex don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Nic. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>re Atm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> and lastly the Popes San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie must be consulted, about the vtter rooting out, and abolishing of his name, and doctrine from amongst the memorie of men, &amp; herevpon letters are sent in all post haste from the Bishops vnto the <note n="d" place="margin">Walsing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. Ib pag 204.</note> Pope, from the Pope to the king, from the king to the Archbishop, and from both king Pope and Archbishop vnto the <note n="e" place="margin">Ib p. 306. Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ent a Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>▪ brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>eats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Vniuersity for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>uffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>es opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to take so deepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="5 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> aduen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>us dicti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> nun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ij d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>u in pendu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>o, haerebant, vt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>um papalem Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> honor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> reciper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> velomnino cum dedecore refutare. Walsing. p. 200 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>undry other Bulles against him Ib.</note> Chancellour of Oxford, and last of al to make the matter more sure▪ the high Court of Parliament is summoned wherein his articles beeing before condemned, must needs be published and recorded; But man
<pb facs="3"/>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Ipse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silium eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ū d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ssipauit, qui perdit sapientium sapientiam &amp; pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium prud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> tiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>epro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat solo nutu Wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>▪ words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted pag▪ 218.</note> purposeth, and God disposeth, for behold that God which sitteth on high, laughed thē to scorne frustrated their bloudie designements, preserued his painful &amp; learned works, to stop the mouths of lying <note n="g" place="margin">The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie of the Roman Church is deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral tracts wherof the second is this that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giō was not so much as in being at▪ or before Luthers first appear ing. See the Title pag. This is a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>st mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Pamphleters which write that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is nothing else but a newe and vpstart do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>scarsly euer heard of before Luthers time,</hi> the sharpnes of which obiection (if there be any edg in it I haue rebated in another Treatise dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto an other verie Honorable Iudge of this land, of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ordships neere acquaintāce <hi>Iudiciā sit pene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> lectorem▪</hi> where I haue demonstrated most cleerely, to the eie, (as they saie) the fondnes and vanitie of Father <note n="h" place="margin">Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ons in his 3▪ Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Part▪ 2 pag. 487. The Apol. Tract. 2. Cap 2. pag. 105.</note> Parsons, &amp; our Pseudo-Catho like Apologists calumniations, both against the parson of Wickliffe, and doctrine of our Catho▪ like Protestant Religiō: accusing the one of foul heresies, and monstrous absurdities, and appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other of manifest newnes and new-fāgle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>▪ I haue (as I trust) freed both from that vniust and slaunderous imputation, in the iudgment of the indifferent reader: for others that stand po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, indeed sottishlie affected, in the Romish religion, from whom a man shall not bee able to wring any other answere but this, <hi>we know that we are in the right and you are in the wrong</hi> (I am affraide)
<pb facs="4"/>
I shall not be able to satisfie <hi>non si persuasero</hi> no, not when I haue perswaded them. But to let them passe, &amp; to excuse my selfe vnto your Lordship, why amongst so manie Scholastical Treatises by him written, which are with vs extant, I shoulde choose rather to publish these two small Bookes, taken out of his popular discourses, and those pēned (as it should seeme) not long after his first open manifestation of his mislike with their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted corruptions and abuses. The motiues or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements were these: first because these Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises are short and entire of them selues: secondly because our <note n="i" place="margin">Hee with his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples went barefooted and basely clothed, in course rus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set garmēts—ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>oined himselfe to the beging Friars, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and extolling their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. Tract. 2. Cap. 2, pag. 106. Wickliffe himselfe sai eth, he wēt too wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, rather thē otherwise <hi>consumendo bona paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessiuo victu &amp; vestitu</hi> De Ver. Scrip. pag. 192. &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Friars more then any man of his ranck place or time. Woodeford in a Ms. Treatise in defence of the orders of Friars obiecteth too great excesse of apparrel vnto his followers.</note> Adversaries, whose forheads are tenderer then other mens, shame not to write and cite Wickliffe for one of the order of the Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Friars, <hi>adioining himselfe vnto that Sect, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving there pouerty,</hi> &amp; <hi>extolling there perfection:</hi> which notorious vntruth, is confuted in everie page &amp; passage almost of these Two Books: lastly I haue chosen rather to publish somewhat of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in regard of your Lordships vtter detestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Iesuiticall Friars, and Friarlike Iesuits. For what is spoken of the one, <hi>mutato nomine</hi> may wel be vnderstood of the other, and what is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="4"/>
against the Friars, may truly be extended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iesuits, they are so like in hypocrisie, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, treacheries, treasons, lyings, and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Equiuocations.</hi> And as <note n="k" place="margin">Tales po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes in Clero▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>siue personae simplices Collegiat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> aggregatae, quae religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti dissip ant sub pallio sanctitatis vel punien tur hic per praepositos suos, aut la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icos; vel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struentur per vastra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiles; vel congregāt facino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>a in vltionem diuini iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij, dicente Apostolo Rom. 2 <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xistimas autem o homo &amp;c</hi>—Est enim dare mensuram in scelera vs{que} ad▪ quam opo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tet vltio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem diuini iudicij expectare. De Verit. Scrip pag. 432 433.</note>
      <hi>Iohn VVickliffe</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied of the Friars, that in short time their great Monasteries, (their great sinnes so requiring it, when the measure of their iniquities shoulde bee compleat and full,) would come to great confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and desolation: so of that other Sect is there a prophecie extant of a <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Arias Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>anas praefatione prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixa Bib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>iis Interlinearibus, sublata sunt haec verba in quibusdam edit, contra eos</hi> qui soli sapere so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li bene viuere Iesum{que} propius insequi sibi videantur, at{que} id palam professi iactitent. At{que} hi (inquit) quod neminem qui alias bene audiat, palam improbare audent, aliorum quos ad eam rem occulte inducere possunt ingenijs &amp; nominibus abutuntur. Horum aut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ec ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes fallunt, nec gregem prodere aut cognomen indica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e iuuat: vtuntur quidem il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>i ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>no &amp; inaccessibile ad suas agendas res mysterio, sed quod faci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e ijs qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>plicius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> agere volunt pelluceat: quod{que} non post multos annos tandem aperiendum est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> illius qui illuminabit abscondita cordis, &amp; occulta tenebrarum, tunc laus erit vnicui{que} secundum opera sua.</note> man very famously lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that in short time these counterfet Iesuits, would be vnmasked, their vizors pulled of from their faces, and there knaueries and treacheries discovered vnto the whole world. For my parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular I neither wish nor prophecie there finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, only the downe-fall and ruine of that damned Sect, is that which I professe I do aime at, and to vse <note n="m" place="margin">Against the order of Friars pag. 22.</note>
      <hi>VVickliffs</hi> words <hi>to saue there persons &amp; destroy their errors.</hi> Wherefore, fearing lest too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="5"/>
of all sorts of men should bee bewitched with this Circean Sect, I haue presumed to offer vp these few lines, as it were so many warrants to bee signed by your Lordships hand, and sent abroad into all parts of this land, that by vertue of them, mēmight ether apprehēd, or amend thē, take thē, or take heed of thē. What should I trouble your Lordship any farther, <hi>VVickliffe</hi> hath not as yet wanted a <note n="n" place="margin">There was one <hi>William Iames</hi> a great Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Wickliffe. Vir vti{que} pulchrae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraturae, &amp; elegantis facundiae▪ Walden. To. 2. p. 47.</note>
      <hi>Iames</hi> to follow and embrase his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor your Lordship a deuine to honor you and your most honorable <hi>Profession;</hi> professing my selfe to haue learned of this <note n="o" place="margin">Vide lib. Ms De ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posit. 10. Mandat in sine libri. Heagreeth fully with my L Cook in his 5. book of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and the booke De funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Angliae in defēse of the Kinges Regaltie.</note>
      <hi>Doctor of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall truth</hi> (as I find him by Papists stiled) to make more account and vse of the <hi>Common Lawe</hi> of this lād. And thus crauing pardō of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship for hauing so long detained you from grea ter businesses of the Cōmon wealth, committing both him and my selfe vnto your Lordships pro tection, I end, wishing vnto your Lordship, and to your vertuous Lady my derest Sister, with al yours endlesse comforts both of this life, and of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to come <hi>From the Publike Librarie in Oxford. Feb.</hi> 10. 1608.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in al Christian dutie.
THO: IAMES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>