<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE ENGLISH READER, whether Protestant, or Papist, be he a true Catholique, or a Romane. An Aduertisement to helpe his Vnderstan∣ding in the reading of this strange Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121001_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19586</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6023</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121001</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE ENGLISH READER, whether Protestant, or Papist, be he a true Catholique, or a Romane. An Aduertisement to helpe his Vnderstan∣ding in the reading of this strange Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mittimus to the iubile at Rome: or, the rates of the Popes custome-house : Sent to the Pope, as a New-yeeres-gift from England, this yeere of iubile, 1625. And faithfully published out of the old Latine copie, with obseruations vpon the Romish text, by William Crashavv, Batchelor of Diuinity, and pastor at White-Chappell</title>
                 <author>Catholic Church, Cancellaria Apostolica</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 44, 2, 70 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE ENGLISH READER, whether Protestant, or Papist, be he a true Catholique, <hi>or a Romane. An Aduertisement to helpe his Vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> in the reading of this strange Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope, the learned will giue me leaue to informe the lesse skilfull Readers, (such especially as haue beene vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in the Popes proceedings and Romish Markets) in some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, wherein otherwise they can hardly satisfie themselues. <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
      </label> As first, it will be obiected by them that maintaine their owne Religion, or rather Romish faction, by such tricks, that all this is but counterfeit, and falsly fathered vpon them, to their disgrace. <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Answere. </seg>
      </label> But heereto I answer: First, the Originall Booke in Latine, out of which this is taken and translated is their owne, and none of ours, and printed amongst themselues at <hi>Paris</hi> more then an hundreth yeeres agoe, being first made, and printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the dayes of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, and the Booke it selfe remaines in a publique Library ready euer to bee shewed for the iustification of our sincere
<pb facs="3"/> dealing heerein, and the satisfaction of all such as shall make doubt thereof.</p>
   <p>This euidence is true, and dare abide the Test; yet for further cleering of the truth, take one more, against which the very enemies shall not except. Know ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (good Reader) that howsoeuer this vngodly Booke past currant, and relisht well enough in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> yet, when it came into <hi>France,</hi> it tasted not so well, but contrariwise, was so harsh, and vnpleasant, nay, so loathsome and odious to them who had any sense of sin, or sparks of Gods feare in them, as (though they were otherwise Papists) yet they cryed, shame vpon this Booke and vpon the Makers, and Patrons of it: Amongst whom, <hi>Claudius Espencaeus,</hi> a Doctor of <hi>Sorbone,</hi> one of the most learned of that time, noble by his blood, but more by his Learning and good life, a <hi>Bishop</hi> before hee dyed, and designed also to be a <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> (but as one writes, hee was too good, as <hi>John de la Casa</hi> was too bad,<note place="margin">Thnanus Hist. Lib. <hi>16.</hi> ad An. <hi>1555.</hi>
      </note> and so both of them mist the red Hat) <hi>Espencaeus.</hi> I say, was both so honest, and so hardy, as not onely publikely in the Pulpit, but euen in priuate, to reproue this shamelesse Strumpet, by laying open to the worlds view, the vilenesse, &amp; villany of this Booke: whose very words, because they speake home to the Point, and containe a most excellent and irrefragable euidence for the truth &amp; the true Church, and worthy to be kept as a neuer-dying witnesse against the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and her spirituall abominations, I hold well worthy to bee heere inserted; the rather, seeing since the Iesuites preuailed to abuse the World, those worthy Commentaries of <hi>Espencaeus,</hi> that formerly were so frequent in learned mens hands, are now so sought and snatcht vp euery where and burnt, by those wily Inquisitors, as they are now very hard to come by. Thus then speakes this Popish, yet honest Bishop in his learned Commentaries vpon <hi>Titus,</hi> hauing cryed out
<pb facs="3"/> vpon the horrible abuses reigning in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> especially, the setting to sale of all sorts of Sins; hee proceedeth, and saith:</p>
   <q>
      <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
         <body>
            <div type="text">
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <head>Ipsa Ʋerba Espencaei.</head>
                  <p>FIcta sint haec,<note place="margin">Ci. Espenc. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentan Lit. Cap <hi>1.</hi> Digress. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> &amp; in odium Romanae sedis ab haereticis iactata, si non quod ait &amp; conqueritur ille velut <hi>prostat, &amp; in quaestu pro Meretrice sedet,</hi> liber palam ac publicè hic impressus hodie{que} vt olim venalis, <hi>Taxa Camerae, seu Cancellariae Apostolicae</hi> inscriptus, in quo plus scelerum discas licèt, quàm in omnibus omnium vitiorum Sūmistis, &amp; Summarijs; Et plurimis quidem <hi>licentia,</hi> omnibus autem <hi>Absolutio</hi> ompturientibus proposita: parco nominibus, nam quod ait, nescio quis, <hi>Nomina sunt ipso pene timenda sono.</hi> Mirum hoc tempore, hoc Schismate, non suppressum, tot tam{que} foedorum, tam{que} horrendorum scelerum, velut Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicem, adeo infamem, vt non putem in Germania, Heluetia, &amp; vbicun{que} à Romana sede defectum est, opus prostare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iore huius scandalo, &amp; adeo tamen non supprimitur ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae Romanae fauissoribus, vt tantorum ac talium facino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum licentiae ac impunitates, in facultatibus Legatorum illine tunc venientium bona ex parte innouentur at{que} con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmentur, aduersus (si Deo placet) quaecun{que} fatalia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituendo, ac etiam quoscun{que} Spurios, Manseres, Bastar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, ex quocun{que} illicito coitu, &amp;c. Cum his qui se per adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terium polluerint vt connubere possint, Periuros, Simonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, Falsarios, item Raptores Vsurarios, Schismoticos, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos, sed ad cor reuersos, non absoluendi tantùm, sed ad ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, honores, dignitates &amp; beneficia quaecun{que}, quotcū{que} qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licun{que} dispensandi homicidasquo{que} (sed casuales seu inuolun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarios, nam nec voluntarios quidem excepit Taxa superior) Presbytericidas, Patricidas, Matricidas, Fratriecidas, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roricidas, Ʋxoricidas, Infanticidas, Ʋenisicas, Jneanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices, Concubinarios, Adulteros, Incestos cum Affimbus,
<pb facs="4"/> aut Consanguineis, deni{que} contra naturam cum Brutis, &amp;c. <hi>Habeat iam Roma pudorem,</hi> &amp; tam nullius frontis cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum omne genus Catalogum prostituere desinat, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <head>The Words of <hi>Espencaeus</hi> in English. or, the same in effect.</head>
                  <p>LEet all this bee held faigned, &amp; falsly charged vpon vs by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> were it not that the Booke it selfe being come from <hi>Rome,</hi> is openly set to sale, and as the Poet saith, euen like a Strumpet offers it selfe to all that will but pay the price, being here publikely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, and euery where vendible, as well at this day as in former times, and beares this shamelesse Title, <hi>The Taxe, or the Rates of the Chamber, and Chancerie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall.</hi> A Booke, wherein (if thou couldest not) thou mightst learne to sinne; and hee that is so minded, may come to the knowledge of more wickednesse, then was yet euer discouered in all the Summists, and Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Vices that bee in the World: And for all those sinnes, there is offered, to all that will pay for it, Absolution for what they haue done; and to many Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense for what they shall doe. I spare to name them, for, the very names of some of them are enough to make an honest heart to tremble. It's more then maruell, that in the time of this dangerous <hi>Scisme,</hi> when so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fall dayly from the Church, so shamefull a Booke should not bee suppressed, which is no better then a very Index pointing men the way to the most foule and hatefull sinnes: so as, I am perswaded there was neuer set out in <hi>Germany, Switzerland,</hi> nor among any of our enemies that bee fallen from vs, any Booke that euer bred more scandall, or did more hurt to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church.</p>
                  <p>And yet so farre is it from being supprest at <hi>Rome,</hi> by our great States-men there, as contrariwise the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censes,
<pb facs="4"/> and impunities for these abominations, are for the most part daily renewed, and confirmed in the Commissions, and faculties of those Nuncious, or Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats that be sent from thence to vs, who haue power not onely to legitimate all kinde of Bastards, of neuer so damnable copulations, and to giue leaue euen for Adulterers to marry, but to dispence euen with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, Symony, Periury, Robbery, Schisme, Heresie, and not onely to absolue them from the Sinne, but to enable them to be capable of benefices, dignities, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours: nay, to absolue Murderers, (&amp; one book excepts not so much as the villaine that shall wilfully kill his owne Father or Mother, Wife or Childe) nay keepers of Whores, violaters of Virgins, Adulterers, Incestu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous euen in the neerest bloud, nay sinnes against Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not to be named, euen with beasts, &amp;c. <hi>O Rome, blush at these abominations,</hi> and cease for shame to prostitute thy selfe thus in the sight of friends, and enemies, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </body>
      </floatingText>
   </q>
   <p>And thus writes not <hi>Luther,</hi> nor <hi>Caluin</hi> those Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heretiques, nor male-contented <hi>Erasmus,</hi> (for so they stile them) nor any of ours, but <hi>Espencaeus</hi> a <hi>Sorbonist,</hi> a Papist, and euery way their owne, saue onely for his honesty: Of whom, not onely <hi>Thuanus Bechelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and other indifferent, and moderate: But euen <hi>Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuine</hi> the Iesuite, and <hi>Genebrard</hi> that rough and bitter Papist, giues most honourable testimony. And lest it might be obiected that this <hi>Espencaeus,</hi> being a <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> spake partially, as one infected with the old iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie, or emulation that hath bin betwixt <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Rome:</hi> That therefore the indifferent Reader, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires to sway on no side, but to be informed in the truth, may see our faire dealing, and sincere intention to doe right; take another testimony touching this booke, out of <hi>Guicciardine</hi> an <hi>Jtalian,</hi> nay a <hi>Florentine,</hi> euen the Country-man of that <hi>Pope</hi> in whose time this
<pb facs="5"/> Booke was written: A learned and iudicious Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and one held on all sides as indifferent, and free from passion, or partiality, as any Writer of these later ages, whose words are as followeth:</p>
   <q>
      <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
         <body>
            <div type="text">
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Guicciard. hist. lib. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>LEo Papa x. à natura, ocio &amp; voluptatibus deditus, tunc verò etiam ob nimiam Licentiam, potentiamque supra modum, à negotijs alienus, musicis, ac scurris totum diem, audiendis immersus, &amp; praeter decorū voluptatibus deditus à bellis, penitus alienus esse debere videbatur: huc accedebat quod, cum in eius animo tanta magnificentia &amp; splendor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esset, vt vel in quonis qui longissima successione, à poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimis Regibus oriundus esset summa admiratione digna fuisset: Neque in sumptibus muneribusue dandis modum delectumue seruaret, non modo breuissimo temporis spatio, gazam ab Iulio cumulatam, incredibili profusione exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serat, verum etiam cum ex ijs quae in curia expediuntur, multisque nouis &amp; ad pecuniam emungendam excogitatis, ingentem auri copiam cumulâsset, adeo profuisse sumptus fecerat, vt subinde nouas rationes quibus immanes illos sumptus, quos non modo continenter faciebat, verum etiam augebat, sustinere posset, excogitare cogeretur, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <head>The same in English.</head>
                  <p>POpe <hi>Leo</hi> the x. beeing giuen by nature to ease and pleasure, and much more by the great licentious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse that beares sway in the Papacy, would trouble himselfe with no businesse, but spend the whole day in musicke, mirth, sports and pastimes, amongst witty fellowes, and ieasters, and beyond all <hi>decorum</hi> was drencht and drowned in voluptuousnesse: And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, was of so stately a minde and carriage, and so magnificent in all things, as though hee had descended by many degrees, from the greatest and most illustrious
<pb facs="5"/> Kings of Europe: Neyther kept hee any measure, nor practized any discretion in his gifts and bounties: so as in short time hee had not onely foolishly exhausted, and shamefully wasted the great treasures his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessour <hi>Iulius</hi> left him, but also gathered great summes, by all the businesses expedited in the Court of Rome. Nor contented with the old, hee had them who day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuized him new trickes, and wayes to bring in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Insomuch, as in his time an incredible masse of Gold was gathered, or rather scraped vp, yet was all this too little, for money came not in so fast as hee found vents and meanes to spend it, so as, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his charge (and satisfie his new pleasures and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions of expence which hee also daily deuised) hee was euen forced still to excogitate, and by fit instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to finde out new wayes and meanes to bring in money into his alwayes filling, and yet alwayes emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Coffers. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </body>
      </floatingText>
   </q>
   <p>Now consider (good Reader) who these two witnesses were, consider their Nations, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, consider their places and professions, and weigh well their words, and then wee dare put this issue to tryall, to a Iury of any indifferent men in the World, whether this Booke be counterfeit by vs, or rather the Popes owne brood, euen the true and vndoubted childe if not of the Church, yet of the Court of Rome. And if eyther trauellers may be trusted, or bookes beleeued that speake and write of the Pope and Court of Rome, it so kindely shewes the House it came of, as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for shame deny it, or so much as doubt it to bee their owne: for neuer was Bastard more like the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than this resembles the manners, disposition, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, and complection of the Court of Rome. And this (good Reader) is the first thing I desire to cleare to thy vnderstanding, before thou take in hand the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Booke.</p>
   <p>Another matter whereof I would informe the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb facs="6"/> is touching the meaning of those offices or <hi>Courts</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> which are so often mentioned in this Booke: Namely, the <hi>Chauncery,</hi> the <hi>Chamber,</hi> the <hi>Penitentiary,</hi> and the <hi>Datary.</hi> The <hi>Chauncery,</hi> is the highest office in the Popes Court,<note place="margin">The Popes Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor.</note> and his <hi>Ʋice-chancellor</hi> is the first, and immediate officer next himself, and is called <hi>Vice-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor,</hi> not <hi>Chācellor,</hi> because by the <hi>Popes</hi> presumptuous <hi>Law, God</hi> and hee, haue but one, and the same <hi>Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or <hi>Chancery,</hi> whereof (say they) only the <hi>Pope</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe is <hi>Chancellor;</hi> And because they make him <hi>Gods Chancellor,</hi> therefore the other is but his <hi>Ʋice-chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor.</hi> This office, as it is of supreme authority, so it is of mighty reuenewes, but was of much more, when <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and other <hi>Nations,</hi> were vnder the <hi>Popes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, for his Writ (for matters <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi>) went as familiarly into euery Nation as our <hi>Chancery</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> sends into euery Shire. Vnder him are many great officers, &amp; vnder them an incredible number of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our officers, who are all fed, and maintayned by the multitude of <hi>suites,</hi> and <hi>Suitors</hi> from all parts of the Popish world, who come thither like foolish wandring Sheepe, and leaue their fleeces behinde them there.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The Popes Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine.</note>The next <hi>Officer</hi> in the <hi>Romish Court,</hi> is his <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> whose proper duety is, to looke to the <hi>Popes Reuenew,</hi> both for his constant Rents, and his casuall commings in: and is called <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall Chamber,</hi> or a <hi>Chamber</hi> in the Popes Palace, where that Court is kept, and in our <hi>English,</hi> it may not vnfitly be called, the <hi>Popes Chequer,</hi> or his <hi>Chequer Chamber:</hi> This is also daily filled with suiters, for as their <hi>Writs,</hi> or <hi>Letters,</hi> are dispatcht in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> so their <hi>sines,</hi> and other <hi>Rates,</hi> or <hi>payments</hi> they be <hi>taxed</hi> at, are payd into this <hi>Chamber;</hi> and there bee also many things expedited in this <hi>Court,</hi> which come not in the <hi>Chancery;</hi> for they haue at <hi>Rome mille nocendi artes:</hi> vnsearchable deuices to bring in money, and
<pb facs="6"/> wayes past finding out. Vnder him, first, the <hi>Popes Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curator generall,</hi> then the <hi>Receiuer generall,</hi> the <hi>Auditor</hi> of the <hi>Chamber,</hi> the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Apostolicall Secretaries,</hi> who dispatch the <hi>affaires</hi> of <hi>Kings, Princes, Common-wealths, free Atates Cities, Cardinalls</hi> that be absent, and <hi>Bishops:</hi> Here be also the <hi>Summists,</hi> the <hi>Protonotaries,</hi> called of old time, <hi>Regionaries of the seuen Regions,</hi> or <hi>ancient Parishes of Rome,</hi> whereunto they were assig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but now they be without number. These goe in habit little differing from <hi>Cardinalls.</hi> Then follow the <hi>Auditors of the Wheele,</hi> so called, for that they sit round, and of old time had power to heare, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine onely, but now haue to determine also: All these being vnder the <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> are <hi>mighty Offices,</hi> and haue infinite number of other subordinate to them; for from this <hi>Court,</hi> or some branches of it, proceed all those <hi>writs</hi> that are called <hi>the Popes Brenes,</hi> which past of old time vnder <hi>Leade,</hi> but now of late <hi>sub annulo piscatoris:</hi> Hereto also belong <hi>Faculties, Pardons, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensations, Licences, Confirmations, Jndulgences, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations, Exemptions, Donations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dations, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cutsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to <hi>benefices,</hi> and a <hi>million</hi> more, all hookes &amp; crooks to worke in money.</p>
   <p>The next great <hi>office</hi> is the <hi>Penitentiary</hi> so called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is the <hi>Court</hi> of the <hi>Penitents,</hi> and properly this is, or should be the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Conscience</hi> (if there bee any such thing as <hi>Conscience</hi> left in <hi>Rome:</hi> For the <hi>Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> there, is properly their <hi>Court of Iustice,</hi> but <hi>cases</hi> of <hi>Conscience</hi> belong to the <hi>Penitentiary,</hi> where sinners and offendors, of tender troubled Consciences, should, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Confession, and discouery of their hearts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue direction and consolation. This was certainely of old an excellent Institution, and of most necessary vse in the Church, had it beene preserued in the ancient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity: but the old, holy, and spirituall vse thereof, as all other parts, and poynts of true holinesse, was long
<pb facs="7"/> agoe lost at <hi>Rome,</hi> and for many ages hath been wholly peruerted to the ensnaring, &amp; seducing of simple soules, to the distracting &amp; troubling of tender Consciences, to the discouering of the secret intentions of <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>great Persons,</hi> and to the raking in of <hi>mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> of <hi>money</hi> into the <hi>Popes coffers:</hi> so as indeed this that should be the best, is now the worst; and that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which was originally erected for the increase of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, deuotion and true holinesse, is now turned into one of the <hi>chiefe Stratagems,</hi> and one of the principall pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of prophane and carnall policy that was yet euer practised in any State of the world. <hi>The Grand Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiary is the Pope himselfe,</hi> and so indeed he ought to be, if he knew himselfe, and so he was of old time, whilest any goodnesse and honesty remained amongst them: But of later times, since they grew to be so great in the world, and so poore in grace, he hath designed that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto some <hi>Cardinall,</hi> whom they call the <hi>Maior Penitentiarius,</hi> vnto whom, and whose Court, there is resort of all sorts of people, to whom lye Appeales from all places, in all cases of Conscience, and from whom there is none: And no maruell though he euer conferre this place vpon a <hi>prime Cardinall,</hi> and one of his owne kindred, and chiefe Minions, for it is of mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and profit.</p>
   <p>Vnder this great <hi>Penitentiary,</hi> are many subordinate, as first, his <hi>Ʋicar generall,</hi> that sits in St. <hi>Peters Church</hi> in the <hi>Ʋaticane:</hi> The next in St. <hi>Iohns Church in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane:</hi> Another in St. <hi>Maries,</hi> and so in all the 7. <hi>great Churches of Rome,</hi> and vnder them they haue their <hi>Ʋi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars</hi> and <hi>Deputies</hi> in all the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and al the <hi>Confessors</hi> that be in euery Parish ouer all the Popish world. The <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> of the <hi>grand Penitentiary,</hi> hath beside many other great <hi>Officers,</hi> no fewer than foure and twenty <hi>Proctors</hi> for the expediting of <hi>causes,</hi> and bringing in of money the more <hi>artificially,</hi> which
<pb facs="7"/> is now the high and Soueraigne end of all the <hi>policies,</hi> practices, and <hi>Religion</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These three great Officers be alwayes Cardinalls.</p>
   <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> and last of the <hi>Offices</hi> mentioned in this Booke, is the <hi>Datary,</hi> touching which I confesse I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not giue the <hi>Reader</hi> so good light as in the former, there being but rare mention made thereof among the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of these things; so as it seems this is one of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>mysteries</hi> of their <hi>State.</hi> Its probably thought he is as it were the <hi>Popes Almoner,</hi> as the word <hi>Datarie</hi> may seeme to import. Others thinke that the <hi>Actiuo signification</hi> of giuing to the Pope, which happely it bore of old, is of late times turned into the <hi>Passiue,</hi> and signifies now the bearer of his priuy Purse. But by that that is often mentioned in this booke, if this <hi>Officer</hi> be his <hi>Almoner,</hi> it were more credit for him to giue his <hi>Almes</hi> out of better gotten goods; and if hee be the bearer of his priuy Purse, it is a shame for him to fill it by such meanes: for, of the foulest and most exorbitant Dispensations, it is said, that besides the other Fees, hee must in such or such a case compound also with the <hi>Datary.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For the Conclusion, thus much for thy satisfaction (good Reader) who neyther hast been, nor intendest to goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> nor canst informe thy selfe by <hi>Reading:</hi> For the <hi>learned,</hi> they may, as cheap as I, know this and more, out of the <hi>Authors</hi> that haue written hereof, as namely:</p>
   <list>
      <item>Syntag. Juris Petri Gregorij. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>15.</hi> cap. <hi>42.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Gomerius in Prooem. ad reg. Cancell.</item>
      <item>Octau. Ʋostrius de Aula Rom. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Cassanci. Catall. gloriae mundi. part. <hi>4.</hi> consid. <hi>29.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Gomerius de officialibus Rom. Curiae.</item>
      <item>Moscouius de Maiest. militantis Ecclesiae.</item>
      <item>Rebuffus. Praxis beneficiorum.</item>
      <item>Nauarri Consil. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> de praeb. &amp; alibi.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>