<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MY much Honoured Lord, RAFE, Lord EVRE, Lord President in these parts: all true Honour, with increase.</title>
           <author>Horn, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121133_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03694</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13821</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121133</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MY much Honoured Lord, RAFE, Lord EVRE, Lord President in these parts: all true Honour, with increase.</title>
                 <author>Horn, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian gouernour, in the common-wealth, and priuate families : described by Dauid, in his 101. Psalme. Guiding all men in a right course to heauen. Herewith also a part of the parable of the lost sonne. Luke 15. Both expounded and opened by Robert Horn. With the doctrines and vses thence arising. The more particular contents see on the page following</title>
                 <author>Horne, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>432 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MY much Honoured Lord, RAFE, Lord EVRE, Lord President in these parts: all true Honour, with increase.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian Lord:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing a great desire, in my great want of meanes, to <hi>expresse my selfe</hi> by some <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie</hi> for <hi>your Honors good thoughts</hi> of <hi>mee,</hi> in words of vndeserued commendation: the rather because one Countrie <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> in
<pb facs="3"/>
which <hi>you</hi> were <hi>borne Noble,</hi> and one Countrey now containes <hi>vs,</hi> in which <hi>you gouerne</hi> with <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>loue</hi>: I light vpon certaine <hi>briefes</hi> of <hi>Lectures</hi> deliuered by <hi>me,</hi> vpon a very worthy <hi>Psalme,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a worthy <hi>Audience, your Honours</hi> immediate <hi>honourable Predecessour,</hi> and <hi>others, his</hi> reuerend and graue <hi>associates</hi> then in place. A <hi>Psalme</hi> made by a <hi>King,</hi> and for <hi>Kings,</hi> which (also) may indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, serue as a <hi>Table</hi> of direction for all <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Policies,</hi> vnder that which is <hi>Kingly.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore in the <hi>mirrour</hi> of this <hi>Psalme,</hi> and example of <hi>him</hi> who made it, as in a true <hi>Glasse,</hi> your <hi>Honour</hi> may <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold clearely</hi> the right and liuely <hi>image</hi> and <hi>face</hi> of a Christian Gouernour and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement. And, though no <hi>Psalme,</hi> as it were <hi>pearle,</hi> in this Booke of <hi>Psalmes,</hi> or <hi>boxe</hi> of <hi>pearles</hi> can iustly displease: yet, as in the estimation of <hi>precious things</hi> That may please <hi>vs</hi> for one vse, for which another (being to no such vse) will not please so well, albeit <hi>precious</hi> for the <hi>vse</hi> it hath; so it is in all these excellent <hi>Psalmes,</hi> the Iewels of <hi>Gods Church.</hi> For, for some purposes, one
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Psalme</hi> may be fitter, that is, more excellent then another, though all be excellent and do <hi>edifie</hi> greatly in their seuerall kindes. And indeed, as when the <hi>Prophet</hi> gaue <hi>his</hi> mind to the <hi>preparing</hi> of those things that might serue for the <hi>building</hi> of the materiall <hi>temple, He</hi> disposed in <hi>his</hi> minde to what <hi>vse</hi> this or that <hi>Iewell</hi> or <hi>waight</hi> of <hi>gold</hi> and <hi>siluer,</hi> and a number of other things should be applied: so for these <hi>Psalmes</hi> (most of which were penned by this sweet <hi>singer of Israel</hi>) the Prophet hauing <hi>sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> and layd them <hi>vp,</hi> as the <hi>ornaments</hi> of <hi>Gods Church,</hi> in <hi>his Sanctuary,</hi> for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vse, and as <hi>precious stuffe</hi> for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a spirituall <hi>Temple to God; He</hi> had great consideration whereto each <hi>Psalm</hi> should serue. Wherefore some <hi>he</hi> made for the <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> chiefly, some (indifferently) for all dayes and places: some for a remembrance of the generall, some for a more speciall remembrance of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar workes of God to <hi>his Church:</hi> some for meditation and practise, some for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Prayer: some for comforts, some for threatnings: some for confession of sinnes, some of conuersion from sinne; all
<pb facs="4"/>
which <hi>hee</hi> consecrated as <hi>Tables</hi> of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall thankefulnesse to <hi>GOD</hi> in his <hi>House,</hi> better then the three hundred shields and two hundreth targets that <hi>Salomon</hi> put in <hi>his house</hi> at <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> though they were all of beaten gold, <hi>1 King. 10.16.17.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, as <hi>Gods wisedome</hi> by <hi>Dauid</hi> thus sorted and disposed these <hi>holy Songs,</hi> that they might be sutable to all the occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and necessities of the <hi>Church</hi> for euer: so in more speciall manner, the same <hi>wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of GOD</hi> by <hi>him,</hi> did indite this <hi>Psalme</hi> for <hi>instruction,</hi> that it might teach euen <hi>Kings,</hi> and all vnder <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> how to <hi>please</hi> and <hi>serue</hi> God in those <hi>high places,</hi> and that <hi>they</hi> might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, and not forget that religious <hi>seruices</hi> belong to the <hi>Noblest</hi> as well as to the <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest,</hi> and in reason, rather to <hi>great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> then to common <hi>men.</hi> For, who should doe most worke, but <hi>hee</hi> that receiueth most <hi>wages?</hi> and who should <hi>pay</hi> the greatest <hi>rent,</hi> but <hi>hee</hi> that hath the largest <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This <hi>Psalme</hi> therefore (my Honoured Lord) deserueth right well your best <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> both for the <hi>contemplatiue</hi> vse of it,
<pb facs="4"/>
and <hi>your practicall</hi> in <hi>your Familie,</hi> and the <hi>Prouince.</hi> It is Gods <hi>Psalme,</hi> or charge to <hi>you,</hi> and such as <hi>you</hi> are, by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> But because the <hi>Text</hi> of it (short as it is) is like to <hi>Tapestrie,</hi> which (being <hi>foulded vp</hi>) sheweth but a part of that which is <hi>wrought,</hi> and (being <hi>laid open</hi>) sheweth plainely to the <hi>eye</hi> all the <hi>worke</hi> that is in it: therefore I, though most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy) haue presumed thus to <hi>vnfolde</hi> this <hi>Tapestrie</hi> of the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> in so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a <hi>Psalme,</hi> and to hang vp the <hi>cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of it in a very meane <hi>Exposition,</hi> giuen vnto it by my weake iudgement and gifts, which in <hi>humblest good-will,</hi> out of <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>dutie,</hi> I <hi>humbly</hi> tender into <hi>your Lordships</hi> owne <hi>hands,</hi> knowing the <hi>same</hi> to be willing, and ready, graciously to pardon, and beare with things somewhat meanely <hi>done,</hi> but with a well-meaning heart; and to respect, not so much the <hi>gift,</hi> as the <hi>good-will</hi> of the <hi>giuer,</hi> in matters of this <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Howsoeuer I haue dealt, the <hi>Psalme</hi> is the same that euer it was: which if I haue so <hi>opened,</hi> that is, so to the life of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> words, and so <hi>vnfolded,</hi> that your
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Honour</hi> may <hi>discerne</hi> of all the pieces and sundry <hi>workes</hi> and matters <hi>contained</hi> in it, as in a <hi>piece</hi> of <hi>Tapestrie</hi> opened <hi>you</hi> may: I humbly thanke <hi>God,</hi> and wish the <hi>fruit</hi> of it in <hi>your Lordships heart</hi>; and, from so good a <hi>treasurie</hi> in the places of your <hi>Honours</hi> publike and priuate <hi>emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to fructisie there: <hi>that is,</hi> turne it into a Prayer; that <hi>you</hi> may follow in the steppes of <hi>Dauids</hi> obedience to it; doing as <hi>hee</hi> did.</p>
   <p>Often <hi>pray this Psalme to God</hi> (my good Lord:) let it bee <hi>your meditation,</hi> and <hi>counsellour</hi> in all <hi>your</hi> high affaires, and when <hi>you</hi> would <hi>stirre</hi> the <hi>wheeles</hi> of all good graces in <hi>you</hi> for some holy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>dispensation</hi> of <hi>Iustice</hi> in the same, vse it. Lastly, and for <hi>my selfe,</hi> I hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly beseech your <hi>Honour,</hi> fauourably to remit this <hi>trespasse</hi> of my presumption, respecting rather, what I would doe then what is done, and in how homely manner. So, not further to trouble your <hi>Honour:</hi> I pray God hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, that, as <hi>hee</hi> hath <hi>honoured you</hi> with a double <hi>honour</hi> of <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> so <hi>hee</hi> would <hi>accompanie your earthly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> with such abundance of <hi>heauenly</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
graces to goe with the same, that here <hi>you</hi> may <hi>abound</hi> in euery <hi>good worke,</hi> to the <hi>praise of God,</hi> and, in <hi>Heauen,</hi> may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the pure crowne of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and glory, which is laid vp for</hi> you, <hi>and for all who loue and looke for the comming of Iesus Christ,</hi> to whose grace most humbly I commend <hi>your Honour</hi> now and euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>At your Honours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> most humbly <hi>in the Lord.</hi>
         <hi>ROBERT HORN.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>