<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all those that sincerelie loue the Lorde Iesus, and seeke the  estate of his kingdoms, and namelie, in the brethren throughout Englande, VVales, &amp; Ireland: IOHN  know∣ledge,  and  with al other .</title>
           <author>Cotton, Roger</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121983_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19612</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121983</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all those that sincerelie loue the Lorde Iesus, and seeke the  estate of his kingdoms, and namelie, in the brethren throughout Englande, VVales, &amp; Ireland: IOHN  know∣ledge,  and  with al other .</title>
                 <author>Cotton, Roger</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise vvherein is manifestlie proued, that reformation and those that sincerely fauor the same, are vnjustly charged to be enemies, vnto hir Maiestie, and the state : Written both for the clearing of those that stande in that cause: and the stopping of the sclaunderous mouthes of all the enemies thereof</title>
                 <author>Penry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all those that sincerelie loue the Lorde Iesus, and seeke the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> estate of his kingdoms, and namelie, in the brethren throughout Englande, VVales, &amp; Ireland: IOHN <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> with al other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Cluds of England, (beloued in the Lorde) to wit, Peace and prosperity, haue now of a long time to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> all estates among vs for the most part, that in stead of our thankfulnesse vnto God, for his great &amp; vndeserued blessings: they haue caused our land to bring forth most strange effects, vnto the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of the Lords name, the hinderance of his truth, the lykelie ruine of his Church, and the generall griefe and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of all his children. VVe knowe wel enough, what kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the Lord hath generallie shewed vnto our kingdome at such time as we little deserued the same, and what thankfulnesse wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed him again, our practise doth evidentlie testifie.</p>
   <p>It is not yet manie yeares aboue 30. since we were matched, yea,
<note place="margin">King Philips mariage.</note> and ouermatched with strangers, readie daye and night to haue the same crueltie shevved vpon vs, whiche that proude and bloodie nation the Spainyard, doth now the second tyme purpose to execute. But our God deliuered vs from that imminent bondage. The blessing is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred, especiallie seeing the kindenes was then shewed vnto our state, when not onelye the whole kingdome being moste shamefullie fallen from God to the worship of deuils, was ouergrowne with the weeds of Idolatrous poperie and superstition: but euen those plantes graffed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs by the diuels owne hande, were so highly accounted off, that rather thē they should not haue their ful growth in England, they were watered with the blood of the saints of God. Behold here, O England, thy deliueraunce from bondage, in the day wherein thou didst deserue captitutie, and looke for an heauier yoke, if thou continuest to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful. But what do I speake of this outward libertie, seeing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freedome of the soule bestowed vpon vs at the same instant, doth vtterlie obscure this blessing, and make it seeme nothing in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. The Lord therefore, that al the glorie of his kindnes towardes a rebellious nation might indeede be his owne, and that he might justly require the fruit of thankfulnesse at our handes, together with the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of hir right excellent Majestie, brought vnto vs the inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treasure of his Gospell, which to this day he hath continued contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto our deserts. Howe this gospell was at that time, and nowe is receaued among vs, it shalbe partlie declared afterward.</p>
   <p>Since the enjoying thereof (how vnthankfullie soeuer our state hath
<pb facs="3"/>entertayned the same) it is well knowen that in regarde of outwarde peace and prosperitie, this land hath bene in our dayes the miracle of al the kingdomes in the earth. For the Lord hath from heauen comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the blessing of outward plentie to be with vs in al that we haue set our handes vnto:
<note place="margin">Deu. 28.11.12</note> and as for our peace, it hath beene such as other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue bene glad to borrow the same from vs, which also we haue bene able to lend vnto them. And although the Lord to testify his wrath against the abuse of his blessings hath somtimes chastened vs with some taste of famine, and threatned diuers times to take awaye our peace, yet whensoeuer wee haue had but one deare yeare in all our quarters, hee fullie recompensed the dearth thereof, with the vnexpected abundance and plentie of the next. And if you look vnto our enemies that haue ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen vp, either at home or abroad to disturbe our quietnes, they may bee trulie saide to come against vs one waye, and to haue fallen before vs seauen. So that if within the circuite of heauen, you woulde see a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wonderfullie blessed with outward peace and prosperity, Englād must be the pattern thereof. And I woulde to God that this were the onelie president that England doth afforde vnto vs and our posterities? But alas, it is far other wise. For as the Lords blessings haue bene mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied vpon vs, so hath our vnthankfulnesse augmented it sense out of measure. Consider the state of religiō at this day, &amp; see what a grateful cuntrie Englande hath bene vnto hir God. The Lord by the mouthes of his seruantes, and by his fore-named blessings, hath these 31. yeares besought and earnestly intreated, yea wooed as it were al estates among vs, to looke vnto their owne soules to day, wrile it is called to day, and to lay a sure hold vpon him while he may be found, by a thorow recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Gospel: together with the ministers thereof: and by shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindenes vnto his desolate house. But what hath England answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? Surelie with an impudent fore-head The hath said: <q>I wil not come neere the holie one.
<note place="margin">Englands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> And as for the building of his house, I will not so much as lift vp a finger towardes that work, nay I wil continue the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations thereof. And if anie man speaketh a worde in the behalfe of this house, or bewaileth the miserie of it: I wil accounte him an enemye to my state. As for the gospel, and the ministeries of it, I haue already receaued al the Gospels, and al the ministeries that I meane to receaue. I haue receaued a reading Gospel, and a reading ministery, a pompous Gospel, and a pompous ministery: a Gospel and a ministery that stren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth the hands of the wicked in his iniquity, a gospel and a ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that will stoupe vnto me and bee at my beek either to speake or to be mute when I shal thinke good. Briefly I haue receaued a gospel &amp; a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie that wil neuer trouble my conscience with the sight of my sinns which is al the gospels and al the ministeries that I meane to receaue: &amp; I wil make a sure hand, that the Lords house it I can chuse, shalbee no otherwayes aedified, than by the handes of suche men, as bring vnto me the foresaid gospel and the foresaid ministery.</q> Loe heere Englands thankfulnes (beloued) foral the mercies and kindnes whiche hir God hath vouchsaued vnto hir. And tell me in thy conscience whether thou thinkest that shee hath rendred according vnto the rewarde bestowed vpon hir,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 32.25</note> who in so great a desolation of Gods service, hath not once
<pb facs="3"/>shewed hir self to be moued with any compassion that way. And I doe apeale vnto thy conscience, whether I haue not trulie set down the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which all estates among vs generallie considered doe beare vnto the Lords pure worship and seruice. In so much as if he shoulde sende some Ieremy to stād in our high wayes, &amp; inquire whatsort of men he could finde within our land, who had in any thankful manner remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Lords goodenes, by regarding his wast and ruinous sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, well hee might meete with some one heere and there, as a cluster of grapes after the vintage, that in some gratefull sort, acknowledged the Lords hand towards vs: but as for the general state either of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy, of the ministerye or of the common people, behelde nothing els, but a multitude of conspirators against God, against his truth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the building of his house, against his Saints and children: and consequentlie against the wealth of their owne soules, and the publike peace and tranquillity of this whole kingdome.
<note place="margin">Our common people.</note> Concerning the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, their profannesse, impiety, contempt of God and his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and their hatred vnto his children, with al other their wickednes, may seeme to deserue some excuse,
<note place="margin">Ier. 5.3.4.</note> because they never as yet had anye meanes to know God aright, for the holy ghost may truly say of them They are poore, they are foolish, for they haue not knowen the way of the Lord, nor the judgements of their God. And therefore what mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell is it, thoughe they have made their faces harder than a stone, and refused to returne.</p>
   <p>But these that would be accounted our Prophetes,
<note place="margin">Our supposed Ministery.</note> and the ministers of the Sanctuary, haue had better meanes to know the wil of their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and therefore just &amp; righteous shal he be, whensoeuer he rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them with the fruites of their owne handes, if they haue broken the yoak: of their obedience, and caste from them the bondes of that carefulnes, whereby it behoued them to binde themselues, that they should not forget the house of their God. VVil you then come vnto them, and see what they are? Alas, you can beholde heere no other sight but a multitude of desperate and forlorne Athiests, that haue put the euil day far from them, and endeuoured to perswade their owne hartes, that gods holy ministery, and the sauing health of mens soules, are matters not to be regarded. You shal finde among this crue, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but a troup of bloody soule murtherers, sacriligious church robbers, and suche as haue made them selues fatte with the bloude of mens soules, and the vtter ruine of the Church. The whole endeuour of which cursed generation, ever since the beginning of hir Maiesties raigne, hath tended no otherway, then to make a sure hand to keepe the church in bondage, that being bound in their handes, it shoulde not dare for feare of being murthered to seeke for liberty. Of these men, contained within the nomber of proud and ambitious prelates, our Lord Archbishops and Bishops, godlesse and murthering Non-resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, profane and ignorant idole shepheards, or dumbe doggs, <q>I will say no more in this place but this.
<note place="margin">Revel. 6.10. Psal. 65.2.</note> How long Lord * just &amp; true doest thou suffer thine inheritance to bee polluted and layd waste, by this vncircumcised generation. O * thou that hearest the prayer, let the supplications which thy children haue made before thee day and night
<pb facs="4"/>(for the removing of this our plague,) be at the length effectuall in thine eares, and with speed thrust these caterpillers as one man out of our Church, and let the memory of them be forgotten in Isean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Sobeit Lord for thy sonne Christs sake.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Now if they who woulde bee accounted the ministers of the holye Sanctuary,
<note place="margin">Magistracy.</note> are found so vnanswerable, both vnto the callings, which they would claime vnto them selues, and also vnto the Lords kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes snewed vnto our Land: it were but folly to demaund what thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes our Magistrats and such as deale in the execusion of iustice, haue repayed vnto their God. For they hauing suffered themselues, to bee led by the forenamed blinde guides must needs stumble at that stone, which is offensiue vnto their leaders. And therefore hande in hande, haue our magistracye and ministerye walked in the contempt of true Religion. And the one of these hauing vncircumcised eares, haue made that the other cannot hearken, and vnto both the word of the Lorde, (in which they haue no delight) is made a reproche: Insomuch as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong those who deale in the cause of justice, there are founde wicked persons,
<note place="margin">Ier. 5.26.27.</note> as the prophete saieth, even wicked lawyers and judges (who seeme to know of no other God, but their owne gaine,) that lay waite for the bloud of Gods saints, as hee that setteth snares, and mark whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can heare of any that goe further in the cause of God, than the corruption of our state doth permit. And if they finde any such, they know how to wrest against them, a clawse of some statute, contrarye not onely to the meaning thereof, but even contrary vnto all justice &amp; aequity, yea common reason it selfe, and the very groundes of al good Lawes, and statutes. So that it is now growne, and hath beene of a long time a common practise of these godles men, to make of the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes ordained for the maintenance of Religion and common quietnes a pit wherein to catch the peaceable of the land. The common endite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the Lords true and faithful ministers for matters of trifles, as the omission of the surplise, Churching of women, Crosse in baptism &amp;c. doeth manifestlye witnes the iniquity of these Atheistes. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by though as the Prophet also complaineth they are become great, waxē rich, and growen into fauor with our counsel, and such as beare chiefe authority vnder hir Maiesty: yet let them be assured they procure vnto their soules, swift and heauie damnation, without speedye &amp; earneste repentance. And because our counsaile may be truly said to delight in this iniury and violent oppression of Gods saincts and ministers, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whensoever the Lord shal come to search for the sinnes of Englād with lights,
<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> as Zephaniah sayth, he wil surely evisite our counsaile with an heauy plague. Because vndoubtedly they are frozē in their dregs, &amp; perswade their owne hartes that the Lord wil do neither good nor evil in the defence of his messengers and children. And then shal they feele what it is to winke at (muche more to procure) the oppression of the Churche of Christe. I wil not in this place charge our counsel with that which followeth in Ieremy,
<note place="margin">Ier. 5.28.</note> vpon the place before aledged, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they execute no judgement, no not the judgement of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles. But this I will say, that they cannot possibly deale truly in the matter of justice betweene man and man, inso muche as they bend al
<pb facs="4"/>their forces to beceaue Christ Iesus of that right, which he hath to the governement of his Church.
<note place="margin">Their Honors.</note> The which vngodly and wicked course as they haue held on ever since the beginning of hir Maiesties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, so at this day they haue taken greater boldne, and growen more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious against the Lord and his cause then ever they were. Insomuch as their Honors in token of their thankfulnes to him, that hath exalted them, dare now charge the cause of reformation to be an enemy vnto our state, and such as fauour the same, to be vnquiet and factious men disturbers of the common peace and quietnes, and sowers of sedition among the subiects. This euil dealing of their Honors with the Lords truth, and vs that profes the same within England, haue enforced me to take some paines in the writing of this treatise. The whiche in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of mine owne weakenesse, and the waight of the matter, I would haue left most willingly, vnto the handling of some that had beene of greater guiftes than my self, it the cause being more depelye charged with the former crimes in my person, then in any other that I can hear off at this present, did not require my weak labours and endeuours for the clearing of the same, from so godlesse and vntrue an accusation.</p>
   <p>For the farther vnderstanidng of this particular occasion mouing me to write, thou art to vnderstand (beloued in the Lord) that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in these fewe moneths, a warrant vnder six counsellors hands, hath beene given out from their Honors, and sent by publick messengers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al such places of the Land, as ther was any lykelihood of mine abode. The effect whereof was this.
<note place="margin">So Amasiah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ew Amos to be a traytor.</note>
      <q>That if men haue not hitherto knowne so much, their Honors whose names were hereunto adioined: doe as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure them of their owne knowledge, that one Iohn Penry, is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the state, and if they haue not taken him for such heretofore, they should now take knowledge and information thereof from them, &amp; so henceforth account of him. In which regarde they should be so farre from aiding, consorting, or releuing of him, that if they can by anye meanes apprehend or lay hould of him, they shal therein do her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie good service.</q>
   </p>
   <p>The names of their Honors, who haue by these letters proclaimed themselues to be of their nomber that shal lend their shoulders to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the kingdome of darknes, I doe for the reverence whiche I owe vnto hir Maiesties government conceale, saue only Iohn Cant. (as he writeth himself) whome both in respecte of his Antichristian Prelacve ouer Gods Church, and for the notable hatred which he hath euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed towardes the Lord and his truth, I thinke one of the dishe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablest creatures vnder he auen, and accordingly doe account of him. Desiring the Lord, if it be his wil, to conuert both him and al other the detected enemies of Sion, that their soules may be saued: or if he hath appointed them to damnation, and meaneth not otherwise to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by them, speedelye to disburden the earthe of suche reprobate cast-awayes.</p>
   <p>But to returne again vnto our purpose, if the accusation wherwith I am vniustly charged in the former warrant, reached no farther then my owne person, it were my dutye in regarde of the quietnes of our state, to put it vp: But seing that it doth not touch me at al, any further then
<pb facs="5"/>I haue bene an instrument to promote the cause of Christs governmēt and wholly striketh at that truth, in the defence whereof it pleased the Lord to vse my weake and polluted hands: I do make it knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde. Firste that I am accounted an enemye vnto our state, for no other suspition and colour, but onely because I haue by publicke writing, laboured to defend and induce in our churche, that vniforme order of church regiment, which our Sauiour Christ hath ordained in his word, to continue perpetually therein: and also haue endeuored to seek the vtter ruine and ouerthrow of that wicked hierarchye of lorde Bishops, together with whatsoever corruption dependeth therevpon. Nowe that I cannot bee charged of enmitye to our state, for any other cause than this which I haue expressed: I make it clear, in that my brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp hauing bene al the dayes of my life at my studies, I never as yet delt in any cause more or lesse, that any wayes concerneth the civil state and government. And as for attempting any thing against hir maiesties person, I know the diuel himself dares not be so shameles as to intende any accusation against me in that point. The case then being thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest and cleare, that I am thought an enemye to the state, not for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling with any civill action, but only for seeking the wealthe of Sion. I do in the second place make it known by this present treatise, that the sincere handling of this cause is so far from being an enemye vnto our state: that they do notably detect their impiety against God, and their enmity to the kingdom of his sonne Christ,
<note place="margin">Our persecuters are enemies to the state of Christs king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> whosoever they be that dare presume to burden, either the cause or the sincere professors thereof, with so palpable and manifest a sclaunder, And as for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, that heerein they offer vnto hir Maiestye, who woulde by these sclaunders enforce hir to lay down hir peaceable scepter, and to take vp a bloody sword against hir best subiects: our bloud (though they never haue power to spill it) which they thirst after, shal in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment testify the same to their condemnation, except they repent. And hir Maiesty, if shee giue eare vnto such counsellors is to feare, leaste in the Lords just judgement the day maye come vpon hir and hir Lande, (which in thy mercies Lord remoue far from hir) wherein she shal full bitterly lament and bewaile,
<note place="margin">Enemies to hir Maiesty.</note> that in time she tooke not greater tryall of our loyaity, who now are reckened within the nomber of hir moste dangerous subiects, So that the iniury by the former vniust accusatiō, offered vnto Gods cause and vs his people, stryketh also at hir Maiessies owne estate And the Lord vouchafe hir an harte to consider thereof, before it bee too late. For assuredly those that are our enemies for the profession of the truth, cannot be hir sure fiends, whatsoever they may pretend.</p>
   <p>And because I see that we be fallen into those times, wherein Sathan worketh the defacing of the waye of truthe, and supporteth his owne kingdome by instrumentes of no meane countenance: and also per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that base man beginneth to take strength vnto himselfe againste his maker: I haue purposely framed my selfe to make it knowne vnto Sathan and his complices that all their might and power in oppugning vs for this cause is spent in vaine. For although the cause bee stood vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by weake and sinful men, if respect bee had to that which wee are in
<pb facs="5"/>ourselues, I yet let man know that in the strength of our God, we are so far from being dismayed with the wisedom, countenance, or power of whatsoeuer is made of flesh, that for mine owne part, I cannot suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently wonder, that any creature dares be so bold, as to proclaime war against vs for this cause. And therefore whatsoever enemies the Lorde bath raised vp against me (a contemptible worme,) for the maintenāce of his truth, be they noble or vnnoble, counsellors or inferiour men, I am so far from fearing their power, that the more I see them rage, the greater strength I see reached vnto me by the Lords free mercies to stand to that truth, which they raue against. And by how much the more I see them banded against the sonne of God, by so muche the greater hope do I conceaue, that the case wherein I stand, shal get the vpper hande over them, whether they wil or not. I beleeue, and therefore I am forced to speak these things. In the vttering whereof, as I thank my God, I haue a feeling of mine own great wants and imperfections: so I am not with out some comfortable assurance of his hand with me in this cause, to seale whatsoever truth I shal vtter heerin, according to his word. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect wherof, I do warne and admonish those counsellors with whom and against whome, especially I deale in this treatise, to repent them of their great insolency, whereby they haue bene puffed vp with Senacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib to magnifie and oppose themselues against the cause and people of the Lord of Hostes:
<note place="margin">2. Chron. 32.19. Zeph. 2.8.9 10.</note> as against the religion and people of some of the gods of the earth. Otherwayes they are to feare, least the Lord hauing raysed vp many of them, out of meane places into the throne of justice, meaneth to shew his power and great name, by making them examples of his feareful wrath as he did Pharaoh, who wrought his owne ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw as the * text expresly noteth:
<note place="margin">Exod. 9.17.</note> by exalting him self against the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of the Lord. For assuredly the Lord wil not forget his churche for ever, but at the * appointed time,
<note place="margin">psal. 75.3.8.11</note> he wil break the horne of the wicked and the righteous shalbe exalted. If men wil wonder that wee being so contemptible in the sight of the world, dare yet be so bold, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole great states and mighty men, and to challenge them of iniustice against the sonne of God and his members, who wil not stick to bragge with Pilate, that they haue power to crucifie Christ,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 19.10.</note> and to absolue him they are to vnderstand, that we know of no power, but from aboue: &amp; therefore of no power, that is able to beare out iniustice and wrong: the hilles of the robbers we grant to be high,
<note place="margin">Iob. 5.3.</note> and vnassaileable in the sight of an eye of flesh: but we haue learned of the holy man, to account the habitation of the wicked to be accursed even when he semeth to be best rooted: for we know that the steppes of his strength shalbee restrained,
<note place="margin">Iob. 18.7.</note> and that his owne counsel shal cast him downe. And as for our selues, we confes that we are but base worms, (and we would to God that we were lower in our own eyes,) such as liue not according vnto outward appearance, because our life is hid with Christ in God.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> But yet least me should take occasiō to persecute vs, because they know not with whom they deale, because they are ignorant, whence wee are, or whether wee intend: seing by our walking they may truly judge vs to be descended of some other race than themselues are, and to look for an other dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place than any we can enjoy here. They are to vnderstand that we
<pb facs="6"/>are borne not of mortal but of immortal seede,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note> by the liuelye worde of God, and that we are the servants of that Lord, who is not ashamed to be called our God.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.16.</note> And we are so far from hunting after the wages of vnrighteousnes with them, that we freely confes our selues to bee but pilgrimes and straungers vpon earth: and therefore travell towardes that heavenly city which our God hath prepared for vs. To be briefe, we are the law full successors of those men, who through faith quenched the violence of fire,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.34, 36</note> escaped the edge of the sword. Of weake, were made strong, who were tryed by mockings and scornings, yea moreover, by bondes and improsonments, who were stoned, hewen a sunder, slaine with the sword, wandered vp and down in sheep skinnes, being desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, afflicted and tormented, and yet in al these distresses were more then conquerers through the power of their God. VVherrwith also we hope to be assisted, whensoever it shal please the Lord to giue our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies leaue to try our pacience. To conclude, we are those vnto whom the Lord made this promise,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13 5.6.</note> I wil not fayle thee, nor forsake thee. So that we may boldly say, the lord is mine helper, neither wil I feare what man can do vnto me.</p>
   <p>If then our counsellers and great men wil not provoke this God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their owne soules, they are to be exhorted before they deale any farther against the procurers of reformation, to betake them vnto their second thoughtes, and acknowledge their temeritye in lifting vp their handes against God and those whome hee accounteth of, as the apple of his owne eye.
<note place="margin">Zachar. 2.</note> For in fighting against vs they labor very strongly we grant, to aggrauat &amp; hasten their owne damnation, but their purposes are they neuer able to effect.</p>
   <p>To come vnto you beloved, for whose strengthening and comforting I haue especially taken paines in this treatise, if God hath called any of you to suffer for this cause, think it an exceding preferment that he hath vouchsaued you to be partakers of the afflictions of the gospel,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.8.</note> and in any case be not dismaied at your trobles. The cause is proued to be such, as for the which you may not onely suffer with a good conscience: but such as in the defence wherof, you may expect for the affistāce of Gods comforting spirit: and such, as wherein al christians are bound to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, when they are thervnto called. I haue also shewed it to be that cause, which is compassed about with a cloude of wi nesses, and made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and bewtiful vnto al christians, with the blood of the holye Martyrs of Christ. The same spirit which assisted them vnto the end, wil not leaue you in any of your temptations. So that by your prayers you seek vnto the Lord for strength,
<note place="margin">Obedience.</note> and be careful to learne obedience by the things which you suffer. As we are taught by his example, who by sufferings was made vnto vs the author of aeternal salvation. Be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humbled vnder the hād of your God,
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.8.9.</note> &amp; know that you stand nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by your owne strength, nor by the goodnes of that cause wherein you suffer:
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.29</note> but onelye by the assistance of his spirite, who requireth a great care in all his children to please him in reverence and feare: for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our God is a consuming fire.</p>
   <p>Concerning such of you as the Lord hath not tryed with any afflictiō for this cause, I beseech you be not ashamed of the chaine of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="6"/>mourne with those that lament for the cause of God. VVhen they are imprisoned, think your selues to be in bondes. And I do es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially and aboue al thinges beseech those that fauor the reformation, to labour more and more in the reforming of themselues and such as be long vnto them. VVe know that considering the season, it is now time to rest from sleep.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.12.</note> For now is our salvation neerer than when we firste beleved. It might haue bene something tollerable in times past for a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere professor, to haue an ignorant, an vntaughte, and a vnreformed family: but in this cleare light,
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27. 1. cor. 13.5.13 Zeph. 1.8. Ephes. 5.11. Col. 1.6.</note> and in a profession of so great sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to continew in these sinnes, is altogether vnbeseeming the gospel of Christ. Long haire, great ruffes, laying out of wemens haire, and strange attyre, is a participating with the vnfruitful works of darknesse and a token that the gospel hath not beene faithfully receaued. And therefore let it be no longer tolle rated among the reformed professours of England. Vow and performe with the holye man Dauid,
<note place="margin">Psal. 111.12.</note> that you wil sing mercy and judgement, &amp; walke in the vprightnes of your harts in the midst of your families,
<note place="margin">Iob. 22.22.23.</note> and if you wil make peace indeede with the Lord, follow the counsel of the holye ghost in removing iniquitye far, not only from yourselues, but also from your tabernacles &amp; hou ses. Shew what reformation can do in a whole kingdome, by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise thereof in your owne persons and families. And that wilbe the best argument both to confute the aduersary, and to draw the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to lyke the cause. And as the Lord shal giue vnto any of you accesse either vnto hir Maiesty, or any of their Honors, so be careful to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this truth. VVe haue al of vs (we must confes,) be ne so carelesse and secure in these points, and therefore it is, that by the juste judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, our Bishops are at this day so insolent against the truth. And vnles we labour more strongly to haue these Cananits rooted out we may write vpon it, that they wilbe prickes in our eyes,
<note place="margin">Nomb. 33.55.56.</note> &amp; thornes in our sides, &amp; stil vexe vs as they do at this day. VVhere I say that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors should labour strongly, to haue our hierarchy and contemptible Idoles rooted out of our Church, my meaning is not that any priuate strength should so much as lift vp a hand, muche lesse vse any violence against these caterpillers: but I meane that we should more vehemēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labour with the Lord by prayers, and by the reforming ourselues &amp; our families, and deale earnestly with hir Maiesty &amp; their Honors that our cause may be aequally heard.</p>
   <p>My meaning in the former point I thought needful to expresse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I know what sclanders would otherwise be raised against me, to the hurt of the cause by those that are enemies therevnto: whose mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (I doubte not) will shortlye appeare vnto all men. And I trust in the Lord, that he wil one day giue hir Maiesty a descerning ey, to judge aright between them and vs, and then shal it appeare, whether we or they do seek the peace and quietnes of hir kingdome. In the meane time we wil content our selues with the eye of our God. Yet one thing I would wish to be considered of by hir right excellent Maiesty, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whether it be not an inconvenient season when our fortaine enemies are at the dores, publikly to traduce hir beste and most trusty snbiects as enemies to hir state. For if the Spainyard shal heare, that (besids the
<pb facs="7"/>popish faction) the fore-wardest professors of the gospel in Englande are but her Maiesties half frendes,
<note place="margin">Mark the issue.</note> what wil not the hope of a threfold discorde in our state moue him to attempt? I doe therefore feare that many of the forwardest enemies of reformation, are not the backwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest friends that the King of Spaine hath in England at this day. But least the enemy should deceaue himself, with a golden dreame: I am to make it knowen vnto al Spaniards and Spanish practisers, that we are such enemies vnto Queene Elizabeth,
<note place="margin">The enmity which the favo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers of reforma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion beare vnto hir Maiesty and the state.</note> as we do not onely pray day and nighte for the state of hir Kingdome and hir person: but also wee are readye to stande in the defence of hir royal person and right, to the losse not onely of our goods and blood, but even of our lyues, and that against men and Angels, even al creatures without exception. Thus much my good brethren, I may boldly set down in the name of you al, because I know by what spirit you are guided. And as for your sakes, nexte vnto the defence of the truth, I haue taken this labour in hand: So I do with the Apostle humbly entreat the Lord,
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.31.</note> that my service herein may be acceptable vnto the Saints throughout England, VVales &amp; Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: whome together with my self: and al the Lords elect, I commit vnto his hand, who is able to reserue vs vnto the day of redemption.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>