<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A declaration of the Frontispice.</title>
           <author>C., J.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121250_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121250</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A declaration of the Frontispice.</title>
                 <author>C., J.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the holy vvarre : by Thomas Fuller, B.D. prebendarie of Sarum, late of Sidney Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Fuller, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Williams, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 286, 30 pages, 2 leaves of plates (1 folded), illustrations, map, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>A declaration of the Frontispice.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore you travel to the Holy land,</l>
   <l>Behold a Page that in the front doth stand</l>
   <l>To give you aym and guidance i' the way.</l>
   <l>First Europe bids your observation stay</l>
   <l>Upon a Purse of gold (warres surest nerve)</l>
   <l>Whose every Crosse is interess'd to serve</l>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>'th' Holy warre. The gain (alas!) no more</l>
   <l>Then Crosses <hi>Gules</hi> in stead of Crosses <hi>Or.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>But see the troups, see how they march along:</l>
   <l>Where severall ranks and orders make a throng</l>
   <l>Promiscuously blended; sex and age,</l>
   <l>Nation and language jointly do engage</l>
   <l>Their devout forces to redresse thy woes,</l>
   <l>Ierusalem, ravisht by barbarous foes.</l>
   <l>Peter the Monk, leaving his sullen cell,</l>
   <l>His Beads, and Offices, and every spell</l>
   <l>Of his mysterious zeal, breaks forth at last</l>
   <l>To kindle all the world with fat all blast.</l>
   <l>First Kings proceed; and Captains follow them:</l>
   <l>The helmet waits upon the diadem.</l>
   <l>The next are Prelates; who stray farre from home</l>
   <l>To winne the glorious name of Martyrdome.</l>
   <l>Since all their mild perswasions could not work</l>
   <l>Upon th'obdurate Antichristian Turk,</l>
   <l>They will at length (if nought prevent their plot)</l>
   <l>Confute his Alcoran with sword and shot.</l>
   <l>After those reverend men, whose cloven mitres</l>
   <l>Speak them not warriours so much as writers,</l>
   <l>A bald-pate regiment of Friars comes;</l>
   <l>Whose crowns might serve the army for their drums,</l>
   <l>And give as full a sound, if you'l confesse</l>
   <l>The greatest noise t'arise from emptinesse.</l>
   <l>Then moves the main Battalia, straitly knit</l>
   <l>Into a steadie <hi>Phalanx,</hi> square, but fit</l>
   <l>To spread, or lengthen, or with art to pare</l>
   <l>The corners till the band grow circular</l>
   <l>T'environ th'enemy; briefly, to reduce</l>
   <l>Their various postures unto every use.</l>
   <l>These are the onely <hi>Forces;</hi> all the rest</l>
   <l>Impediments but specious at the best.</l>
   <l>But oh amazement! what is that we see?</l>
   <l>A troup of Ladies in the next degree.</l>
   <l>Each one appears a <hi>Pallas</hi> t' the field</l>
   <l>Dropt newly from <hi>Jove's</hi> brain with spear and shield:</l>
   <l>Or <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs</hi> so long his <hi>Venus</hi> hath possest,</l>
   <l>Courage is stol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n into her tender breast.</l>
   <l>March on, brave <hi>Amazons</hi>: conquest and praise</l>
   <l>Weave you a chaplet of immortall bayes;</l>
   <l>Which you, when Autumn-age shall pluck your hair,</l>
   <l>In stead of costly perriwigs may wear.</l>
   <l>March on: For the shrill trumpet and the fife,</l>
   <l>Your tongues may serve; then to secure your life</l>
   <l>You need no weapons, every face and eye</l>
   <l>Carrieth sufficient artillerie.</l>
   <l>A slender company doth next succeed:</l>
   <l>Call it the <hi>Infantrie</hi>; 'tis so indeed.</l>
   <l>As if the driving of the Turks away</l>
   <l>From Christian cities, were but childrens play.</l>
   <l>The last in this Religious army crawls</l>
   <l>A band collected out of Hospitals</l>
   <l>And Spittles. One would think this piteous sight</l>
   <l>Did rather come from warre then go to fight.</l>
   <l>Their commendation's this, How-e're the day</l>
   <l>Shall chance to prove, they'l hardly run away.</l>
   <l>This is the totall muster. Let the book</l>
   <l>Tell their atchievements: Mean time as you look</l>
   <l>Vpon this Frontispice, you'l plainly see</l>
   <l>Their dismall end and sad Catastrophe.</l>
   <l>Th'incensed Angel with his flaming blade</l>
   <l>Great slaughter of perfidious souls hath made.</l>
   <l>To teach us truth and justice, see how God</l>
   <l>Scourges their falshood with a fiery rod.</l>
   <l>Then the grand Signor his proud fauchion stretches</l>
   <l>With domineering hand over the wretches</l>
   <l>Low prostrate at his foot. Can Christian eyes</l>
   <l>Endure this figure! Let the captives rise,</l>
   <l>Surly black Saracen; their bended knee</l>
   <l>Has higher objects then to reverence thee:</l>
   <l>They serve a Lord greater then Mahomet.</l>
   <l>Though now their sunne be darken'd and beset</l>
   <l>With clouds of disadvantage, time will be</l>
   <l>When such poore things shall triumph over thee;</l>
   <l>And their old prophecie shall be made good,</l>
   <l>Thy <hi>Moon shall</hi> then <hi>be turned into bloud.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The last of their destroyers that you see,</l>
   <l>Is that same gastly thing th' Anatomie</l>
   <l>Doth represent; a naked cage of bone,</l>
   <l>From whence the winged soul long since is flown:</l>
   <l>They call it Death. He with his double band,</l>
   <l>Sicknesse and casualty on either hand,</l>
   <l>Met many stragglers, forcing them to yeeld:</l>
   <l>And where the Turk be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore him got the field,</l>
   <l>He took the gleanings. Thus our souldiers f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll</l>
   <l>By th'Angel, Turk, and Death; heaven, earth, &amp; hell.</l>
   <l>Those that escap'd, came home as full of grief</l>
   <l>As the poore Purse is empty of relief.</l>
   <l>They're turn'd, and so is it; but nothing in't,</l>
   <l>Till new devotion shall repair the Mint.</l>
   <l>Mean while read o're the Historie: your brain</l>
   <l>There you may fill, though not the Purse again.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>J. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>