<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF Cato his Preceptes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121116_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18234</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4854</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF Cato his Preceptes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Preceptes of Cato : with annotacions of D. Erasmus of Roterodame vere profitable for all [...]</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>352 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE OF</hi> Cato his Preceptes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I perceiued not a few to erre and misse in the true trade &amp; waie of good nurtour, I thought to putte to my help yng hande and counsail in the repairyng of the same their ruine: for this intēr specially that thei might liue i some reputacion and honestie, and mighte therby attein and come to some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocion and prefermente. Here now (my deare beloued sonne) I shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct thee how to ordre thy self, and to furnishe the behauioures and the maners of the minde. Therefore read thou my preceptes and lessons with soche diligence, that thou maiest tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly vnderstande them. For to read any thing, and not to vnderstande what it meaneth, is none other but thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> to neglect and despise.
<q>
         <p>Firs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>fore I will the God to honour</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="7"/>
And nexte him thy parentes haue in honor.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>The chifest loue, zeale, and affecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ought (by teachers, fathers, and mothers, and all other bringers vp of youth) to be grauen and liuely fourmed in childrens hartes, should and must be the perfeict and feruent pitie and dasire towardes God &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thinges. And vnder this precepte is commaunded all vertue, first of all to bee infused and powred into the newe and freshe vesselles of tender Babes hartes. And after this loue ones perfaictly founded and rooted, to learne thē the true fauour and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccion, with like obedience and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, that ought of children to be geuen and shewed towardes their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers. Wherein thei so brought vp, maie in more age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege due reuerēce and duetie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>heir
<pb facs="7"/>
rulers, superiours and betters.
<q>
         <p>The nexte loue to this, for to be had in dignitie.</p>
         <p>Is the loue of thy aliance and consan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie:</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Here is the third loue that oughte to be kindled in childrens stomaches that is, the loue of their kindrede. Whiche loue although the Lawe of God had geuen no precept to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, yet very nature and reason would this loue to be had, seing that no smal bonde of frendship is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by knit. And without it, no litle oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of dissenciō maie be ministred For if this precepte were not obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kept: what tragical and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuous dissencion should there bee while the sonne resisteth the father? the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ewe the vncle, the brother his a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> naturall brother As it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the historie of Thyestes &amp;
<pb facs="8"/>
Atreus in Nero, and in other trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies not vnlike these, or as bad alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But now it shalbe necessarie to declare in what thinges these thre loues doeth, and ought to consist, and how euery one of these oughte to bee reuerenced, and had in estimacion. Then the loue of God dooeth consist in geuyng true honour, true praise, &amp; true sacrifice to him, of whom we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all thinges that are good. And this sacrifice canbe no purer, no clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, no pleasaunter, then to yelde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him a spirite sory for our offences and fully with a firme purpose to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne no more to the filthe of sinne. The father and the mother, the ruler and superiour are loued, whē al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges lawfully and godlie by them cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maūded are obeied and folowed. We dooe loue our kinsfolke (emong whō the nerest kinsman that we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e, our neighbour is to bee chiefly rekened) when we dooe with mutuall benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb facs="8"/>
offices, dueties, &amp; honest familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and cōuersacion one loue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one helpe thother: &amp; one instruct the other, in good example of liuyng.
<q>
         <p>Feare thy master for to displease.</p>
         <p>And with thy negligence dooe not him disease.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>This teare is harde to finde, and chaunceth but to fewe children. And the cause theróf is sometime the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters negligence. And therefore this feare ought so to bee tempred, that it bee not compelled by threatenynges and stripes, nor diminished by remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and lenitie. I tought to bee soche that the Scholer should more feare the displeasyng and vexyng of his Master, then the sharpenesse of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oode. In the olde time Princes and noble menne toke vnto theim infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>d instructours of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> whom thei called Pedagoges,
<pb facs="9"/>
and whom wee now call Scholema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. Soche a one was Aristotle with king Philip, teacher to Alexā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Plinie to the Emperor Traiane And soche had Marcus Aurelius for his sonne Commodus. And many of these teachers were but bondmenne, whom noble men boughte to teache their soonnes. As it is witnessed of Diogenes in the Apothegmes, who was bought in the market of Xenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; was in the house with him tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng his children to his liues ende, and was of his awne scholers buried
<q>
         <p>Whatsoeuer is committed to thy fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie.</p>
         <p>Kepe it priuie, and dooe it not discrie.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Herein is euery faiethfull frende taught a lesson and rule how to kepe in truste, scilence and faithfulnesse, soche secrete matiers as shalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and geuē to his fidelitie: how
<pb facs="9"/>
be it he maketh not his precepte, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be kepte in Scilence and Hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>germugger, but those thinges onelie that shal not offende either God, nor his Prince, as Heresie or treason. Yea and besides these, leat a manne haue a iuste respecte to his owne conscience, so that the hiding or the vttering of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny secrete matier be to the wrongfull hurte of no manne, and speciallie of his owne soulle.
<q>
         <p>Be thou at al seasons in a redinesse.</p>
         <p>To applie thy market and businesse.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ Wheras thenterpretours minde is that a manne should in those sciences moste chieflie occupie himself, whiche might helpe him to the knowelege of the lawe, forasmoche as in Catones time, and in our time also, the nexte &amp; spediest waie to promotiō, is by soche meanes: Yet I dooe rather folowe his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> minde and will, that is, for a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> applie himselfe to thinges present,
<pb facs="10"/>
and as the time serueth, according to the Prouerbe &amp; common saiyng: Take thy market while time is, Least of thy price thou dooe misse. And then it be saied vnto the, thou comest a daie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Faire.
<q>
         <p>with good menne euer let thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersacion be.</p>
         <p>And then shalt thou get moch honestie</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ It is communelie seen, that he that toucheth pitche, is of the same de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, spotted, &amp; carieth some token of it about him, either in sauour, or one parte or other of his garmentes is therwith distained. So it fareth with them that companie with euill dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed persones, that haūt suspected pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, either thei smel of the same naugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinesse, or thei get vnto them as bad a name as though thei were naughtie packes in dede: for no man can let the peoples iudgement, whiche wil iudge
<pb facs="10"/>
accordyng to the behauiours of theim that thou art in companie withal. So that by the companie of good mē thou shalt euer be sure to lese nothing, but rather win somewhat, either in name or in perfeictnesse of liuyng.
<q>
         <p>Enterprise not to come in presence.</p>
         <p>where thou seest men talke in scilence.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>This lessō serueth not onely to the ignoraunt mindes of young children, but also to the rudenesse of some car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly and loutishe felowes, and to the malopert boldnes of some Iacke sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Whiche all for lacke of nurture, dooe sodeinly without all regarde or blushyng, thrust theimselues into the secrete counsall of wisemenne, and so disturbe them from their earnest ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, with their vnlearned rudenesse.
<q>
         <p>In thy minde and bodily fauor.</p>
         <p>Be thou cleane &amp; of an honest behauor</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Surely there is no better token of
<pb facs="11"/>
the disposicion of the minde inwarde, then is the fashion and behauiour of the bodie outwarde. And there is no readier meanes to furnishe the bodie, then first to decke &amp; garnishe the mind with godlie vertues &amp; nurtures. So that the one is in maner shapē by the other, and one the fairer for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ornament of the other. And in this the furniture of both is very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient and for euery good Christian to be diligētlie obserued, but alwaies pride is to be abandoned, and to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer curious and picked.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>whosoeuer thou dooest mete.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Gentlie &amp; gladlie dooe him salute.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ There is no redier waie to get the loue &amp; frendeshippe of many, then in metinges and communinges toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for a manne to behaue himselfe gentlie and lowlie in his speaking &amp; gestures of his bodie, so moche that manne is of soche purenesse of nature
<pb facs="11"/>
that with gentlenesse he is soone pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified though he bee in neuer so greate a rage of furie. yea and by gentle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainmente frendes are long time kept. Whom after we haue ones lost, is verie harde, yea nothing more harde to finde and get again.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>when thou hast to dooe with one greater then thou art.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Yelde vnto him mekelie, for so it is thy parte.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ It is no smal strength and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that maie be ingēdred in the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and due obseruing of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte. Therefore it is necessarie for al degrees and states to herken vnto it. Learne here thou subiecte to forbeare thy rulers &amp; their Officers: thou ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte, thy master: thou Scholar, thy instructour: yea, &amp; thou wife thy hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande. For by contention of inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that is the lower with the higher
<pb facs="12"/>
the weaker and porer with the richer and mightier, all occasion of mischief is wrought and ministred.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>In strief thou that art superiour.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Be euer fauour able to thine inferiour.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>A precepte hauyng no lesse strength of loue and prefeict amitie, then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before. And would to God euery one of power and might would with litle childrē learne this lessō, I would the riche cobbe to fauour the poore se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labourer in the ieoperdous &amp; pein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wrastelyng of the Lawe. And I would to God that there might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different sticklers set betwene theim, that is vpright iudges to se the poore man take no foule plaie at the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie mannes hande. Likewise I would haue vsed in spirituall iudgementes, whose courtes for lacke of sande bee so slipperie, that excepte a man be the connynger, he is lightely tripped and laied on the fower quarters.
<q>
         <pb facs="12"/>
         <p>
            <hi>whatsoeuer gooddes, God dooeth to thee sende.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Kepe it, and foolishly dooe not it spende</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>I am afraied least some kepe this rule to straight, and obserueth it with ouermoche diligence, for some there are that bee soche hinchers and pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that thei had rather break their necke, then spende one ferthyng more then very shame driueth them to dooe and scarse then. Other there are, that nede more then one soche good lesson. And thei are those prodigall soonnes who will not sticke to spende their whole enheritaunce vpon a foule sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe queane, and to hassarde and dice out at sixe or seuen, their fathers pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase in one litle moment of an houre that he laboured for in all his whole life time, and then must thei go steale or take a staffe and a wallet, and goe begge.
<q>
         <pb facs="13"/>
         <p>
            <hi>whether thou be in the state of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke or virginitee.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>See that thou kepe thy self in chastite</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ Great hede is to be taken, least this vice of the fleshe, that is to saie, lecherie dooe raine in the tendre age of any childe, or young manne, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie for that soche age is moste prone and readie to soche maner of vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and then reason &amp; feare lacking, the weake fleshe of young persones is sone by very litle temptacion ouer throwen: Yea leat not the elders dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine herof to learne how to leade a life pure and immaculate, frō the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie carreine and stencious rotteunes of carnal lustes.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>In al thy businesse take good hede.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>That thou applie the with good spede.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ The earnest desire and prompte wil in a seruaunt or scholar is moche regarded, for therof it cometh, that be
<pb facs="13"/>
the matier neuer so harde, yet by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and good wille it is easelis brought about, and with a good lucke ended: Where as by negligence there is nothing that spedeth, or is well brought to passe.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>If thou wilt proue to bee a good scholer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Be euer reading one booke or other.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ Longe life thou maiest haue and many thinges maiest thou by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and practise learne, yet peraduē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in reading some frutful woorke thou shalt perceiue more wit &amp; iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente, then euer could by experiēce be attained vnto, or by any man here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after inuented, forasmoche as graces and giftes are nothing so plentious, as thei were in the beginning of the worlde, when God did make manifest his woundreful power and might in the wittes of the Heathē, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter instruction, and confirmation of
<pb facs="14"/>
the faithe of the christians to come.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>whatsoeuer thou haste seen beare it in minde.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>An forgette not thinges that bee behinde.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Some are of that opinion that thei thinke the perfeictnesse of learnyng to consist and be in the swift and hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long readyng ouer of many aucthours There bee also some parentes of like iudgemente, whiche thinke their son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to haue profited nothing, if thei bee one yere in one booke, or one daie in one lesson, but both these are farre deceiued, for thei profeict in learnyng who dooeth throughly vnderstande what thei read, and the same so vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande, dooe firmely and surely fasten in their perfeict memorie.
<q>
         <p>¶ <hi>Seke not in another house what there dooeth want.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="14"/>
            <hi>But prouide, that in thine awne be nothing scant.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>There is many a busis bodie that will finde faultes in another mannes dooynges, although he himself bee in his awne matiers moste negligēt and ouerseen. And soche dooeth often ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes geue better counsaill to other mō then thei can geue vnto theimselues. But surely most quietnesse shalbe for euery manne, to haue to dooe in his awne causes, and to suffre other men to haue their willes and pleasures in their awne businesse. For brablets &amp; intermedlers were euer causers of contencion and variaunce. And many there are that marke how litle meate another man hath in his dishe, but he findeth no fault with his awne cold cost at home.
<q>
         <p>¶ <hi>Behaue thy self gently to euery one.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>And in felowship a good companion.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="15"/>
¶ The behauiour of a manne or childe is moche commended, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted emong men of honest reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And more is he sette by that is poore &amp; gentle in his behauiour, &amp; can plaie the good felowe, thē is the riche churle with his proude and disdeinful looke. But that is a special grace, and greatly estemed, when that the noble dooe humble theim to the felowelike companie of honest poore men: for so did King Philip exhorte his soonne Alexandre to dooe, whereby he wan the heartes of many a true subiecte.
<q>
         <p>without a cause, be not thou angrie.</p>
         <p>Nor for a trifle driuen into a furie.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ There is no man, excepte he bee a very blockehead, but he hath some mocion and passion in him of anger, and displeasure, seeing that no man kepeth his nature so cleane, but it is corrupte, either with colere, fleume, or els with some other corrupte ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier.
<pb facs="15"/>
And as it is more like a stocke then a manne, not at all to be moued: So is it more nearer the propretie of cattes and dogges then men to braule and wrangle for euery wagging of a strawe, yea and some time vpō no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion: soche is the waiewardenes of many frowarde &amp; weiwarde weasels.
<q>
         <p>Disdeigne not the poore, no, nor yet skorne thou any bodie.</p>
         <p>Nor for an others miserie, thinke thy selfe more woorthie.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ It is a wounderful thing to see some statelie merchauntes, whō God hath indewed with a speciall gift and qualite aboue many other, how thei abuse thesame grace in disdaining their euē Christians &amp; felowes in the faieth and vocation of Iesus Christe, whiche made al of vile claie &amp; dust, &amp; to thesame hath promised vs that we shal returne. And then leat theim see
<pb facs="16"/>
how moche thei passe by their proude lookes, the poorest wretche that goeth by the high waies side.
<q>
         <p>when thy neighbour is fallen into miserie.</p>
         <p>Reioise not, nor haue therin felicitie.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ To mocke and scorne at naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie packes and vicious liuers, to cause thē to be ashamed of their leudnes, &amp; abominable life, is to be commended but surelie to see thy neighbour or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe in daunger of sickenesse, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or other mischaūces of this world thou hast more cause to wepe, then laughe, seing that thou maiest and hast deserued a worse thing to chaunce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy selfe. Therefore saieth Marcus Aurelius on this wise.
<q>
         <p>It is geuen to euerie man of nature.</p>
         <p>One to augmente anothers hurte and displeasure.</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="16"/>
Lende if thou maie any thing spare.</p>
         <p>Yet to whom thou lendest, see thou beware.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ There is choise and hede to bee takē in lending and geuing. For some times a manne maie either lende, or geue to his owne hurte, &amp; the borower maie be made his enemie, whiche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be his frende. Therefore to ouerie begger thou must not geue, nor to euerie borower &amp; crauer thou maist not lende, but vnto a faiethful asker, or where wretched pouertie is, or vnto theim that thou thinkest woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, vpon whom a good tourne maie wel bee bestowed, or elles towardes whom thou bearest fauour and frende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie affection, there sticke not to extēde thy liberalitie and charite, least per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture otherwise thou maiest bee constreigned thus to saie.</p>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="17"/>
      <l>When I lent, I was a frende.</l>
      <l>And when I asked, I was vnkinde.</l>
      <l>So of my frende I made my to.</l>
      <l>Therefore I wil no more do so.</l>
   </lg>
   <q>
      <p>when thy clientes matier is in trial of iudgemente.</p>
      <p>Then stande faste at the barre &amp; euer present.</p>
   </q>
   <p>¶ I would to Christes passion euery atturneie, outter harrester, councellous sergeaunt, &amp; iudge of the lawe, would print in their vpright cōsciences this precepte, into whose handes is cōmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the right suite, and splee of many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> poore man, the whiche thei someti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes willinglie (when thei are of the contrarie parte wel bribed) and some<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>time neglectlie (when of their clien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes thei are not largely and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie rewarded (let the matier grow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> to a nonesute, or driue him to sue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> commission into the countrie, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="17"/>
by frendshippe and mastershippe the poore man betwene .ii. stooles lieth flat vpon the grounde. And thus the poore man is vtterly enbarred of his right, either by the negligence of the atturney in callyng slackly vpon the counsailers, or els by the coūsailers and sergeantes absentyng theimsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from the courte barre, or els the iudges themselues in deferryng iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente, or at least waie by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt fauour of the countrey.
<q>
         <p>Feastyng and bankettyng seldome dooe thou vse.</p>
         <p>And theim to haunte often, vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuse.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Whether of these twoo thou custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mablie dooest vse, thou shalte bee sure to haue a ready displeasure and hurte folowyng. As if thou bee a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune feast maker, it shall weare the hangelles of thy purse, and make thy
<pb facs="18"/>
liuyng full bare. And then loke whē all is spent, whiche of thy gestes wil bid the to so many feastés again? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so if thou bee a commune smelfeast, thou shalte by and by runne in the sclaunder and infamie of a pinchefist and a commune rauenyng dogge that thrusteth his head in euery mannes pot, and licketh of the crommes from euery bodies table. But now &amp; then to feast thy frende, and thy frende to feast thee, is the signe of frugalenes and moche humanitie.
<q>
         <p>Slepe quietly, and take thy rest.</p>
         <p>As moche as shalbee thought for nature best.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>There are some soche sluggerdes, whiche put so greate delight &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in slepyng, that thei thinke the onely felicitie &amp; happinesse of this life to be in slepe, wheras thei are in very dede dead images, and the liuely
<pb facs="18"/>
pictures of death. And their saiyng is we thinke no man hurte, as long as we slepe soundly, although whē thei are wakyng, thei can speake as euill and as shreudely as the wourst.
<q>
         <p>whatsoeuer thou haste sworne with thy will.</p>
         <p>Kepe thine othe and thy promise fulfill.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Behold christians the preceptes of an Heathen, against our customable and damnable othes and blasphemie that we vse. we maie be ashamed that very infideles shall passe vs in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conuersacion of liuyng. Seeyng vnto them was geuen no rule or com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maūdement, but soche as reason and nature did instruct them in. But how oft haue we of god himself commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement not to sweare either in vain, or to the mischeuous and naughtie purpose of any thing? Yea, when we
<pb facs="19"/>
dooe, or be caused of right to sweare, how litle truth and credence is there founde in our othe? Derely none but periurie aboundauntly. And in our promises, bee thei by neuer so greate an othe made, we are craftie &amp; slowe performers, and subtile dealers with our neighbours.
<q>
         <p>Drinke wine with temperatnesse.</p>
         <p>And in thy drinking vse no excesse</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>It is not vnknowen how many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities haue and dooe daiely ensue and folowe the great excessiue bibbyng and bollyng of wine. Some of these swilbolles haue their yies bleared &amp; winkyng. Some haue rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tethe and breath stinkyng. Some their faces empearied with rubies, &amp; saphires of the tauerne. Some blob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chekes and puffed faces. Some gore, bellies &amp; slaggyng stomaches. There bee other that haue goutes, dropsies, their liuers cōsumed, yea, their brain
<pb facs="19"/>
and wit confounded and dulled And will ye haue fewe wordes? thei shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their life, marre their youth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten and bring quickly olde age, and many times sodein death. And as for youth to drinke wine, is none other, then where there is a good fire and heate sufficiēt, to cast in oile to make the flame bigger.
<q>
         <p>If thou wilte needes fight, fight for thy countrey.</p>
         <p>And trie thy manhode against thine enemie.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>There are many braggers and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that will for euery small trifle laie their handes vpō their daggers and be ready to kill God haue in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> vpon his soulle, while thei are emōg their awne nacion, and shewe their strength like valiaunt and puissaunt champions, in defendyng their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie from forrein enemies: But then
<pb facs="20"/>
soche braggers wilbe readier to crepe in at a bēche hole, then to shewe their heades, or bide one stroke in a fielde. There bee also souldiours that will proffer themselues to goe a warfare more for the lucre and vaūtage of the spoiles, robberies, and praies taken of their enemies, then for the loue and affeccion that thei beare towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the saufegarde of their countrey.
<q>
         <p>whatsoeuer thou hearest, bee it good or badde.</p>
         <p>Dooe not hastely beleue it vntill the trueth be had.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Suche is the nature and condicion of many one, that thei thinke euery tale of Robinhode and litle Ihon, to be as true as the gospell. And of this sort are the common people, who for lacke of reason and knowelege, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port those thinges that firste come to their eares as thinges of very truth
<pb facs="20"/>
when there is in deede nothing more ferther from the trueth. And herof it cometh that tales, rumours, and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges bee in so shorte space conuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed into so sondrie and diuerse pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and farre countries. For if euery man would take deliberacion and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisement vpon soche thinges, as are tolde them. Newes &amp; lies would not runne abroad with soche short spede.
<q>
         <p>I thinke many matiers would come to passe well.</p>
         <p>If first of thine awne self thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest take councell.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Many a man runneth from place to place to seke helpe and remedy of his griefes and troubles, where as perchaūce if he would somwhat depe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ponder the occasions of soche vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnesse in his awne minde &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, he might with light cost and lesse peines, redresse &amp; amende soche
<pb facs="21"/>
his troubles and displeasures, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer set steppe out of his awne doore. It is good therefore first to counsaill with the familier spirit of a mannes awne minde, &amp; there see whether any ferther remedy bee to bee sought for, or not, and so accordyngly to procede.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>If thou muste nedes other mennes counsaill take.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Bee sure to folowe the best, and the euill forsake.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Thou muste not take euery manne to bee thy counsailer, neither euery mannes counsaill is to bee folowed, but that counsaill muste thou chiefly sticke vnto, by the whiche thou shalt get spedy and sure remedy of thy bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse. For many there are that can geue counsaill, but fewe geueth coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saill profitable for their clientes, and many tourneth their coūsail to their awne commodities and profeictes. As
<pb facs="21"/>
witnesseth the tale of Esope, where the Crowe coūsaileth the Egle how to breake his coccle, by fliyng vp an high, and lettyng the coccle fal doune vpon the harde stones, whose coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saill when the Egle had folowed: the Coccle letten fall and brast, was by thesame Crowe cōueighed cleane out of the Egles sight.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>Eschue harlottes &amp; queanes company</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>And to verteous lerning thy self apply</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>There is no better meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain and kepe in youth frō the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and volupteous lust of the fraile fleshe, then earnestly to occupie the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same in some verteous and Godlie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xercise. And of the contrarie part the onely prouoker, tickeler, and setted forwarde of filthie delites, is slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gishenesse, and idle wanderyng of the minde, who beeyng deliuered of all good and honest occupacion, draweth brittle fleshe to his moste corrupte
<pb facs="22"/>
and stinchious lustes and desires. So that one Egistus demaundyng of the Goddes vpon what occasion he was made an adulter. Answere was made him. Marie thou warte euer slouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and idle.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>whatsoeuer of the shalbe demaunded.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>By trueth alwaie, let it be answered.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>In all ages, and in all degrees, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng is a vice moste odious and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, and contrarie to the professiō of christianitie: but yet moste especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a noble mannes child, whiche should bee the mirroure and example to the baser sort: liyng is abandoned as a thing chiefly dishonouryng and distainyng his nobilitie. There is no man that knoweth what a thief and a lier meaneth, and what their quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties bee, but will with all his harte bee ridde of a lier to take a thief, for of the thief he maie bee ware, of the other he cannot.
<q>
         <pb facs="22"/>
         <p>
            <hi>To good me be thou alwaies beneficial</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>And vnto kinde persones bee thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer liberall.</hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>It would greue the to bestowe thy benefites, to haue nothing for theim again: but how moche more would it greue thee not onely to lese thy good tourne, but also for thesame, to bee requited and recōpensed with a shre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed tourne, and to haue for thy kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denesse and good wille, a churlishe prāke or shrowed touche plaied the? As thou shalt be sure to haue, if thou dooe good for a churle. Therefore, if thou looke to haue good of thy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites bestowed, bestowe theim vpon good men, and vpon soche, whō thou knowest to haue kinde hartes, and cā beare in minde who haue dooen them good in times past.
<q>
         <p>
            <hi>Be thou no common checker nor railer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="23"/>
Nor of other mennes deedes a sauci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> deprauer.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Good it is, yea and christenlike to monishe and warne one another, whē any thing is amisse: But to raile at, skorne at, disdainfully to rebuke, or arrogauntly to checke and taunt one another, is not onely vnbesemyng, but also farre from the parte of any good menne, in whom any morsell or crūme of honestie or ciuile behauior dooeth abide. And what shall I doubt any thing at all, to exempt them out of the numbre of menne, and numbre thē emong the moste sauage &amp; brutest beastes that be, the whiche haue any soche cōdiciō. For thei are the distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and breakers of al good ordre &amp; vniformitie of al peace &amp; trāquilliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <q>
         <p>In what estimacion soeuer thou bee in</p>
         <p>Lose it not, but studie more to win.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>A good estimacion &amp; name passeth
<pb facs="23"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> numbre of riches, in so moche that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>he preciousnesse of it, surmounteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>he value of the gooddes of the whole worlde, and no treasure is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with it. What strong boltes &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>kes, what bulworkes, munimētes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>nd defences, what vigilante &amp; wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefull kepers ought wee then to set about this incōparable treasure? and specially because the losse of it cā ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>y hardely be gotten again: &amp; seldome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> is seen to be recouered, and to like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ignitie and fauour to be restored.
<q>
         <p>Let thy Iustice bee indifferent, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>hy Iudgement right.</p>
         <p>Iudge wrong to no manne by power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r might.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Oh Cato Cato: if that thou couldest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>arke &amp; espie this faulte in the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Iustices of thy time, when onely the lawe of nature and reason <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uled, and not the feare &amp; knowelege
<pb facs="24"/>
of God: what wouldest thou now saie if thou shouldest beholde what false accusyng, what vniust pleadyng, and accordyng to thesame, what moste false condemnyng is of poore sely so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>lles, and very innocēt persones?
<q>
         <p>If thy father and mother be displea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed with thee.</p>
         <p>winne thē again by pacient humilitee</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Although thy father and mother dooe chastice thee somewhat sharplie and extremely, yet it shall not be thy part for to behaue thy self stubburne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly or frowardly against theim, or els to go about by any meanes or waies how to exasparate theim, and to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister more occasiō of displeasure: but with meke, milde, and gentle wordes to molifie, pacifie, and quallifie their angre. For nature abhorreth in the very brute beastes, that the yong one should resist or hee in any thing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasaunt
<pb facs="24"/>
vnto his damme, no not in the fierce Molues and Tigres, or in the venemous Serpentes.
<q>
         <p>If thou receiue of any man a benefite.</p>
         <p>Remembre with like kindenesse, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same to requite.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>I dooe iudge him worthie, to whom not onely any good tourne ought to be geuē at any time after, but also to whō greate vnkindnesse ought to be shewed, the whiche will not knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege himself to haue receiued a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite at his frendes handes, or doth by negligence and ouersight forgette to requite and repaie, when he is hable, like kindnesse as he had in his neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie and nede receiued. Surely many there are that remembre very well what thei dooe for other menne, but what other men do bestowe vpon thē that is quickly forgottē or slowly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and nothing at al requited
<q>
         <pb facs="25"/>
         <p>Stande at the barre, herken what is there saied.</p>
         <p>That thou maiest learne other men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes matiers to plead.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>A very notable science and a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng moche estemed was the law in the time of Cato, so that the next and the spediest waie to promocion was then to haue a perfeicte sighte in the Lawe. And euen in these our daies it hath nolesse, yea, rather more auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and is had in farre better esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maciō. Therfore this precept of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to maie be well marked of the youth of this realme, who willeth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth thē to the knowelege of the Lawes, not for to auenge his awne wronges, with extreme sute, and not for to woorke iniurie, and to woe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spleasure: but to maintein righte, to help the nedy and poore sely creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to their true possessions and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce
<pb facs="25"/>
to see iustice ministred, and true causes alwaies preferred.
<q>
         <p>Soche gifte and qualite as God hath to the lent.</p>
         <p>See that with discretion it bee spent.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ If God haue indued the with manhode and corporal strengthe, this gifte is not to be tourned into the vse of auenging euerie iniurie, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure, not to quareling &amp; fighting for euerie light matier, not to bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheding and manslaughter, but to the defence of thy prince and countrey, to the mainteinaunce of thy wife &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, by dooyng soche labours and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupacions as thy strength maie well susteine and beare, yea in whatsoeuer gifte and qualitie thou dooest excel, it is not to be vsed for any forceable op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression by might, nor for any disceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful detrusion by gile and policie.
<q>
         <p>Tempre thine angre, and Lefraine
<pb facs="26"/>
thy displeasure.</p>
         <p>And the same to auenge, take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte and leasure.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ His councel was heretofore not to be angrie for euerie wagging of a strawe. And now his ferther and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aduise is, in no case to bee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or displeased; but then to punishe and then to auenge, when anger and malice dooeth not blinde reason and expel godlie charite.
<q>
         <p>At the toppe &amp; scourge let thy plaie be</p>
         <p>And from the dice, see that thou flie.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ The toppe &amp; scourge is a plate moste agreable and welbeseming for children, dicing was of an euil report and moche abandoned emong the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heathen and Gentiles.
<q>
         <p>Dooe nothing according as thou art of power and might.</p>
         <p>But lette thy dooynges be of iustice
<pb facs="26"/>
and right.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ What can there be more apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to a very tiraunte then for a man putte in aucthorite, to haue onely a respecte and regarde what he is able to dooe, and not what thing becometh him, or is lefull for him to dooe. And in soche a persone maie well be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the saiyng of the Poete.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>For reason true and iuste.</l>
      <l>Standeth his owne wil and Iuste.</l>
   </lg>
   <q>
      <p>Thy inferiour dooe thou not dispise.</p>
      <p>Neither yet him refuse in any wise.</p>
   </q>
   <p>¶ To beare either hate, displeasure or disdaine to a manne, being of lesse abilite and power then thou thy lesse art of, is a verie euident signe &amp; moste manifest token of a proude arrogant and presumpteous minde and not of a lowelie and kinde harte.
<q>
         <p>An other mannes gooddes dooe thou not craue.</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="27"/>
And by vntrueth, desire not them to haue.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ There is no one thing that dooeth more manifest and declare the brickle and fraile nature of manne then that he rareth neither what, nor whose gooddes thei be, nor by what meanes he hath theim, so that he maie gette them ones to be his owne.
<q>
         <p>Loue thy wife with a true affection</p>
         <p>For at al saies she must be thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ A worlde it is to see the diuerse affections of menne in chosing and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of wiues, but this one thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēbre that thou oughtest to take thy wife of loue, and neither for gooddes nor beautie, and then louinglie to vse her, remēbring that of .ii. ye are made but one bodie, least it be said emōg vs
<q>
         <p>Emong the Heathen Matrimonie was wel estemed.</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="27"/>
And emong vs Christians litle regarded.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <p>Instructe thy children to vertue, and vnderstandyng.</p>
         <p>And in ignoraunce and blindnes let them not be wandring.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ I dooe not onely marueile, but rather woundre what phantased folie reigneth in the heades of many fathers the whiche either altogether witholde their children from the education and bringing vp in honest disci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lines and knoweleges, or elles will sette theim to no other maisters, but to soche as maie and can tendrelie, yea, rather wantonlie and negligentlie instructe them and teache them.
<q>
         <p>Loke what thou dooest make vpon other.</p>
         <p>Be not agreued in thy selfe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same for to suffre.</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="28"/>
Soche measure as thou makest, soche looke thou receiue again.</p>
         <p>when thou art sitting at thy meate and table.</p>
         <p>Of diuerse and many thinges, dooe thou not bable.</p>
         <p>Talke litle, and let it be with adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semente.</p>
         <p>¶ Let euer thy studie and endeuer be. About that, that is iust &amp; honestie</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>¶ Endeuour your selues with an earnest desire and diligence to folowe and doe those thinges wherof cometh no rebuke, shame, or dishonestie.
<q>
         <p>No mannes loue haue thou in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine.</p>
         <p>But euerie mannes good wil, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to obteine.</p>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="28"/>
¶ All meanes and waies are of a quiete harte and minde to bee sought how to auoide the displeasure and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the least childe that gooeth in the strete. For asmoche as there is nothing so precious as loue, and no manne dooeth pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse better riches, then he that hath the loue of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>