<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST happie Prince, IAMES the first, by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121041_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04317</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14426</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121041</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST happie Prince, IAMES the first, by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lucta Iacobi: or, A bonefire for His Maiesties double deliuerie, from the deluge in Perth, the 5. of August, 1600. And the doomesday of Britaine, the 5. of Nouember. 1605. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Univocè-catholicus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST happie Prince, IAMES the first, by the grace of God, King of Great <hi>Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Maiesties most blessed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery by the power of God from that bloodie <hi>Diluge</hi> of PERTH, and this <hi>Fierie Doomesday</hi> of BRITAINE, being to all your people a cause of Gods euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting praise, &amp; their present ioy, as the multitude made shewe by their <hi>Bonefires,</hi> whose earthly smokes in great measure ascended the heauenly regions. It hath kindled such a <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire</hi> in the furnace of my breast, as must needes bee knowne to your Maiestie; whose Builder is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worker, whose Fewell is Affection, whose flames may well warme, but neuer harme you: and the more you anneere them, the more tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate shall you finde them, comforting such as loue you, and consuming such as hate you: whose gleames I haue made first to glance on your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties selfe, secretly and vnsigned; as being vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="3"/>(though they should euen please you) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent them; much lesse to come in your presence, if they should offend: leauing to your Maiesties most royall and vpright iudgement, as you finde my Fire well built, to set it where you will haue it seene: or being fallen from his grounds, more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally to reedifie it: or if of too grosse materialls, to purge the drossie errors of it: or if nothing of it like you, by a breath of your Maiesties mouth vtterly to extinguish it. Doe as you please (Sir) for so long as I liue shall I euer loue you. Your Deliuerer be alwaies with you. From towards the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of your Maiesties <hi>Canaan, Tuesday, Doomesday</hi> 5. <hi>Nouember.</hi> 1605.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties most loyall and louing subiect, without any Acquiuocation.</hi> Vniuocè-catholicus.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>