<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR VNTO THE CHRISTIAN READER, AS TOV∣CHING THE TRANSLATION OF THESE AVNCIENT HISTORIES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121374_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00440</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121374</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR VNTO THE CHRISTIAN READER, AS TOV∣CHING THE TRANSLATION OF THESE AVNCIENT HISTORIES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The auncient ecclesiasticall histories of the first six hundred yeares after Christ : wrytten in the Greeke tongue by three learned historiographers, Eusebius, Socrates, and Euagrius. Eusebius Pamphilus Bishop of Cæsarea in Palæstina vvrote 10 bookes. Socrates Scholasticu of Constantinople vvrote 7 bookes. Euagrius Scholasticus of Antioch vvrote 6 bookes. VVhereunto is annexed Dorotheus Bishop of Tyrus, of the liues of the prophetes, apostles and 70 disciples. All which authors are faithfully translated out of the Greeke tongue by Meredith Hanmer, Maister of Arte and student in diuinitie. Last of all herein is contayned a profitable chronographie collected by the sayd translator, the title whereof is to be seene in the ende of this volume, with a copious index of the principall matters throughout all the histories</title>
                 <author>Eusebius, of Caesarea, Bishop of Caesarea</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 176, that is 190, 201-402, 4, 403-538, 2, 56, 18 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR VNTO THE CHRISTIAN READER, AS TOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHING THE TRANSLATION OF THESE AVNCIENT HISTORIES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I am geuen to vnderstande (good Christian reader) there haue bene diuers vvhich attempted to translate these auncient Ecclesiastical histories, yet haue geuen ouer their purpose, partly being discouraged vvith the diuersitie and corruption of Greeke copies, and partly being dismayed vvith the crookednes of <hi>Eusebius</hi> stile, vvhich is by reason of his vnperfect allegations, and last of all, beinge vvhollie ouercome vvith the tedious studie and infinite toyle and labour. The occasion that moued me to take so great an enterprise in hand vvas, that I read them in Greeke vnto an honorable Ladie of this lande, and hauing some leasure besides the lecture and other exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses agreeable vnto my calling, I thought good to turne the priuate commoditie vnto a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique profite, and to make the Christian reader of this my natiue countrey partaker also of these learned, zealous, and pleasaunt histories. VVhen I tooke penne in hande, and considered vvith my selfe all the circumstances of these Histories, and founde in them certen things vvhich the autors peraduenture might haue left vnvvritten, but the interpretor in no vvise vntranslated: I remembred the saying of Augustine, <hi>Diuinitatis est non errare,</hi> It belongeth to the Diuinitie, or to God him selfe not to erre, and that these Historiographers vvere but men, yet rare and singuler persons. Daily experience teacheth vs there is no gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dē vvithout some vveeds, no medovv vvithout some vnsauerie floures, no forest vvithout some vnfrutefull trees, no countrey vvithout some barren land, no vvheate vvithout some tares, no day vvithout a cloude, no vvriter vvithout some blemish, or that escapeth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of all men. I am sure there is no reader so foolish as to builde vpon the antiquitie and autoritie of these histories as if they vvere holy scripture, there is an historicall Faith vvhich is not in the compasse of our Creede, and if you happen to light vpon any storie that sauoureth of superstition, or that seemeth vnpossible, <hi>penes autorem sit fides,</hi> referre it to the autor, take it as cheape as ye finde it, remember that the holy Ghost sayth, <hi>omnis homo mendax.</hi> if so, peraduenture the reader to, then let the one beare vvith the other. VVhere the places did require, lest the reader shoulde be snared in errour, I haue laide dovvne Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of an other letter then the texte is of, vvhere the autor vvas obscure, I haue opened him vvith notes in the marge, vvhere I founde the storie vnperfect, I haue noted it vvith a starre, and signified vvithall vvhat my penne directed me vnto. Manie Latine vvriters haue imployed great diligence and labour about these Greeke Historiographers, one transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one peece, an other an other peece, one interpreting one of the autors, an other trāslating almost all, one perusing, an other correcting. <hi>Ierome</hi> turned <hi>Eusebius</hi> into Latine, but it is not extant. <hi>Ruffinus</hi> tooke vpon him to translate <hi>Eusebius.</hi> Of him <hi>Ierome</hi> vvryteth in<note place="margin">Ierom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Ruffinus</note> this sort: <hi>Ecclesiasticam pulchre Eusebius histo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> texuit, quid ergo de interprete sentiendum, liberum sit iam cuique iudicium. Eusebius</hi> hath very vvell compiled the Ecclesiasticall historie, but as for the interpreter, euery man hath to thinke of him vvhat
<pb facs="5"/>
himlist. <hi>Beatus Rhenanus,</hi> a man of great iudgement, saith thus of <hi>Ruffinus. In libris à se versis parum laudis meruit, quod ex industria nō verba vel sensum autoris quem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendum susceperit appendat, sed vel minus vel plusculum tanquam paraphrases, non velut interpres pro sua libidine plerum{que} referat. Ruffinus</hi> deserued but small praise for his translations, because of purpose he tooke no heede vnto the vvordes and meaning of the autor vvhich he tooke vpon him to translate, but interpreted for the most parte at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, by adding and diminishing, more like a Paraphrast then a translator. I finde by perusing of him that he vttered in fevv vvords, vvhich <hi>Eusebius</hi> vvrote at large: that he is tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vvhere <hi>Eusebius</hi> is brief: that he is obscure vvhere <hi>Eusebius</hi> is plaine: that he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vvhere <hi>Eusebius</hi> is darke, vvords and sentences and pages, and Epistles, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vvholl bookes. Half the eight booke of <hi>Eusebius</hi> (so hath <hi>Musculus</hi> to) and in maner all the tenth booke, he hath not once touched. <hi>Ruffinus</hi> vvrote the historie of his time in tvvo bookes, and erred fovvly in certen things, as <hi>Socrates</hi> doeth report of him. <hi>Epiphanius Scholasticus</hi> translated the Tripartite historie. <hi>Ioachimus Camerarius</hi> geueth of him<note place="margin">ohanius.</note> this iudgement. <hi>Tantam deprehendi in translatione non modo barbariem sed etiā in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scitiam ac somnolentiam istius Epiphanij, vt mirarer vlli Graecorum non adeo alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam linguam Latinam, sed ignoratam suam esse potuisse.</hi> I founde in the translation of this <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> not onely such barbarous phrases, but also ignoraunce and palpable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that I can not chuse but maruell, hovve any Grecian coulde be vnskilfull, not so muche in the straunge Latine tongue, as ignorant in his ovvne language. <hi>VVol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gangus Muscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> a learned interpretour, hath translated the histories of <hi>Eusebius,</hi> yet <hi>Edvvardus God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salfus</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sculus.</note> geueth of him this Censure. <hi>Hic autem satis correctis exemplaribus, vt credibile est destitutus innumeris locis turpissime labitur. Est porro adeo obscurus vt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres egeat interprete, adeo salebrosus vt lector identidem inhaereat, adeo lacunosus vt autores ipsi Graeci historiae suae sententias non fuisse expletas grauiter conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur.</hi> This <hi>Musculus</hi> as it is very like, vvanting perfect coppies, erred fovvly in infinite places. Moreouer, he is so obscure that the Translator hath neede of an interpretour, so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate that the Reader is novve and than graueled, so briefe that the Greeke autors them selues doe grieuouslie complaine, that the sentences in their Histories vvere not fullie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed. Though the reporter be partiall being of a contrarie religion, yet herein I finde his iudgement to be true, and specially in his translation of the tenth booke of <hi>Eusebius.</hi> yet not I only, but others haue founde it. <hi>Iacobus Grynaeus</hi> a learned man, corrected many faultes,<note place="margin">naeus.</note> explicated many places, printed in the marge many notes, yet after al this his labour vvhich deserueth great commendation, there are founde infinite escapes, and for triall thereof, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me vnto the Reader. <hi>Christophorson</hi> (as for his religion I referre it to God and to him<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>isto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rson.</note> selfe, vvho by this time knovveth vvhether he did vvell or no) vvas a great Clarke, and a learned interpretour, he hathe Translated passing vvell, yet sometimes doeth he addicte him self very much to the Latine phrase, and is caried avvay vvith the sound and vveight therof. If anye of the former vvryters had done vvell, vvhat needed the later interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to take so much paines? I vvoulde haue all the premisses, and vvhatsoeuer hath bene spoken of these Latine Translatours by me (althoughe one of them chargeth an other) to be taken, not that I accuse them of mine ovvne heade, but by beholding their doings, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse the faultes that myghte escape in this Englishe Translation. I founde the Greeke coppie of <hi>Eusebius</hi> in manie places vvonderfull crabbed, his Historie is full of allegations, sayings<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bius.</note> and sentences, and Epistles, and the selfe same autoritie oftentimes alleaged to the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of sundrie matters, that the vvords are short, the sense obscure &amp; hard to be trāslated. Yet the learning of the man, the autoritie of his person, &amp; the Antiquitie of his time vvill cause vvhatsoeuer may be thought amisse to be vvell takē. <hi>Socrates</hi> vvho follovved <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebius</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ates.</note>
      <pb facs="5"/>
about a hundred and fortie yeares after, and continevved the Historie, vvrote an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent and an artificiall stile, he vseth to alleage vvholl Epistles, perfecte sentences, and hath deliuered the historic very plaine. His vvords are svveete, his vaine pleasaunt, &amp; his inuention very vvittie. though the historie be large, his bookes long, and the labour great in vvryting of them, yet vvas I very much recreated vvith the svvetenesse of the vvorke. <hi>Euagrius,</hi> vvho beganne vvhere <hi>Socrates</hi> left, and continevved his penne vnto the ende<note place="margin">Euagrius</note> of the first six hundred yeares after Christ, is full of Dialects, and therefore in Greeke not so pleasaunt as <hi>Socrates.</hi> He hath many superstitious stories vvhich might very vvell haue bene spared. But in perusing of him I vvould haue the reader to note the great chaunge that vvas in his time more then in the dayes of the former vvryters, and therafter to consider of the times follovving, the difference that is in these our dayes betvvene the Church and the Apostolicke times. the encrease, augmentation, &amp; daily adding of ceremonies to ceremonies, seruice vpon seruice, vvith other Ecclesiasticall rites and decrees, is not the encrease of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and the perfection of godlines, for our Sauiour telleth vs in the Gospel, that tovvards the<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> later dayes loue shall vvaxe colde, and iniquitie shall abound: but the malice and spite of the Deuell, vvho vvith the chaunge of time, altereth (as much as he may) the state of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall affaires, and thrusteth daily into the church one mischiefe vpon an other. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer <hi>Euagrius</hi> being a tēporall man, stuffeth his Historie vvith prophane stories of vvarres and vvarlike engines, of battailes and loudshed, of Barbarians and Heathen nations. In describing the situation of any soyle, the erection of buildings, and vertues of some proper person, he doth excell. <hi>Dorotheus</hi> Bishop of Tyrus &amp; Martyr, vvhom I haue annexed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Dorothe</note> these former Historiographers, being vvell seene in the Hebrevv tonge, and a great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquarie, vvrote briefly the liues of the Prophets, Apostles, and seuentie disciples of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. The faultes that are therein, I attribute them rather vnto the corrupt coppies, then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vvant of knovvledge in him. Such things as are to be noted in him, I haue laid them in the preface before his booke. After all these Translations (gentle Reader) not vvithstanding my great trauell &amp; studie, I haue gathered a briefe <hi>Chronographie,</hi> begining vvith <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">A Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nograph</note> and ending vvith <hi>Euagrius,</hi> vvhere thou maist see the yeares of the Incarnation, the raigne of the Emperours, the famous men and Martyrs, the kings of Iudaea, and highe priestes of the Ievves in Ierusalem, from the birth of Christ vnto the ouerthrovve of the Citie, the Councels, the Bishops of Ierusalem, Antioch, Rome, Alexandria, and all the heresies vvithin the first six hundred yeares after Christ, deuided into Columnes, vvhere the yere of the Lord stāds right ouer against euery one. The profite that riseth by reading of these histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, I am not able in fevv vvords to declare▪ besides the vvorks of the autors thē selues, they haue brought forth vnto vs Sentences, Epistles, Orations, Chapiters and bookes of auncient vvryters, such as vvrote immediatly after the Apostles, and are not at this day extant saue in them. Namely of <hi>Papias</hi> Bishop of Hierapolis, <hi>Polycarpus</hi> Bishop of Smyrna, <hi>Polycra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Bishop of Ephesus, <hi>Dionysius</hi> Bishop of Corinth, <hi>Apollinarius</hi> Bishop of Hierapolis, <hi>Dionysius</hi> Bishop of Alexandria, <hi>Melito</hi> Bishop of Sardis, <hi>Serapion</hi> Bishop of Antioch, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> Bishop of Lions, <hi>Alexander</hi> Bishop of Ierusalem, <hi>Theoctistus</hi> Bishop of Caesa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atolius</hi> Bishop of Laodicea, <hi>Phileas</hi> Bishop of Thumis, <hi>Alexander</hi> Bishop of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, <hi>Eusebius</hi> Bishop of Nicomedia, <hi>Theognis</hi> Bishop of Nice, <hi>Athanasius</hi> Bishop of Alexandria, <hi>Gregorie</hi> Bishop of Nazianzum, <hi>Cyrill</hi> Bishop of Alexandria, <hi>Eusebius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Dorilaeum, <hi>Peter</hi> Bishop of Alexandria, <hi>Gregorie</hi> B. of Antioch. Of <hi>Gaius, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius, Iulius, Liberius,</hi> Bishops of Rome. Of the Councels, as the Synode in Palaestina and Antioch, the Councel of Nice, Ariminum, Ephesus, Chalcedon and Constantinople. Of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vvriters as, <hi>Quadratus, Rhodon, Africanus, Miltiades, Apollonius, Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Macarius, Origen, Euagrius, and Symeon.</hi> If vve be disposed to see the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
<pb facs="6"/>
their Decrees, Epistles, Constitutions and Edicts, vve may soone finde them euen fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> the first, vnto <hi>Mauricius</hi> the last, vvithin the first sixe hundred yeres, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly <hi>Augustus, Tiberius, Caligula, Claudius, Nero, Galba, Otho, Vitellius, Vespasia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Titus, Domitian, Nerua, Traian, Adrianus, Antoninus Pius, Verus, Comodus, Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinax, Didius Iulianus, Seuerus, Caracalla, Macrinus, Heliogabalus, Alexander Maximinus, Gordianus, Philip, Decius, Gallus, Aemilianus, Valerianus, Claudius Quintilius, Aurelianus, Tacitus, Florianus, Carus, Diocletian</hi> and <hi>Maximianus, Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantius</hi> and <hi>Maximinus, Constantinus Magnus</hi> and <hi>Licinius, Constantinus the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Constantius</hi> and <hi>Constans, Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apostata, Iouian, Valentinianus</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens, Gratian, Valentinianus the yonger,</hi> and <hi>Theodosius Magnus, Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norius, Theodosius iunior, Martianus, Leo, Zeno, Anastasius, Iustinus, Iustinianus; Iustinus the 2. Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Mauricius.</hi> VVe may see the Bishops hovve they gouerned, Ministers hovv they taught, Synodes vvhat they decreed, Ceremonies hovv they crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, Heresies hovv they rose and vvere rooted out. If vve stande vpon the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Martyrs, and there beholde the valiant vvrastlers, and inuincible champions of Christ Iesu, hovv can vve chuse but be rauished vvith zeale vvhen vve see the professors of the truth torne in peeces of vvilde beastes, crucified, beheaded, stoned, stifled, beaten to death vvith cudgels, fried to the bones, slaine aliue, burned to ashes, hanged on gibbettes, drovvned, brained, scurged, maimed, quartered, their neckes broken, their legges savved of, their tongues cutte, their eyes pulled out and the emptie place seared vvith scalding i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, the vvrapping of them in oxe hides vvith dogges and snakes and drovvned in the sea, the inioyning of them to kill one an other, the gelding of Christians, the paring of their flesh vvith sharpe rasors, the renting of their sides vvith the lashe of the vvhip, the pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of their vaines vvith bodkins, and famishing of them to death in deepe and noysome dungeons. It is a vvonder to see the zeale of their prayers, their charitie tovvards all men, their constancie in torment, and their confidence in Christ Iesus. These be they vvhome <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in his Apocalypse savve in a vision vnder the altare, that vvere Martyred for the<note place="margin">c. 6. 7.</note> vvord of God and the testimonie of Christ Iesus, vvhich cried vvith a loud voyce, saying: Hovve long tariest thou Lord, holy and true, to iudge and to auēge our bloude, on them that dvvell on the earth. And long vvhite garments vvere geuen vnto euery one of them, and it vvas sayd vnto them, that they should rest yet for a litle season, vntill their felovve ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts and their brethern that should be killed as they vvere, vvere fulfilled. The Angell telleth him vvho they vvere that vvere arayed in long vvhite garmentes, and vvhence they came, saying: these are they vvhich came out of great tribulation, and haue vvashed their long robes, and made them vvhite by the bloude of the Lambe, therfore are they in the presence of the throne of God, and serue him day and night in his temple: and he that sitteth in the throne vvill dvvell among them. They shall hunger no more, neither thurst, and God shall vvipe avvay all teares from their eyes. Very comfortable vvordes. But the executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the tyrantes, and tormentours hearts vvere so hardened, that neither voyces from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, nor signes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er threatning vengeance and the vvrath of God to light vpō them, neither the svvetting of stones, nor the monsters that the earth brought forth could molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their stonie mindes. The sea ouerflovved the land, the earth opened and left daungerous gulphes, Earthquakes ouerthrevve their Tovvnes and Cities, fire burned their houses, yet vvoulde they not leaue of their furie. They vvere as <hi>S. Paul</hi> sayeth, turned into a reprobate sense, they left no villanie vnpractised, in the ende many of them fell into frensie and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they ranne them selues vpon naked svvordes, they brake their ovvne neckes, they han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them selues, they tumbled them selues headlong into riuers, they cutte their ovvne throtes, and diuersly dispatched them selues. This is the viall full of the vvrathe of God,
<pb facs="6"/>
vvhich the Angell in the reuelation povvred vpon the vvaters, and the voyce that folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved after may very vvell be spoken of them: O Lord vvhich art and vvast, thou art righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and holy, because thou hast geuen such iudgements, for they haue shed out the bloud of Saincts and Prophets, and therefore hast thou geuen them bloud to drinke, for they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued it. The aforesaid Martyrs gaue forth godly sayings, diuine precepts for the posteritie, they sealed their doctrine vvith their ovvne bloude, they spared not their liues vnto the death, they are gone before, they shevved vs the vvay to follovv after, these (good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reader) vvith other things are to be seene throughout these Histories. The Chapiters in the Greeke vvere in many places very small, if I shoulde haue follovved the Greeke diuision, then had I left much vvast paper, I haue sometimes ioyned tvvo or three together, some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times taken them as they lay, yet vvhere I altered the diuision, I noted in the marge the number of the Greeke Chapiters. There is no raigne of any Emperour, no storie almost vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the noting, but thou hast in the marge the yeare of the Lord for the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing therof. VVhatsoeuer I found in the Greeke, vvere it good or bad, that haue I faithfullie vvithout any parcialitie at all laide dovvne in English. VVherfore if ought be vvell done, geue the praise vnto God. let the paines be mine, and the profit the Readers.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>PSAL. 113.</bibl>
      <q>Non nobis Domine, non nobis, sed nomini tuo da gloriam.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>