<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Concerning the Title and the Epi∣stle of the Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121272_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19392</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5819.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121272</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Concerning the Title and the Epi∣stle of the Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver to the two fyrst and principall treatises of a certaine factious libell, put foorth latelie, without name of author or printer, and without approbation by authoritie, vnder the title of An abstract of certeine acts of Parlement: of certaine hir Maiesties iniuctions: of certaine canons, &amp;c : Published by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Cosin, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96, 223, 45, 225-350, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="42"/>
   <pb facs="42"/>
   <head>Concerning the Title and the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of the Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the author of that booke who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, had been mooued of good zeale and conscience (wherof in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery passage of it he giueth euident proofe to the contrary) to haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertised gouernours of this church and church matters, of some whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some lawes <hi>Inforce,</hi> to them) as he pretendeth) <hi>Vnkno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ne,</hi> and therfore necessarilie by them <hi>vnpractised,</hi> to the intente his admonition might indeed haue been profitable heereafter, <hi>For the peaceable gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the church,</hi> it had bin then as much thanke worthie in him, as now, sauoring so strongly of rancor and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it deserueth punishment. But thē would he not haue foisted it to a make-shift, to haue been printed in hugger mugger, but would haue addressed it to those, vnto whom the execution of such pretended necessary, and yet disused lawes, apperteineth: then should not the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted copyes there of, as not daring to looke out at noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, haue beene so soone shufled vp, and sent by hundreds into mutinous places abroad, thought most to fauor such factious writings: then should not his alledged texts of acts, canons, &amp;c: haue come out accompanied with such peruerse glosses <hi>Quae corrumpunt textum,</hi> particularizing at pleasure, <hi>Tanquam</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, vpon such persons as his distempered affections cannot brooke: neither would his booke haue growne to that bignes, but that it might well haue carried the title of an <hi>Abstract,</hi> whereas now by wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and wresting, by shrinking and stretching of lawes, by gnawing and nipping at particular mens dealings ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie, and traducing them <hi>Quasi in veteri comoedia</hi> both the author dooth seeme <hi>Distract</hi> of modestie, and by
<pb facs="43"/> his booke is found <hi>Tanquam sorex proprio iudicio,</hi> to wante that insight in law, that he would so faine be intituled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. In which <hi>Acts, iniuctions, canons, &amp;c:</hi> bicause he was loth to appeare to haue no more skill than ordinarie, he saith they were <hi>For the most part heeretofore vnknowne:</hi> whereby hee must needes <hi>For the most part</hi> holde those excused, of whom they were <hi>vnpractised:</hi> and therefore in his booke ought not so egerlie to haue bitten at them, for vndue practise of such mysteries, as till nowe it pleased him not to reueale vnto them. And surely, looking into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time &amp; occasion, I cannot be otherwise led to thinke, but that this proctor, of peruersenesse being netled that his clients are now by force of hir Maiesties godlie lawes, sought something to be recalled backe, from their fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall breaches of the lawfull vnitie and vniformitie of this church, too long by them vsed to the great anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the papist: and that none of his priuate hot apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies for them do giue anie sufficient colour of law or equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to protect them, dooth now thinke, he shall be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie therfore reuenged, by beating back one naile with another, and by obiecting breach of lawe also vnto those graue Fathers, whome hir Maiestie hath put in authoritie, for reducing of others to conformitie of hir lawes ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall. Whose faults and ouersights (if any such be as are supposed) as they are not by themselues defended, or by others to be excused: so in christian charitie, ought they not in this manner, as <hi>Cham</hi> did his fathers nakednesse, to be laid open, and <hi>Quasi in scena</hi> insulted vpon, to the thrus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting through of religion, by the sides of the ancientest, learnedest, and most godlie professors thereof. Neither dooth it become euery triobolar mate, thus couertlie to carpe, either at hir Maiesties singular wisedom, who with the aduise and assistance of hir renowmed wise Conncell, hath made choise of those Fathers, as hauing more inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie and sufficiencie than he is willing by any meanes to agnise: or at the lawes of the land by parlement heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="43"/> established, where they satisfie not his appetite, not onlye disputing against them, but ouer-ruling <hi>Quasi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria virga,</hi> in what manner they ought to be altered, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deepe iudgement: or so dangerouslye to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force so great innouation, or yet so spitefully to sow seeds of dissention, amongst the Great men of the land. Which course of his, if others should vpon this occasion begin to vse against himselfe, and those whome hee so affecteth by setting downe, out of their speeches, preachings and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, grosse absurdities, and dangerous errors in opinion, and by theyr practise the vyolent breaches of sundrye lawes and statutes of this realme, not committed vpon ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or frailtye, but stoutly stood vnto, and maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; I do coniecture, that both he and they would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye repent them, for offering to put their matter to triall vpon such an issue. But it is well knowne to children, that, although it is <note n="*" place="margin">3. q. 7. c. qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sine c. iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. c. postu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus.</note> most conuenient for him to be free from blame, who is ready to accuse or iudge another, yet one mans fault is not any warrantise for another man to doo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse, and yet howe little hee hath found or effected of that, which hee hoped for, and <hi>Tanto cum hiatu</hi> promised, the discourse following shall (I hope) in parte make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest.</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N his Epistle to the Reader is pretended, these paines of his, cheeflye to haue beene vndertaken, that <hi>By better execution of these lawes, many and notable pointes of such contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies as haue beene a long time amongst vs, might more easilye and speedily by the same lawes he decided.</hi> By which controuersies and contention about <hi>Reformation of Ecclesiasticall discipline and popish ceremonies,</hi> he sayth, <hi>The quiet and peaceable estate both of the church and common-wealth, haue beene shrewdlye troubled, and brought in hazard.</hi> Surely though his wish of excommunication, not to be inflicted by one alone, would (if it were expedient)
<pb facs="44"/> put some of them in a kinde of <hi>Paradise,</hi> of obteining their souereigntie of seniors in euery parish, the want whereof breedeth these threats of <hi>hazard</hi> to the common-wealth, and which is the onely thing they meane, by <hi>Reformation of ecclesiasticall discipline,</hi> and the <hi>Helena</hi> which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, naie the popedome which they gape after, as though no other course (this now in vse being once abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated) could be taken or deuised, but that: yet can I not conceiue, but their seniors, which will sometime inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle vnder pretense of conscience or charitie, with euery kinde of matter most ciuill, euen to the reuersall of iudgements, as is notorious where that consistorie is set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled: shall leese as much another way, if all matters nowe handled in ecclesiasticall courts should <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 234.</note> (according to this mans deuise) as meere ciuill causes bee haled away from them, vnto the temporall courts. As for all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of the booke, if this turbulent <hi>Tribune,</hi> might of his absolute power, inspire them with the life of lawes: they would no more do good vnto his clients about their breaches or impugnings of the booke of <hi>Common prayer,</hi> or for their hot skirmishing with the ceremonies of our church, odiously by him termed <hi>Popish,</hi> than <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or the smoke of a hot ladle would do good to a man that is hungrie. And therefore herein, he hath not (otherwise than by tickling factious humors, which are delighted to heare their betters girded) any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot pleasured <hi>His brethren and neighbors,</hi> for whose <hi>sakes</hi> hee hath atchieued this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie peece of worke. Another cause is alledged for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise of this worke, <hi>The defense of hir Highnes lawes,</hi> How many of these by him brought, are to be called in trueth hir Maiesties lawes in force, remaineth to bee discussed. But how agreeth this with that <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 238.</note> part of his booke, where he calleth these hir Maiesties lawes and all <hi>The ecelesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call law popish, to be abandoned, and as a froth or filth to be spew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
      <note place="margin">A contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note>
      <hi>out of the common-weale: that hir Maiestie cannot gratifie hir capitall enimie so much, as by authorising and practising his
<pb facs="44"/> lawes: that it were not a dodkin matter, all the bookes thereof were laid on a heape in Smithfield, and sacrificed in a fire vnto the Lord: &amp;c.</hi> Such faults as these being <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> will seldome be wanting <hi>In multiloquio.</hi> But I pray God, send hir Maiesties lawes better patrones, than such: as in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished booke dare dispute against sundry of them, father such for lawes as be not, and which he himselfe in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality dooth condemne: and which fostereth and cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth manifest and wilfull breakers of hir Maiesties lawes in deed, and also inueigheth bitterly against such, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to law and trust reposed in them, by hir Maiesty, do seeke to reforme and reclaime such offendors of lawe, from their former contempts, in despight of whom, and in fauor of such wilfull law breakers, all in this booke to haue beene written, a man which hath but halfe an eye, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silie discerne: and not <hi>In defense of hir Highnesse lawes,</hi> as hypocriticallie is auouched, neither yet for any <hi>Peace and prosperitie in the wals and palaces of Ierusalem,</hi> which I praye God by other better meanes than this, to grant to this church, vnder the long, peaceable, and prosperous go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of our souereigne Ladye Elizabeth, for his Christes sake: Amen.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The Booke, Pag. 1, &amp; 2.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E read of some politike capteines of this our countrie, that haue partlye vsed the arrowes shotte shorte at themselues, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst theyr enimies, and partlye haue suffered them to sticke still, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noye theyr fyrst owners at the ioyning
<pb facs="45"/> of the battell: euen so, our author is heere content verye politikely, to alledge against vs the establishing by act of parlement 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. of <hi>Canons, constitutions, ordinances, and sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodals prouinciall,</hi> to the intent, and in hope to beat vs with our owne weapons, and not for any loue or liking he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto them: which he sufficiently bewrayeth in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 238.</note> partes of his booke, and is sory (I dare saye) that so much of them is in force. And although it cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that many of them were published by latter Popes, after that See was become the chaire of pestilence, a cage of vncleane birds: <hi>Et postquam ciuitas fidelis facta fuit mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix:</hi> yet such amongst them as fight not with the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting worde of GOD, or the lawes and customes of this land, beeing set downe no doubt by aduise of the best learned lawyers in those times, though vnder Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs authority, and beeing now indenized and made English by the whole church and common-weale in parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are no more in that regarde to be abandoned, than wheate because it was inuented by the heathen goddesse <hi>Ceres,</hi> many good ciuill lawes of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> set out by Paynims and cruell persecutors of Gods saints, (for no one author of the <hi>Pandects</hi> is thought to haue beene chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian but <hi>Gaius)</hi> or than pretious Stones, and gold of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir</hi> in <hi>Salomons</hi> time, because as some <note n="*" place="margin">Goropius.</note> thinke they were fet from among the <hi>Cannibals,</hi> eaters of mans flesh, and other partes nowe called the <hi>West Indies,</hi> beeing both then and now grosse idolaters. And howsoeuer many of the said Canons, &amp;c: doo carrye with them, the drosse and superstition of those times, beeing promulged for the vpholding of Poperye: yet for many points (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue) all the best heads now in the worlde beeing layd togither, and taking no light from thence, were not in many yeares able for sinceritie and equitie, to set downe the like ordinances in those causes. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, seeing they were both vpon mature deliberation of the best lawyers deliuered, and were so long in gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="45"/> together, vpon seuerall occasions, from time to time falling out, which for the varietie of them, no one mans life is possible to haue experience of, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ns wit not able to forecast or prouide for. But I muse how this could so escape the criticall and <hi>Lynceus</hi> eyes of such an <hi>Aristarchus,</hi> as that he which rappeth out so many syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gismes in <hi>Barbara</hi> and <hi>Darij,</hi> throughout his whole booke, should be so ignorant (for I will not say it was of malice) as, in that argument which he maketh the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke to set his whole frame vpon, to deliuer vs a <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, by curtaling off, in <hi>Assumpto</hi> a <note place="margin">A childish fallacie in his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reason.</note> peece of his <hi>Dedium,</hi> and so <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> to make <hi>Quatuor terminos</hi> in his principall syllogisme. For although it be confessed on all partes, <hi>Such canons, constitutions, &amp;c: as be not contrariant nor repugnant to the lawes, statutes, and customes of this Realme, nor to the damage or hurte of the Queenes prerogatiue roiall, as they were vsed and executed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the making of that act, shall nowe still bee vsed and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> yet if hee would haue assumed in his <hi>Minor</hi> propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition (as by the rules of reason and reasoning hee ought to haue doone) that those points which he toucheth in his booke, were <hi>Not repugnant to the customes of this realme, but were in vse and execution before the making of that act.</hi> (All which hee cunningly left out:) then because wee learne by law, <hi>Quòd facta non praesumuntur,</hi> matters in fact are not intended to be doone, till they be prooued so: we would haue put him to his proofe heerein, as wee must doo still, and in the meane time say, that he hath gaped wide to say nothing to the purpose, and that in his whole booke he hath talked, but not reasoned. So that till he can make it appeare, that <hi>The canons specified in any parte of his treatise, are not contrariant or repuguant to the customes of this realme, but were vsed and executed before the making of that act:</hi> hee can not inforce the vse of them now, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the act limited to bee vsed and executed no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, but as they were before the making of it. Which
<pb facs="46"/> answer might serue, without anye more adoo, vnto his whole discourse, which therfore hangeth no otherwise to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, than <hi>Scopae dissolute,</hi> or than a rope of sand. Yet wee will not deale so sparingly and peremptorily with the man, but will shewe vnto him diuers canons, constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and synodals prouinciall, neither <hi>Contrarie nor repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the lawes, nor to the damage or hurt of hir Maiesties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue royall,</hi> which hauing not by the <hi>customes</hi> of this realme beene <hi>vsed,</hi> and executed, he himselfe being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aduised, will not say to be in force of law, or now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to be put in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e or practise. And although the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall worde of <hi>Constitutions,</hi> put downe in the act may seeme to extend vnto constitutions made by christian emperours, for ecclesiasticall persons and matters, as the author seemeth to thinke, whereof sundry to this purpose might bee brought: <label type="milestone">
            <seg type="milestoneunit">Pag. </seg>16</label> yet because it is put after <hi>Canons,</hi> whereof (sauing some canons for matter of faith agreed on before, by certaine generall counsels) there were but fewe set out at that time: I doo coniecture uone other constitutions to be ment thereby, but such <hi>Prouinciall,</hi> as were gathered together by <hi>Lindewood,</hi> or <hi>Nationall,</hi> as were framed by <hi>Ottho</hi> and <hi>Octobonus:</hi> and therefore I will not wearie the reader with such superfluous allegations. First therefore to begin with the canons collected by <hi>Gratian,</hi> it wyll easilye appeare that there be very many such which are neither repugnant to any lawes that I doo know, or haue heard reported for lawes within this land, nor hurtfull any way to hir Maiesties royall prerogatiue, which yet are by generall <hi>custome</hi> thereof, so long disu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that no man can iustlye say they are in force still, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, which for breuitie sake, I will set downe in as shorte a summarye as I can finde them gathered. <note n="a" place="margin">De confir. dist. 5. c. cont.</note> That rules of Physike are to be holden as contrary to a diuine state, which in some case forbid fasting. <note n="b" place="margin">Ibid. c. vt ieium. c. vt episc.</note> That none are to confirme, or to bee confirmed, but fasting. <note n="c" place="margin">c. in Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. dist. 4. de Baptismo.</note> That baptisme must bee conferred with
<pb facs="46"/> three dippings into the water. <note n="d" place="margin">c. perue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> dist. 3. de feriis.</note> That a man may not fast on the Thursday. <note n="e" place="margin">c. quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ibidem.</note> That on the Lords day, or in the feast of Whitsontide, in prayeng wee ought not to kneele. <note n="f" place="margin">c. ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am 1. dist. 1. de feriis.</note> That a church may not bee consecrated to holy assemblies, wherein a pagan or heathen hath beene buryed. <note n="g" place="margin">Dist. 3. de paenit. per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> That publike and solemne penance may not twise be inflicted. <note n="h" place="margin">32. q. 1. c. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud S. crimen.</note> That women may not sue their husbands for adulterie. <note n="i" place="margin">32. q. 1. c. sicut.</note> That he is an abbettor of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse, that putteth not away his adultres wife. <note n="k" place="margin">30. q. 3. c. quod autem.</note> That a man and a wife may not promise for a child in baptisme togither. <note n="l" place="margin">30. q. 1. c. peruenit.</note> That if a man by any casualtie should offer his owne childe to the Bishop to be confirmed, he ought to be separated from his wife. <note n="m" place="margin">28. q. 1. c. idololat.</note> That a man may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put away his wife, which seeketh to persuade him to that which is euill. <note n="n" place="margin">Ibid. c. non solum.</note> That she which maketh an image. and will not repent, is to be put away by the husband. <note n="o" place="margin">26. q. 2. sed &amp; illud.</note> That it is a kinde of idolatry to search after the course of the starres. <note n="p" place="margin">24 q 2. c. vlt.</note> That heretikes after theyr death are to be excommunicated. <note n="q" place="margin">23. q. 8. c. si nulla.</note> That without great necessitie, it is not lawfull to goe to warre in Lent time. <note n="r" place="margin">23. q. 4. c. sicut.</note> That with the enemyes to religion, wee are bounde to wage warre. <note n="s" place="margin">22. q. 5. c. honestum.</note> That a man ought to bee fasting when he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an oath. <note n="t" place="margin">Ibid. c. si quis conuictu</note> That hee shall neuer during life be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to communicate, which hath suborned periurye. <note n="u" place="margin">22. q. 2. c. dolo.</note> That hee may bee accounted to haue forsworne himselfe, that goeth about to doo otherwise than hee hath promised. <note n="x" place="margin">15. q. 3. c. terrio.</note> That a woman may not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to accuse a priest, or to beare witnesse against him. <note n="y" place="margin">14. q. 2. c. quanquam.</note> That to publike instruments, priests are not to bee called to beare witnesse. <note n="z" place="margin">14. q. 1. c. Episcopus.</note> That a Bishop though hee bee vrged, ought not to go to law about temporall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <note n="a" place="margin">12 q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. c. vlt.</note> That a Byshop dyeng intestate, the church succeedeth wholye into all hys goods. <note n="b" place="margin">12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. 4. c. presbyter.</note> That of those things which priests doo buie, they should make the writings in the churches name. <note n="c" place="margin">12. q. 2. c. Episcopus.</note> That a Bishop ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no heyre, ought to make the church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ys heyre.
<pb facs="47"/>
         <note n="d" place="margin">12. q. 1. c. dilect.</note> That all clearkes are to liue togither in a communitie. <note n="e" place="margin">11. q. 3. c. Clericus.</note> That he which would appeale from a Bishop, must she to a synod <note n="f" place="margin">11. q. 3. c. si Episcopus.</note> That a priest, which is deposed by a Bishop must complaine thereof to the next Bishops. <note n="g" place="margin">1. q. 1. c. decreuimus.</note> That the Bishop ought yearely to visit his diocesse. <note n="h" place="margin">Ibidem. c. antiquos.</note> That hee ought to haue the halfe of all oblations. <note n="i" place="margin">2. q. 7. c. ipsi.</note> That none should be admitted to accuse or testifie against a Priest, which either was not or could not bee a priest himselfe. <note n="k" place="margin">Ibid. c. oues.</note> That the sheepe ought not to accuse the sheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, except the swarue from the true faith. <note n="l" place="margin">Ibid. c. sicut.</note> That lay men may not accuse cleargie men, nor cleargie men those of the laitie. <note n="m" place="margin">2. q. 5. c. nullam.</note> That a Bishop cannot be condemned, but with seuentie and two witnesses. <note n="n" place="margin">3. q. 4. c. sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum.</note> That an oth is not to be exacted of priests. <note n="o" place="margin">1. q. 2. c. Clericos.</note> That he which is able to sustaine himselfe of his owne charges, should receiue no stipend of the church. <note n="p" place="margin">c. dictum est dist. 94.</note> That Archdeacons should not exercise iurisdiction ouer priests. <note n="q" place="margin">c. Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. dist. 93.</note> That there ought to be seauen Deacons in euery citye. <note n="r" place="margin">c. si euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelia. dist. 55.</note> That a priest which hath lost his eye, is not to receiue anye duties. <note n="s" place="margin">c. aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos. dist. 51.</note> That such as haue serued in warres, or haue sued in courts after they were baptized, may not bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned. <note n="t" place="margin">c. illud. dist. 50.</note> That it is not lawfull for a clearke to doo publike and solemne penance, nor for him▪ that hath such penance to be performed, to be ordeined. <note n="u" place="margin">c. non oportet dist. 42.</note> That it is not lawfull to eat, or to haue a bed set in a place that is dedicated to God. <note n="x" place="margin">c. elegant. dist. 37.</note> That Bishops are to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended which traine vp theyr children in humaine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <note n="y" place="margin">c. Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ibidem.</note> That Bishops may not read bookes compiled by heathen men. <note n="z" place="margin">c. Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri dist. 34.</note> That priests may not be at mariage feasts. <note n="a" place="margin">c. denique d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>st. 4.</note> That those which be in clericall orders, should begin to fast at <hi>Quinquagesima.</hi>
         <note n="b" place="margin">gl. in verb. supra vires c. illud 10. q. 3.</note> That all clerks should absteine from flesh, seauen whole weekes before Easter. <note n="c" place="margin">ad eius dist. 5,</note> That a Bishop when he visiteth, must haue nothing to drinke but milke. And that a husband ought not to keepe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye with his wife, till the childe that was borne betwixt
<pb facs="47"/> them were weaned, with diuers other not vnlike to these. In like manner there be diuers other parts of the canon law, which neither beeing repugnant to any lawes in this land, nor hurtefull to hir Maiesties prerogatiue: yet being disused, and therefore repugnant to the customes of the realme, doo stand in no force with vs at this day.</p>
      <p>As (<note n="a" place="margin">c. cum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses &amp;c. rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum extra de testamentis.</note>] where it is required to the testification of euerie testament, euen in that which is <hi>Ad pias causas,</hi> that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the parish be present, beside two other suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent witnesses. Whereas by generall custome among vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and as it is testified by diuers lawyers reports herevpon, two good witnesses are sufficient. Also if a man make his sonne his heire, or (as we equiualently to that do now vse and speake) his vniuersall and sole executor, and do charge him to pay and make ouer to some other his whole goods, dues, and credits, by the canon lawe he <note n="b" place="margin">c. Rainuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp;c. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naldus extra. de testam.</note> may retaine <hi>Legitimam iure naturae debitum,</hi> his childs part, which by the ciuill law <hi>Falcidia &amp; T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ebellianica</hi> is a fourth part, but by the canon law a third part: and also the fourth part of the remnant <hi>per Trebellianicam,</hi>
         <note n="c" place="margin">L. Papini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus S. si quis impubes ff▪ de en off. testam. iuncta gl in S. meminisse ib.</note> especially if the said charge were to be performed after some certaine day or condition happening: yet by the custome in England which hath preuailed, he shal in this case without either of these deductions, so long as there is <hi>Assetzentre les mains des biens &amp; chattels paternelles,</hi> restore and pay according to the deuise comprised in the will. <note n="d" place="margin">c. 2. Ext. de adulteriis.</note> Again, if a single man commit fornication with a single woman not espoused to any, he is to end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> wher with a dowrie in stead of hir father, and to take her to wife, according to the like law of God in the 22. of <hi>Exod.</hi> And the canon addeth, that if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to marrie hir, hee shall besides endowing of her, bee also corporally chastised: yet we haue no such necessarie exacting of a dowrye in vse among vs. <note n="e" place="margin">De conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. dist. 3. c. celebritatem &amp; 6. q. 1. c. om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c. illi qui.</note> Moreouer, by the canon law euery sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> is reputed to make a man infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, which is not obserued in England. <note n="f" place="margin">c. hoc ius. 12. q. 2.</note> Likewise the canons do forbid, any thing belonging to the church
<pb facs="48"/> to be sould any whit aboue the iust value, which is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired nor looked vnto in this realme. <note n="g" place="margin">L. scimus C. de iure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberandi. &amp; l. haere ditariis C. de haered. acti.</note> Furthermore, though both by the ciuill law and practise in this land, the heire or executor is not tyed to pay more than the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie (truly made) will amount vnto: yet the <note n="h" place="margin">c. in literis Ext. de rapt. 16. q. 6. c. si. Episcopum.</note> canon law seemeth not so to distinguish, but to bind the heire or executor, to whom any part of the deads goods do come, to a full satisfaction. And the canon law seemeth wholy to <note n="i" place="margin">c. 1. de tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neamentis c. vnico de sagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> condemne by the word <hi>Torneamenta,</hi> all iusting, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at tilt, tourney, or such like commendable exercise of the body vsed in England. Yea, and elsewhere prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth euen our notable old renowmed defence of arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to be vsed against any christians. <note n="k" place="margin">c. 1. &amp; 2. dist. 6.</note> Moreouer, the canons (cleane contrarie to the practise in many places of England) do forbid all bastards to beare any office of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit or charge. And I thinke that it is not ordinarily in practise in this realme, if a cleargy man being a patron, do present an vnworthy clearke to a benefice, that thereby the right of collating should be deuolued to the superior, which the <note n="l" place="margin">c. cum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Ext. de off. ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ii &amp;c. cum in cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>s Ext. de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione.</note> canons do appoint against him as a punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Moreouer though the canon <note n="m" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. cum in off. Ext. de te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</note> law be directly to the contrary, yet it is a general custome through England, and so testified to be by the <note n="n" place="margin">Gl. in verb. lega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. c. statut. prouin. constit. de consuetud.</note> glosse in <hi>Lindewood,</hi> that a beneficed person may freely declare his last wyll and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>h mooueable goods as he is poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssed of, being gotten in respect of the church. And againe, euen against our owne prouinciall constitutions, custome in some part hath very farre preuailed. For the constitution prouinciall is so farre from taking away from the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors the emblements sowne vpon the glebe land by the incumbent afore his death: that if hee doo <note n="o" place="margin">Prou. Constitutio. De consuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine c. nullus Rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>or.</note> liue till the feast of the Annunciation of the blessed Virgin, all the fruits which for the other part of the yeare are to be receiued, shall be imployed to the paiment of his debts, and fulfilling of his legacies and deuises: which now is generally growne out of vse▪ and the exetutors of such a
<pb facs="48"/> beneficed person shall haue no more fruites, what ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> soeuer the incumbent shall dye, but that which the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> of his death (whether it were haye, corne, or fruite) was seuered from the free hold. Which course I haue read to haue beene also obserued, euen before the statute of 28 <hi>Hen</hi> 8. Besides it <note n="p" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap> 3. H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Encumbent &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>b. 1.</note> appeareth by diuers bookes at the common law, that if a beneficed person doo die before the conception of our Ladie (as they terme it) being the 8. of December, the emblements and corne which he had sowne before vpon his glebe-land, are due to his successor, and not to his executor. There is another <hi>Constitution</hi> also out of vse, as being such, which custome hath very<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> long preuailed against<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that in a cause of matrimonie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> sentence were giuen for the matrimonie, the aduocate which was of counsell against the matrimonie, should bee suspended from practise, by the space of one whole yeare afterwards. And againe, there was a prouinciall <note n="q" place="margin">Prou. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> stit. de vita &amp; honesta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ricorum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution made, being neither repugnant to the lawes of this land, nor preiudiciall to hir Maiesties royall preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, for certaine kinde of apparell, not to bee worne by any cleargie man: which I may not doubt but our Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractor and all his complices will easilye graunt to bee past date, as being foreworne by contrarye custome. Like as there bee some other also, which though I doo no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> doubt but that they obteyne still the force of lawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, yet these men will willinglye yeelde to bee sufficient, that they haue lost theyr string, euen by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome it selfe. Albeit the Abstractor left it foorth of the Minor of his mayne syllogisme, as though it were not able to impeach the validitie of a lawe once establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. <note n="r" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> For a <hi>Constitution prouinciall decideth, that hee which denyeth that a Synod assembled may not make such lawes, which may inhibit a preacher from preaching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ill hee bee tryed, is to bee excommunicated.</hi> Which is to be vnderstood of such lawes as were established in conuocation before any acte of Parlement was set downe to abridge that libertye. Againe, <note n="s" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bidem</note> another constitution hath d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>creed▪
<pb facs="49"/> that <hi>Where either the clergie or the people of any place, haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any man to preach which is not licenced, there that church should be interdicted.</hi> And another hath <note n="t" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> also determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that <hi>If a preacher before the clergie shall preach of the faults of the laitie, or before the people shall preach of enormities of the clergie, he shall be punished by the Ordinarie of the place, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the qualitie of his offense.</hi> These fewe thus alledged, being such as for the present time I could hit vpon, I thought good to touch as a surplusage for the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest refelling of the crafty defectiue Minor of his chiefe argument, which if he had dealt plainly in, and had laide foorth the <hi>Medium</hi> thereof fully, as it is in the act of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, he could not but haue foreseene, that hee should haue had more adoo, to haue prooued all those <hi>Canons,</hi> which he alledgeth to <hi>Haue beene vsed and executed before the making of the said act,</hi> in such sort as he would vrge: than he had to gather so much stuffe togither in view of the simple, being in truth to so slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der purpose, in the iudgement euen of all such as be but euen meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye skilled in those lawes.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>