<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Worshipfull Maister Robert Cicell Esquire, one of the Sonnes of the right hono∣rable the Lord high treasurer of England.</title>
           <author>Hichcock, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121812_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11493</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21744</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121812</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Worshipfull Maister Robert Cicell Esquire, one of the Sonnes of the right hono∣rable the Lord high treasurer of England.</title>
                 <author>Hichcock, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The quintesence of wit : being a corrant comfort of conceites, maximies, and poleticke deuises, selected and gathered together by Francisco Sansouino. VVherin is set foorth sundrye excellent and wise sentences, worthie to be regarded and followed. Translated out of the Italian tung, and put into English for the benefit of all those that please to read and vnderstand the works and worth of a worthy writer</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 66, 66-81, 81-98, 4 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right Worshipfull Maister <hi>Robert Cicell</hi> Esquire, one of the Sonnes of the right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord high treasurer of <hi>England.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N reading and reuiewing</hi> the manifolde discourses and famous works of sundry worthie writers, (right Worshipfull) some translated out of French, Italian, and some reduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our English tung, by learned Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestes and Grecians, (whose studies and labours benefites a multitude) I happened on a book written to <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the second, (a mighty, graue and wise Emperour) which book treated on so many mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and touched with quick conceites and sentences, such a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of rare arguments and politicke deuises, that it seemed not only a register of wit, but a naturall quintesence of knowledge, gathered and collected out of the highest and deuine spirites of Philosophie, the value and varietie of the worke is so excellent: that it argues of it selfe to be a rich store-house of precious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundes, fraught and furnished full of deep insight and profound reasons. Then to hide or keep secret the same worke, were an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable error, and a wilfull offence and fault committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the common societie of men, that dayly and hourely are nourished and fedde with the sweet and sugred taste of Histories, and vnderstanding of true nouelties, penned out with painefull studie, and printed to exercise wise iudgements with matters of great moment. So vnder your fauour good Sir, the hope of your <pb facs="3"/> towardnes and good bringing vp, and the desire I suppose you haue to aduaunce learning and good letters, (the sensible sap of life) commaunds me by a bond of causes, to honor you with a work not only worthy the reading, but likewise worthie the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and bearing in minde, a burthen so pleasant to embrace and delectable to carry in memory, as shall vnload and make light a heauie hart, and discharge a waighty imagination of disquiet thoughts. For the dissoluing of doubts, and discouering o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> secret sentences: breedes a lightsomnes in man, and puts away the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of time, and labour of the spirites, such care and foresight of our commoditie had our fore-fathers and auncient writers, that alwaies they filled the Printers shops full of great vollumes, and maintained the worldes knowledge with an innumerable number of bookes, and neuer in any age bookes were more sought for and better esteemed (if the authors therof be of sound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) then in these our florishing daies, where flowing wittes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound and reapes the reward of well dooing and vertuous dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition. The praise, preferments, great fame and good fortunes they haue found: is such a gazing glasse to looke in, that thousands therby seek after vertue and learning, to shun the rebuke of vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous idlenes and sloath, none more disliked then ignorant Idiots, nor more admired then the worthie wits of our world. Who is not abashed to follow a painted shadowe? and who takes not great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to waite where some substance is looked for? though the wise for their wisedome are enuied of the foolish, yet the fond for their folly are derided and pointed at by all kinde of people, wisdome is honoured in his meanest attire, and fondnes is but scorned in his brauest garments, the bare presentation of the honorable, brings gladnes to the beholders, and the proud pomp of the vain-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, are both irckesome and disdained, golde is more made off for his goodnes then his cullour, and men look more into the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of things then to the outward apparance, this book though it be printed in common paper, yet was it not penned in ordinarye discourses, it spreadeth it self like a tree that hath many braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whereon some bowe is greater then another, and yet the <pb facs="3"/> fruit of them all are alike in taste, because no soure crabbes were graffed where sweet Apples should growe, nor no bitter Oranges can be gathered where sweet Powngarnets are planted, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this fruit, must be sencibly felt and tasted with a well seasoned minde and iudgement, and the delicatenes therof must be chewed and chawed with a chosen and speciall spirite of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, not greedily mumbled vp and eaten as a wanton eates Peares that neuer were pared. Philosophie and farre fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched knowledge may not be handled and entertained like a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury tale, nor vsed like a riding rime of sir Topas, (this spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the generall iudgements of men) for I know to whose hands this woork is commended, and I doubt not the vsage therof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I see some good sparkes of a noble Father, shining in the eyes of a happie Sonne, wherefore this booke needes not feare (as I hope and beleeue) who barketh against it, nor the writer thereof (if he were aliue) neeeds not to doubt who looketh on his labours, for generally and absolutely (in a most louing phrase and manner) he bountifully hath imparted his secrets te a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and bestowed a great deale of thankeful paines on the wise, if the worlde be not ingrate and forgetfull of a good turn offred, he setteth foorth to sale, no speeches farssed full of fables, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senteth to our viewe (in an open manner) heapes of hidden se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, that none but noble and venerable aucthors did euer open before, and in a manner leaues neither peace, warre, pollicy, prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice nor any thing vntouched, that is fit for a publike state or common weale to knowe, his golden booke beautified with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand graces, is translated out of the Italian tung, though not in such beauty as becomes the grauitie thereof, yet stripped gentlye out of his gaye garments, it is clothed and plainely apparelled in such comely weeds and cleane roabes, as euery parte and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the booke may easily be seene and well perceiued, and albeit that a fine Italian in an English groce gaberdine is not fashioned in all formes to please euery strangers fancye, yet the personage may be passable when all comelines is vsed for the setting forth of the same. Thus presuming that <hi>Francis Sanssouino</hi> is no whit <pb facs="4"/> disfigured to walke openly in such English habit as is found fitte for him (crauing fauour that he may speak his owne minde) I hope you of curtesie will let him passe through our Countrey, that all kinde of people may see and heare what opinion he was of, in matters of state and mighty affaires of this worlde, the booke is dedicated vnto you, for many good considerations, one is that by your meanes a second life may be breathed into <hi>Sansouinoes</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections through your good liking, and being reuiued (or awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of a long sleep) when it lay dead from our common know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it may shewe some such singular spirit: as shall reioice both men of greatest capacitie and meanest iudgements, so commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the worthines of the matter to your censure and protection, (alwaies hoping my good will and good meaning shall be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) I take my leaue, leauing you to the blessing of God, and to iudge fauourably of my boldenes, and wishing you encrease of woorship and credit, euen such as your selfe can desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours at commaundement in that he may.</hi> Robert Hichcock.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>