<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>From the Author OF The Illustrations.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121639_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A97346</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7228</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121639</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>From the Author OF The Illustrations.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chorographicall description of all the tracts, riuers, mountains, forests, and other parts of this renowned isle of Great Britain : with intermixture of the most remarkeable stories, antiquities, wonders, rarities, pleasures, and commodities of the same. Diuided into tw bookes; the latter containing twelue songs, neuer before imprinted. Digested into a poem by Michael Drayton. Esquire. With a table added, for direction to those occurrences of story and antiquitie, whereunto the course of the volume easily leades not</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                            <distributor>Dewe, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 303, 9 pages, 18 folded plates, maps, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="annotator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>From the Author OF The <hi>Illustrations.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>PErmit mee thus much of these Notes to My Friend. What the Verse oft, with allusion, as supposing a full knowing Reader, lets slip; or in winding steps of Personating Fictions (as some times) so infolds, that suddaine conceipt cannot abstract a Forme of the clothed Truth, I haue, as I might, <hi>Illustrated. Breuity,</hi> and <hi>Plainenes</hi> (as the one endur'd the Other) I haue ioyned; purposely auoyding frequent commixture of different language; and, whensoeuer it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, eyther the Page or Margine (specially for <hi>Gentlewomens</hi> sake) summarily interprets it, except where Interpretation aides not. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not very Prodigall of my Historicall Faith, after <hi>Explanation,</hi> I oft aduenture on <hi>Examination,</hi> and <hi>Censure.</hi> The Author, in Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages of <hi>first Inhabitants, Name, State,</hi> and <hi>Monarchique succession</hi> in this Isle, followes <hi>Geffrey ap Arthur, Polychronicon, Matthew</hi> of <hi>West minster,</hi> and such more. Of their Traditions, for that one so much controuerted, and by <hi>Cambro-Britons</hi> still maintayned, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Troian Brute,</hi> I haue (but as an Aduocat for the Muse) argued; disclaiming in it, if alledg'd for my own Opinion. In most of the rest, vpon weighing the Reporters credit, Comparison with more perswading authority, and <hi>Synchronisme</hi> (the best Touch-stone in this kind of Triall) I leaue note of Suspicion, or adde coniecturall Amendment: as, for particular examples, among other, in <hi>Brennus</hi> mistooke by all Writers of later time, sollowing <hi>Iustins</hi> Epitome of <hi>Trogus</hi> ill conceiu'd; in <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Swaphams</hi> Story of K. <hi>Wulphers</hi> murdring his Children; in <hi>Rollo</hi> first D. of <hi>Normandy</hi> his time; none of them yet rectified (although the first hath been aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on) by any that I haue seene; and such more. And indeed my Iealousie hath oft vext me with particular inquisition of whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer occurrs, bearing not a marke of most apparant Truth, euer since I found so intollerable Antichronismes, incredible reports, and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> impostures, as well from Ignorance as assum'd liberty of Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in some of our Ancients; and red also such palpable Fauxeties, of our Nation, thrust into the World by Later Time: as (to giue a tast) that of <hi>Randall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> affirming the Beginning of <hi>Wards</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Hen.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Polydores</hi> assertion (vpon mistaking of the Statute of I.
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Hen.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.) that <hi>it was death by the</hi> English <hi>laws for any man to weare a Visard,</hi> with many like errors in his History, of our <hi>Trials</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Shriues, Coate</hi> of the Kingdome, <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and other like; <hi>Bartol's</hi> deliuering the custome in this Isle to be, <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Ad C. de summ. Trinit. l. 1. num. 4. 2. Vnum blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis, ad pulsū linguae longè mellitum.</hi> Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius <hi>De Aur. Asin. 6.</hi> and you may remember (as like enough he did) that in <hi>Plautus Curcul. Qui vult Cubare pangit saltèm suauium,</hi> &amp; such more in other wanton Poets, with the opiniō of <hi>Baldus,</hi> that a Kisse in those Southerne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent consent to imperfit espcu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sels, nothing of that kind, but <hi>Copulation,</hi> with vs &amp; our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Dutch</hi> being so. <hi>E'v <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, quae nempè verior videtur lectio.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>quod Primogenitus succe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in omnibus Bonis;</hi> The <hi>Greeke Chalcondylas</hi> his slanderous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of our vsuall forme of kind entertainment to begin with the Wiues Courteous admission to that most affected pleasure of Lasciuious fancy (he was deceiu'd by misunderstanding the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Our <hi>Kissing Salutations,</hi> giuen and accepted amongst vs with more freedom then in any part of the Southern world, errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously thinking, perhaps, that euery Kisse must be thought seconded with that addition to the Seuen promist by <hi>Mercury</hi> in name of <hi>Venus</hi> to him that should find <hi>Psyche;</hi> or as wanton, as <hi>Aristophanes</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:) and many vntruth's of like Nature in Others. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Arcadian deduction of our <hi>British</hi> Monarchy; within that time, from <hi>Brate,</hi> suppos'd about <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. of the world (<hi>Samuel</hi> then Iudge of <hi>Israel</hi>) vnto some <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. before <hi>Christ</hi> (about when, <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> visited the Island) no Relation was extant, which is now left to our vse. How then are they, which pretend Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologies of that Age without any Fragment of Authors before <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, Taliessin</hi> and <hi>Nennius</hi> (the eldest of which was since D. of <hi>Christ</hi>) to be credited? For my part, I beleeue much in them as I do the finding of <hi>Hiero's</hi> Shipmast in our <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Ad C. de summ. Trinit. l. 1. num. 4. 2. Vnum blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis, ad pulsū linguae longè mellitum.</hi> Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius <hi>De Aur. Asin. 6.</hi> and you may remember (as like enough he did) that in <hi>Plautus Curcul. Qui vult Cubare pangit saltèm suauium,</hi> &amp; such more in other wanton Poets, with the opiniō of <hi>Baldus,</hi> that a Kisse in those Southerne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent consent to imperfit espcu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sels, nothing of that kind, but <hi>Copulation,</hi> with vs &amp; our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Dutch</hi> being so. <hi>E'v <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, quae nempè verior videtur lectio.</hi>
      </note> Mountaines, which is collected vpon a corrupted place in <hi>Athenaeus,</hi> cited out of <hi>Moschi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> or, that <hi>Ptolemy Philadelph</hi> sent to <hi>Reutha</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> some <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. yeares since, for discouery of this Country, which <hi>Claudè Ptolemy</hi> afterward put in his Geography; or that <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> built <hi>Arthurs Hoffen</hi> in <hi>Stirling</hi> Shirifdome; or, that <hi>Britons</hi> were at the Rape of <hi>Hesione</hi> with <hi>Hercules,</hi> as our excellent with <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi> of <hi>Excester</hi> (published falsly vnder name of <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi>) sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: which are euen equally warrantable, as <hi>Ariosto's</hi> Narrations <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Persons and Places in his <hi>Rowlands, Spensers</hi> Elfin Story, or <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> his strange discoueries. Yet the Capricious faction will (I know) neuer quit their Beliefe of wrong; although some <hi>Elias</hi> or <hi>Delian</hi> Diuer should make open what is so inquired after. Briefly, vntill <hi>Polybius,</hi> who wrote neere <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. since (for <hi>Aristotle</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> is cleerely counterfeited in title) no <hi>Greeke</hi> mentions the Isle; vntill <hi>Lucreti'</hi> (some <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. years later) no <hi>Roman</hi> hath exprest a thought of vs; vntill <hi>Caesars</hi> Commentaries, no piece of its description was known, that is now left to posterity. For time therefore preceding <hi>Caesar,</hi> I dare trust none; but with Others adhere to <hi>Coniecture.</hi> In An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter since, I relie on <hi>Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Dio</hi> especially, <hi>Vopiscus, Capitolin, Spartian</hi> (for so much as they haue, and the rest of the <hi>Augustan</hi> Story) afterward <hi>Gildas, Nennius</hi> (but little is left of them, and that of the last very imperfect) <hi>Bede, Asserio, Ethelwerd</hi> (neere of bloud to King <hi>Alfred) William</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury, Marian,
<pb facs="7"/>
Florence of Worcester</hi> (that published vnder name of <hi>Florence</hi> hath the very syllables of most part of <hi>Marian</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> Story, fraught with <hi>English</hi> Antiquities; which will shew you how easily to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer <hi>Buchanan's</hi> obiection against our Historians about <hi>Athelstans</hi> being King of all <hi>Albion,</hi> being deceiu'd when he imagined that there was no other of <hi>Marian</hi> but the common printed Chronicle, which is indeed but an Epitome or Defloration made by <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Hereford</hi> vnder <hi>Hen.</hi> I.) and the numerous rest of our Monkish and succeeding Chronographers. In all, I beleeue him most which freest from <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Hate</hi> (causes of corruption) might best know, and hath, with most likely assertion, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his report. Yet so, that, to explaine the Author, carrying himselfe in this part, an <hi>Historicall,</hi> as in the other, a <hi>Chorogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall</hi> Poet, I insert oft, out of the <hi>British</hi> story, what I impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune you not to credit. Of that kind, are those <hi>Prophecies</hi> out of <hi>Merlin</hi> sometime interwouen: I discharge my selfe; nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute you to me any serious respect of them. Inuiting, not wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, occasion, I adde sometime what is different from my task, but such as I guesse would any where please an vnderstanding Reader. To aide you in course of Times, I haue in fit place drawn <hi>Chronologies,</hi> vpon Credit of the Ancients; and, for matter of that kinde, haue admonisht (to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Canto) what as yet I neuer saw by any obseru'd, for wary consideration of the <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysian</hi> Cycle, and mis-interpreted Roote of his Dominicall yeere. Those <hi>old Rimes,</hi> which (some number) you often meet with, are offer'd the willinger, both for <hi>Variety</hi> of your Mother Tongue, as also, because the Author of them <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Gloster</hi> neuer yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in common light. He was, in Time, an Age before; but, in Learning and Wit, as most others, much behind our Worthy <hi>Chaucer:</hi> whose name by the way Occuring, and my worke here being but to adde plaine song after Muses descanting, I cannot but digresse to admonition of abuse which this Learned allusion, in his <hi>Troilus,</hi> by ignorance hath indured.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>I am till God mee better mind send <note place="margin">Chaucer expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note>
      </l>
      <l>At Dulcarnon right at my wits end.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Its not <hi>Necham,</hi> or any else, that can make mee entertaine the least thought of the signification of <hi>Dulcarnon</hi> to be <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his sacrifice after his Geometricall Theorem in finding the Squares of an Orthogonall Triangles sides, or that it is a word of <hi>Latine</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epocha <hi>Selea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidarum.</hi>
      </note> deduction; but indeed by easier pronounciation it was made of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> .i. <hi>Two horned:</hi> which the <hi>Mahometan Arabians</hi> vse for a Root in Calculation, meaning <hi>Alexander,</hi> as that great Dictator of knowledge <hi>Ioseph Scaliger</hi> (with some Ancients) wills, but, by warranted opinion of my learned friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Lydyat</hi> in his <hi>Emendatio Temporum,</hi> it began in <hi>Seleucus Nicanor,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. yeares after <hi>Alexanders</hi> death; The name was applyed, either because af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="8"/>
time that <hi>Alexander</hi> had perswaded himselfe to be <hi>Iupiter Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> sonne, whose Statue was with <hi>Rams</hi> hornes, both his owne and his Successors Coines were stampt with horned Images: or else in respect of his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. pillars erected in the East as a <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Christman.</hi> Comment in <hi>Alfragan.</hi> cap. 11. <hi>Lysimachi</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum <hi>apud</hi> Cael. Rhodigin. <hi>Antiq. lect. 20 cap. 12. hîc ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuina interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio.</hi> Of whō euen euery ingenio{us} strangermakes honorable mention. <hi>Comitem verò illum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> R. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singstochium (<hi>Cuius Historie magnam partem quasi <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Choro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structio plerá{que} ad Antiquitatis amussim, ab Eruditissimo hoc <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> populari ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta, ne dicam suppilata, est) adeòinhumat. ū fuisse miror, vt bené merentem non tam libentèr agnoscat, quàm Clariss. Viri syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labis et inuentis Codicem suum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> perquam ingrate suffar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinet. Atque id ferè genus Plagiarios, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des omniuò, et <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, et Vernaculos <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Nostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes iam nunc im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> video indignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ringor. Ianus Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Nthil vltra</hi> of his Conquest, and some say because hee had in Power the <hi>Easterne</hi> and <hi>Westerne</hi> World, signified in the two Hornes. But, howsoeuer, it well fits the Passage, either, as if hee had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonated <hi>Creseide</hi> at the entrance of two wayes, not knowing which to take; in like sense as that of <hi>Prodicus</hi> his <hi>Hercules, Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> his Y, or the Logicians <hi>Dilemma</hi> expresse; or else, which is the truth of his conceit, that shee was at a <hi>Nonplus,</hi> as the interpretation in his next Staffe makes plaine. How many of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Chaucers</hi> Readers neuer so much as suspect this his short essay of knowledge, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the common Rode? and by his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of the <hi>Astrolabe</hi> (which, I dare sweare, was chiefly learned out of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>) it is plaine hce was much acquainted with the Mathematiques, and amongst their Authors had it. But, I return to my selfe. From vaine loading my Margine, with <hi>Books, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Folio's,</hi> or <hi>Names</hi> of our <hi>Historians,</hi> I abstain: Course of Time as readily directs to them. But, where the place might not so easily occurre (chiefly in matter of <hi>Philogie</hi>) there onelie (for view of them which shall examine mee) I haue added assisting references. For most of what I vse of <hi>Chorographie,</hi> ioyne with me in thanks to that most Learned Nourice of Antiquitie
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Christman.</hi> Comment in <hi>Alfragan.</hi> cap. 11. <hi>Lysimachi</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum <hi>apud</hi> Cael. Rhodigin. <hi>Antiq. lect. 20 cap. 12. hîc ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuina interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio.</hi> Of whō euen euery ingenio{us} strangermakes honorable mention. <hi>Comitem verò illum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> R. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singstochium (<hi>Cuius Historie magnam partem quasi <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Choro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structio plerá{que} ad Antiquitatis amussim, ab Eruditissimo hoc <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> populari ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta, ne dicam suppilata, est) adeòinhumat. ū futsse miror, vt bené merentem non tam libentèr agnoscat, quàm Clariss. Viri syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labis et inuentis Codicem suum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> perquam ingrate suffar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinet. Atque id ferè genus Plagiarios, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des omniuò, et <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, et Vernaculos <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Nostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes iam nunc im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> video indignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ringor. Ianus Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
my instructing friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Camden Clarenceulx.</hi> From him and <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald</hi> of <hi>Cambria</hi> also comes most of my <hi>British;</hi> And then may <hi>Mercury</hi> and all the Muses deadly hate mee, when, in permitting occasion, I professe not by whom I learne! Let them vent iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on mee which vnderstand: I iustifie all, by the selfe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors cited, crediting no <hi>Transcribers,</hi> but when of Necessitie I must. My thirst compeld mee alwayes seeke the <hi>Fountaines,</hi> and, by that, if meanes grant it, iudge the <hi>Riuers</hi> nature. Nor can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Conuersant in Letters bee ignorant what error is oftimes fallen into, by trusting Authorities at second hand, and rash col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting (as it were) from visuall beam's refracted through ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eye. In performance of this charge (vndertaken at request of my kinde friend the Author) Breuity of <hi>Time</hi> (which was but little more then since the Poem first went to the Presse) and that daily discontinued, both by my other most different <hi>Studies</hi> seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously attended, and interrupting <hi>Busines,</hi> as enough can witnes, might excuse great faults, especially of <hi>Omission.</hi> But, I take not thence aduantage to desire more then <hi>Common Curtesie in Censure:</hi> Nor of this, nor of what else I heeretofore haue published, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Christman.</hi> Comment in <hi>Alfragan.</hi> cap. 11. <hi>Lysimachi</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum <hi>apud</hi> Cael. Rhodigin. <hi>Antiq. lect. 20 cap. 12. hîc ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuina interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio.</hi> Of whō euen euery ingenio{us} strangermakes honorable mention. <hi>Comitem verò illum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> R. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singstochium (<hi>Cuius Historie magnam partem quasi <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Choro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structio plerá{que} ad Antiquitatis amussim, ab Eruditissimo hoc <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> populari ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta, ne dicam suppilata, est) adeòinhumat. ū futsse miror, vt bené merentem non tam libentèr agnoscat, quàm Clariss. Viri syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labis et inuentis Codicem suum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> perquam ingrate suffar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinet. Atque id ferè genus Plagiarios, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des omniuò, et <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, et Vernaculos <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Nostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes iam nunc im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> video indignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ringor. Ianus Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Historicall deduction of Our Ancient Lawes,</hi> wherein I scape not without Tax
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Sunt quibus in verbis videór{que} obscurior, hoc est,</hi> Euandri <hi>cum Matre loqui,</hi> Faunis{que} Numá{que} <hi>Nec secùs ac si auctor</hi> Saliaris <hi>Carminis essem.</hi>
I haue read in <hi>Cicero, Agellius, Lucians Lexiphanes,</hi> and others, much against that forme; But withall, this later age (wherein so industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous search is among admired Ruins of olde Monuments) hath, in our greatest Latine Critiques <hi>Hans Douz, P. Merula, Lipsius</hi> and such more, so receiued that <hi>Saturnian</hi> Language, that, to Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in <hi>Philogy,</hi> it is now grown familiar; and (as he saith) <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba à Vetustāte repetita non solum magnos Assertores habent, sed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> afferunt Orationi Maiestatem aliquam, non sine delectatione.</hi> Yet for Antique Termes, to the Learned, I will not iustifie it without exception (disliking not that of <hi>Phauorin, Viue Moribus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, loquere verbis praesentibus;</hi> and, as Coine, so words, of a publique and knowne stamp, are to bee vsed) although so much, as that way I offend, is warranted by example of such, of whom to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor imitation allowes me more then the bare title of <hi>Blameles.</hi> The purblind Ignorant I salute, with the English of that Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Epigram
<note n="*" place="margin">If thou hast no taste in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning medle no more with what thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand'st not. That the Godlike fort of men, may worthily guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don his labors.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
Reprehension of them, whose Language and best learning is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chast from such Volumes as <hi>Rablais</hi> reckons in <hi>S. Victors</hi> Library, or Barbarous Glosses
<hi>Quàm nihil ad Genium,</hi> Papiniane, <hi>tuum!</hi>
or, which are furnisht in our old story, only out of the Common <hi>Polychronicon, Caxton, Fabian, Stow, Grafton, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, Cooper, Holingshed</hi> (perhaps with gift of vnderstanding) <hi>Polydore,</hi> and the rest of our later Compilers; or, of any aduenturous <hi>Thersites</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring find fault euen with the very <hi>Graces,</hi> in a straine
<hi>Cornua quod vincát{que} Tubas—</hi>
I regarde as metamorphized <hi>Lucius</hi> his looking out at window; I Slight, Scorne, and Laugh at it. By <hi>Paragraph's</hi> in the Verses you know what I meddle with in the <hi>Illustrations;</hi> but so, that with Latitude, the direction admonishes sometimes as well for explaning a Following or Preceding passage, as its owne. Ingenuous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to you I wish your best desires; Grant me too, I pray, this one, that you read mee not, without comparing the <hi>Faults esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped;</hi> I haue collected them for you. Compell'd <hi>Absence,</hi> endeuor'd <hi>Dispatch,</hi> and want of <hi>Reuises</hi> soone bred them. To the Author, I wish (as an old Cosmographicall Poet did long since to himselfe.)
<note n="*" place="margin">If thou hast no taste in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning medle no more with what thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand'st not. That the Godlike fort of men, may worthily guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don his labors.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
To <hi>Gentlewomē</hi> &amp; their <hi>Loues</hi> is consecrated all the <hi>wooing Language, Allusions</hi> to <hi>Loue-Passions,</hi> and sweet <hi>Embracements</hi> fain'd by
<pb facs="9"/>
the Muse mongst <hi>Hils</hi> and <hi>Riuers;</hi> Whatsoeuer tastes of <hi>descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Battell, Story, Abstruse Antiquity,</hi> and (which my particular Study caus'd me sometime remember) <hi>Law</hi> of the Kingdome, To the more <hi>Seuere Reader.</hi> To the one, Be contenting <hi>enioyments</hi> of their <hi>Auspicious Desires;</hi> To the other, Happy <hi>Attendance</hi> of their chosen <hi>Muses.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From the <hi>Inner Temple</hi>
         <date>May. IX., <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. XII.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>