<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY LOVING GOOD FRIND N. SECRETARY TO THE right honorable the L. Treasurer of Inglande.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121696_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09610</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19885</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121696</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY LOVING GOOD FRIND N. SECRETARY TO THE right honorable the L. Treasurer of Inglande.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An aduertisement written to a secretarie of my L. Treasurers of Ingland, by an Inglishe intelligencer as he passed throughe Germanie towardes Italie : Concerninge an other booke newly written in Latin, and published in diuerse languages and countreyes, against her Maiesties late proclamation, for searche and apprehension of seminary priestes, and their receauers, also of a letter vvritten by the L. Treasurer in defence of his gentrie, and nobility, intercepted, published, and answered by the papistes</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>67, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
   <head>TO MY LOVING GOOD FRIND N. SECRETARY TO THE right honorable the L. Treasurer of Inglande.</head>
   <p>LOVING Sir, yf my former letters written to you from Midleburg, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Heid leberg, &amp; Franckford, as I passed by those places, haue come safely vnto your handes, then haue you vnderstood by thē the estate of affayres, as I coulde learne thē in so shorte a stay, as the continuance of my iourney per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted me to make in euery of these cityes: especially I wrote vnto you in all my former, of the great variety of bookes both in Inglishe and Latyn, and other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages already come forth, or in makinge (as by good meanes I vnderstoode) against the laste proclamation of her Maiestie published in Nouember for searching <note place="margin">1591.</note> out, apprehendinge and punishing of Seminarie priestes, and Iesuites, and such as receaue or fauoure them in Ingland; which proclamation seemeth to haue so netled the papistes, which we call here Catholiques, (and so muste I in the reste of my letters, especially those that shal come from Italie,) that there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther talke almoste now in these partes, nor of any other matters, but of this combate of Englande, and in this countrie here of Germanie, where both parties liue in peace together, our course of Ingland hath diuerse that approue it not, though otherwise no papistes, for that they thincke it both troublesome, and daungerous,
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
whereof at an other time I shal write more vnto you, yf I may perceaue that my letters doe come vnto your handes safely, whereof I haue greate feare and doubt, consideringe the difficulties of passages, and manifolde interception of letters, whereof I vnderstande daily by reason of warres.</p>
   <p>But to come to the matter, I sent you with my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer letters while I was in flandres two or three diuers kindes of answers made and printed in Inglishe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out name of authours against the said late proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and some others I was told were in coming foorth though I could not learne by whome. Afterward frō Colen I sente you one written in Latine by <hi>Ihon Perne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glis he man,</hi> as he nameth himself, &amp; it goeth by way of a letter, or discourse, written to a frinde of his that desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his opinion and judgemente aboute the saide pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamatiō, and it is directed to my L. Treasurer himself.</p>
   <p>But now comming to Augusta, I haue learned of an other booke also written in Latin, and lately sent hither to be printed againe, &amp; is now in hande &amp; some sheetes already drawen of: which booke, though I can neyther hynder the printinge thereof, (for I haue assayed) nor yet get any whole copy into my handes to sende vnto you (for I vnderstande there is but one onely as yet in this citie, and this is that which serueth for the printer, sent hither by a certaine principall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be reprinted as soone as euer it had passed the presse in an other place) yet haue I so wrought as ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterday beinge sunday, and the print standinge still, I gat for mony the sighte of the booke, and in some few nightes I tooke out all the summe, and chiefe effecte thereof, &amp; doe sende it herewith vnto you, promisinge further to send also the whole woorke as soone as euer it shal come forthe, albeit yf the haste and greedinesse of printinge it in so many places and countreys, at one time be such, as here some woulde make me beleeue,
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
it is like yow shal haue it otherwise there in Inglande, before I can send it from hence, but yet this shall not lett me from doinge my dewtie also in sending it from hence as sone as I can get it.</p>
   <p>And in truthe yf I shal tell you myne opiniō about the hastie spredding of this booke (which I suppose you will also thinke, when you shal haue seene the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracte that herewith I do sende you) there are so many poynts of curiositie, and hidden histories touching our estate discouered in the same, and so many personall causes, conditions of men, and secret affaires vnfolded, (whereof mans nature partly by desire of nouelties, partly by corrupt inclination to heare willingly other mens defects is greedy to vnderstande) as I maruaile not though printers to gaine thereby, doe striue in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places to diuulgate the same with all celerity, and the like I finde by experience in the late historie of D. Sanders in Latin <hi>de schisimate Anglicano,</hi> which for that it conteyned matter of such curiositie, and noueltie in personall affayres, I find it printed againe in Latin almost in euery state, <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ydes the translations that go in other languages, which I am tolde are many.</p>
   <p>But for this booke againste the proclamation, I do assure you it is the moste sharpe, bitter, and odious thing that euer I thinck was written by the papistes, though the writer pretende great modestie, and doeth not in deede vse open raylinge tearmes, but by a close, fluente, and cutting stile, and by discussing (as I haue saide) of many, and curious perticularities, and by pretending to proue all he saith, by our owne bookes, lawes, cronicles, and recordes, he filleth his reader with infinite desire to reade al through out.</p>
   <p>More ouer he putteth downe the whole proclamatiō turned in to latin by partes or Sections, (which is an other curiositie, that other bookes come out before ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued not,) and after he awswereth the same by seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eades distinstely, and in the ende, he putteth also in Latyn the articles annexed to the commission for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction to the commissioners, How to proceede in the execution thereof, with his iudgemēte, and censure vpon the same.</p>
   <p>He put<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth downe also in his awnswere a lettre of my L. Treasurers writte with his owne hande (as this fellow anoucheth) from westminster the tenth of lanuarie laste paste vnto one in the love countries, as by the extracte you shall see.</p>
   <p>The writer nameth himself <hi>Ihon Philopatris</hi> prieste, and divine, that hath studied at Rome, and descended in tymes paste of the English blood, but he that shall see, and reade the booke (which is some xviij. or twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie leaues of printed paper or more) will easily see that he hath lined lately in Inglande, or is very extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily instructed in the affayres thereof, and when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that <hi>Philopatris</hi> in greeke signifieth a louer, or a frinde of his country, I easily see that the name is but borowed, and may be taken vp in theire sense by any of our Inglish papistes, that live here abrode, and so make your accompte that it is.</p>
   <p>More I shal write vnto you from Italie, and namely from <hi>Venice,</hi> or <hi>Padua,</hi> for here I will stay onely vntill this booke come forth, that I may sende you a copie. VVhich yf you thinke good, you may present to our good Lord and master in my name, as you may doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the exstract thereof that now I send, though in trueth, the tooth and stomack of the writer seemeth to be so specially great against his lordship aboue all others, and toucheth him so bitterly in so many places (estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him the principall cause of al the bloudshedd of his partie) that I am ashamed, and half afraide also, that it sholde be given vnto his honour in my behalf, yet could I not with my dewtie and allegeance but aduertise the matter as I finde it, and so haue I done in
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
the abbreuiation, taking out euery thinge as neer as I cā in sense though not in wordes as in the booke it lieth, and that in more sweete, and temperate manner also di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tymes, then there it is sett downe, culling out onely the heades of the most principal matters, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vtterly the discourses, declarations, and proofes of the same, wich are in truth more pearcing, plausible, and popular then will easily be imagined but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the whole: and in one word beleeue yow Sir, that it is a very pestilent booke, and so I pray you aduertise his lordship, and commend my seruice with continuing me in his honors good grace and fauour, which I euer desire to deserue as I may, and so to the lord I commyt you from Augusta this first of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. 1592.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most affectionate.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>