<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Honourable

EDWARD MONTAGU,
Sr JOHN POWLET,

Sonnes and Heirs to the Right Honourable

EDWARD Lord MONTAGU of Boughton.
JOHN Lord POWLET of Hinton-St-George.
</title>
           <author>Fuller, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121250_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121250</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Honourable

EDWARD MONTAGU,
Sr JOHN POWLET,

Sonnes and Heirs to the Right Honourable

EDWARD Lord MONTAGU of Boughton.
JOHN Lord POWLET of Hinton-St-George.
</title>
                 <author>Fuller, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the holy vvarre : by Thomas Fuller, B.D. prebendarie of Sarum, late of Sidney Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Fuller, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Williams, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 286, 30 pages, 2 leaves of plates (1 folded), illustrations, map, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Honourable
<list>
         <item>EDWARD MONTAGU,</item>
         <item>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> JOHN POWLET,</item>
      </list>
Sonnes and Heirs to the Right Honourable
<list>
         <item>EDWARD Lord MONTAGU of Boughton.</item>
         <item>JOHN Lord POWLET of Hinton-S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>-George.</item>
      </list>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I observe the severall alterations in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, I find foure principall actours on the theatres of great Families; the Beginner, Advancer, Continuer, and Ruiner. The Beginner is he who by his vertues refineth himself from the drosse of the vulgar, and layeth the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his house: An excellent workman indeed, as who not onely bringeth his tools, but maketh his materialls. The Advancer, who improveth the patrimonie of Honour he receiveth; and what his Father found glasse and made crystall, he findeth crystall and maketh it pearl. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuer, who keepeth his Nobilitie alive, and passeth it along neither marring nor mending it; but sendeth it to his Sonne as he received it from his Father. The Ruiner, who base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly degenerateth from his Ancestours; so that in him Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie hath runne so farre from its first starting, that it is tired: and whilest he liveth he is no better then his Grandfathers tombe; without, carved over with honourable titles; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, full of emptinesse, or what is worse, corruption.</p>
   <p>Now to apply. You cannot be Beginners of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; that care was cared for before your nurses were
<pb facs="4"/>
chosen, or your cradles provided. Your Fathers, though of late yeares fixed in a higher Sphear, were bright Starres long before. None can go on in our English Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but they must meet with a <hi>Montagu</hi> and a <hi>Powlet,</hi> either in peace in their gowns, or in warre in their armour. Yea, when I go backward by the streams of your Paternall Nobilitie, (not to speak of the tributarie brooks of their matches) I can never find the first fountain; and hope none shall ever find the last fall. For as for the ruiners of houses, I should rend that thought out with my heart, if it should conceive that of you. Nay, let me tell you; if you be but bare continuers of your Honour, you deceive both the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires and hopes of your friends. Good is not good when proceeding from them from whom farre better is expected. Your youthfull vertues are so promising, that you cannot come off in your riper age with credit without performing what may redound to the advancing of the honour of your family, and without building your houses one storie higher in the English Historie.</p>
   <p>Now know, next Religion, there is nothing accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man more then Learning. Learning in a Lord, is as a diamond in gold. And if you fear to hurt your tender hands with thornie School-questions, there is no danger in meddling with History, which is a velvet-study, &amp; recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-work. What a pitie is it to see a proper Gentleman to have such a crick in his neck that he cannot look backward! yet no better is he who cannot see behind him the actions which long since were performed. History maketh a young man to be old, without either wrinkles or gray hairs; privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him with the experience of age, without either the
<pb facs="4"/>
infirmities or inconveniences thereof. Yea, it not onely maketh things past, present; but inableth one to make a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall conjecture of things to come. For this world afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no new accidents, but in the same sense wherein we call it <hi>a new Moon,</hi> which is the old one in another shape, and yet no other then what hath been formerly. Old actions return again, furbished over with some new and different circumstances.</p>
   <p>Now amongst all particular histories (I may say) none is more generall then this of the Holy warre, which now I present to your Honours. Some will condemn me for an ill husband, in lavishing two Noble Patrones on one book, whereas one of them might have served to have patronized many volumes. But first, I did it in the weak expression of my thankfulnesse unto you, being deeply indebted to you both; and I thought it dishonestie to pay all to one cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditour and none to another; and therefore conceived it best, to share my estate joyntly betwixt you, as farre forth as it would extend. Secondly, considering the weaknesse of this Work, now being to walk abroad in the world, I thought it must be led by both arms, and needed a double supporter. And now I am sure this Holy warre, which was unhappie heretofore, when acted; will be happie hereafter, now writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and related, because dedicated to your Honours. So resteth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all service <hi>THO. FULLER.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>Broad-windsor, <date>
            <hi>March</hi> 6. 1638.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>