<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The French AVTHOVRS Epistle Dedicatorie. To the most Noble and Learned Lord, Monsieur Maistre NICOLAS LE CLERC, Lord of Franconuille, of Tremblay, of Sainct Remy, &amp;c. Counceller to the King in his High Court of Parliament at PARIS.</title>
           <author>Favine, Andrew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121368_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00580</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10717</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The French AVTHOVRS Epistle Dedicatorie. To the most Noble and Learned Lord, Monsieur Maistre NICOLAS LE CLERC, Lord of Franconuille, of Tremblay, of Sainct Remy, &amp;c. Counceller to the King in his High Court of Parliament at PARIS.</title>
                 <author>Favine, Andrew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theater of honour and knight-hood. Or A compendious chronicle and historie of the whole Christian vvorld : Containing the originall of all monarchies, kingdomes, and estates, with their emperours, kings, princes, and gouernours; their beginnings, continuance, and successions, to this present time. The first institution of armes, emblazons, kings, heralds, and pursuiuants of armes: with all the ancient and moderne military orders of knight-hood in euery kingdome. Of duelloes or single combates, with their originall, lawes, and obseruations. Likewise of ioustes, tourneyes, and tournaments, and orders belonging to them. Lastly of funerall pompe, for emperours, kings, princes, and meaner persons, with all the rites and ceremonies fitting for them. VVritten in French, by Andrew Fauine, Parisian: and aduocate in the High Court of Parliament. M.DC.XX</title>
                 <author>Favyn, André</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 108, 107-580, 571-572, 286, 285-406, 18, 407-538, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The French AVTHOVRS Epistle Dedicatorie. To the most Noble and Learned Lord, Monsieur Maistre <hi>NICOLAS LE CLERC, Lord</hi> of <hi>Franconuille,</hi> of <hi>Tremblay,</hi> of Sainct <hi>Remy, &amp;c.</hi> Counceller to the King in his High Court of Parliament at PARIS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Poet <hi>Euripides,</hi> being aduised by his Friends, to put forth (for publique view) a Worke written by his owne hand, which they esteemed to be of worth, and to Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the same to <hi>Archelaus,</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi>; made them this answere.</p>
   <q>
      <l>To a Rich man I must no poore Gift send,</l>
      <l>That may my folly iustly reprehend:</l>
      <l>Or else suspect thereby, that giuing so,</l>
      <l>I begging aske great Bounty to bestow.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Hauing communed with you some yeares past, concerning this Worke, roughly hewne by mine owne hand; you iudged it worthy to see day-light, vnder the Fauour and Name of some Prince, or great Lord. And then, I requited your aduice with those Verses of <hi>Euripides.</hi> For in mine owne Naturall disposition, I am of a quite contrarie humour to them, that set all to sale, and make a price of their paines. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath alreadie twice resolued mee, that in this Iron Age, the Dedication of painfull Labours to Great Persons, vnder hope of meeting with deserued Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; is vainely sayling to the <hi>Indiaes</hi> of <hi>Peru,</hi> and by such a cutting North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>west Winde.</p>
   <p>Sweating vnder the Armour of Learned <hi>Minerua,</hi> full Fiue and Twentie, if not Thirtie yeares, trauayilng day and night, to choose the fayrest Flowers growing in the Worlds best stored Gardens, and then offering them to Great men: All your recompence will bee but Crimosine Taffata fine tearmes, as thus. <hi>Beleeue mee (Sir,) it is an Historie of exceeding great Trauaile: Therein are many curious and costly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherches: You are a Worthy Man: And you meri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e much.</hi> Like to the Bottle of <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides,</hi> of <hi>Grands-Mercys,</hi> full of nothing, but Winde and Smoake of the Court.</p>
   <q>Est Labor ingratus, quem debita praemia fallunt.</q>
   <q>


Because Recompence is the Nursing Mother of Arts and Sciences.</q>
   <p>The Reigne of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, swarmed with braue Spirits, excelling in
<pb facs="4"/>
Knowledge and Learning: as also rare Artizans, who indeede (to speake vprightly) were not borne vnder the Reigne of <hi>Alexander,</hi> but made by <hi>Alexander,</hi> a Liberal and Magnificent Prince, especially to them that knew any thing. He heaped no mean store of goods on <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and his Followers: yea, he honoured the memorie of the Greeke Poet <hi>Homer,</hi> because he had celebrated that of <hi>Achilles.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For he knew by sound and setled iudgement, that all that a great Prince could doe, to sauour of Excellencie in his life, was but comparable with clapping the hands and fingers, which maketh no Sound or Hermonie whatsoeuer (the Symbole of a Man dying without Memorie, among the Aegyptians) if in his life time he did no good to them, that could draw him out of the Charnell-house of Obliuion.</p>
   <p>Such men are they, as may raise their Tombes and Monuments, vpon a Module and Patterne more excellent a thousand times, then that of <hi>Memnon</hi> the Aethyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian Prince, which was made with such Artificiall cunning: that his Statue fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereon, yeelded a most pleasing Hermonie to heare, at all times, and as often as the Worlds great Eye the Sunne, came and darted his Golden Beames, in at the eyes and mouth of the same Statue.</p>
   <p>Princes of the Earth, are as subiect to death, as the poorest and meanest Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zants in the World. <hi>Mors Omnibus ex Natura aequalis est: Obliuione apud Posteros, vel Gloria Distinguitur.</hi> So speaketh the Noble Historian <hi>Tacitus,</hi> in the First Booke of his Histories.</p>
   <p>Hfter this common passage, and this generall Procession, although they are no more then <hi>Skelitons,</hi> couered either with Marble or Brasse: yet notwithstanding, they reuiue, and see all the Sunnes golden dayes, onely by the Pennes of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and skilfull Writers, who engraue their Memorie with the Instrument of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</p>
   <q>
      <l>— Monumentum Aereperennius,</l>
      <l>Regalique situ Pyramidum altius.</l>
   </q>
   <p>But this is to be vnderstood of such, as are truely louers of Arts and Sciences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bountifull to the maintenance of them: Otherwise, their liues are iustly worth nothing, and their Actions of greatest Fame and report, no more then as the sound and clapping of hands, or fillipping the singers. Hereupon it was, that the queint and Learned <hi>Sapho,</hi> emblazoning an ignorant person in generall; made this Epitaph for him, during his life time.</p>
   <q>
      <l>To Graue thou carriest all, thus dead,</l>
      <l>Because thou hast not gathered</l>
      <l>The <hi>Roses</hi> on Pieriaes Mount:</l>
      <l>That flourish by the Siluer Fount.</l>
   </q>
   <p>The <hi>Rose</hi> is the Liuery of the Muses, and the Hieroglyphicke of such as loue them: So <hi>Plutarke</hi> enstructeth vs, in the third Booke of his Table discourse. Whose Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie shall neuer perish by the Wheele of Time.</p>
   <q>Virum laude dignum Musa vetat Mori:</q>
   <p>Because that
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>Th'Immortall Sisters Chaplets in their Bowers;</l>
         <l>They wither not, as doe all other Flowers.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>To you my Lord it is, that I offer this Worke, and giue it to publique view, vnder the fauour of your liking and allowance. It is a Chaplet or Garland, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed and combined with all kindes of Flowers, gathered in the Gardens of the Kingdomes and Prouinces of the World. To you, who perticularly (among all the Learned men of this Age) that haue a solid and perfect knowledge, of
<pb facs="4"/>
all whatsoeuer Nature hath produced; euen from the Hisope and the Ant, so farre as to the Caedar of Libanus, and to the Royall Eagle: But more principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you haue most certaine and vndoubted knowledge, in all things that haue past for excellent and famous, in the Parliament of <hi>France,</hi> yea, all that concerneth the distribution of Iustice, the chiefest Piller of this Monarchie.</p>
   <p>You are the Refuge and Sanctuarie, of all such as make profession of Learning, whom you loue and cherish without any feigning. Whereby plainely appeareth, that it was not without good cause; that your Noble Great Grandfathers (renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their times for knowledge and Learning) did beare (as now you doe) in their Armes, the Colour and Liuerie of the Immortall Sisters: <hi>D'Argent Clair-&amp; lui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, au Cheuron d'vn Azur Bleu-Coeleste, accompagne de Trois Roses d'vne Riche-couleur, Deux en Chef, &amp; Vne en Poincte.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>By your singuler humanitie towards mine and me, God hath enabled me with the grace and leisures, to beget and cloath (vnder you) this Infant of my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And therefore, such as it is, it is yours, and if it can doe any seruice or benefit in publique; the honor is onely due to you. And for so many good turnes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, as I haue already, or can receiue from you: I wish those of Heauen to you, and (my good Lord) desire of God with all my heart, that he will be pleased, to blesse you with perfect health, happie and long life.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At</hi> Paris, <hi>from your House,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>this fifteenth day of June,</hi> 1619.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your most humble and deepely obliged Seruant for euer: ANDREVV FAVINE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>