<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Rea∣der, zeale and knowledge in true and harty prayer through Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>D., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121845_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19989</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6429</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121845</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Rea∣der, zeale and knowledge in true and harty prayer through Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>D., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke of Christian prayers, collected out of the auncie [n] t writers, and best learned in our tyme, worthy to be read with an earnest mynde of all Christians, in these daungerous and troublesome dayes, that God for Christes sake will yet still be mercyfull vnto vs</title>
                 <author>Day, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 137, that is 138, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, zeale and knowledge in true and harty prayer through Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auid, a Prophet and a Prince, to whom the lord had done ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, great, &amp; singular benefites, bethought him selfe, not so much to increase thē by vse, as to requite them by thankes. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, willing as a Prophet, &amp; able as a prince, but not able in deede, though willing so to doe, opened his good hart, and sayd: <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuam Domino? What reward shall I geue vnto the Lord?</hi> Being resolued, he answered: <hi>I will receaue, I will call, and I will pay. Psal. 116.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Doe thou the like (Christiā Reader) which art as farre indebted as euer he. And seeing that Iesus Christ him selfe calleth, saying: <hi>Come vnto me all you that labor, and are laden, and I will refresh you. Mat.</hi> 11. Answere thou, <hi>I come,</hi> Lord Iesu, <hi>I come. I come,</hi> and will pay my vowes, promysed to thee in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of all thy people, euen in the Courtes of thy house, when I was receaued into the houshold of faith.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>I come,</hi> and will pray and prayse thee for al thy benefites. <hi>I come,</hi> and will harken to thy blessed word, and keepe the same. <hi>I come,</hi> and will receaue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cup of saluation, at thy holy ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, in remēbrance of thy death, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thanksge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.




<pb facs="3"/>
In this sort, &amp; so many waies, by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, by prayer, by hearing his blessed word, by frequenting his table, must we <hi>come</hi> vnto him, and that with a liuely faith. <hi>The Spirite is willing,</hi> but the flesh is weake. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26▪ <hi>come</hi> vnto him therfore, especially by prayer. Pray that he would strengthen both flesh, and Spirite.</p>
   <p>And thinke it not superfluous to pray, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause God already knoweth what we neede, and what we will aske. But pray, because God hath commaunded. <hi>Luke.</hi> 8. Pray to hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble thy selfe before the feete of his maiestie. Pray because <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> doest hourely want that grace, which he will assuredly geue. <hi>Pray ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that you may haue. Mat.</hi> 7. And pray, <hi>least you fall into temptation. Luke.</hi> 12.</p>
   <p>And because God vnderstandeth, pray not thou therfore in a language which thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandest not, but with <hi>Spirite and Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. Not with <hi>mouth and lippes onely, but with the hart. Mat.</hi> 15. <hi>For the spirite also helpeth our infirmities, making request for vs with sighes which cannot be expressed. Rom. 8</hi> As Anna, and Mary Magdalen, with teares from a groning hart, &amp; spake nothing. 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 1 <hi>Luke.</hi> 7. For <hi>God must be worshipped in spirite and truth. Iohn.</hi> 14. And pray not with <hi>much babling, and vayn repetition. Math.</hi> 6. <hi>Neither be rash with thy mouth, neither let thy hart be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty to bring forth a word in the sight of God: for God is in heauen, and thou art in earth, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thy words be few. For as a dreame com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth by multitude of busines: so is the voice of a foole in the multitude of words. Eccle.</hi> 5.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Prepare therfore thy selfe, and <hi>soul to pray. Eccle.</hi> 18. with <hi>teares. Mach.</hi> 5. with <hi>watching. Col 4.</hi> with <hi>almes. Act.</hi> 10 with <hi>fasting. Luke.</hi> 1. as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Niniuites. <hi>Iona.</hi> 3. as Dauid. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. as Dani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell. <hi>cap. 9.</hi> For <hi>with fasting prayer is good. Tob.</hi> 12 Which exercises, as they are the only meanes, not onely to excite and stirre vs vp to pray, but also to make them acceptable before God through Iesus Christ: so also a great care &amp; diligence must be vsed of vs, to vse the same, not of constraint, but willingly <hi>geuing our selues therunto. Luke.</hi> 5. <hi>without ostentatiō. Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>praying continually. 1. Thessal.</hi> 5. <hi>without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing. Col.</hi> 1. as the widow. <hi>Luke. 18.</hi> and as the woman of <hi>Canaan. Mat.</hi> 15. <hi>Praying alwayes.</hi> 1. <hi>Thess.</hi> 1 and at al times, <hi>day and night. 2. Tim.</hi> 1. in all places, <hi>euery where. 1. Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, and congregation. Act.</hi> 22. <hi>and that bare hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. at home <hi>in thy chamber secretly. Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>in thy bed. Psal.</hi> 6. at meale <hi>and meate. Mat. 26. morning and euening. Psal.</hi> 44. abroad in the field. <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.</p>
   <p>The Scripture is full of examples Peter prayd in the vpper part of the house. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. Eliseus aboue in his chamber. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyell in the kinges chamber secretly. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. and among the Lyons. <hi>Dan.</hi> 14. Moyses in the wildernes. <hi>Iosu. 1.</hi> Ezechias the king in his bed. <hi>Esay.</hi> 34. Ionas in the Whales belly. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. Christ in fieldes and gardens. <hi>Math.</hi> 26. and on his cros. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. For the place of pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er is not materiall. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. I meane of Priuate prayer: in which consideration, pray in all pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, &amp; at all times, whether it be <hi>seuen times a day</hi> with Dauid. <hi>Psa.</hi> 118. or thrise a day with




<pb facs="4"/>
Danyel. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. Whether on the Sabaoth day, or at the ninth houre, especially when Gods Spirite shall moue thee so to doe. For at any such time to defer thy prayer, vntill thou find a better place, to sitte, stand, or kneele, is as much, as to hinder (if not to quench) Gods Spirite. Now it followeth to whom we must <hi>come. To me</hi> (sayth Christ) <hi>for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me you can doe nothing. Ioh.</hi> 15. <hi>whatsoeuer you shall aske the father in my name, it shall be geuen you Ioh.</hi> 16. <hi>Come</hi> to no earthly man, <hi>for cursed is he that putteth his trust in man. Ier.</hi> 17. <hi>and who shall deliuer his brother, or make agree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment with God for him? Psal.</hi> 49. <hi>Come</hi> to no heauenly saint. <hi>For Christ is our onely Mediator and intercessor betweene God and vs.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>and whom haue I in heauen but thee</hi> saith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid? <hi>Psal.</hi> 33. <hi>Come</hi> onely vnto him therfore. And why to him only? <hi>For in him the Father is well pleased. Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>No man can come to the Father, but by him. Ioh.</hi> 14. He onely is present euery wher to heare the prayers of the whole world. <hi>All power is geuen into his hands. Ioh. 5</hi> He onely knoweth the secrets of our hartes.</p>
   <p>But who shall <hi>come? Al you</hi> (saith he) <hi>that labour, and are laden.</hi> How laden? Not with bags of gold, and brags of righteousnes. <hi>For he came not to call the righteous but sinners to repentance. Luke.</hi> 5. <hi>Presēt not therfore thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in thine own righteousnes. Dan.</hi> 9. Play not the <hi>Pharisie,</hi> but pray as the <hi>Publicane. Luk.</hi> 18. And albeit <hi>God heareth not sinners. Ioh.</hi> 9. yet y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is meant of desperate sinners, &amp; malicious de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>spicers of Christ &amp; his Gospel: not of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tant, in whom, as it is requisite there be no




<pb facs="4"/>
brag of righteousnesse: so is it as necessary, that there be a harty confession of vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes, yealding to Gods mercy, and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing forgeuenes. Such, though they <hi>labor, &amp; be heauy laden,</hi> yet let thē come. But how? with a true faith, nothing <hi>wauering, or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Iam. 1. without fainting. Eccle.</hi> 7. <hi>For the Lord is nigh vnto all those that call vpō him faythfully. Psal.</hi> 145. <hi>According to your fayth be it vnto you,</hi> saith Christ vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> two blind men <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. What faith was y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>? <hi>Do ye beleue,</hi> sayth Christ, <hi>that I am able to do this? we beleue lord</hi> say they. According to this faith they prayed for their eyesight, and had it. Pray thou in the same faith for thy soules health, &amp; thou shalt receaue it. Perswade thy selfe that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but performe (for Christes sake) all his promises of grace and mercy. Beleeue that Iesus Christ shed his hart bloud not only for our sinnes (speaking generally,) but for thy sinnes, and that he can, and will helpe thee. To such a one Christ him selfe sayth: <hi>What so euer you desire when you pray, beleue that you shall haue it &amp; it shalbe done vnto you But whē you pray</hi> (sayth he) <hi>forgeue if you haue ought a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst any man, that your Father in heauen, may forgeue you.. Mark.</hi> 11. So that with this faith must be ioyned peace &amp; loue with our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. Also a life answerable to this faith. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. Least either our prayers be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. Or not regarded. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>Or tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into sinne. Psal.</hi> 109. But who hath this perfection? Or whose prayers then shall be accepted? <hi>Come</hi> therfore in the name of Christ For Christ is perfect, though we vnperfect.




<pb facs="5"/>
his holynes maketh our prayers holy, when he offereth thē vnto the Lord. His righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is our righteousnes, <hi>and he was made sin for vs, that we might be made the righteousnes of God.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>For to him that worketh not, but beleueth in him that iustifieth the vngodly, his fayth is coūted for righteousnes. Rom.</hi> 4. Let not thy sinne therefore withdraw thee from this exercise: for none asketh, but he that wā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: none seeketh to find, but he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath lost.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Come</hi> therfore vnto him thou that doest <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bor,</hi> and art heauy <hi>ladē,</hi> carying in thy minde this one speciall note by the way, what it is thou wilt demaund whē thou commest vnto him, and for whom. For prayers at aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are vnprofitable, proceeding of custome from the lips, not of zeale frō the hart. What we should pray for, the Scripture teacheth plainly. First, for the glory of God. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. <hi>For the peace of Ierusalem. Psal.</hi> 132. <hi>That the word of God may haue free passage.</hi> 2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 3. <hi>that our flight be not in the winter. Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>For our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer sinnes. Eccle</hi> 81. <hi>For soules health. Psal.</hi> 36. <hi>For wisedome.</hi> 2. <hi>Parali.</hi> 1. <hi>For increase of loue. Phil.</hi> 1. <hi>In time of sicknes. Exod.</hi> 8. <hi>In afflictiō. Ia.</hi> 1</p>
   <p>Finally, for all such thinges as the vse and want of man doth require, whether they be earthly graces, or spiritual: alwayes framing our petitions to that certayn and iust rule of Gods will, to the which all manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests must be referred: <hi>for we know not what we should pray as becommeth vs. Rom.</hi> 8. And therefore <hi>we aske and haue not.</hi> Why? <hi>Because we aske amisse. Iam.</hi> 4. <hi>But this trust we haue, that if we doe aske according to his will he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth




<pb facs="5"/>
vs.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. According vnto this his will therfore, I meane his reuealed will, knowen in Scripture, <hi>pray for all men. 1. Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>For all Kinges Esdr 6. Baruc.</hi> 1. <hi>For all that are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>For the Ministers of Gods blessed word Heb.</hi> 1. <hi>That God may open their vtterāce Col</hi> 4. <hi>and increase their nūber. Mat. 9. And that the word of God may be geuen vs. Ephesi.</hi> 6. Finally, we must <hi>pray one for an other. Iam</hi> 2. <hi>And for them that hate vs wrongfully. Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Forgeuing not seuen tymes but seuentye seuen tymes. Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>And as Christ forgaue you, so do ye. Col.</hi> 3. For as the Chirurgian cannot soūd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly heale a wound, so long as the iron of the dart which gaue the wound, is lodged in the bottome therof: So likewise cannot prayer profite, so long as the hart is cankered. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore <hi>forgeue thy brother if he repent him. Luk.</hi> 17 if he repent not, yet forgeue him, doe good vnto him, <hi>so shalt thou heap coles of fire on his head. Rom.</hi> 12. It followeth: <hi>And I will refresh you.</hi> Wherin thou mayst behold (Christian Reader) the assured mercy of God in Iesus Christ, &amp; the effect of true and harty prayer. <hi>For if thou shalt confesse with thy mouth, the Lord Iesus, and shalt beleue in thyne hart, that God raysed him vp from the dead, thou shalt be saued. He is rich vnto all thē that call vpon him. for whosoeuer shall call vpon the name of the Lord shalbe saued. Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Ye shall goe and pray vnto me, and I wil heare you</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>and you shall seek me, and find me, because you shal seek me with al your hart, and I wil be foūd of you, and I wil turn away your captiuity. Iere.</hi> 29. <hi>Seeke and you shall find. Mat.</hi> 6. God is true




<pb facs="6"/>
of his promise, and therfore we find in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, that at Moises prayer <hi>the plague ceased. Exod.</hi> 8. <hi>Miriam by it was deliuered from his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prosy. Num.</hi> 11. By prayer <hi>Anna was of a barrē woman made fruitfull. 1. Reg.</hi> 1. <hi>Dauid obtained forgeuenes for his manslaughter, and whoredōe</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. <hi>Helias caused great plenty of rayne. Ia.</hi> 5.<hi>Ezekias ouercame Zenacharib.</hi> 4. <hi>Reg</hi> 19. <hi>Toby prospered. Tob.</hi> 4. <hi>Susanna deliuered from death Dan.</hi> 13. By prayer <hi>Queen Hester deliuered her and her people. Hest.</hi> 14. <hi>Ionas was deliuered out of the whales belly. Ionas. 2</hi> By prayer <hi>Lepers were clensed. Luk.</hi> 17. <hi>the blinde restored to sight Luk.</hi> 18. <hi>The palsy cured Mat.</hi> 11. <hi>many men &amp; we omen obtained health for their sonnes, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and seruaunts. Mat.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 15. By prayer <hi>the lame was restored to lims. Ma.</hi> 4. <hi>the deafe men to heare. Ma.</hi> 21. <hi>the dome to speake Ma.</hi> 12. By prayer <hi>remissiō of sinnes was obtayned. Ma.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp; the holy ghost purchased for the Apostles, &amp; all the faythfull. Ma.</hi> 26. To be short, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the strength and force of prayer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which, nothing prospereth with vs fortunately.</p>
   <p>But yet here remaineth a farther question, how it may stād with Gods immutable wil, and decree, that our prayers should be of such strength &amp; force to alter y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> threatnings which are decreed, &amp; therfore of force must come to passe. I aunswere God neuer promysed any thing in scripture, for the most part, except it were the absolute promises concerning <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ssias</hi> and such like) but it hath a condition an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto it, ether expresly, or to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood. Likewise, he neuer threatneth (for the




<pb facs="6"/>
most part) but a conditiō is added thereunto. As for example. Adam was created of God that he should haue liued continually in bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed estate, if he would so remayne: this was the conditiō, and the decree. Destructiō was preached to the Niniuites, if they repented not: this was the condition, and the decree. Niniue repented and was not destroyed, but saued: was therfore Gods decree altered? no? For he decreed their destruction, but vpō this condition, if they repented not. Pray therfore (if thou be godly,) that he would geue thee the grace to cōtinue: and if thou be sinful pray that he geue thee the grace to repent. And thus very well our prayers haue strength to stay Gods wrath, his decree remayning im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mutable, because it is threatned but vpō a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition, if we repent not.</p>
   <p>But whence hath prayer this strength? of it self? No. <hi>For we being iustified through faith haue peace toward God</hi> (y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is the fauor of God) <hi>through our Lord Iesus Christ. Rom.</hi> 5. So that Christ is our mouth whereby we speake to the Father: our eyes by which we see the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: our right hand, by which we offer to the Father. Which Christ, except he be our aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, neither we, nor all the saints, can haue a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny thing to doe with God. <hi>For no mā cōmeth to the father but by him. Ioh. 14.</hi> Why then are not our prayers alwayes heard, hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually such a spokesman, who hath all pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er both in heauen and earth? Truely because either we aske amisse, not according to Gods will, and that which is not for vs to receaue, or it pleaseth the Lord to defer our requestes,




<pb facs="7"/>
for tryall of our faith and patience. Hereupō it was that Dauid sayd: <hi>Expectans expectaui Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minum. With long wayting, I waited for the lord and he inclined vnto me and heard my calling. Psal.</hi> 40. Pray therfore continually, with faith, loue, &amp; vnderstanding, in the name of Iesus Christ: pray for al men, at al times, in al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and for al things according to Gods wil. Though thou be a sinner, though God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knoweth the hart, though his decree be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable yet pray vnto him in Iesus Christ, and he will refresh thee. Of this I thought good to admonish thee (Christian Reader,) because it is an easy thing to pray, but to pray aright, is a thing very difficult. Here are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thee zealous, and godly, prayers, some translated out of Latin, &amp; French, some made by the best learned of our time. Use thē as I haue taught thee, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they may be to good vse. Accuse not mine insufficiency in teaching but amend thine owne imperfection in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: praying that we talke not smoothly, &amp; walk crookedly, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we may giue to God y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> father our maker, obedience: faith to Iesus Christ our redemer: and mortification of the flesh to God y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy ghost, our comfortor. Fare wel in Christ Iesu.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>