<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Burton, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121852_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10457</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Burton, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seven dialogues both pithie and profitable : The 1 is of the right vse of things indifferent. 2 sheweth what comfort poperie affordeth in time of daunger. 3 is betweene a good woman and a shrew. 4 is of the conversion of a harlot. 5 is of putting forth children to nurse. 6 is of a popish pilgrimage. 7 is of a popish funerall. By W.B</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>162 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, here I exhibite vnto thy view, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Dialogues, compiled first in Latine by that famous man <hi>Erasmus,</hi> and now by mee translated into English, for the generall good of our Church and Common-wealth: not <hi>absque delectu,</hi> or hand ouer head (as they say) haue I gathered them, but according to the Apostles rule, I haue tried all, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen the best. If thou wilt but enter into them, thou shalt find so delightfull and fruitfull a walke, that thou wilt hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly retire vntill thou hast gone through. They are full of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, both sound and substantiall. Repleate they are with sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nces, not prettie, but pithie, and garnished they are with si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and examples, both wittie and weighty. Of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie both naturall and supernaturall, thou shalt finde there great plentie. Of learning both diuine and humane, thou shalt haue thy fill: Both pleasure and profite will entertaine thee at thy entrance, and recompence abundantly thy trauell all the way thou goest. What should I say more? Good wine needes no Iuy bush, and <hi>Erasmus,</hi> hath no need of my commendations. To the learned and iudicious, yea generally to all men, he is so wel knowne for his deepe learning, and profound iudgement: that for the entertainment of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>se his conferences, I needed not but only to haue said <hi>Erasmus</hi> wrote them. For the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or subiect of them, I refer thee to heir seuer all titles: Only thus much I thought good to make knowne vnto thee, that
<pb facs="6"/>
he fifi Dialogue, which is of a woman in Childbed, is especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tended against the monstrous and vnnaturall expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of children to nurses by wanton women, and such as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing dame Nature most beneficiall vnto them, doe yet shew themselues both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Dames, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> most cruell mothers to their tender infant, whereby many sweete babes, which might haue liued, and done good ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ice, both to God and their Prince, to the Church &amp; Common-wealth are now made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yea, cast away by an vntimely death, hasted by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall dealing of Mothers, and Nurse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>. And many, though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>y liue, yet are marred in the handling, and caused to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> out of kind, by the vnkinde prouision that is made for them, (poore babes) betweene the nice wanton mother, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conscionable greedie nurse. Of men that come to their end by vntimely death, the saying is, that <hi>Plures periere crapula quam gladio:</hi> surffeting killes more then the sword, which I thinke to be true. But of children that come to their end by vntimely death, I suppose I may (and that not vnprobably) say, that more haue miscaried in the nursing, then otherwise, as shall further appeare by the reasons of this reuerend and learned Authour. And for further confirmation thereof, marke what I shall tell thee. Not yet a yeare since, it was my happe (being in London) to be present at s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>pper in a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants house, where this matter of putting forth children to nurse, was debated, <hi>Pro &amp; contra,</hi> (as they say.) There was then in presence an ancient graue Matrone, and a midwife, who openly protested, that she knew a Nurse, that had taken (for greedinesse of gaine) three seuerall women children to nurse at one instant, and they were not of the meanest sor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> neither: and her manner was to goe forth in the morning, and come no more in againe till night, but to leaue the poore tender Infants in the Cradle togither without any companie or comfort, which within a short space by continuall crying
<pb facs="6"/>
and beating themselues one against another for want of food, ended their miserable and wofull dayes: a thing able to break a heart of flint. This midwife being demaunded whether she spake this vpō hearesay or no, did protest that she was an eie witnesse thereof her selfe, and saw them all three laid forth vpon a boord together. The hearing whereof caused some wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try eyes, and bitter sighs. This cruell murtherer answered the Law, but she could not giue the poore Infants their innocent blood againe. When thou hast aduisedly read th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, learned Dialogue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. If by my publishing hereof, but one Infant in the world may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, or be the better educated, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. In the rest of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> perceiue how little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the Papists <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Erasmus,</hi> as a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n of their side. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and reape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> thy prayers.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> the Lord Iesus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> William Burton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>