<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Copie of a Letter sent by the Ministers of Germany to the Dutch Church in LONDON.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121128_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24760.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Copie of a Letter sent by the Ministers of Germany to the Dutch Church in LONDON.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentations of Germany : Wherein, as in a glasse, we may behold her miserable condition, and reade the woefull effects of sinne. Composed by Dr Vincent Theol. an eye-witnesse thereof; and illustrated by pictures, the more to affect the reader. Hereunto are added thre letters, one whereof was sent to the Dutch consistory in London, under the hand and seales of 14. distressed ministers of Swyburggen in Germany</title>
                 <author>Vincent, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 20, 2, 25-33, 32-63, 1 page, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>A Copie of a Letter sent by the Ministers of <hi>Germany</hi> to the <hi>Dutch Church in</hi> LONDON.</head>
   <p>
      <figure>
         <head>Snalles and froges eagerly eaten</head>
      </figure>
      <figure>
         <head>Eatinge dead mens guts and Interalls</head>
      </figure>
      <figure>
         <head>A diuines wife saw 6 of her Children ley starued before her eyes. Corne 3 pounds 18 shilling a bushell.</head>
      </figure>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
SInce the Imperialists passing the Rhine, first entred into our Countrey, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most two yeeres agoe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction hath come upon as like a whirlewind, and sudden desolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath depopulated this our most flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tishing country; our Cities are turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Townes, our Townes into Villages, our Villages into Cottages; where before were a thousand, there now scarce a hundred, and where a hundred, there the tenth is hardly left alive: Those which the sword hath spared, the Pestilence hath consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, those which the Pestilence hath left, Famine hath destroyed, and the small rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which pale-fac'd Famine hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, are so transcēdently miserable, as it
<pb facs="9"/>
even exceeds the most hyperbolical expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of the loftiest Rhetorician, yet that your thoughts may be elevated to a higher pitch, and more serious consideration, we<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> will give you some instances, some exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. After that the Caesarian forces the last yeere had taken <hi>Swybruggen,</hi> &amp; passing with a numbersome army towards <hi>Lotharinge</hi> had destroyed all round about; there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed such a fearefull famin, that the most part of men, especially of thē that dwelt in the country, being urged by pressing neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, was driven to feed on Acorns, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of herbs, roots, briars, nettles, grasse, leaves of trees, so that we may truly take up the complaint of the <hi>Psalmist</hi> (though there it's to be taken in another sense) that man is become like the beast that perisheth, but further, the intralls of beasts, the skins of beeves, sheepe, horses, the haire being first burned, was highly prised, yea Snailes, Frogs with their guts and egs, the flesh of dogs and cats, carrion that hath been dead six weeks or more, hath beene valued at a great rate,
<pb facs="9"/>
nay, sometimes not the price, but a sword hath decided who should have a young colt, or some such thing, though not halfe a yard long. Two women did so long fight with their fists for horse-flesh, that one of of them dyed, yea, in some Famine made such a rage, that they did not abstaine from mans flesh. In a parish neere unto <hi>Sweybruggen,</hi> a brother and sister surviving their parents, and the sister also dying, he (wee tremble in the very writing) fed upon his sister, and devoured the thighes of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Diocesse of <hi>Blissoe Capellana</hi> the corpses of men starved, whose skin cleaved to their bones, so that whilest they were alive, we might truely have said, that their flesh did but infunerall their buried ghosts, yet they being dead, had their in wards, their heart and lungs taken our, and devoured, and that which is more, they have laine in waite to intercept passengers, and those whom they have taken, after they have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, they make their own bellies then graves. A boy of some three yeeres old, the
<pb facs="10"/>
son of a souldier in <hi>Biten</hi> territory, was stollen and carried away by a begger, as she was about to strangle him with a haltar, the mother opportunely comming, rescued him, and moved with wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion slew her, these are the fearefull effects of Famine, so that if we scape the being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by others, yet hunger will even fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish us: the widow of <hi>Iohn Peters Laëri.</hi> Minister, saw before she died (O dreadfull spectacle) sixe of her children perish with Famine. The widow of <hi>Albogastus Rumela</hi> perished her selfe, and foure children, and when they are extinguished by Famine (if they escape being eaten of others) they lie unburied, stinking and torne in pieces by dogs, wolves, and other beasts. Some ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eaten mad dogges, were taken with phrensie themselves, and ragingly dyed. Hence comes such a wildernesse, that in 300 parishes, there's not any left alive, those few that remaine, hide themselves in the woods, and in the townes, the tenth man doth not survive, and many of them too,
<pb facs="10"/>
having their strength dryed up, totter to and fro, nodding and sliding like carved pictures without life, and many being no longer able to stand, fall downe in the middest of the streetes, groveling on the ground, and being onely able to aske for sustenance are ready to give up the ghost. This is the state of our afflicted Countrey, so that we may lament, as <hi>Isay.</hi> The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Sion</hi> is like a city of devastation, like a Sommer cottage in a garden, like a little nouse in a vineyard. It the Lord of Hosts had not left us a remnant, we had beene as <hi>Sodome</hi> and as <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <table>
         <head>In the Dukedome of <hi>Sweybruggen</hi> are left</head>
         <row>
            <cell>Ministers.</cell>
            <cell>40.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Schoolemasters.</cell>
            <cell>16.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Wives.</cell>
            <cell>52.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Widowes</cell>
            <cell>26.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Children.</cell>
            <cell>140.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Orphanes.</cell>
            <cell>18.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>Somme 292. Persons.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
In the names of all the Ministers of <hi>Swey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brugen</hi> sent forth under hand and seale:</p>
   <q>Iohannes Wilthelmus. Rauschius Pastor Numbacensis. Exul.</q>
   <q>Iohannes Christianus. Neuhorelius Pastor Ohmbacensis. Exul.</q>
   <p>This we have had from such good hands, even from the Dutch Cō sistory in <hi>London,</hi> where the Originall is, that it must needes seeme malicious ignorance in any that will but faint in the beliefe hereof.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Sweybruggen.</signed>
      <dateline>14. Novemb. 1636.</dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>