<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Iudgement which a Godly Reuerend man (a Doctor of Diuinity) gaue of this Booke, in a Letter of his to the Author, after he had seene some part of it.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121081_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25786</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Iudgement which a Godly Reuerend man (a Doctor of Diuinity) gaue of this Booke, in a Letter of his to the Author, after he had seene some part of it.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian dictionarie : opening the signification of the chiefe wordes dispersed generally through Holie Scriptures of the Old and New Testament, tending to increase Christian knowledge. Whereunto is annexed: a perticular dictionary for the Reuelation of S. Iohn. For th Canticles, or Song of Salomon. For the Epistle to the Hebrues. By Tho: Wilson minister of the Word, at Saint Georges in Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 240, 243-577, 1, 234, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Iudgement which a Godly Reuerend man (a Doctor of Diuinity) gaue of this Booke, in a Letter of his to the Author, after he had seene some part of it.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y leasure would not suffer me to read so much of your Dictionary, as I wish I had: but that I haue perused, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me that good liking of it, that I assure you, I do take it to bee a very profitable worke, both in regard of the easie Method and order of finding out such mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as are therein contained; as also, for the sound exposition of such Wordes and phrases as you set downe: besides, the manifolde variety of thinges, which a man shall see in a <hi>Synopsis</hi> laide before his eyes. Of all which, the faithfull Reader (especially the Preacher of the word) shall make singular vse. I must therefore giue my best approbation to this worke of yours, as to other your godly labours in this kinde: and when it shall be finished, I shall bee glad to vse the benefit of it, and will aduise such as I am acquainted with, to do the like. Fare ye well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Friend
R. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>