<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The  of a certaine letter fained uder te name of Lucifer Prince of darkenesse, writing to the persecuting Prelates of the Popish Clergie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121078_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10189</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20466</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The  of a certaine letter fained uder te name of Lucifer Prince of darkenesse, writing to the persecuting Prelates of the Popish Clergie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A looking-glasse for all lordly prelates : Wherein they may cleerely behold the true divine originall and laudable pedigree, whence they are descended; together with their holy lives and actions laid open in a double parallell, the first, betweene the Divell; the second, betweene the Iewish high-priests, and lordly prelates; and by their double dissimilitude from Christ, and his Apostles</title>
                 <author>Prynne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 104 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of a certaine letter fained u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>der t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e name of Lucifer Prince of darkenesse, writing to the persecuting Prelates of the Popish Clergie.</head>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Lucifer Prince of darkenesse and profound<note place="margin">The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer, to the proud Prelates of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> heauinesse, Emperor of the high Misteries of the King of Achar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>nt, Captaine of the dungeon Erebus, King of hell, and control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the infernall fire: To all our children of pride, and companions of our Kingdoome, and especially to our Princes of the Church of this latter age and time (of which our aduersarie Iesus Christ, according to the Prophet, saith: I hate the Church or congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wicked) send greeting, and wish prosperity to all that obey our commandments, as also to all these that bee obedient to the Lawes of Satan alrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>y enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and are diligent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> of our behests, and<note place="margin">To diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Bishops of primitive Church &amp; of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Church</note> the precepts of our decree. Know ye that in times past eertaine vica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>s or vicegerents of Christ, following his steps in miracles and vertues, living and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> in a beggerlie life, conuerted (in a manner) the whole world from the yoake of our tyrannie unto their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and manner of life: to the great de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ision and contempt of our prison house and Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>, and also to the no little prejudice and hurt of our Iurisdiction
<pb facs="6"/>
and authoritie, not fearing to hurt our fortified power, and to offend the Majestie of our estate. For then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued we no tribute of the world, neither did the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable<note place="margin">Humilitie edifieth.</note> sort of common people, rush at the gates of our deep dungeon as they were wont to doe, with continuall<note place="margin">Pride de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyeth.</note> pealing and rapping, but then the easie, pleasant and broade way, which leadeth to death, lay still without great noise of trampling travellers, neither yet was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>rod with the feet of miserable men. And when all our Courts were without suters, Hell then began to houle. And thus continuing in great heauinesse and anguish, was robbed and spoiled. Which thing considered, the impatient rage of our stomack could no longer suffer, neither the vglie rechlesse negligence of our great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine generall could any longer indure it. But we, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king remedie for the time that should come after, haue prouided us of a very trim shift: for in stead of these A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles and other their adherents which draw by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ame line of theirs, as well in manners as doctrine, and are odious enemies to vs: we have caused you to be<note place="margin">Placing of all mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</note> their successors, and put you in their place, which be Prelats of the church in these latter times, by our great might &amp; subtiltie, as Christ hath said of you: They have<note place="margin">Thechurch never well governed since the divells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ere taken of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> reigned, but not by me. Once we promised unto him all the Kingdomes of the world; if he would falldowne and worship us; but he would not, saying, My Kingdome is not of this world, and went his way, when the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dudewould have made him a temporal King. But to yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> truly which are fallen from the state of grace and that serve us in the earth, is that my promise fulfilled: and all terrene things by our meanes which we bestowed upon you, are under gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>rment. For he hath said of vs
<pb facs="6"/>
ye know: The Prince of this world cometh, &amp;c. And hath made us to reigne over all children of vnbeleese. Therefore our adversaries before recited, did patiently submit themselves unto the Princes of the world, and did teach that men, should doe so, saying: Be ye sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to every creature for Gods cause, whether it be to the King as most chiefest. And againe: Obey ye them that are made rulers over you, &amp;c. For so their Master commaunded them saying: The Kings of the heathen, have dominion over them, &amp;c. But I thinke it long till we have powred our poyson upon the earth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fill yourselves full. And now bee ye not vnlike those fathers, but also contrary unto them in your life and conditions, and extoll yourselves above all other<note place="margin">Pride in Prelates noted.</note> men. Neither doe ye give unto God that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to him, nor yet to Caesar that which is his: but exercise you the power of both the swords, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">Popish Pre lates nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give to God no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Caesar that which belongeth to God and Caesar.</note> to our decrees, making yourselues doers in word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters, fighting in our quarrell, intangled with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular labours and businesse. And clime ye by little and little frō the miserable state of povertie, unto the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est seats of all honours, and the most princely places of dignitie by your devised practises, and false and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiles and subtiltie: that is, by hypocrisie, flatterie, lying perjurie, treasons, deceits, simonie and other grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wickednesse then which our infernall suries may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>se.<note place="margin">Thedouble Iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Popes tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ords co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of Lucifer.</note> For after that ye have beene by us advanced thit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>er where ye would be, yet that doth not suffice you, but as greedie starvelings more hungrie then ye were before, ye suppresse the poore, scratch and rake together all that comes to hand, perverting and turning every thing topsie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>: so swolne, that ready ye are to burst for
<pb facs="7"/>
pride, liuing like Lechers in all corporall dilicatenesse,<note place="margin">Dominus. Sanctus. Sanctiji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> and by fraud directing all your doings. You challenge to yourselves names of honour in the earth, calling your selves lords holie, yea and most holie fathers.</p>
         <p>Thus, either by violence ye raven, orelse by ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, subtillie ye pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ter away and wrongfully wrest, and by false title possesse those goods which for the susten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the poore members of Christ (whom from our first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>all we have hated) were bestowed and given, consuming them as ye yourselves list, and wherewith<note place="margin">The lasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> life of the Romish Clergie.</note> ye cherish and maintaine an innumerable sort of who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, strump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> with whom ye ride pompou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ie like mightie princes, farre otherwise going, then those poore beggerlie Preists of the primitive Church. For I would ye should build yourselves rich and gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous palaces: ye farelike princes, eating and drinking the most daintiest meates, and pleasantest wines that many be gotten; yee hoord and heape together an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite deale of treasure, not like to him that said, Gold &amp; silver have I none; yee serve &amp; fight for us according to your wages. O most acceptable society or fellowship, promised unto us of the Prophet, and of those fathers<note place="margin">Vhe who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish latter Church of Rome.</note> long agoe reproved: whilest that Christ called thee the Synagogue of Satan, and likened thee to the mightie whore which committed fornication with the Kings of the earth, the adultero is spouse of Christ, and of a chast<note place="margin">Pope Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor not of Simon Peter, but of Simon Magus.</note> person made a strumpet. Thou hast left thy first love &amp; hast cleaved unto us, O our beloved Bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>lon, O our citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, which from the transmigration of Ierusalem come hither: we love you for your deserts, we rejoyce over you, which contemne the Lawes of <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> and imbrace the Lawes of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> our friend, and have them at
<pb facs="7"/>
your fingers ends, and exercise the same publickely<note place="margin">Wicked &amp; vnworthie Ministers admitted in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes Church Vnworthy bestowing of benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> buying and selling spirituall things in the Church of God, and against the Commandement of God. Ye give benefices and honours by petition, or else for money, for favour, or else for filthie service. And refusing to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit those that bee worthy, to Ecclesiasticall dignity, you call unto the inheritance of Gods sanctuary, bauds, liers, flatterers, your nephewes, and your owne children, and to a childish boy, yee give many prebends, the least whereof yee deny to bestow upon a poore good man: ye esteeme the person of a man and receive gifts, yee regard money and have no regard of soules. Ye have made the<note place="margin">Extorsion.</note> house of God a denne of theeves. All abuse, extorsion, is<note place="margin">Perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</note> more exercised, a hundreth fold in your judgement seats, then with any secular tyrant. Yee make lawes and keepe not the same, and dispence with your dispensati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as it pleaseth you; you justifie the wicked for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Acception of person.</note> and take away the just mans desert from him. And briefly, yee perpetrate or commit all kinde of mischiefe,<note place="margin">Bribery.</note> even as it is our will yee should. And yee take much<note place="margin">Love of lucre.</note> paines for lucres sake in our service, and especially to destroy the Christian faith. For now the lay people are<note place="margin">Dstructio of true faith.</note> almost in doubt what they may beleeve, because if ye preach any thing to them at sometimes (althouhg it be but seldome seene, and that negligently enough, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as we would haue it) yet notwithstanding they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you not, because they see manifestly that ye doe cleane contrarie to that ye say. Wherevpon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">The life of Papists contrary to their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> people doing as ye doe, which have the goverment of them, and should be an example unto them of well doing: now many, of them leaning to your rules, dee runne headlong into a whole sea of vices: and so conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb facs="8"/>
a very great multitude flocketh at the strong &amp; well fenced gates of our dungeon. And doubtlesse, ye send us so many day by day of euery sort and kind of people, that we should not be able to entertaine them, but that our insatiable (Choas with her thousand raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning jawes is sufficient to deuour an infinit number of soules. And thus the soueraigntie of our empire, by you hath beene reformed, and our intollerable losse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored.<note place="margin">The Pope increaseth hell.</note> Wherefore, most specially we commend you, &amp; giue you most heartie thanks; exhorting all you, that in any wise ye perseuere and continue, as hitherto ye haue done: neither that you slacke henceforth your enterprise. For why? by your helps we purpose to bring the whole world againe under our powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap> and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Over and besides this, we commit unto you no small authoritie, to supplie our places in the betraying of your brethren; and we make and ordaine you our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, and the Ministers of Antichrist our son, now hard<note place="margin">Antichrist</note> at hand, for whom ye have made a very trim way and passage. Furthermore, we counsell you which occupie the higest roomes of all other, that you worke subtillie, and that ye (fainedly) procure peace between the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note place="margin">The Pope a fained procurer of peace between princes.</note> of the world, and that ye cherish and procure secret causes of discord. And like as craftilie ye have destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and subuerted the Roman Empire: so suffer ye no kingdome to be ouermuch inlarged or inriched by tranquillitie and peace; lest perhaps in so great tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie (al desire of peace set aside) they dispose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to view and eonsider your most wicked works, suppressing on euery side your estate: and from your treasures take away such substance, as we haue caused to be reserued and kept in your hands, vntill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="8"/>
of our wel beloued son Antichrist. We would ye should doe our commendations to our intirely beloved daughters, pride, deceit, wrath, auarice, bellicheere, and lecherie, and to all other my daughters; and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie ho ladie Simonie, which hath made you men, and<note place="margin">Simony the Popes nurse</note> inriched you, and hath giuen you sucke with her owne breasts, and weaned you, and therefore in no wise see that ye call her sinne. And be ye loftie and proud, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that the most high dignitie of your estate doth require such magnificence. And also be ye couetous, for what soeuer ye get and gather into your fardell, it is for St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for the peace of the Church, and for the defence of your patrimonie and the Crucifix; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye may lawfully doe it. Ye may promote your Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals<note place="margin">Promoting of provd and rich Cardinals</note> to the higest seat of dignities, without any let in all the world, in stopping the mouth of our adversarie Iesus Christ, and alleaging againe, that he preferred his kins folks (being but of poore and base degree) vnto the Apostleship; but doe not you so, but rather call, as<note place="margin">Cloked ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse.</note> ye doe, those that live in arrogancie, in haughtinesse of mind, and filthie lecherie, unto the state of wealthie riches and pride; and those rewards and promotions, which the followers of Christ forsook, do ye distribute unto your friends. Therefore as ye shall have better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, prepare ye vices, clocked under the simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of vertues. Alleage for yourselues the glosses of the holie Scripture, and wrest them, directly for to serue<note place="margin">Wresting of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> for your purpose. And if any man preach or teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then ye will, oppresse ye them violently. With the sentence of excommunication, and by your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures heaped one upon another, by the consent of your brethren; let him be condemned as an heretike, and let
<pb facs="9"/>
him be kept in most strait prison, and there tormented<note place="margin">Tyranny and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the <hi>P</hi> pe.</note> till he die, for a terrible example to all such as confesse Christ. And setting all favour apart, cast him out of your temple, lest peradventure the ingrafted word may save <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> soules, which word I abhorre as I do the sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of o her saithfull men. And do your indeuour, that ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> deserue to haue the place which we have prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, under the most wicked dw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>lling on of our dwelling place. Farre ye well with such felicitie as we desire and intend finally to reward and recompence you with.</p>
         <closer>Given at the center of the earth, in that darke place, where all the rablement of divels were present, specially for this purpose ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>led unto our most dolorous Consistorie, under the the Character of our terrible seale, for the confirmation of the premisses.</closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <p>Ex Registro Herefordensi ad verbum <note place="margin">Ex Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</note>
   </p>
   <p>This letter of <hi>Lucif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r</hi> to your Lordly Predec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ssors, then, will I trust, excuse my Epistle and <hi>Parallels</hi> here dedicated to your <hi>Lordships,</hi> now; both from the unjust imputation of calumnie, slaunder, or reviling. And so leaving your <hi>Lordships</hi> to Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>we and reueiw your selves in this new <hi>Looking-Glasse</hi> made purposely for your sweet holy faces, I take my leave of you (as I trust you will now doe of all your Lordlinesse, worldlinesse, pride, and other vices, here discovered) till you have exactely trimed yourselves thereby, to make yoursel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves more amiablc both to God and man, then now you are.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>