<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Jackson, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121045_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03586</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13708</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121045</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned discovrse of ivstification, workes, and how the foundation of faith is overthrowne : By Richard Hooker, sometimes fellow of Corpus Christi College in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Hooker, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 69, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas many, desirous of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutiō in some points hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this learned Discourse, were earnest to haue it copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out: to ease so many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, it hath beene thought most worthy and very necessarie to bee prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that not only they might be satisfied, but the whole Church also hereby edified. The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because it will free the Author from the suspition of some errours, which he hath been thought to haue favoured. Who might well haue answered with <hi>Cremutius</hi> in <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Lib. 4. Ann▪</note>
      <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamea arguuntur, adeò factorum innocens sum.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, the event of that time, wherein he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, shewed that to be true, which the same <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. 1. Hist.</note> Authour spake of a worse, <hi>Cui deerat inimicus, per amicos oppressus;</hi> and that there is not <note n="c" place="margin">In vita A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricolae.</note>
      <hi>minus periculum ex magna fama, quàm ex mala.</hi> But he
<pb facs="3"/>
hath so quit himselfe, that all may see, how, as it was said of <hi>Agricola, Simul suis virtutibus, simul vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs aliorum in ipsam gloriam praeceps agebatur.</hi> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching whom I will say no more, but that which my Authour said of the same man, <hi>Integritatem, &amp;c. in tanto viro referre, iniuria virtutum fuerit.</hi> But as of all other his writings, so of this I wil adde that, which<note n="d" place="margin">Lib. a.</note>
      <hi>Velleius</hi> spake in commendation of <hi>Piso, Nemo fuit, qui magis, que agenda erant, curaret, sine vlla ostentatione agendi.</hi> So not doubting, Good Christian Reader, of thy assent herein, but wishing thy favourable acceptance of this worke, (which will be an inducement to set forth others of his learned labours) I take my leaue; from Corpus Christi College in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus HENRY IACKSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>