<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS HONORABLE FRIEND AND MOST WOR∣thie
knight, Sir Francis Ʋere, chiefe commander
of her Maiesties forces in the seruice of the
states, in the vnited Prouinces, and Gouer∣nour
of the Cautionarie towne of
Briele, in Holland.</title>
           <author>Roberts, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121459_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21131</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7488</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121459</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS HONORABLE FRIEND AND MOST WOR∣thie
knight, Sir Francis Ʋere, chiefe commander
of her Maiesties forces in the seruice of the
states, in the vnited Prouinces, and Gouer∣nour
of the Cautionarie towne of
Briele, in Holland.</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Obseruations, vpon the fiue first bookes of Cæsars Commentaries : setting fourth the practise of the art military, in the time of the Roman Empire. Wherein are handled all the chiefest points of their discipline, with the true reasons of euery part, together with such instructions as may be drawn from their proceedings, for the better direction of our moderne warres. By Clement Edmunds</title>
                 <author>Edmondes, Clement, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 199, 1 page, 6 plates (4 folded), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS HONORABLE FRIEND AND MOST WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
knight, Sir Francis Ʋere, chiefe commander
of her Maiesties forces in the seruice of the
states, in the vnited Prouinces, and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of the Cautionarie towne of
Briele, in Holland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, hauing at length ended this taske of obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
it falleth necessarily vnder your patronage,
as well in regard of the continual incouragement,
which I receiued from the fauor you beare to such
imploiments; as also for that this worke of Caesar
hath alwaies beene held in your particular recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,
as the <hi>Breuiarie</hi> of soldiers; and thought worthie of as
great regard, as euer M. Brutus attributed to Polybius, or Charles
the fift to Philip de Commines. I must acknowledge the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of this work to haue proceeded from Sir Iohn Scot, a knight
deseruing great honour for his iudgement and skill in matter of
war, whose desire to vnderstand the true sense of this history, and
the mysterie of that discipline, first mooued me to vndertake this
labour. The obseruations which I haue taken, are such as offer
themselues to vulgar wits, vpon the consideration of such points
as are handled in this discourse: for as an old Gouernesse well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced
in error, directeth her young charge to vertue, by such
documents as rise from her owne mistakings; so the fruit of this
worke riseth chiefely from thence, where the benefit of good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
is manifest; or where ill atchieuement beareth witnesse of
an error. The specialities of greater consequence, which are either
skilfully shadowed, or necessarily implied in the historie, I leaue
to the wisedome of iudicious commanders, as an obiect fit for
such iudgments, and impertinent to conceits of an inferiour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
That which is alreadie handled shall serue to witnesse, that
Caesars works containe matter sufficient to entertaine the greatest
wits, and that my desire is to gratifie our souldiers with my best la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
which I recommend chiefely to your Lordship, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Readie to doe you seruice,
C. EDMVNDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>