<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Worshipfull, Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight: one of the worship∣full Aldermen, of the honorable Citty of London: VV. M. wisheth Earths Happines, and Hea∣uens Blessednes.</title>
           <author>Muggins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121897_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07877</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18248</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Worshipfull, Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight: one of the worship∣full Aldermen, of the honorable Citty of London: VV. M. wisheth Earths Happines, and Hea∣uens Blessednes.</title>
                 <author>Muggins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons mourning garment, or funerall teares : worne and shed for the death of her wealthy cittizens, and other her inhabitants. To which is added, a zealous and feruent prayer, with a true relation how many haue dyed of all diseases, in euery particuler parish within London, the liberties, and out parishes neere adioyning from the 14 of Iuly 1603. to the 17 of Nouember. following</title>
                 <author>Muggins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Worshipfull, Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight: one of the worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Aldermen, of the honorable Citty of London: VV. M. wisheth Earths Happines, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens Blessednes.</head>
   <p>RIght Worshipful and graue Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: if my knowledge and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, were answerable to my good will and affection: this my poore labour now mourning in a sable Weede, should be as great and precious, as to the contrary it is weake, and slender. And knowing that the Vertuous minde, respecteth not so much the valewe of the guift, as the good will of the giuer, emboldeneth me to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sēt this smal Pamphlet to your Worships view; most humbly crauing pardon for my rash attempt, which if to your wonted clemmencie I doe obtaine. I shall liken my selfe to a poore Debtor owing much, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgiuen of all his large reckonings and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous accounts, and bound in duty to pray for your Worships long life, with increase of honor.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships at Commaund, VVILLIAM MVGGINS</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>