<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Harrison, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121191_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02728</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12859</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121191</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Harrison, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short relation of the departure of the high and mightie Prince Frederick King Elect of Bohemia: with his royall &amp; vertuous Ladie Elizabeth; and the thryse hopefull yong Prince Henrie, from Heydelberg towards Prague, to receiue the crowne of that kingdome (Whearvnto is annexed the solempnitie or maner of the coronation. Translated out of dutch. And now both togither published ... to giue satisfaction to the world, as touching the ground, and truth, of his Maties. proceedings, &amp; vndertaking of that kingdome ... As also to encourage all other noble &amp; heroicall spirits (especiallie our owne nation, whom in hônour it first and chieffelie concerneth) by prerogative of that high, and soveraigne title, hæreditarie to our kings &amp; princes: defendees [sic] of the faith) to the lyke Christian resolution, against Antichrist and his adhærents</title>
                 <author>Harrison, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THis was my meditation coming downe the Rhyne, (the day after their Ma<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> departure from Heydelberg) writtē in my table booke, among other observations; which vpon my arrivall, I thought to have published; ut for some reserved reasons (not heare to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed) as then not thought convenient. So deferred till now (as may be thought also) vnseasonable; after the newes of their Ma<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> entrie, Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; all other Solempnities past. Yet the two principall motives remayne still thearin mentioned; to wit, my zeale &amp; affectiō, which I can not supresse, but must crave leave vpon so good a warrant (as my conscience assureth me of) to expresse And (perhaps) may be of some further vse to incense o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And hearvnto I have annexed some <hi>Anagrams</hi> which à frend of myne gave me: yet not privie to my intent of publishing eyther the one or the other. I say they are not myne, but a frend (whose name I conceale) did them. The honour wherof I dare not assume, lest (perhaps) he should vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>write:</p>
   <q>Hos ego versiculos feci tulit alter honores.</q>
   <p>If I have offended either in the one, or the other; the two former motives shall excuse me: I take all to my selfe: <hi>Me me, adsum qui feci.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Harrison.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>