<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right high and mighty Prince Edwarde, Duke of Somerset, Protector of the kynges maiest. real∣mes and dominions, and gouerner of his most Royall person, Christo∣fer Langton wyssheth health and encreace of all god∣lynesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121147_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05064</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15205</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right high and mighty Prince Edwarde, Duke of Somerset, Protector of the kynges maiest. real∣mes and dominions, and gouerner of his most Royall person, Christo∣fer Langton wyssheth health and encreace of all god∣lynesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A uery brefe treatise, ordrely declaring the pri [n] cipal partes of phisick : that is to saye: thynges natural. Thynges not naturall. Thynges agaynst nature. Gathered, and sette forth by Christopher Langton</title>
                 <author>Langton, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>190 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To the right high and mighty Prince Edwarde, Duke of Somerset, Protector of the kynges maiest. real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and dominions, and gouerner of his most Royall person, Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Langton wyssheth health and encreace of all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Hisicke hath bene so affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted &amp; clogged wyth ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt wryters (it were to tediouse to rehearce ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theyr names or theyre opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) that before Gallenes dayes, none knewe which was the truth. And though Gallen wrot orderly, yet by the iniurye of tyme, the best parte of his workes be lost, to the great hynderaunce of all suche as shalbe studentes in Phisicke: Yet yf but halfe that that remayneth, were englysshed, I woulde then thynke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we shoulde haue al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="4"/>
in Phisicke a greate deale the playnar, to the great profit &amp; welth of the realme dyuers wayes. For fyrst it woulde saue great exspence of money, which vnlearned stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers dayly carrye awaye. Than it woulde be the safegarde of manye mennes lyues, whiche myght be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do the king otherwyse right good seruice: And finally it wolde cause a great encrease of wisdome, whiche passeth bothe golde &amp; preci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous stones. Wherefore I conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the wealth of the greater nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, haue taken vpon me to wryte orderly of a great peace of phisicke which I dedicate vnto your grace not that I thynke it worthy so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Prince, but partly because I iudge you a man muche desirous to knowe suche thinges as be here set foorth for the bodyly healthe, &amp;
<pb facs="4"/>
partely for that I trust your noble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes wil further al godly ententes: whiche yf ye doe, ye shall not only encorage me (whiche am but a ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar, and as yet a young student in Physicke) but other also (whiche are alredy perfect in the workes of Physicke) dayly to set foorth suche thinges, as may profit many, and hurte none. Thus I praye god graunt to youre grace in al your affayers, most prosperous successe, and after this trāsitory lyfe, ioye withoute ende. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>