<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE, THE EARLE OF MIDLESEX, LORD HIGH TREASVRER OF ENGLAND, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Misselden, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121074_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07594</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17985</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121074</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE, THE EARLE OF MIDLESEX, LORD HIGH TREASVRER OF ENGLAND, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Misselden, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The circle of commerce. Or The ballance of trade : in defence of free trade: opposed to Malynes little fish and his great whale, and poized against them in the scale. Wherein also, exchanges in generall are considered: and therein the whole trade of this kingdome with forraine countries, is digested into a ballance of trade, for the benefite of the publique. Necessary for the present and future times. By E.M. merchant</title>
                 <author>Misselden, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 145, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, THE EARLE OF MIDLESEX, LORD HIGH TREASVRER OF ENGLAND, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Great <hi>Grande</hi> of <hi>Italy, Right Honourable,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted much in the delightfull skill of <hi>Picture;</hi> sent a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier in post haste to all the principall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof, to take a touch, of the rarest and best Masters in that Science, for his choyce of some rare and exquisite Piece. The Messenger posting from place to place, and getting of every one some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, at last found out <hi>Giotto,</hi> a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb facs="3"/>man, and second to none of his time in that skill; as <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> thus saye's in his praise,</p>
   <q>
      <l>— Per quem pictura revixit,<note place="margin">In Epitaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Iotti. Peachams Compl. Gent. Cap. <hi>12.</hi>
         </note>
      </l>
      <l>Cui quàm recta manus tàm fuit &amp; facilis:</l>
   </q>
   <p>Of him I say, this Messenger desired, as hee had done of the rest, some Master Piece, to present vnto his Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. <hi>Giotto,</hi> willing to shew the dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Art and wit, and the facility of his hand, call'd for a sheet of paper, and in the turning of an hand, drew a <hi>Circle</hi> so perfect and exact; that it was impossible for any man living, to circi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, or circulat, with the helpe of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe, a more absolute <hi>Orb.</hi> The Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier not being an Artist, ask't if that were all: yes said <hi>Giotto,</hi> and it may bee, more then all. And so indeed it proov'd. For when the Messenger had presented to his Lord and Master all the Pieces, <hi>Giotto's Circle</hi> was preferr'd to all the rest, and hee honoured aboue the rest: and thence it went into a Proverb in <hi>Italy, Piu tondo ch'il Circolo di Giotto:</hi> more round then
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Giotto's Circle.</hi> Others, <hi>My Lord,</hi> may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto <hi>Your Lordship, Little Fishes, Great Whales, Par's of Exchange, Pieces</hi> of greater price; I haue nothing but a <hi>Circle:</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, the <hi>Circle of learning;</hi> but the <hi>Circle of Commerce:</hi> yet such a <hi>Circle,</hi> as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends within the <hi>Periphery,</hi> or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference thereof, the <hi>Ballance of Trade.</hi> There's my draught: or rather <hi>My Lord,</hi> it's <hi>Yours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For although the <hi>Ballance of Trade,</hi> is an ancient <hi>Piece,</hi> which in elder times, hath beene in great vse in this Kingdome, as I shall shew in this <hi>Circle,</hi> in it's owne <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle:</hi> yet it was almost worne out and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faç't, but renew'd and refresh't by none, but by <hi>Your Lordship</hi> onely. When the <hi>Eye of Heaven,</hi> in the <hi>Eye of the King,</hi> had look't vpon <hi>You,</hi> and pickt <hi>You</hi> out, and plaç't <hi>You</hi> in an higher <hi>Orb; You</hi> were first seene in this <hi>Circle,</hi> of the <hi>Ballance of Trade:</hi> Other faire <hi>Pieces You</hi> had, but this was <hi>Your Master Piece,</hi> because all the rest had reference vnto this. For all your servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces done to <hi>The King,</hi> and in <hi>The King, The
<pb facs="4"/>Kingdome:</hi> of what <hi>Longitude,</hi> or <hi>Latitude</hi> soever those <hi>Pieces</hi> were, you tryed them all by this <hi>Scale: You</hi> discerned the <hi>Right</hi> from the <hi>Oblique,</hi> by this <hi>Circle,</hi> by this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Oracles of Apollo,</hi> being ask't when the warres of <hi>Greece</hi> should haue a <hi>Period,</hi> Replyed, when they could <hi>Double the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique Altar in Delphos:</hi> which <hi>Plato</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them, to be an answer in reproof of their ignorance in <hi>Geometry.</hi> For the <hi>Doubling</hi> of the <hi>Cube in Solids,</hi>
      <note place="margin">P. Ramus Geom. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> and the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drature</hi> of the <hi>Circle in Plaine,</hi> is a <hi>Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call probleme,</hi> not to bee knowne without the knowledge of that <hi>Art.</hi> And sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if any man aske, when we shall haue an end, of this decay of Trade: it may be answered, when <hi>Your Lordship</hi> will <hi>Double this Cube,</hi> and <hi>Quadrat this Circle of Commerce in the Ballance of Trade.</hi> Which prooue's a <hi>Hercules</hi> labour vnto <hi>Others,</hi> but will be easie vnto <hi>You:</hi> because <hi>You</hi> see with <hi>Your Owne; They</hi> with others eyes.</p>
   <p>And hence it is that wee here below,
<pb facs="4"/>haue had so much stirre, about <hi>Malyne's Par:</hi> the <hi>Parity</hi> and <hi>Disparity</hi> whereof, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst ignorant men, is made a <hi>Mystery in Exchange,</hi> and to haue in it a great deale of <hi>Causality</hi> of the <hi>Decay of Trade.</hi> But we are happy in <hi>Your Lordship,</hi> which can easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discerne this <hi>Flemish,</hi> from our <hi>Sterling Standard.</hi> No glosse, no false face, can deceiue <hi>Your Lordships</hi> sight. For as <hi>You</hi> were <hi>Of vs,</hi> and now <hi>You</hi> are farre <hi>Aboue vs:</hi> so can <hi>You</hi> iudge, as farre <hi>Beyond vs,</hi> as <hi>You</hi> are <hi>Distant from vs.</hi> I shall therefore bee a Suitor to <hi>Your Lordship,</hi> that if there be any place or vse, in the whole <hi>Circle of Commerce,</hi> for <hi>Malyne's Par of Exchange,</hi> that <hi>Your Lordship</hi> will let him bee the <hi>Master</hi> of that office when it is Created: if not, that <hi>Malynes</hi> may know the price of these paines, to teach vs a new doctrine, which we never learnt of <hi>Your Lordship:</hi> and with such counterfeit stuffe to abuse <hi>The State,</hi> which happely doth enioy <hi>Your Lordship,</hi> and in <hi>You</hi> the knowledge of <hi>Commerce.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Your Ballance of Trade,</hi> my <hi>Lord,</hi> will
<pb facs="5"/>soone discover the lightnes of this va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. <hi>That,</hi> not <hi>This,</hi> was <hi>Your</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, let it bee <hi>Your</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> also. <hi>That</hi> was the <hi>Foundation,</hi> let it bee the <hi>Consummation</hi> of <hi>Your Noble building.</hi> Let none build vpon <hi>Your Lordships foundation,</hi> finish it, perfect it <hi>Your Selfe, Your Selfe</hi> shall haue all the honour.</p>
   <p>Goe on therefore <hi>Noble Lord,</hi>
   </p>
   <q>Spartam quam nactus es constanter tueri.</q>
   <p>
      <hi>You</hi> are the <hi>Mirrour of Merchants,</hi> the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the <hi>Renowne of your name,</hi> the <hi>Beautie of Your Familie,</hi> the <hi>Glorie</hi> of <hi>Your Countrie,</hi> an <hi>Honour</hi> to <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> and the <hi>Choice</hi> of the <hi>Choicest King.</hi> Honour <hi>His</hi> choice, in the choicest service, <hi>You</hi> can doe, to <hi>So Good,</hi> to <hi>So Great a King.</hi> Adorne the <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> doe good to <hi>Your Countrie,</hi> Embellize <hi>Your Familie,</hi> make <hi>Your Name</hi> more and more <hi>Noble,</hi> loue <hi>London,</hi> and make much of <hi>Merchants.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And I pray God, with encrease of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> giue you encrease also of the gifts and graces of Gods Spirit: without
<pb facs="5"/>which <hi>You</hi> can doe none of these: and with which, <hi>You</hi> may doe <hi>So</hi> and <hi>So,</hi> and <hi>More</hi> also.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> giue <hi>You</hi> fauour with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and conserue <hi>Your Lordship</hi> long, <hi>Regi, Gregi, mihi;</hi> to <hi>The King, The Kingdome:</hi> And last of all, to him that's least of all,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>But Affected most of all, to doe your Lordship seruice,</hi> EDW. MISSELDEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>