<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121926_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19675</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To those of the Romish CHVRCH.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three conformities. Or The harmony and agreement of the Romish Church with gentilisme, Iudaisme and auncient heresies. VVritten in French by Francis de Croy G. Arth. and newly translated into English. Seene, perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Cro, François de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 130, 6, 131-177, 25, 179-258 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>To those of the Romish <hi>CHVRCH.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>YOu Romane Catholicks, who sees this work,</l>
      <l>I'st possible, that it you can behould?</l>
      <l>And cannot marke that horrible inchaunt,</l>
      <l>Wherein bewitching Sathan doth you hould?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If the Apostles, those most holy men,</l>
      <l>Should now into the world againe returne,</l>
      <l>Would neuer thinke that Christians you were,</l>
      <l>Because al means, might teach you truth, you shun.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I speake, and pronounce this, not bitterly,</l>
      <l>I speake it with a godly louing zeale;</l>
      <l>Your pietie, of which you make such bragges,</l>
      <l>No warrant hath, your grieuous sinnes to heale.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For you in humane merits firme your trust,</l>
      <l>And that's your anchors-hould, and not in him,</l>
      <l>Who sets you free from the eternall death,</l>
      <l>And is the onely ransome for your sinne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Antichrist by little, and little, and by craft,</l>
      <l>And subtill shifts into the Church is slid,</l>
      <l>And in Gods holy Temple now, at last</l>
      <l>He sits in pompe, trusting there still to byd.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <l>It was often foretold, that he should come,</l>
      <l>And for our sinnes, this reuolt was suffr'ed,</l>
      <l>And that there must of meere necessitie,</l>
      <l>Great, and most blind errours be permitted.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yea, so ordain'd by our most puissant God,</l>
      <l>That his most sacred Church should be opprest,</l>
      <l>For a time in the bonds of Papacie,</l>
      <l>For so long time as he would thinke it best.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But from these crooked and peruersed wayes,</l>
      <l>Full of dreadfull, and most deadly darknesse,</l>
      <l>God hath bin pleased, through his great bountie,</l>
      <l>Vs for to draw, and eke with peace to blisse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Euen so Christ our Lord, and <hi>Ionas</hi> were,</l>
      <l>The figures of Gods Church, in these last dayes:</l>
      <l>For one was dead, the other prisoner,</l>
      <l>Christ in tombe, <hi>Ionas</hi> in the fish, he prayes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Lift vp your eyes, with speed behould this light,</l>
      <l>Which shines in you, and Iesus Christ imbrace,</l>
      <l>By liuely faith; cast off those euill Sp'rits,</l>
      <l>Which makes you scorne Gods word to your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Christ is the truth, the way, and onely life,</l>
      <l>The Churches most deare spouse, run then amaine</l>
      <l>And by a constant faith, liue chast to him,</l>
      <l>His company brings comfort, that's your gaine.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>