<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas N. to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Fisher, John, of Chester</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121210_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68108</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12147</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121210</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas N. to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fisher, John, of Chester</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chronicle at large and meere history of the affayres of Englande and kinges of the same : deduced from the Creation of the vvorlde, vnto the first habitation of thys islande: and so by contynuance vnto the first yere of the reigne of our most deere and souereigne Lady Queene Elizabeth: collected out of sundry aucthors, whose names are expressed in the next page of this leafe. Anno Domini. 1569. Cum priuilegio</title>
                 <author>Grafton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 192, 8, 2, 1369, 43 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Thomas N. to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMVCH AS THE EXAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of good and euill doinges, in thys that the one sort doe allure to good, the other doe fraye from euill, doe tende both to one good ende in well dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed mindes, it hath euer beene thought a beneficiall woorke to the societie of men to set forth in histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and true report, the doings and liues of men as they haue deserued. And though vertue of it selfe be of worthynesse ynough to be loued for it selfe, and in honest mindes free from vanitie, is to her selfe sufficient recompense, yet hath God for commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of mankinde planted in nature a prayse worthye affection to be well spoken of for doing well, and shame to beare infamy for doyng euill. Thys hath made vertue cōmended to encrease: This hath restreyned those from sinne, whom conscience coulde not: This hath holden men in order for feare of the sight of men, whome the feare of God that seeth all withheld not: This hath raysed men out of drowsie idlenesse whome the sounde of Gods promises and threatnings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked not: This, whereby is quickened endeuour to lyue after death, is the very proofe in nature, that mans minde confesseth and hopeth for immortality.</p>
   <p>As true reporting therfore auayleth to the encrease of well doing, so good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation is profitable to the furtheraunce of the true reporters labour, and is the verie recompense that euerye honest trauayler in any good worke shall be sure to finde at the hands of euery one that feareth not to heere shame for his euill deedes.</p>
   <p>And as it is reason that good be done to him that doth good to many, so where the author and gatherer of this woorke hath with his honest labors made the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actes and good deseruings of many to liue in good memorie, so I thought it not reason, specially hauing among infinite other receaued commoditie by his labors, that his owne well doyngs should altogether dye in forgetfulnesse. I must there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good Reader, to the intent to prouoke thy fauourable receauing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struyng of thys worke, put thee in remembraunce how manye wayes the great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of this man susteyned with great charge and perilles, haue bene to vs profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that we be not to him vnthankfull. It hath suffised him to deserue well, it shall not suffise vs to receaue without receauing well, that is, to the encouragement of him and other to deserue well. That which he of modestie maye not vtter, we of honestie maye not hide. This therefore I am to affirme, because I knowe it, and the more assuredly to affirme because many moe knowe it, and most reasonably to allege because the whole Realme hath profite by it, that the man hath not spent one quarter of hys lyfe to his owne ease or commoditie, but as a good Citezen for the benefite of the Citie of London, as a good Englisheman for the profite of the Realme of Englande, and as a good Christian for the furtheraunce of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Bible in English, that vnvaluable Iewell, we haue by his trauayle, first with his charge and attendaunce procuring the translation thereof, then sundrie times copying the same out with his owne hande, thirdly printing it in Fraunce with his great expense and perill, when the rage of those holy fathers which then enuyed Christian men christianity, not only would not suffer it to be done in England, but also procured the same beyng printed to be attached in Fraunce &amp; openly burned, himselfe hardly escaping with his life. Not discouraged herewith, but still caried with zeale to doe good, he attempted the woorke againe, and to Gods great praise and to the edification of Christes Church, performed it. Sithence that, how benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall he hath beene in furthering good wittes to learning, in setting learned wittes to working, because the rehearsall in particularitie cannot but haue some affinitie with exprobration, I leaue to their remembraunce that haue tasted of it, and shall be mooued in their conscience where it maye doe him good, to testifie it. But the
<pb facs="7"/> Citie of London may not forget, or forgetting may not be vntolde of it, or well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring may not suppresse it, that moe maye be mooued by his example and their thankfulnesse, to be suche Citezens as he hath beene, how he hath trauayled in their affayres from time to time, as if anye priuate man among them had but a seruaunt or factor of such faythfulnesse, policie and painefulnesse, as he hath shewed himselfe for them all, it should not for shame be forgotten, I will not saye vnrecompensed. Who knoweth not his diligence in laboring for and attending on that noble worke of that most blessed Prince, King, yea saint, Edwarde the sixt, in erecting the Hospi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles? his labors and expences in ouerseing the same beyng erected, preferring it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all his awne businesse to his great hinderaunce? It is proueable ynough if any will be so past honest thankfulnesse to denie it. And nowe lastly, beside a number of good bookes by him published, he hath for the whole realme gathered thys Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycle of Englande, wherein thou mayest readily see with small trauayle and coste that which heretofore scattered in manye woorkes was chargeable to get and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome to finde, beside very much that in none heretofore hath beene vttered.</p>
   <p>In this he hath brought things vnknowne from darknesse, vntrue reportes from error, confusion of affayres from disorder, impertynent tediousnesse to reasonable proportion, and hath made a large, playne, true and meere historie of this Realme, wherby men may be certified of truth, the Reader may haue delitefull &amp; profitable knowlege: our Countrie men and the subiects, but specially the princes therof, dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from slaunderous reportes of foreyne writers: Kings maye learne to depende vpon God, and acknowlege his gouernaunce in their protection: the nobilitie may reade the true honor of their auncestours: The Ecclesiasticall state maye learne to abhorre trayterous practises and indignities done against kings by the Popishe vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Clergie: high and lowe may shonne rebellions by their dreadfull effectes, and beware how they attempt against right, how vnhable soeuer the person be that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it: we all may be warned to thanke God for the most vertuous, wise and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able gouernement that we now enioye in comparison of terrible times heretofore: Eche man maye haue a glasse to see things past, whereby to iudge iustly of thinges present and wisely of things to come; To beholde the beautie of vertue and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of vice: what sweetenesse remayneth after well doing, what stinges of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce euill doing leaueth: Men of elder honor, maye learne not to deface their forefathers prayse: The newer sort maye seeke to bring light and dignitie to their houses: and finally all men in seing the course of Gods doings, may learne to dread his iudgementes and loue his prouidence: maye see how good doings be defended, euill doings and wrongs reuenged, bloud with bloud, violence with violence, iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with miseries, and so growe into an affection to geue to eache matter his right iudgement, to eche superiour his right duetie, to eche other that which iustice or charitie wylleth, and to all well doers, &amp; among others to this setter forth of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny well doyngs, such thankfull acceptation as his whole life employed to common benefite hath deserued. Receaue it therfore good Reader so, as thy selfe maiest haue most benefite of it, and he may in his age thinke his youth well spent in doing good to London, Englande and Christianitie. And aboue all things forget not, to geue God thankes for the Queenes maiesties most gracious reigne, so farre in comparison exceeding the tymes that here thou readest of: And beseeche him long to preserue her, without or after whome there is great daunger and small hope: and specially let euery one endeuour for himselfe, not to moue God for our sinnes to cal her home from vs to him to hastily:</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Sera at in coelum redeat, diu{que}</l>
         <l>Loeta vt intersit populo Britanno,</l>
         <l>Neu sinat hostes equitare inultos,</l>
         <l>Se duce, Christi.</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>