<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>HENRIE STEPHEN to his friend.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121359_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68037</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10553</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121359</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>HENRIE STEPHEN to his friend.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A world of vvonders: or An introduction to a treatise touching the conformitie of ancient and moderne wonders : or a preparatiue treatise to the Apologie for Herodotus. The argument whereof is taken from the Apologie for Herodotus written in Latine by Henrie Stephen, and continued here by the author himselfe. Translated out of the best corrected French copie</title>
                 <author>Estienne, Henri</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Norton, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 217, 7, 229-358, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_friend">
   <pb n="13" facs="16"/>
   <head>HENRIE STEPHEN to his friend.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I first tooke pensill in hand to draw the lineaments of this present Apologie, wherin I haue shadowed out a world of wonders, I perswaded my selfe that such as were acquainted with my daily emploiments (whereof the weale-publike, I meane such as loue and like good literature may reape lesse pleasure, but more profite, then by this discourse) would reckon this worke for none of the least wonders. And nothing doubting but that you (Sir) were one of that number, I was the more willing to ease you of that paine, (paine I say, seeing admiration is counted a passion by Philosophers) and to satisfie you touching the inducements which moued me to vndertake this present businesse. Marke then in what tearmes it stands. Hauing set forth <hi>Herodotus</hi> translated by <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> and corrected by my selfe, and prefixed an Apologie in behalfe of his historie, I had intelligence not long after of one who was minded to translate it into <hi>French:</hi> which I did the rather beleeue, and the more feare, for that I remembred a like pranke which had bene played me about eight yeares before. For I had no sooner published a little Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, but it met with a tinkerly translator, who Pigmalion-like doted vpon his owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, thinking he had put out the Popes eye; whereas to my thinking he roued at randon, and erred the whole heauen; in such sort that I could neither conceiue what I had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, nor yet perceiue any footsteps of my wonted stile. So that I may well say with the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> that he performed not the office of a <hi>traduttore,</hi> but of a <hi>traditore,</hi> that is, that he played not the part of a <hi>translator,</hi> but of a <hi>traitor.</hi> Which notwithstanding I pardoned in that namelesse author, not doubting but that in doing amisse he did his best endeuour. Fearing therefore lest the like inconuenience would befall this mine Apologie, I thought good to take order for it betime. And after a short summons of my thoughts, I soone per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that it was my onely course to preuent these turkishers, by being mine owne inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter; as knowing I could not only vnderstand mine owne meaning better then another, but also take that libertie to my selfe, which would neither be permitted them, nor yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeme them. Notwithstanding all fell out crosse and contrary to my expectation. For the translation which I had begun, disliked me so much, that I gaue it ouer in the plaine field, and in stead thereof (for mine owne satisfaction) began to prosecute this present worke, or rather some shadow or semblance thereof. For certes it was not my purpose to lanch so farre into the deepe; but going about to saile by the shore, I straight found that I was flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the maine. And then I remembred the Greeke prouerbe, that a man ought to be well aduised before he take ship, but when he hath once hoised vp the sailes, it is too late to intreate the winds. Notwithstanding I am arriued (God be thanked) at the last, if not at the wished hauen, yet where I rest content. But to leaue these flourishes of Rhetoricke, and to speake plaine English, whereas my purpose was not to exceed the particulars hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Latin Apologie, I fell by little and little into other discourses, the prosecuting whereof I found to be more tedious then I had thought, and such as you here see. Howbeit I am in good hope that this worke (once come to perfection) will be both pleasant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; so as the Reader may not only reape benefite by euery particular here recorded, but further learne to parallele auncient stories with moderne, by obseruing their conformitie
<pb n="14" facs="17"/>
and Analogie (if this word sound not too harshly in English eares;) and consequently to speake with greater reuerence and respect of auncient historians: as also to omit no remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable thing (which may stand him in stead when occasion shall serue) without due obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. I say, <hi>this worke once come to perfection,</hi> because this is but an Introduction or Preparatiue treatise, as the title purporteth: albeit a man may here take a tast of that which hath bene said, which is the cause why I call it <hi>A preparatiue Treatise,</hi> or <hi>The first booke of the Apologie.</hi> But you may here haply demaund the reason that moued me first to pen the Latin Apologie, which was my first Essay? Verily (to deale plainly with you) the great pleasure which I tooke in reading the Greeke storie, made me not onely forget my paines in correcting infinite scapes in the Latin translation: but further so ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged me vnto it by the great content it gaue me, that I could do no lesse then pleade for it in these my Apologeticall discourses, against the Philippicks and sharpe inuectiues of such seuere and rigide censurers as cease not to accuse it of falshood, forgerie and fabulositie: and that the great desire I had to testifie my good will and affection towards this author, shold banish all feare of mine owne insufficiency to vndertake the penning of such an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, til some other, better able to furnish out this argument, should take it in hand. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer I confesse (for I can conceale nothing from my friend) that one reason among the rest which moued me to affect this storie (being common to me with all French-men who are seene in the <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue) was not onely the great affinitie the French hath with the Greeke aboue any other language (as I haue shewed at large in a treatise which I publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed touching the conformitie of these two languages) but for that there is not a Greeke author extant at this day, nor any to be found in the best Libraries in <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Italie,</hi> which agreeth so well with the French phrase, and to the vnderstanding whereof the knowledge of the French is so necessarie and auaileable, as <hi>Herodotus</hi> is.</p>
   <p>Now as I haue taken vpon me to be <hi>Herodotus</hi> his aduocate: so I am to intreate you to be mine, in pleading for me, against such supersilious censurers as not content to lash me for my faults (for I feare me I haue giuen them iust cause in many places) shall straine themselues to go a note aboue Ela, and to correct <hi>Magnificat,</hi> in calumniating that which their consciences tell them cannot be bettered. And albeit it may be thought that I haue stretched euery storie vpon the tainters, and made mountaines of mole-hils, in enlarging each other narration, thereby to winne the greater applause and admiration: yet you (who know me so well) can witnesse with me, that I make conscience of enhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the meanest historie. And verily I was so farre from taking this libertie to my self, that where I found my authors (who are for the most part classique writers, or historians of note) iarring and at discord, I left all circumstances doubtfull and vncertaine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting my selfe with the substance of the storie fully resolued and agreed vpon. You may also boldly speake it vpō my word, that if I haue brought in any like mummers in a mask, concealing their names, it was not because I was ignorant of them, but for that I knew it would be more odious to some, and lesse profitable to others. How profitable? (may some say) Verily the examples in the first part of the Apologie serue in stead of crystals, wherin we may see the waiwardnesse and vntowardnesse, the peeuishnesse and peruersnesse of our nature, how backward it is to any thing that is good, and how prone and propense to that which is euill; as also what we are of our selues when we are destitute of the feare of God, which as a bridle should curbe and keep vs in; which point is handled more at large Chap. <hi>11.</hi> sect. <hi>4.</hi> Againe, they serue in stead of aduertisements or warning-peeces, to admonish vs of sundrie subtill sleights and deceits, so common and rife in the world. Those in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part shew how farre one age exceeds another in clownisme and rusticitie: more especially they serue vs in stead of so many mirrours, wherein we may behold the naturall blindnesse of the multitude in the maine matter concerning their saluation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently
<pb n="15" facs="17"/>
in what great need they stand of diuine illumination. True it is indeed, I haue there also blazoned the vertues of our good Catholickes of the Popish Clergie, who feede themselues fat by famishing of others, in debarring them of the foode of their soules, and wickedly prophaning that which they beare the world in hand, and vrge vpon others as the onely true religion. Whose inditement I haue so hotly pursued, and trauersed eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie point thereof, that (I feare me) I haue somewhat ouershot my selfe in setting downe some of their sweete sayings and doings in the darke, not worthie to be heard but by their owne eares: which, I perswade my selfe, not you onely, but all that know me, will inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete no otherwise. Notwithstanding let me intreate you to do the part of a faithfull friend, in informing those with whom you shall conuerse, of the sinceritie of my meaning herein: lest haply they stretch my words beyond the leuell of my thoughts, or make some other construction of my meaning then indeed was meant. And thus Sir, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I recommend my suite vnto you, and my selfe to your fauour, desiring the Lord you may rest in his.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From our <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon</hi>
         <date>the sixt of Nouember. 1566.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>