<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121344_Bo2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00728</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10858</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121344</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the Church : fiue bookes. By Richard Field Doctor of Diuinity and sometimes Deane of Glocester</title>
                 <author>Field, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 906, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="748" facs="389"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE the time I presumed (good Christian Reader) to offer to thy view, what I had long before for my priuate satisfaction obserued touching certaine points, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the nature, definition, notes, visibility, and authority of the Church much questioned in our times: first there came forth a Pamphlet; intituled; The first part of Protestant proofes for Catholique Religion and recusancie: After that a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger discourse bearing the name of, A Treatise of the grounds of the old and new religion: &amp; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the first motiue of one <hi>Theophilus Higgons,</hi> lately minister, to suspect the integrity of his Religion. The Author of the first of these worthy workes, vndertaketh to proue out of the writings of Protestant Diuines, published since the beginning of his Maiesties raigne ouer this Kingdome, that his <hi>Romish</hi> faith and profession is Catholique. The second endeauoureth to make the world belieue, that Protestants haue no sure grounds of Religion. And the third, hauing made ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of the faith, and forsaken his calling, laboureth to iustifie and make good that he hath done. Euery of these hath beene pleased for the aduantage of the <hi>Romish</hi> cause, amonst the Workes of many worthy men, to make vse of that which I haue written; the first seeking to draw mee into the defence of that hee knoweth I impugne: and the other two taking exceptions to certaine parts and passages scattered here and there. Such is the insufficiencie and weakenesse of the idle and emptie discourses of these men, that I almost resolued to take no notice of them: But finding that the last of these good Authors fronteth his booke with an odious title of Detection of falshood in Doctor <hi>Humfrey,</hi> Doctor <hi>Field,</hi> and other learned Protestants, and addeth an Appendix, wherein hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaketh to discouer some notable vntruethes of Doctor <hi>Field,</hi> and D. <hi>Morton,</hi> pretending that the consideration thereof moued him to be come a Papist; I thought it not amisse to take a little paynes in shewing the folly of these vaine men, who care not what they write so they write some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and are in hope, that no man wil trouble himselfe, so much as once to examine what they say: yet not intending to answere all that euery of these hath said (for who would mispend his time, and weary himselfe in so fruitlesse a labour?) but that which concerneth my selfe, against whom they bend themselues in more speciall sort, then any other; as it seemeth because I haue treatised as Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Higgons</hi> speaketh, of that subiect, which is the center and circumference in all religious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes. And b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>cause <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Higgons</hi> is pleased to let vs know his name, whereas the other cōceale theirs (it being no small comfort for a man to know his Aduersary) I will do him all the kindnesse I can, &amp; first begin with him, though he shewed himselfe last, and from him proceed to the rest. What it is that maketh him so much offended with me, I cannot tell; but sure it is, he hath a good vvill to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me: for hee chargeth mee vvith trifeling, egregious falshood, collusion, vnfaithfull dealing, abusing the holy Fathers, and I knowe not what else. But such is the shamelesse, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant vntrueth of these horrible imputations, that it is altogether needelesse to spend time, &amp; bestow labour in the refutation of them. Yet because in the suspicion of heresie, falsehood and vfaithfull dealing in matters of faith, &amp; religion, no man ought to be patient; I will briefely take a view of his whole booke. And though his beginning bee abrupt, and absurd, his whole discourse confused, and perplexed, and all that he doth, without order, or method; yet to giue satisfaction to all, I will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him the same way hee goeth. I was vnwilling (good Christian Reader) to trouble thee with such discourses; but the restlesse importunity of our aduersaries, setting euery one a worke to say some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing against vs, forceth mee thereunto. Read without partiality, and Iudge betweene vs, as God shall direct thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>