<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO BOTH SORTS, as well Vniuo-catholique, as Aequiuo-catholique Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121041_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04317</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14426</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121041</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO BOTH SORTS, as well Vniuo-catholique, as Aequiuo-catholique Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lucta Iacobi: or, A bonefire for His Maiesties double deliuerie, from the deluge in Perth, the 5. of August, 1600. And the doomesday of Britaine, the 5. of Nouember. 1605. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Univocè-catholicus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO BOTH SORTS, as well Vniuo-catholique, as Aequiuo-<hi>catholique Readers.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man lighteth a candle to put it vnder a Bushell;</hi> and no man buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a fire of publike ioy, and shutteth it vp in priuate chimnies. Those Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons haue ouercome my priuate reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions: and howsoeuer the iust feare of my owne infirmities did awe mee; yet, seeing my betters perswade me, my dutie bindeth me to let it goe: And since the royall eyes both of <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> haue once looked vpon it, what care who passe by it?</p>
   <p>That it was not then so early as others, take it not to haue beene my slownesse in beginning: for mine eares no sooner heard, then my heart reioyced, and my hand set it selfe a worke. Neither was it my long somenesse in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it: for my whole bodie is but a chest of such fewell. Nor yet was it my feare it should quickly die; for vntill the memorie of the fact die, my Fire shall alwaies liue. But thus it is, whilst vpon the point of such a practise, all mēs tongs wagged, most pens walked, &amp; the whole world wondred, it was not then necessary my Fire should haue appeared, being fitter to awake men now from the slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of forgetfulnesse, then to haue accompanied the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of their ioyes.</p>
   <p>That it goeth out thus namelesse, doe not impute it to
<pb facs="4"/>any feare of party <hi>bloodie,</hi> or <hi>firie;</hi> howsoeuer, I must confesse my selfe much younger in Treatises then yeares: for who shall feare to defend his Country, so gratious a King, so glorious a cause? No, my Fire hath no feare, and in this could I willingly say, <hi>Meme adsum qui feci, &amp;c.</hi> But thus it is; I finde that as the grauitie and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Authors, bring often credite to bad causes, and make <hi>Paradoxes</hi> passe for probable: so, meane and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure instruments darken most graue &amp; true argumēts; then while as no man knoweth the Author, all men will take them to the matter. Wouldst thou then haue mee leaue my Treatises? I beseech thee leaue thy Treasons: fire not our Parliament, and I shall not foile thy profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
   <p>To you then of the <hi>Vnivoque</hi> sort, true Christians, loyall subiects: let my fire serue to quicken your memories, comfort your hearts, confirme your hopes, and encrease your thankfulnesse; calling backe your mindes to those Parliament mines: so that that day which was once thoght so admirable, may be held euer memorable. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get neuer then these two restlesse <hi>Arch-aequiuocators,</hi> the Diuelin an Oracle, and a Iesuite in an Oath.</p>
   <p>As for you of the vocation of <hi>Aequiuocation,</hi> halfe tongued, hollow hearted, and disloyal Subiects (for what serue faire words in so foule warres, where no quarters are kept?) To you, I say, could I wish my fire as a flame of your dreamed Purgatory, to diuide (not your soules from your bodies, as you doe with vs) but that seede of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from your soules; that as you are the naturall breede of our soile; so ye might proue the loyall subiects of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne.</p>
   <p>Let your submissiue <hi>Parere,</hi> meete his sacred <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare,</hi> and not dresse a <hi>Perire</hi> for him, his posteritie, and
<pb facs="4"/>whole state, by a Popish, Antichristian, Aequiuocating Conspiracie. But what talke I of Antichrist? seeing the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Iesuites</hi> iumpe in one: the <hi>Iewes</hi> looking still for Christs comming, haue lost Christ come: And the <hi>Iesuites</hi> (as all Romish Catholiques) looking for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs comming; hanging him on the hornes of their Altars, and harbouring him in their hearts, yet are lost by their ouer looking him.</p>
   <p>God almightie either seperate that Religion from you, or else both you and your Religion from our Region. Amen: without Acquiuocation.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours as free as his Fire is,</hi> Vnivo-catholicus.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>