<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A briefe Catalogue of the words of Art, with the Explanation thereof.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121936_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20030</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121936</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A briefe Catalogue of the words of Art, with the Explanation thereof.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the vvorld: commonly called, The naturall historie of C. Plinius Secundus. Translated into English by Philemon Holland Doctor of Physicke. The first tome</title>
                 <author>Pliny, the Elder</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 614, 54, 632, 88 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="glossary">
   <pb facs="360"/>
   <head>A briefe Catalogue of the words of Art, with the Explanation thereof.</head>
   <list>
      <head>A</head>
      <item>
         <hi>ABort,</hi> or <hi>Abortiue fruit,</hi> is an vntimely birth.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Abstersiue, i.</hi> scouring, cleansing, or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping away, such as the Greekes call Sme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctica, and they enter into sope &amp; washing balls.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Accesse, i.</hi> a fit, whether it be of an Ague, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling sicknesse, or any such diseases as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne at times.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Acetabulum,</hi> or <hi>Acetable,</hi> a measure among the Romans, of liquour especially, but yet of dry things also, the same that oxybaphon in Greeke: and for that, as both words do import, they vsed to dip their meats in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negre out of such, it may wel go for a sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer with vs; for it contains, as some think, fifteen drams, which grow neere to two ounces, of which capacitie our small sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are: but as others suppose, it receiues two ounces and an halfe, the measure of ordinary saucers.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Acrimonie, i.</hi> Sharpenesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Actually, i.</hi> sensibly and presently, as fire is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually hot.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Aditiales,</hi> or <hi>Adijciales epulae,</hi> were great and sumptuous feasts or suppers, held by the Pontifices or high Priests in testimony of publique ioy.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Almonds,</hi> see <hi>Amygdals.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Amphora,</hi> a measure in Rome of liquors only: it seemes to haue taken that name of the two ears which it had of either side one: it contained 8 Congios, which are much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 8 Wine gallons, or rather betweene seuen and eight: so as in round reckoning it may go for a ferkin, halfe kilderkin, or half sestern with vs.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Amygdals</hi> be kernils at the root of the tongue subiect to inflammations &amp; swellings, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned by deflux or falling down of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors from the head: they be called Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades. Paristhmia, &amp; Tonsillae: the foresaid infirmities also incident vnto them, doe likewise cary the same denominations.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>A</head>
      <item>
         <hi>Antidotes, i.</hi> countrepoysons, properly, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiues or preseruatiues against poyson, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence, or any maladie whatsoeuer.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Antipathie, i.</hi> contrarietie, enmity, and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancie in nature, as between fire and water, the vine, and the Colewort, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>S. Anthonies</hi> fire is a rising in the skin occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by hot bloud mixt with abundance of choler, and such be the shingles and other wild fires called in Greek Erysipelas.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Aquosities</hi> be waterish humors apt to engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dropsies called Ascites and Leuco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlegmatia.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Aromatised, i.</hi> Spiced.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Arthriticall</hi> griefes, such as possesse the ioints, as all the sorts of gout.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Astrictiue</hi> or <hi>Astringent,</hi> be such things as bind the body, or any part thereof.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Attractiue, i.</hi> drawing, as the loadstone draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth iron, amber straws or bents, Dictamnus arrow heads or spils out of the bodie, and cupping glasses (or ventoses) humours and wind.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Austere,</hi> harsh or hard, as in fruits vnripe, and hard wines of hedge grapes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Axinomantie,</hi> a kind of magicke diuination by an ax head red hot.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>B</head>
      <item>
         <hi>BAsis</hi> in a compound medicine is that drug or simple which is predominant, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the greatest force in it, as the ground thereof, whereupon the whole taketh the name; as Poppy in Diacodion, Quinces in Diacydonium, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Bole</hi> is the form of a medicine when it may be giuen in grosse manner at a kniues point to the quantitie of a nutmeg at a time, vntill the whole receit be taken.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Browning,</hi> a term vsuall in the mouths of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners and winnowers of corne, when they are calmed and do call for wind.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Bulbes,</hi> although <hi>Pliny</hi> seemed to giue that name vnto some one speciall hearbe, yet it
<pb facs="361"/>
signifieth generally all those as haue round roots, as Onions, Squilla, Wake-robin, and such like; whereupon these and other of that kind are said to haue bulbous roots.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cacochynne</hi> is that indisposition of the body in which there is aboundance of humors.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Calcining, i.</hi> the burning of a minerall, or any thing, for to correct the malignitie of it, or reduce it into pouder, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Callositie,</hi> thicknesse and hardnesse of skinne in maner senslesse, as in fistulaes, and vnder our heeles.</item>
      <item>to <hi>Carminat,</hi> is to make more fine and thin the grosse humours, by such medicines as by their heat are apt to cut and dissolue them; wherupon they likewise be called <hi>Carmina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> a terme receiued by Apothecaries, and borrowed from those that card wooll.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cancer</hi> is a swelling or sore comming of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy bloud, about which the vems ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare of a blacke or swert colour, spread in manner of a Creifish clees; whereupon it tooke that name in Latine, like as in Greek <hi>Carcinoma.</hi> And such vlcers as in that sort be maintained and fed with that humor, are called cancerous, and be vntoward to heal, worse commonly for the handling.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Carnositie, i.</hi> fleshly substance.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cataplasm,</hi> a pultesse or grosse maner of plastre</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cartilage</hi> in man and beast is a gristle; in roots and fruits, that substance which we obserue in the radish root, and the outward part of a cucumber, as <hi>Pliny</hi> seems to take it; which thereupon be called Cartilagineous.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cataract</hi> is a dimnesse of sight caused by an humor gathered and hardned betweene the tunicle of the eye, called Cornea, and the Crystalline humour; it is next cousine to blindnesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Caustick, i.</hi> burning, blistering, or scalding.</item>
      <item>to <hi>Cauterise,</hi> is to seare or burne by a Cauterie.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cauterie actuall</hi> is fire it self or scalding liquor: and so a searing iron, gold, or other mettall made red hot. is called an Actuall cauterie, which without the help of our natural heat doth work presently.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cauterie potentiall</hi> is that which will raise bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and burn in time, after it is once set on work by the heat of our body, as Canthari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Sperewort, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Ceres</hi> the first inuentresse of the sowing &amp; vse of corne.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cerote</hi> is of a middle nature betweene an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and a plaister, not so hard as the one, nor so soft as the other.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cicatrices</hi> in eyes be whitish spots, otherwise called pearls: they be the skars also remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after a sore is healed vp: and so a place is said to be cicatrised, when it is newly skinned vp and healed.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Circulation</hi> is the deuise of subliming or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting water or oile by a stillatorie, a lembick, or such, because the vapor before it be resolued into water or oile, seemes to go round circlewise.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Clysterized, i.</hi> conueyed vp by a clyster into the guts.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Caeliaci</hi> be those that through weakenesse of stomacke are troubled with a continuall flux of the belly.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Colature,</hi> a thin liquour that hath passed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a strainer or colander.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Colliquation</hi> is a falling away and consumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the radicall humour or solid substance of the body.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Collyries,</hi> are properly medicines applied to the eies in liquid forme; whereas the dry kind be rather called Sief &amp; Alcohol, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially in pouder: howbeit <hi>Pliny</hi> attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth this terme to all eye-salues what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer. Also it seemeth that hee meaneth thereby, tents to be put in a fistulous vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, as in <hi>pag. 509 b. 510 k.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Collution,</hi> a liquour properly to wash the mouth, teeth, and gums withall.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Concocted, i.</hi> altred to that substance by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral heate, as either in health may serue to nourish, or in sicknes is apt to be expelled</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Consolidat,</hi> to knit, vnite, &amp; make sound again that which was broken or burst.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Concrete, i.</hi> hardned and grown thicke.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cond te, i.</hi> preserued in some conuenient li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor.</item>
      <item>to <hi>Concorporate, i.</hi> to mix and vnite together into one masse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Consistence, i.</hi> substance or thicknesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Constipate, i.</hi> to harden and make more fast and compact.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Contraction</hi> of sinews a shrinking or drawing, of them in too short.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Contusions, i.</hi> Bruises.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Convulsions,</hi> painfull cramps.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Criticall</hi> daies be such, as in short diseases &amp; those of quicke motion, do giue light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the physitian of life or death. <hi>Pliny</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serues the od daies to be most significant, and those vsually determinof health; and the euen days contrariwise: so that the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth is <hi>Rex, i.</hi> a gratious prince; the sixth <hi>Tyrannus, i.</hi> a cruell tyrant.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="361"/>
Cruditie. <hi>See</hi> Indigestion.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cyath,</hi> a small measure both of liquid and drie things; the twelfth part of a setarius, which was twenty ounces: whereby it appeareth, that a cyath was one ounce, one half ounce, one dram, and one scruple: it may goe with vs for foure ordinarie spoonfulls.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cubit,</hi> a measure from the elbow to the middle finger stretched out at length, which went ordinarily for 24 fingers bredth, or 18 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which is one foot and a halfe: yet <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> in one place maketh mention of a shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cubit, namely from the elbow to the end of the fist or knuckles, when the fingers be drawn in close to the hand.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Cutanean</hi> eruptions be such wheales, pushes, or scabs as do breake out of the skin and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure it.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>D</head>
      <item>
         <hi>DEbilitie, i.</hi> weaknesse or feeblenesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Decoction,</hi> a liquor wherin things haue bin sodden.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Decretorie</hi> daies, be such as in a sicknesse shew some chaunge or alteration in the patient, either for good or bad.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Defensatiue,</hi> in medicines taken inwardly, are such as resist venom or pestilent humor: in outward applications, such as defend the sore or place affected from the flux or fall of humors thither.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Denarius,</hi> a coin of siluer in Rome, and in other countries of gold, the same that Drachma Attica, <hi>i.</hi> a dram in weight, which is <hi>vij. d. ob.</hi> of our mony; and the piece in gold an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth neere to a full French Crowne; in poise it goeth for a dram.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Dentifrices,</hi> are meanes in Physicke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the teeth, and make them white and faire.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Depilatorie</hi> are those medicines which either fetch off the haire, or hinder it from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vp againe at all, or at leastwise from growing thicke. They were called in Greek and Latine both, <hi>Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>lothra.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Desiccatiue, i. <hi>drying.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Digestiues</hi> be those medicines which taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, helpe concoction of meate or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors; or applied without vnto a sore, doe comfort the place, and make way for spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die healing.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Dislocations,</hi> when the bones be either out of ioynt, or else displaced.</item>
      <item>to <hi>Disopilate, i.</hi> to open.</item>
      <item>to <hi>Dissipate, i.</hi> to scatter and dispatch.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Distortion,</hi> crookednesse or turning awry vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Diureticall,</hi> such things as prouoke vrine.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Dose, i.</hi> that weight or quantitie of any medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine that may be giuen either conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or without danger to the patient.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Dram,</hi> the eight part of an ounce, which is the weight of a Roman denier, or Denarius.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Dysenterie,</hi> is properly the exulceration or sore in the guts, whereupon ensueth besides the painefull wrings of the belly, a flux also of bloud at the siege, and therefore it is vsual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken for the bloudy flix.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>E</head>
      <item>EClogues. <hi>See</hi> Eidyls.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Electuaries,</hi> be medicinable compositions or confections to be taken inwardly, made of choise drugs, either to purge humors, to strengthen the principall parts, or to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand any infirmitie for which they are made. The substance is betweene a syrrup and a Conserue, but more inclining to the consistence of conserues.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Eidylls,</hi> or <hi>Eidyllia,</hi> be small poemes or pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets written by Poets, such as <hi>Theocritus</hi> in Greeke compiled, and much like vnto the Pastorals or Eclogues of <hi>Virgill</hi> in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Embrochation</hi> is a deuise that physitians haue for to foment the head or any other part, with a liquor falling from aloft vpon it, in maner of rain, whereupon it took the name in Greeke Embroche, and hath found none yet in Latine, vnlesse we should vse Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusio.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Emollitiues,</hi> medicines that do soften any hard swelling.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Empiricks</hi> were those physitians, who without any regard either of the cause in a disease, or the constitution and nature of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, went to worke with those medicines whereof they had experience in others, fall it out as it would.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Empirick</hi> books of <hi>Diodorus</hi> contained receits approoued and found effectuall by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Emunctories</hi> be those kernelly places in the body, by which the principall and noble parts doe void their superfluities, or such things as offend; to wit, vnder the ears for the brain, the arm-pits for the heart, and the share for the liuer, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="362"/>
         <hi>Emplastration</hi> in the Hortyard, is grafting by inocelation with a scutcheon in Physicke, the applying of a salue or plastre.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Epilepsie, i.</hi> the falling sicknesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Errhines</hi> be deuises made like tents, sharper at one end than the other, to bee put vp into the nose, either to cure some vlcer there, or to draw downe and void humors out of the head, or to prouoke sneesing, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Eschare,</hi> is that crust which ariseth vpon a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, either actuall or potentiall, as also the roufe or scab that groweth vpon a sore.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Euacuation, i.</hi> Voidance and riddance of any thing out of the bodie by vomite, purging, bleeding, sweating, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Excalfactorie, i.</hi> Heating or chaufing.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Excoriation, i.</hi> fretting the skin off, when a part is made raw: a way to exulceration.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Excresence, i.</hi> ouergrowing vnnaturally of any thing in mans bodie.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Exoticall, i.</hi> forraine, and brought from other countries.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Exorcismes, i.</hi> coniurations by certain charmes and spels.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Exorcists,</hi> they that practised such Exorcisms.</item>
      <item>To <hi>Expectorat, i.</hi> to rid and discharge out of the breast by coughing or reaching.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Expiatorie,</hi> were sacrifices or oblations for to make satisfaction and atonement.</item>
      <item>Exiccatiue. <hi>See</hi> Desiccatiue.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Extenuat, i.</hi> to make thin.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Exulceration, i.</hi> a sorenesse of any part inward or outward, when not onely the skin is off, but the humor doth fret deeper still.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Exulceratiue,</hi> be such things as are apt to eat into the flesh and make an vlcer.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>F</head>
      <item>
         <hi>Fermentation, i.</hi> an equall mixture of things working as it were together: a tearme bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the leuaine, which disperseth it selfe into the whole masse or lumpe of dough.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Filaments</hi> bee the small strings that hang to a root like threads or haires, which some call the beard of the root: and in resemblance thereof, other things growing likewise, bee so called.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Fissures,</hi> clifts or chaps, whether it bee in the hands, feet, lips, or fundament.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Flatuosities, i.</hi> windinesse gathered within the bodie.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Flora,</hi> the goddesse of floures among the Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Fomentations</hi> properly be deuises for to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto any affected part, either to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and cherish it, or allay the paine, or els to open the poores to make way for oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and plastres. If they be liquid things they are laid too by the means of bladders, spunges, or such like: if drie, within bags or quilts.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Fractures, i.</hi> bones broken.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Frictions</hi> or <hi>Frications,</hi> rubbings of the bodie vpward or downeward gently or otherwise, as the cause requireth.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Frontall,</hi> the forme of an outward medicine applied vnto the forehead, to allay paine, to procure sleepe, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Fukes, i.</hi> paintings, to beautify the face in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance. They are called at this day complexions, whereas they bee cleane contrarie: for the complexion is naturall, and these altogether artificiall.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Fumosities</hi> bee vapours steaming vp into the head, troubling the braine.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Fungous, i.</hi> of an hollow and light substance like to Fusses or Mushromes.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>G</head>
      <item>
         <hi>GArga rismes</hi> bee collutions of the mouth, and parts toward the throat, either to draw downe and purge humours out of the head, or to represse and restraine their flux, or to mundifie and heale any sore there growing.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Gargarising</hi> or <hi>Gargling</hi> is the action of vsing a liquor to the said purpose.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Gestation,</hi> an exercise of the bodie, by beeing carried in coach, litter, vpon horsebacke, or in a vessell on the water.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Glandulous</hi> swellings. See <hi>Kings</hi> euill.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Gleir, i.</hi> the white of an egge.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Gymnicke</hi> exercises, were those that were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by men naked, and the place for such exercises, was thereupon called Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasium.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>H</head>
      <item>
         <hi>HAbit of the bodie,</hi> is taken for the outward parts thereof, opposit vnto the bowels and principall within; which being comforted and fortified, do thrust forth offensiue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the habit and exterior skin.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Hemine,</hi> a measure in Rome, as well of liquors as drie things: so called, because it was half Sextarius: it contained ten ounces, and is
<pb facs="362"/>
somwhat vnder our wine pint, it is the same that Cotyla in Greeke.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Humiditie, i.</hi> moisture.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Hydromantia,</hi> a kinde of magicall diuination or foreknowledge of things to come, by obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the water.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Hydrophobie,</hi> is a symptome or accident befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to them that are bitten by a mad dog, whereby they are afraid of water.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Hypochondriall</hi> parts, be the flanks or soft parts vnder the short ribs.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>I</head>
      <item>I <hi>Liacke</hi> passion, the wrings and torments of the vpper small guts, occasioned by wind or sharp humors. Some improperly cal it the collicke of the stomacke.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Imbibition,</hi> a drinking or receiuing of any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor into a thing: as when drougs lie stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped therein vntill they be throughly soaked therewith.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Imposthumes</hi> properly be collections or gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of winde and humours especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene parts of the body, whereupon there appeareth a rising or swelling, and in time they become corrupt and do rankle, vnlesse by some meanes they be either drawn away or dispersed. Some terme them wens, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, the word is taken for inflammations and biles.</item>
      <item>To <hi>Incorporate,</hi> is to mixe and vnite well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
      <item>To <hi>Incrassate,</hi> is to make thicke.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Indigestion, i.</hi> want of concoction and digesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which means many crudities &amp; raw humors are ingendered, &amp; by consequence abundance of rheumes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Inflation, i.</hi> swelling or puffing vp with winde.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Infrangible, i.</hi> that cannot be broken.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Infusion</hi> signifieth the conueiance of some me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinable liquour into the body by clystre or other instrument. It importeth also the steeping of drougs in a conuenient liquor: and the liquor it selfe, when it is strained from the rest.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Ingredients,</hi> be those simples that goe vnto the making of any medicine compound.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Iniection,</hi> is the conueiance of any liquid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine by syringe or such like instrument into any part of the body or hollow and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulous vlcer.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Insects,</hi> little vermine or smal creatures, which haue (as it were) a cut or diuision betweene their heads and bodies, as Pismires, Flies, Grashoppers, vnder which are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Earth-wormes, Caterpillers, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Insessions</hi> be bathing tubs or vessels halfe full, wherein the patient may sit vp to the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or aboue in some conuenient decoction</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Intermittent feauer,</hi> are those which come by fits, and yeeld some rest betweene whiles.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Iniunction, i.</hi> annointing.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Iulebs</hi> or <hi>Iuleps,</hi> be drinkes giuen commonly as preparatiues for to open the passages of the inward parts, and to prepare the humours for a purgation, made either of some stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led waters and syrrups mixed together, or of a decoction sweetened with hony or su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, or els mingled with syrrups.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>K</head>
      <item>
         <hi>KIngs euil,</hi> is the hard swelling of the Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules or Kernels commonly about the necke: they be called also Scrophules.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>L</head>
      <item>
         <hi>LAchrymal,</hi> is the corner of the eie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the teares appeare first, and thereof it taketh the name.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Lassitude,</hi> is wearinesse or vnlustinesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Lauature, Lotion,</hi> or <hi>Loture,</hi> is a liquor to bathe or wash withal: likewise to clenseand mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie any part.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Ligula, Lingua,</hi> or <hi>Lingula,</hi> a small measure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Romanes, both of liquour and drie things, containing the fourth part of Cyathus, to wit, three drams &amp; one scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tule or scruple, somewhat vnder halfe an ounce, and may goe well for our Spoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</item>
      <item>A <hi>Liniment</hi> is thicker than oyle, and thinner than an ointment, it may be taken for a thin ner kind of ointment.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Lobes</hi> and fibres are the lappets and extreame parts of the liuer, with the master veines growing thereto.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Locall</hi> medicines, be those that are appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at for the forehead, <hi>Errhine</hi> or <hi>Nasal</hi> for the nosthrils, &amp;c. or to be applied outwardly, ointments, which are not to be vsed before general or vniuersal means by euacuation.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Loch</hi> or <hi>Lohoch,</hi> is a medicin more liquid than an electuary, appropriat for the lungs and windpipe, and is to be licked and let goe downe leisurely.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Longaon,</hi> is the nethermost gut reaching vnto the very seat or the fundament.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="363"/>
         <hi>Luted, i.</hi> close stopped with clay, dough, or such like.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>M</head>
      <item>
         <hi>MAturatiues</hi> be medicins that help to ripen any swelling impostume, bile, or botch</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Maturity,</hi> is the ripenesse thereof.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Membranes,</hi> be fine skins which inwrap other parts, as the brains, eies, and muscles of the flesh.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Metrenchyte,</hi> an instrument seruing to infuse or iniect a liquid medicine into the matrice of a woman, in manner of clystre.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Mitigatiues,</hi> be such remedies as do asswage paine.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Mna,</hi> or <hi>Mina,</hi> was a Roman weight, which poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed twentie ounces, that is to say, the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary pound, called Libra or Pondo, &amp; two third parts: for the common Libra called Medica, weighed twelue ounces, so that Mina seemed to answer vnto the measure Sextarius.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Mollitiue.</hi> See <hi>Emollitiues.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Mordicatiue,</hi> is biting and stinging, as Senuy seed.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Mucilage,</hi> is a slimy liquor drawne from some roots or seeds, as from the marsh Mallow or Althea root, the seed of Psillium or Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort and others.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Muscles</hi> be the fleshie parts of the bodie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within their seuerall membranes or skinnes.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>N</head>
      <item>
         <hi>NArcoticke</hi> medicines, be those that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num and stupifie with their coldnesse, as Opium, Hemlocke, and such like.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Nasals</hi> be Nose-tents. See <hi>Errhina.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Nerues, i.</hi> Sinewes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Nodosities,</hi> hard knubs &amp; knots growing vpon the ioynts in old gouts, and in other parts.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>O</head>
      <item>
         <hi>OBolus,</hi> halfe a scriptule, or the sixt part of a dram.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Obstructions, i.</hi> Stoppings.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Opiats,</hi> were properly at the first such electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or confections, which had a good quan titie of Opium, <hi>i.</hi> the iuice of Poppie in them, such as Philonium and Requies, that were deuised to mitigate intollerable paine, and to bring the patient to sleepe: howbeit, in these daies all electuaries, euen cordials, in a liquid form be called Opiats, although there be not one grain of Opium in them.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Opilation.</hi> See <hi>Obstruction.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Orthopnoicke,</hi> are those that haue the disease Orthopnoea, which is a difficulty of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their wind, vnlesse they sit vpright.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Osses,</hi> be words cast forth at vnawares, presa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging somewhat.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Otenchyte,</hi> an instrument, deuised for to infuse or poure some medicinable liquor into the eares,</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Oxycrate,</hi> a mixture of water and vineger toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>P</head>
      <item>To <hi>PAlliat, i.</hi> to couer: &amp; such cures be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Palliatiue, which search not to the root and cause, but giue a shew only of cure; as when a sore is healed vp aloft, and yet festereth vnderneath: and so sweet Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders do palliat a stinking breath, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned by a corrupt stomacke or diseased lungs, and such like.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Paradoxes,</hi> strange opinions.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Pectorals, i.</hi> such medicines as bee fit for the breast and lungs.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Pellicles.</hi> See <hi>Membranes.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Penetratiue, i.</hi> Percing.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Periodicall,</hi> such agues be called, as return at their iust course from day to day, euery third fourth, or fifth day, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Peripneumony,</hi> is the inflammation of the lungs.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Pessary,</hi> is a deuise made like a finger or suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitory, to be put vp into the natural parts of a woman.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Phlebotomie, i.</hi> bloud-letting, or opening of a veine by incision or pricke.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Phthysicke,</hi> to speak properly, is the consump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body occasioned by the fault of exulcerat and putrified lungs. But <hi>Pliny</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles seemeth to take it for any other consumption.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Pomona,</hi> a deuised goddesse amongst the Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims, of apples and such fruits.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Prodigies</hi> bee strange sights and wonderfull tokens, presaging some fearefull thing to come.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Propinquitie,</hi> nearnesse or affinitie.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Proscription,</hi> was a kind of outlawing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing a man of the protection of the state,
<pb facs="363"/>
with confiscation of his lands and goods.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Propagat,</hi> to grow and increase, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Vine branches, which being drawne along in the ground from the motherstock do take root.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Propitious, i.</hi> gracious and mercifull.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Proximitie,</hi> neere neighbour-hood or resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Ptisane,</hi> the decoction of husked Barley: a grewell made therewith, or the creame thereof.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Pulpous, i.</hi> full of pulpe, or resembling pulpe, which is the soft substance in Apples or such fruits, answerable to the flesh in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bodies.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Purulent,</hi> yeelding filth and Attyr.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Putrefactiue,</hi> such venomous medicines or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, as do corrupt and putrifie the part of the body, which they possesse.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>Q</head>
      <item>
         <hi>QVindecemvirs,</hi> were certain officers, fifteen in number, ioined in one commission.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>R</head>
      <item>
         <hi>REecptorie,</hi> a vessell standing vnderneath, ready to receiue that which droppeth and distilleth from something aboue it.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Reciproeall,</hi> going and comming, as the tides of the sea ebbing and flowing.</item>
      <item>To <hi>Rectifie, i.</hi> to set streight, to reforme, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Repercussiue, i.</hi> driuing or smiting backe.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Residence, i.</hi> the setling toward the bottome, as in vrine.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Retentiue facultie, i.</hi> the naturall power that ech part or member of the body hath to hold that which is committed vnto it, the due time, as the stomacke, meat, the bladder, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, &amp;c.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Reuerberation, i.</hi> rebounding or striking backe.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Rhagadies,</hi> bee properly the chaps in the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament or seat.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Rubified, i.</hi> made red, as when by application of mustard plastres, called Sinapismes; or beating a part that is benummed with net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, it recouereth a fresh colour againe, whereupon such plastres be called Rubifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue, and the operation is named by the Greekes Phoenigmos.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Rupture,</hi> the disease of bursting, as when the guts or other parts fall downe into the bag of the cods.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>S</head>
      <item>
         <hi>SAliuation,</hi> is a drawing of humours to the mouth, and a deliuerie of them from thence in manner of spittle.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sarcling</hi> is the baring of roots, by ridding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the earth and weeds from about them, that did clog them.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Scarification,</hi> is a kind of pouncing or opening of the skin by way of incision slightly, with the fleame or launcet, either to giue some issue for the bloud and humours to passe forth, or prepare a place for the cupping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glasse to extract more.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Schirre,</hi> is a hard swelling almost sencelesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Scriptule,</hi> or <hi>Scruple</hi> is foure and twenty grains weight, or the third part of a dram.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Scrophules.</hi> See <hi>Kings euill.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Seat,</hi> is the circumference or compasse about the tuill or fundament.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Secundine, i.</hi> the afterbirth that infolded the infant within the mothers wombe.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sege,</hi> a stoole of easement, whereupon wee sit to discharge the order and excrements of the guts.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Serosities,</hi> or <hi>Serous humors,</hi> be the thinner parts of the masse of bloud, answering to the whey in milke, such as we see to float vpon bloud that hath run out of a veine</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sextarius,</hi> a measure among the Romanes, whereof six goe to their Congius, wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it tooke that name: it containes two he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, and is somewhat lesse than a wine quart with vs, it beareth twentie ounces.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sinapisme,</hi> a practise by a plaster of mustard seed, and such like, to reuiue a place in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner mortified, and to draw fresh humors &amp; colour to it.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Solstice, i.</hi> the Sunnestead, as well in winter as Summer, when hee is come to his vtermost points North and South, but vsually it is put for Mid-summer onely.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sophisticated, i.</hi> falsified &amp; made corrupt, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, going for the right. Thus drougs and gems are many times thrust vpon vs.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Spasmes,</hi> be painefull crampes or pluckings of the sinewes and cords of the Muscles.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Spasmaticke,</hi> are such as be thus plucked.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Species,</hi> be either the simple ingredients into a composition, or else the bare pouders min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled together, ready to be reduced into an electuarie liquid, or Tables.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Speculatiue knowledge,</hi> or <hi>Speculation,</hi> is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight into a thing by reading only &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation,
<pb facs="364"/>
without practise &amp; experience.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sperme,</hi> is naturall seed.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Spondyles,</hi> be the turning ioints of the chine or backbone.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Stomachicall fluxe,</hi> is the same that Coeliaca passio. See <hi>Coeliaci.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Stomaticall medicines,</hi> be such as are appropriat for the diseases incident to the mouth, and the parts adioining.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Stypticke,</hi> be such things as by a certain harsh tast, doe shew that they bee astringent, as medlars and alumne, which thereupon is named <hi>Stypteria,</hi> and such like.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Succedan,</hi> that drug which may be vsed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of another. The Apothecaries call such, <hi>Quid pro quo.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Suffusion.</hi> See <hi>Cataract.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Suffumigation,</hi> is the smoke that is receiued in to the body from vnder a stool, for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases of the guts, fundament or matrice.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Suppuration,</hi> is when a bile or impostume ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth to an head and must be broken.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sympathie, i.</hi> a fellow-feeling, vsed in <hi>Pliny,</hi> for the agreement or amitie naturall in diuers sencelesse things, as betweene yron and the loadstone.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Symptome,</hi> an accident accompanying sicknes, as head-ach the ague, stitch, shortnesse of wind; spitting bloud, cough, and ague, the pleurisie.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Syringe,</hi> an instrument in manner of a pipe to iniect a medicinable liquor into the blader.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>T</head>
      <item>
         <hi>TEllus,</hi> the earth.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Tenacitie,</hi> clamminesse, such as is in glew, birdlime, and Bitumen.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Theoricke,</hi> or <hi>Theoretique,</hi> contemplatiue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge without action and practise.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Tinesme,</hi> an inordinat desire to the stool with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any thing to the purpose.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Tonsils.</hi> See <hi>Amygdals.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>Transparent, i.</hi> cleare and bright throughout; as crystall, amber, aire and water.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Transvasation, i.</hi> the pouring of liquor out of one vessell into another.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Triuial, i.</hi> vulgar, common, and of base recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Triumvirat,</hi> the Tripartite dominion of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Octavius,</hi> and <hi>Lepidus,</hi> when they held all the world in their hands, each one their third part.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Trochisques,</hi> or <hi>Trosques,</hi> be litle cakes or roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, into which diuers things medicinable are reduced for to be kept the better, &amp; to be ready at hand when they shall be vsed.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Tuil,</hi> the same that the Fundament or nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most gut.</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>V</head>
      <item>
         <hi>VEgetatiue,</hi> that power in nature which God hath giuen to creatures, whereby they liue, are nourished, and grow.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Ventositie,</hi> windinesse.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Vicinitie,</hi> neernesse, or neighborhood.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Victoriat,</hi> a siluer coine in Rome, Halfe a dena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, so called because it had the image of victory stamped on the one side: it is som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vnder our groat.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Vnction,</hi> annointing.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Vnguent,</hi> an ointment.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Vreters,</hi> be the passages or conduits whereby the water or vrine passeth from the kidnies into the bladder.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Vulnerarie, i.</hi> belonging to a wound; as Sani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is a vulnerary herbe, and <hi>Machaon</hi> was a vulnerarie Physitian.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>