<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worshipfull his good Vncle, Maister Richard Saltonstall, Al∣derman of the Citty of London, and his wife Mistres Susan Salton∣stall, his louing Aunt.</title>
           <author>Pointz, Adrian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121766_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24208</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121766</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worshipfull his good Vncle, Maister Richard Saltonstall, Al∣derman of the Citty of London, and his wife Mistres Susan Salton∣stall, his louing Aunt.</title>
                 <author>Pointz, Adrian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The treasvre of the soule : Wherin we are taught how in dying to sin, we may attayne to the perfect loue of God, &amp; our neighbour, and consequently vnto true blessednes and saluation. Many yeares since written in the Spanish tonge, &amp; and [sic] now newly translated into English: by A.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 302, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the worshipfull his good Vncle, Maister <hi>Richard Saltonstall,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman of the Citty of London, and his wife Mistres <hi>Susan Salton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stall,</hi> his louing Aunt.</head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>Adrian Poyntz</hi> wisheth health &amp; prosperity in the Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>slation of this Booke (louing Vncle &amp; Aunt) I remembred the common order &amp; custome euer vsed, in so much that few commit their labours to the view of the world, vnlesse they first procure some Patrone for their defence. I therefore, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb facs="3"/>to send my translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the presse, before I had committed it to the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of some And standing in doubt to whome I might offer my labour in this kind, trusting vpon your curtesies, did embolden my selfe to commende this Treatise to your protections. The booke was written aboue an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and threescore yeares since in the Spanish tongue, the Authour thereof being vnknowne. As for his stile and methode of writing I meane not to commend it, leauing the iudgment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to those, vnto whom such censures are belonging. I for my parte as I haue faithfully englished his words, &amp; deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red his meaning in such mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that Englishmē may both
<pb facs="3"/>read his treatise and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it, so I doo not doubt, but that it wilbe as profitable vnto them that reade it, for their instruction, as it hath beene to other nations who haue greedily desired the trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation hereof. And thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching you to take my good will and meaning in good part, I commit you to the tuition of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships to commaunde. <hi>Adrian Pointz.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>