<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Statutes Prohemium Iohannis Rastell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1527</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121365_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23086</idno>
           <idno type="STC">9518</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121365</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Statutes Prohemium Iohannis Rastell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The statutes prohemium Iohannis Rastell</title>
                 <author>England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Rastell, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1527</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, cc lxiiii leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>The <unclear>Statutes</unclear> Prohemium Iohannis <unclear>Rastell</unclear>.</head>
   <p>BEcause that the lawys of this real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of eglōd as wel the statutes as other iug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mētis &amp; decreys be made &amp; wrytyn most cōmynly in the frēche tōge, dyuerse men thereof muse &amp; haue oft tymys cōmunicaciō &amp; argumēte cōsyderīg that in reason euery law wherto any people shuld be bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>dyn oughte &amp; shuld be wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n in suche maner and so opynly publyssed &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>yd that the people myght sone without gret di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ficulte haue the knowlege of thesame lawes. But the very cause whithe said lawes of ēglōd were writī in the frēch tōg shuld seme to be this Fyrste it is not vnknowyn that when wyllyam duke of normandy came into this lande &amp; slewe kyng herrold &amp; conqueryd the hole realm / there was a great nōbre of people as wel gentilmē as other that cam with him which vnderstode not the vulgar tong that was that tyme vsyd in this realme but onely the frēch tōg / and also by cause the sayd kyng &amp; other great wyse mē of his coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sel {per}seiuid &amp; supposid that the vulgar tōg w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ich was than vsyd in this realme was in a maner but homely &amp; rude nor had not so greate copy ād <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aboundaūce of wordys as the frenche tōg thā
<pb facs="2"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or that vullgare tonge was not of it sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> suffycyent to expound &amp; to declare the matter of such lawis &amp; ordenaūc{is} as thei hade determine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to be made for the good gouernaūce of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple so effectually and so substauncyally as they cowd indyte thē in the frēch tong / therfore they order<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d wrote &amp; indited the seid law is that they made in the french tong. And forthermore longe after the cōmyng of kynge wylyā conque<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the vse of the frēch tōg ī this real me began to mynyssh &amp; because that dyuers peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple thā inhabytyd withī this realm which coud nother speke the vulgare tongue of this realme nother the french tong. Therfore the wyse men of this realme causyd to be orderyd that the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of law &amp; accyōs betwene {per}tes shuld be ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd shewyd and defendyd / answered debatyd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uggyd in the englyssh vulgar tōg &amp; more ouer y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> wryttyn &amp; enteryd of recorde in the rollys in the latyn tonge by cause that euery man generally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> indyfferently myght haue the knowlege thereof as apperyth by a statute made. in the .xxxvi. yere of Ed. iii. ca. vltimo. wherefore as I suppose for these caus{is} before rehersyd the law is of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alm were īdytid &amp; wryttī in the frēch tōg which was ītēdyd for a ryght good purpose. But yet besyde this now of late days, the moste
<pb facs="2"/>
noble prynce our late souereyn lorde kynge hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry the .vii. worthye to be called the seconde salo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon (whiche excellyd in polytyk wysedome all other pryncis that reyngned in this realm before his tyme) concyderynge and well perseyuynge that our vulgare englissh tong was maruelously amendyd &amp; augmentyd by reason that dyuerse famous clerkys &amp; lernyd men had translate and made many noble workys into our englisshe tōg wherby there was moch more plenty &amp; haboun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dan̄ce of englyssh vsyd than there was in tymys past. &amp; by reasō ther of our vulgare tōg so āplified &amp; sufficient of it self to expound any lawys or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaūcis which was nedeful to be made for the ordre of this realm / and also thesame wyse price consyderyng that the vnyuersall people of this realm had greate pleasure and gaue thēself great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to the redynge of the vulgare englyssh tonge. ordeynyd and causyd that all the statutys and ordinauncis which were made for the commyn welth of this realm in his dayes shulde be indy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyd &amp; wryttyn in the vulgare englyssh tonge &amp; to be publysshyd declaryd and imprītid so that thā vnyuersally the people of the realm myght sone haue the knowleg of the sayd statut{is} &amp; ordynaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cys which they were bound to obserue / &amp; so by reasō of that knowlege to auoid the daūger an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
penaltes of the same statutys / &amp; also the better to lyffe in tranquylyte &amp; pease. which dyscreyt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytable &amp; resonable order our most drad souerey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne lord that now is kyng Henry the .viii. hath cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuyd &amp; folowyd &amp; causyd all the statutys that haue be made in his dayes to be also īdytyd and wrytten in our englyssh tonge to the intente that all his lege people might haue the knowleg ther of All which goodly purposys &amp; intentys in my mynde oftē tymys reuoluyde hath causyd me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ake this lytell payne to translate out of frenche in to englysshe the abbreuyacyon of the statutys ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> before the fyrst yere of the reyn of our late s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uereyn lord kyng Hen. the .vii. &amp; also thoughe y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> the statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>{is} made as well in the tyme of the se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d kinge Hen. the .vii. as in the tyme of our souerey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne lord that now is be suffyciently indytyd &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in our englysshe tong. yet to thē that be desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse shortly to knowe the effect of them they be now more tediouse to rede than thoughe the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter &amp; effect of them were cōpēdyously abbreuiat wherfore now as farre as my symple wyt &amp; smal lernynge wyll extende I haue here takyn vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> me to abbregge the effect of them more shortly in this lytell book / Besechynge al them to whom the syghte ther of shall come to accept it in gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> &amp; though they shall fortune to fynde any thynge
<pb facs="3"/>
my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eportyd or omyttyd! by my neglygēs or ellis by neclygēs of the prynters y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it wold lyke them to pardon me &amp; to consyder my good wyl which haue intendyd it for a comī welth for the caus{is} &amp; consyderacyons before rehersyd / and also if y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> it shal fortune them to be in dout in any poynte therof yet yf it please them they maye resorte to the hole statute where of this book is but a bred gemente &amp; in maner but a kalendre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> And further more I wyl aduertyse euery man that shal fortu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to haue any matter in vre to resort to som man that is lernyd in the lawes of this realm to haue his coūcel in such poyntes whiche he thynketh douteful concernynge the sayde statutys by the knowlege whereof and by the dylygente obser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng of the same he maye the better do his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty to his prynce &amp; souerayngne and also lyue in tranquylyte and pease with his neyghboure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the pleasure and commaundemente of almyghty god to whome be eternall laude &amp; glorye. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>