<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS ESPIST. TO THE KINGE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121027_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20986</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7361</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121027</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS ESPIST. TO THE KINGE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The principall points of the faith of the Catholike Church : Defended against a writing sent to the King by the 4. ministers of Charenton. By the most eminent. Armand Ihon de Plessis Cardinal Duke de Richelieu. Englished by M.C. confessor to the English nuns at Paris</title>
                 <author>Richelieu, Armand Jean de plessis, duc de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cramoisy, Sebastien</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 114 pages, 115-120 leaves, 121-124 pages, 125-126 leaves, 127-335, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS ESPIST. TO THE KINGE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>OVERAIGNE, Knowing well that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seemes à Bishop to speak in the behalfe of the Church and his King and seeing that the writinge of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Charenton made bold to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse it selfe vnto your Maiesty both against the Catholike Church and by consequence, against your Maiesty since that beeing her eldest sonne, her interests are yours, I iudged it to be my duty not to remayne silent, especially amongst such as triumphed, vpon this occasion, as though forsooth, they had borne away some glorious victorie ouer the Faith of our Ancesters.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>This was that <hi>(Soueraigne)</hi> which inuited me to imploy my vacant tyme, to make the Church her innocencie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as glorious in your Maiesties sight, as she hath bene represented vnto you blame-worthy: and the Belief of her Accusers as pernicious, as they striue to haue it esteemed holy.</p>
   <p>In the performance hereof I will vse the greatest moderation that I can possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; desiring, that as our Beleife, and theirs with whom I am to deale, are contrarie, so may also our manner of proceeding be. And in lieu of the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by which they impose vpon vs sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie calumnies, we may render to them truth accompaigned with such sweetnes that if they dispense with their passions, they may receaue occasion of content.</p>
   <p>Thence they shalt knowe that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe is, to doe them good, not euill: to cure, not to wound them: and that we are so
<pb facs="3"/>farre from hating them as they pretend, that wee doe vnfeynedly loue them, and in such à measure, as that we hate not their Doctrine but by reason of the loue which we beare vnto their persons: being à thinge impossible, that à man should not haue in horrour, the kinfe that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders his friend, and the poison which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reeues him of life.</p>
   <p>We loue them <hi>(Soueraigne)</hi> in so full à measure of Charitie, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steede of wishing their hurt, as they mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceaue, we most humbly petition to your Maiestie to inrich them with your Royall fauour, by endeuouring ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaciously to roote vp the errours which haue taken deepe roote in their harts, and to procure their conuersion. And that they may not conceaue that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext of their Good, it is their hurt that I ayme at; and, that speaking of their conuersion, I would incite your
<pb facs="4"/>Maiestie to force them vnto it; I will assure your said Maiestie, that the swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test wayes are those, which I apprehend most conuenient to reclame christian soules from errour: Experience rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs, that offentymes, violent reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies serue onely the more to exasperate the maladies of the mynde. By this meanes your Maiestie corresponding to the glorious title of MOST CHRISTIAN, purchased by the pietie of your Predecessours, shall publish your selfe the most famous king in the world, and shall more and more establish à constant peace and repose in your dominions. It being indoubtedly true, that it is à thing incomparably greater to gaine soules, then to conquere Kingdomes: And by how much more your subiects shall be vnited to God, by so much shall they be more surely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
<pb facs="4"/>to your Maiesties seruice.</p>
   <p>Now wheras, in the deseases which doe affect the parts noble, remedies are to be applied which are proper vnto them; obseruing, that besides that heresie is as poyson which of its owne nature tends to the seasure of the hart, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, haue particularly addressed their writing to your Maiestie which is the hart that doth quicken this flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Realme, though I know, yea it is à thing knowen to the whole world, that the soliditie of your faith preserues it from all perill, yet I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued that my dutie did engage me, to present vnto him the Antidote which I hope will be so much more agreeable vnto him, as my designe, is to testifie vnto him by this action, that all the endeuours of my life, shall neuer haue other ayme then
<pb facs="5"/>his seruice. It is the Protestation that he makes who is</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>DREADE SOVERAIGNE,</salute>
      <signed>Your Majesties, Most humble, most obedient, and most loyall subiect and seruant ARMAND BISHOP OF LVCON</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>