<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121936_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20030</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121936</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the vvorld: commonly called, The naturall historie of C. Plinius Secundus. Translated into English by Philemon Holland Doctor of Physicke. The first tome</title>
                 <author>Pliny, the Elder</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 614, 54, 632, 88 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Appie were they in times past reputed (and not vnworthily) who had that gratious and heauenly gift, <hi>aut facere scribenda, aut scribere legenda:</hi> that is to say, either to do such things as deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to bee written, or to write that which was worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Those that could not attaine to these two branches of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and yet vtterly misliked idlenes, contented themselues in a third degree, namely to take in hand the old workes of their ancients, and by new labours to immortalize their memorie. Thus <hi>Nicophanes</hi> (a famous painter in his time) gaue his mind wholly to antique pictures, partly to exemplifie and take out their patternes after that in long continuance of time they were decaied; and in part to repaire and reforme the same, if haply by some iniurious accident they were defaced. The ingenious mind of this artizan thus deuoted to antiquitie, as I doe highly commend; so I cannot chuse but embrace his policie, seeking here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to auoid the enuie and reproofe of others. In this number I must range those learned men in seuerall ages, who to illustrate the monuments left by former writers, haue annexed vnto them their Commentaries; to saue them entire and vncorrupt, haue set thereto iudiciall obseruations; and to publish them for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefit of posteritie, haue translated the same into their mother language. As for my selfe, since it is neither my hap nor hope to attaine to such perfection, as to bring forth somewhat of mine owne which may quit the paines of a reader; and much lesse to performe any action that might minister matter to a writer; and yet so farre bound vnto my natiue countrey and the blessed state wherein I haue liued, as to render an account of my yeeres passed and studies employed, during this long time of peace and tranquilitie, wherein (vnder the most grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and happy gouernement of a peerelesse Princesse, assisted with so prudent, politique, and learned Counsell) all good literature hath had free progresse and flourished, in no age so much: mee thought I owed this dutie, to leaue for my part also (after many others) some small memoriall, that might giue testimonie another day what fruits generally this peaceable age of ours hath produced. Endeauoured I haue therefore to stand in this third ranke, and bestowed those houres which might be spared from the practise of my profession, and the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie cares of this life, to satisfie my countrimen now liuing, and to gratifie the age ensuing, in this kinde. Like as therefore I haue trauelled alreadie in <hi>Titus Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> a renowmed Historiographer, so I haue proceeded to deale with <hi>Plinius Secundus</hi> the elder, as famous a Philosopher. Now albeit my intention and only scope was, to doe a pleasure vnto them that could not read these authours in the original: yet needs I must confesse that euen my selfe haue not only gained ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by encrease of the Latine tongue (wherein these workes were written) but also growne to further knowledge of the matter and argument therein contained. For this benefit wee reape by studying the bookes of such ancient authours,
<pb facs="4"/>
That the oftner we read them ouer, the more still we find and learne in them: as beeing so judiciously and pithily penned, that, as the Poet said very well, <hi>decies repetita placerent.</hi> Well may the newest songs and last deuised plaies delight our ears at the first, and for the present rauish our senses: like as horarie and earely Summer fruits content our tast and please the appetite: but surely it is antiquitie that hath giuen grace, vigor, and strength to writings; euen as age commendeth the most generous and best wines. In which regard, and vpon this experience of mine owne, I nothing doubt but they also whom I might iustly feare as hard censours of these my labours, will not onely pitie mee for my paines, but also in some measure yeeld mee thankes in the end, when either by the light of the English (if they be young students) they shall bee able more readily to goe away with the darke phrase and obscure constructions of the Latine; or (being great schollers and taking themselues for deepe Critickes) by conferring the one with the other, haply to espie wherein I haue tripped, they shall by that meanes peruse once againe, and consequenly gather new profit out of that authour whom peraduenture they had laid by for many yeers as sufficiently vnderstood. When some benefit (I say) shall accrew vnto them likewise by this occasion, I lesse dread their fearefull doome, to which so wilfully I haue exposed my selfe. Well I wist, that among the Athenians, order was taken by law, That an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude newly acted should be heard with silence and applause: which custome, as it was respectiue and fauourable to the first endeauours of the actours, so it implied an ineuitable danger of hissing out an vtter disgrace, if afterwards they chanced to misse and faile in their parts. Hauing shewed my selfe once before vpon the stage, presuming vpon this priuiledge and the curtesie of the thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, I might haue now sitten still and so rested: In mounting vp thus soon againe, I may seeme either in the assured confidence of mine owne worthinesse, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime a challenge to all mens censures; or else vpon a deepe conceit of some ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conniuencie make reckoning of an extraordinarie and wonderfull fauor. But as the choise that I haue made to publish the monuments of other men, without fathering any thing of mine owne, doth excuse and acquit mee for the one; so the froward disposition of carpers in these daies wherein wee liue, will checke the other. Howbeit considering such paines vndergone by me one man, for the pleasure of so many; so much time spent of mine, for gaining time to others; and some opportunities of privat lucre ouerslipt and lost, to win profit vnto all; I feare not but these regards may deserue a friendly acceptance, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terweigh all defects and faults escaped, whatsoeuer. The persuasion hereof, but principally the priuitie of my affectionat loue vnto my countrey (which assured me of a safe-conduct to passe peaceably through their hands who are of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sort and well affected) induced mee to a resolution not onely to enter vpon this new taske, but also to breake through all difficulties, vntill I had brought the same, if not to a full and absolute perfection, yet to an end and finall conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Besides this naturall inclination and hope which carried mee this way, other motiues there were that made saile and set mee forward. I saw how diuerse men before me had dealt with this authour, whiles some laboured to reforme what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer by iniurie of time was growne out of frame: others did their best to translate him into their own tongue, and namely, the Italian and French: moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the Title prefixed therto so vniuersall as it is, to wit, <hi>The Historie of the World,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
or <hi>Reports of Nature,</hi> imported (no doubt) that hee first penned it for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good of mankind. Ouer and besides, the Argument ensuing full of varietie, furnished with discourses of all matters, not appropriate to the learned only, but accommodat to the rude peisant of the countrey; fitted for the painefull artizan in towne and citie: pertinent to the bodily health of man, woman, and child; and in one word, suiting with all sorts of people liuing in a societie and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale. To say nothing of the precedent giuen by the authour himselfe who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited the same, not with any affected phrase, but sorting well with the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie euen of the meanest and most vnlettered: who also translated a good part thereof out of the Greeke. What should I alledge the example of former times, wherein the like hath euermore been approued and practised? Why should any man therefore take offence hereat, and enuie this good to his naturall countrey, which was first meant for the whole world? and yet some there be so grosse as to giue out, That these and such like bookes ought not to bee published in the vulgar tongue. It is a shame (quoth one) that <hi>Liuie</hi> speaketh English as hee doth: Latinists onely are to bee acquainted with him: as Who would say, the souldiour were to haue recourse vnto the vniuersitie for militarie skill and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: or the scholler to put on armes and pitch a campe. What should <hi>Plinie</hi> (saith another) bee read in English, and the mysteries couched in his bookes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged: as if the husbandman, the mason, carpenter, goldsmith, painter, lapida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and engrauer, with other artificers, were bound to seeke vnto great clearkes or linguists for instructions in their seuerall arts. Certes, such <hi>Momi</hi> as these, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides their blind and erronious opinion, thinke not so honourably of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrey and mother tongue as they ought: who if they were so well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that way as they should be, would wish rather, and endeauour by all meanes to triumph now ouer the Romans in subduing their literature vnder the dent of the English pen, in requitall so the conquest sometime ouer this Island, atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the edge of their sword. As for our speech, was not Latine as common and naturall in Italie, as English here with vs. And if <hi>Plinie</hi> faulted not but deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued well of the Romane name, in laying abroad the riches and hidden treasures of Nature, in that Dialect or Idiome which was familiar to the basest clowne: why should any man be blamed for enterprising the semblable, to the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of that countrey in which and for which he was borne. Are wee the onely nation vnder heauen vnworthie to tast of such knowledge? or is our language so barbarous, that it will not admit in proper tearmes a forreine phrase? I honor them in my heart, who hauing of late daies troden the way before mee in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch, Tacitus,</hi> and others, haue made good proofe, that as the tongue in an Englishmans head is framed so flexible and obsequent, that it can pronounce naturally any other language; so a pen in his hand is able sufficiently to expresse Greeke, Latine, and Hebrew. And my hope is, that after mee there will arise some industrious <hi>Flavij</hi> who may at length <hi>cornicum oculos configere.</hi> For if my selfe, a man by profession otherwise carried away, for gifts farre inferiour to many, and wanting such helps as others bee furnished with, haue in some sort taught those to speake English who were supposed very vntoward to bee brought vnto it; what may be expected at their hands, who for leisure may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend better; in wit are more pregnant; and being graced with the opinion of men and fauour of the time, may attempt what they will, and effect whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="5"/>
they attempt with greater felicitie? A painfull and tedious travaile I confesse it is; neither make I doubt but many doe note mee for much follie in spending time herein, and neglecting some compendious course of gathering good, and pursing vp pence. But when I looke backe to the example of <hi>Plinie,</hi> I must of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie condemne both mine owne sloth, and also reproue the supine negligence of these daies. A courtiour he was, and great favourit of the <hi>Vespasians</hi> both father and sonne: an oratour besides, and pleaded many causes at the barre: a martiall man withall, and serued often times a leader and commander in the field: within the citie of Rome hee mannaged civile affaires, and bare honourable offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of State. Who would not thinke but each one of these places would require a whole man? and yet amid these occasions wherewith he was possessed, he pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chronicles, wrate Commentaries, compiled Grammaticall treatises, and many other volumes which at this day are vtterly lost. As for the Historie of Nature now in hand, which sheweth him to be an excellent Philosopher and a man accomplished in all kinds of literature (the onely monument of his that hath escaped all dangers, and as another Palladium beene reserued entire vnto our time) wherein hee hath discoursed of all things even from the starrie heauen to the centre of the earth; a man would marveile how hee could possibly either write or doe any thing else. But considering the agilitie of mans spirit alwaies in motion: an ardent desire to benefit posteritie, which in these volumes hee hath so often protested; his indefatigable studie both day and night, euen to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie of nature, and the same continued in euerie place, as well abroad as within<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house; in his iourney vpon the high way, where his manner was to read and to indite; in his ordinarie passage through the streets betweene court and home, where he gaue himselfe no rest, but either read, or else found his notarie worke to write; and for that purpose rode vsually in an easie litter, with the said Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie close by his side: lesse wonder it is, that hee performed his service to Prince and state according to his calling; and withall deliuered vnto posteritie so many fruits of wit and learning. For what is not the head of man able to compasse? especially making saile with a feruent desire and resolution to see an end, and besides taking the vantage of all moments, and losing no time, whereof hee was <hi>unus omnium parcissimus.</hi> Touching his affection to search into the secrets of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it was that and nothing else that shortened his daies, and hastened his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death: for hauing liued not much aboue the middle age of man, desirous he was to know the reason, Why the hill Nesuvius burned as it did? and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched so neare, that with the strong vapours and smoake issuing from thence, his breath was suddenly stopped, and himselfe found dead in the place: a man wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to haue liued for euer. What remaineth now, but onely to recommend vnto my countrimen this worke of his (which for mine owne part I wish to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall) were it not for one scruple to bee cleared, which at the first troubled my selfe a little, and might peraduenture otherwise offend some readers. In at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing so much vnto Nature, <hi>Plinie</hi> seemeth to derogat from the Almightie God, to him <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; and therefore dangerous (faith one) to bee divulged. Farre be it from mee, that I should publish any thing to corrupt mens manners, and much lesse to preiudice Christian religion. After conference therefore with sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie diuines about this point, whom for their authoritie I reuerence; whose lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning I honor and embrace; and in whom for iudgement &amp; synceritie of religion
<pb facs="6"/>
I rest, confirmed I was in my first purpose, and resolved to finish that which I had begun, namely, not to defraud the world of so rich a gem, for one small ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish appearing therein. And that it may appeare how I did not abound in mine owne sence, but had regard as well to satisfie the conscience of others as mine owne, I haue thought good to annex immediately hereunto, in manner of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollarie, the opinion of one graue and learned preacher concerning this doubt, as it was deliuered vnto mee in writing; which for that it is grounded vpon suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reasons, and according with the iudgement of the rest, the lesse I respect the rash projects of some fantasticall spirits: nothing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but the same will settle the minds of the weake, and free my labours from the taint of irreligion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>