<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND the most vertuous and Godly Lady, the Lady Harington.</title>
           <author>Hart, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121926_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19675</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND the most vertuous and Godly Lady, the Lady Harington.</title>
                 <author>Hart, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three conformities. Or The harmony and agreement of the Romish Church with gentilisme, Iudaisme and auncient heresies. VVritten in French by Francis de Croy G. Arth. and newly translated into English. Seene, perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Cro, François de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 130, 6, 131-177, 25, 179-258 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND the most vertuous and Godly Lady, the Lady <hi>Harington.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F euer any age hath beene more fertile and abundant then others, in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of writers in all manner of sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, learning and knowledge, truely it is this wherein we liue. But chiefly in Diuinity and the holy mysteries of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the knowledge whereof ought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to bee the chiefe and onely scope of
<pb facs="3"/>
our Christian endeauours, as being the true mirror wherein wee may fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the true pathway which is able to conduct our pensiue soules vnto those supernal mansions, which are in the house of God the Father, and are prepared for the elect. And among so many learned &amp; godly treatises, of this kinde, which the painefull labours of our Pastours and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue set forth for the comfort of the militant Church, I can finde none that doth more aptly, briefly and learnedly conuince the errors of this crooked and naughty generation of the Romish Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, then these Conformities, which are most fit and proper summarily to confound the idle and selfe-pleasing ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, fansies, traditions, additions, fractions, diminutions, substractions, and mutations which they haue distilled out of the naughty and corrupted hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of their distracted braines, and sowne most cunningly in euery corner of the true Church of God. Which things hauing weighed with my selfe, as likewise the vtilitie and comfort which
<pb facs="3"/>
might further bee reaped hereof, if the same were translated into our language, namely in these dangerous and latter dayes, in the which Sathan our euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting aduersarie knowing the end of his kingdome to be very neereat hand, doth so subtlely and carefully watch how to entrappeand deuoure vs, I haue hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to expose the same vnto the view of my countrey; not labouring herein to snatch at any parcell of ambitious and vaine glory: but rather to employ the little peece of a Talent which hath beene alotted vnto mee, in some godly and Christian exercise, to the further increase of Gods glory, and subuersion of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ. Accept therefore (Madame) these three Conformities, which I haue beene the bolder to offer to your Honour; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering as well your most godly and Christian life and conuersation, together with your feruent zeale and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the truth of the Gospell, as like wise those morall vertues wherewith you are adorned. Which concurring together in your noble person are able (no doubt)
<pb facs="4"/>
to deserue farremore then euer hath been bestowed on you, or my meane power able to offer vnto you. The world know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how Religiously, Noblely, Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, Faithfully, and with what paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and long care my Lord your hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and you haue trained vp our most Royall Princesse the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who in her childehood at her first comming into this Kingdome, was by his Maiesty committed to your charge and custodie, after that hee had beene surely informed with what rare gifts and noble parts you were beautified, farre aboue a multitude of your sexe and rancke. And when by the happy coniunction of the Prince E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector Palatine with her Highnesse, it seemed to be no more necessary that your Honours should giue attendance on her Highnesse, and that my Lord and you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therefore honourably and with his Maiesties fauour and consent giuen ouer the sacred charge of her person, and thinking now at length to haue beene rid of so waighty a burden, and that you might haue liued the rest of your daies in
<pb facs="4"/>
some secure port of tranquillity. Yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little time his Maiesty hauing had so many yeares experience of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours prudent and watchfull care of her Highnesse well and prosperous estate, and knowing that your Honourable presence and attendance on her, were no lesse necessary vnto her now of late, then your painefull care and most vigilant cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stodie had beene in the time of her tender age, did yet once againe summond your Honour to take vpon you, though not all, yet a great and principall part of your wonted charge? namely to admonish and impart your most wholesome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels vnto her, to the farther increase of all her Royall vertues and qualities, as well in matters of noble conuersation and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, as of true piety and deuotion. And although the multitude of your most serious affaires doth afford but small leysure vnto your priuate medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Yet I am sure that this treatise will purchase so much fauour at your hands, as to haue some spare houres spent in the reading thereof, wherein you may
<pb facs="5"/>
bee not a little refreshed with the most sweete and delectable varietie of these Conformities which are presented to your Honour, hoping that they shall be embraced with no lesse fauour and goodwill, then they are giuen by him, who remaineth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humble and most deuoted, W. HART.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>