<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1522</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121899_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04975</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15113.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pleasaunt playne and pythye pathewaye leadynge to a vertues and honest lyfe : no lesse profytable, then delectable. V.L</title>
                 <author>Leigh, Valentine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos)</publisher>
                    <distributor>Case, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1522</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eynge gyftes are not so muche to be valued for the price of them as they are to be estemed for the good entente of the geuer (mooste gentyll reader) my small labours and trauayle herein bestowed (whyche I frelye geue thee) I shal hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye desyre thee to take in good parte, wherein althoughe the mattier be not in euerye poynte so exquisytely handeled as my good wyll and seale coulde haue wyshed it, yet I do nothynge at all mystruste but that ye wyll wyth fauoure beare wyth me, and rather frendlye wyncke at the faultes yf there be anye, then spytefullye as carpers at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mennes doynges seke occasyon to dysprayse the same, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuche as the hole effecte thereof treateth of nothynge but of good and holsome counsayles enterlaced wyth pleasaunt mirthe and honesty, to youth no lesse right profytable then necessarye. Licurgus, who for hys grauytie and excellente wysedome gaue lawes vnto the Lacedimonians, amongest hys other laudable and seruyouse statutes, dyd institute and ordayne a certayne kynde of exercyse, at the whyche the elders whyche had borne rule in the common wealth, dyd commonly mete there, to passe the tyme wyth pleasaunte talke and wyttye tales, but suche as were alwayes eyther profytable to the commendation and prayse of honestye, or els to the detestynge and rebukynge of vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, because he perfectlye well consydered that it was a thynge mooste nedefull and requyset sometyme wyth suche goodlye recreation to refreshe the weakenyd powers of the mynde, that it myghte be thereby the more freshe and apte to compasse and accomplyshe other more wayghtye affayres. I omytte other probable auctorities whyche I myghte nowe worthelye brynge herein, to declare that thys lytle woorke is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected althoughe after a nomber of pythye preceptes there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a merye inuented mattier placed therein onely to quyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the spyrytes and to aucyde tedyousnesse. And who is so ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunte, but that he well vnderstandeth that youthe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye taketh more delectation in redynge those thynges which in hys age requyreth then in graue sentences cereouslye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. Yet here shall he learne yf he rede it wyth dylygence bothe howe to leade a quyet and godly lyfe in the feare of God, and also to exchue the assaultes of synne and daungers of the
<pb facs="3"/>worlde, vnto this bryttell age, (I saye) therefore I haue wrytten this, and not the prudente well stryken in yeres, whose experience perchaunce hath sufficiently taught, and who haue alredye passed the daungerouse rockes, and swallowynge quicke sandes of this troublesome worlde. My honest meanynge therefore gentyll reader, herin, yf thou thanckfullye receyue, I shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be the more wyllynge to take some paynes in other mattiers. And so I wishe thee wel to fare.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>