<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE of the Authour to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121766_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24208</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121766</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE of the Authour to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The treasvre of the soule : Wherin we are taught how in dying to sin, we may attayne to the perfect loue of God, &amp; our neighbour, and consequently vnto true blessednes and saluation. Many yeares since written in the Spanish tonge, &amp; and [sic] now newly translated into English: by A.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 302, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE of the Authour to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE more gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a man hath receyued of God, and the more he is indued with knowledge of vnderstanding: the greater punishment he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth, if therefore he be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull. And againe, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer acknowledgeth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites of God, he also by all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reason is bound the more to loue him. Nowe all bookes are replenished with knowledge and learning, nowe is the holy Gospell sealed and confirmed with the precious bloude of the immaculate Lambe of God, to the end we may haue a greater
<pb facs="4"/>assurance of the vnspeakeable loue towards vs. All bookes, I say, are full, the earth doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde with Preachers, sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth as Trumpettes the great power and excellency of the Almighty, for to draw &amp; stirre vs vp to lande, praise &amp; giue thankes to our Creatour, and most louing Father. But we are all so prone to vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and so ready to forget his benefites, so largely bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon mankind, that there is none almost to bee found, who vnfaynedly doo seeke him? But all runne and flie headlong into darke and obscure places of sin and wickednesse. Moued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the premises, I haue fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished this booke, to the glory of God, and (as I hope) to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the godly. And because that nowe a dayes our
<pb facs="5"/>slothfulnesse is so great, &amp; our desire and stomacke to the glory of God so faint, weake and slen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der: I haue vsed here in this my booke sundry similitudes and parables, by these meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice the minds of men the more to the deep consideration of the contentes of this volume.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>