<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader, expressing the
Reason of the whole Worke.</title>
           <author>Sarum, Martin</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121334_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01093</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11205</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121334</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader, expressing the
Reason of the whole Worke.</title>
                 <author>Sarum, Martin</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Atheomastix : clearing foure truthes, against atheists and infidels: 1. That, there is a God. 2. That, there is but one God. 3. That, Iehouah, our God, is that one God. 4. That, the Holy Scripture is the Word of that God. All of them proued, by naturall reasons, and secular authorities; for the reducing of infidels: and, by Scriptures, and Fathers, for the confirming of Christians. By the R. Reuerend Father in God, Martin Fotherby, late Bishop of Salisbury. The contents followes, next after the preface</title>
                 <author>Fotherby, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 68, 99-362 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader, expressing the
Reason of the whole Worke.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not so much of mans owne free election, as of
Gods speciall disposition, that euery man in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
is particularly addicted vnto the handling of
this or that Argument. Not all vnto one: for so, all
but one, should be left vnhandl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd the world of
many excellent knowledges bereaued: but some
vnto one, and some vnto another; that we might not lacke instruction
in any profitable matter.</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Diversis etenim gaudet Natura ministris,</l>
         <l>Vt fieri diversa queant ornantia Terras.</l>
         <l>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> patitur cunctos ad eandem curreremetam,</l>
         <l>Sed varias iubet ire vias, varios{que} labores</l>
         <l>Suscipere, vt vario cultu sit pulchrior orbis,</l>
      </q>
      <hi>Saith the Christian Poet:</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Nature herselfe delights herselfe in sundry instruments,<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aling. in Scor. pag. 217.</note>
         </l>
         <l>That sundry things be done to deck the Earth with Ornaments.</l>
         <l>Nor suffers she her seruants all should runne one single race,</l>
         <l>But will's the walke of euery one frame in a diuers pace:</l>
         <l>That diuers wayes and diuers works the world might better grace.</l>
      </q>
      <hi>Yea, and euen the very Heathen doe likewise confesse, this to be the
proper worke of Gods gracious prouidence; calling euery man to that
wherein he best foreseeth him, most able to doe good: and yet, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing,
but inducing him to doe it.</hi> Eam enim mentem Dij singulis
dant, vt communes vtilitates in medium afferant; <hi>saith the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Orator.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>crat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rat. ad Philip. p. 267.</note>
      <hi>Yea, &amp; he illustrateth his position by example of himself there:</hi>
That God had put into his mind to make that present Oration,
for the generall good of the whole Greekish Nation: <hi>ascribing
that his inclination, not vnto his owne selfe-motion; but vnto Gods
<pb facs="4"/>
prouidence disposing his affection. And so likewise doth</hi> Plutarch <hi>his▪</hi>
Intellige non sine efficacitate coe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stium,<note place="margin">Plut▪ lib. de Fato Tom. 2. p, 670.</note> vel me nunc scribere
isthaec, velte, quic quid agis, eo modo agere quo agis. <hi>And so
likewise doth</hi> Galen <hi>of his booke</hi> De vsu partium:<note place="margin">Galen lib. 10 de Vsu partium, p, 313.</note> Deus aliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s
iussit, &amp; primum scribere, &amp; declarationem eius, ille ipse novit
me scire: <hi>ascribing all his writing vnto Gods inward commanding:
who knew best his ability to write of that argument. Which is indeed, a
very true ascription: yea, and much truer in spirituall matters, than it
is in any ciuill. For, therein it is most euident, that,</hi> The same Spirit,
that hath giuen to euery man his gift, hath also assigned vnto
euery man his taske:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 4. 5. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>calling one vnto one Argument, and another
to another; and euery one to serue his Church, with those <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> and
graces, which he hath bestowed vpon him for that purpose. And this
we may plainely see, euen in those holy Instruments, that haue been the
writers of the holy</hi> Scriptures: <hi>how, as God had endowed them with
their seueral gifts, so he likewise appointed them to their seueral works:
calling some of them to the writing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> holy Histories, <hi>as</hi> Moses, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shua,
&amp;c. <hi>some, of heauenly</hi> Mysteries, <hi>as</hi> Daniel, Iohn, &amp;c. <hi>some, of</hi>
Hymnes, <hi>as</hi> Dauid <hi>in</hi> Psalmes, <hi>and</hi> Salomon <hi>in his</hi> Song: <hi>some, of</hi>
Prophecies, <hi>as</hi> Isaj, Ieremie, &amp;c. <hi>and some, of</hi> Morall, and Ciuill
Precepts, <hi>as</hi> Salomon <hi>in his</hi> Prouerbs: <hi>euery one entertaining both
a different matter, and handling the same in a differing manner: yet
not by his owne election, but by Gods direction. For (as</hi> S. Peter <hi>plam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyteacheth
vs)</hi> There is no Prophecy in Scripture, of any priuate
motion, neither of the will of man:<note place="margin">2. Pet▪ 1. 20▪ 21.</note> but the holy men of God
did onely speake, as they were inspired by the holy Spirit: <hi>who
disposed their affections, to serue the Church of God, with all their best
indowments and endeauors; and euery one of them (according to that
Talent, which God hath giuen vnto him) to helpe to build it vp, in
true piety and religion. So that, they all of them being ioynt-laborers
together, and all of them working in one common worke, vnder one
common master, there could none haue any cause to insult ouer another▪
not the</hi> Hymnographer <hi>ouer the</hi> Historiographer, <hi>nor the</hi> Gnomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher
<hi>ouer either, nor the</hi> Prophet <hi>ouer all, or any of the rest; but
euery one to acknowledge other, as his owne fellow-labourer, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by God himselfe, with that gift which he had, to helpe forwarde the
same building that he himselfe did.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And, the very same course hath the holy Ghost obserued, as well in
<pb facs="4"/>
the new Testament, as he did in the old:</hi> For he hath giuen vnto his
Church, some Apostles, some Prophets, some Teachers,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 28.</note> some
Workers of Myracles, some Helpers, some Gouernours, some
Speakers with Tongues. For the gathering together of the
Saints; for the worke of the Ministery, and for the building vp
of the body of Christ. Not all Apostles,<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 11. 12.</note> not all Prophets, not all
Teachers, not all Gouernours, <hi>but yet, all fellow-labourers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1, Cor. 3. 9.</note>
      <hi>and all
builders vp of the Church, and euery one acoadiutor to the worke of
all the other.</hi> We together are Gods labourers,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 9.</note>
      <hi>and the Church</hi> his
building.<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>odoret. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r. 6. de Prouide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, To. 2. p, 600.</note>
      <hi>So that, as in the natur all body of a man, no one member can
suffice for all his need full vses; but, all of them stand in neede of the
mutuall assistance of all their fellow-members:</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 19. 21.</note>
      <hi>so that,</hi> the eye cannot
say to the hand, I haue no neede of thee; no, nor euen the head
vnto the foote, I haue no neede of thee: <hi>So likewise, in the mysti
call body of Christ, those members that are the chiefest, yet doe neede
the coassistance of those that are the meanest.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The same <hi>Prouidence</hi> (still carefull for the good of the Church)
hath continually raysed vp, throughout all succeeding ages, many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
and wise, and industrious Pastors, to instruct and teach his Church,
in true piety and godlinesse: some by preaching, some by writing, and
some by both. But yet, in no Age, hath God shed out all the riches of his
blessings, both of <hi>Wisedome,</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and all his <hi>high Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi>
more graciously and plentifully, than in this Age of ours. For,
what learning, or what knowledge hath God euer bestowed vpon any
of all the preceding ages, which he hath not greatly amplified and inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
in this of ours? Yea, and that to high degrees.</p>
   <p>And, as he hath in this our Age, bestowed vpon many men, great
variety of Gifts, so hath hee also designed them to great variety of
workes. To some he hath giuen <hi>diuersitie of Tongues,</hi> and those hee
hath called to examine <hi>Translations:</hi> to some, skill in disputing, and
those he hath called to labour in <hi>Controuersies:</hi> to some, a faculty in
Exhortation and Teaching, and those he hath called to instruct men by
Preaching. And thus, as God hath dispensed his gifts diuersly; so hath
he assigned men their Prouinces accordingly: to one after one manner,
and to another after another; appoynting vnto euery one, that, <hi>as he
hath receiued the gift,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 7.</note>
      <hi>so likewise,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 10.</note>
      <hi>he should minister as good
dispensers of the manifold graces of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>So that, now (God be praysed) the Church of Christ goeth vp on all
<pb facs="5"/>
hands, euery man labouring in it with his seuerall gift, to repaire all the
ruines and seuerall bracks of it: some as <hi>Architects</hi> and <hi>skilfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-builders;</hi>
some, as Carpenters: some, as Smiths; some, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,;
yea, and some other, but as Temperers of Lyme and Mortar:
yet these also called <hi>Labourers; yea,</hi> and more properly then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
Whose worke, though in view, it be lesse honorable then therest;
yet, is it in vse, as profitable as the best: yea, and of so great necessity,
to the perfecting of the building; that, as in temporall building, the
greater Stones cannot be firmely layd, without mixture of the lesse: so,
in this spirituall building too; those other Artes, though superiour, yet
cannot either perfect or performe their owne worke,<note place="margin">Lapides magos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ine paruis, benè struinegant Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecti. Plat. li. 10. de Leg. p. 877</note> without the helpe
and ministery, euen of those meane and inferiour.</p>
   <p>Amongst whom, it hath pleased the prouidence of God, to call mee,
to make vp some decayes in the foundations, which, either through
tract of time, or through corruption of manners, or through the vnder-mining
of little Foxes, mentioned in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> are growne by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,
into the very lowest ground-works.<note place="margin">Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2. 15.</note> I am called to vnder-pinne
those foure maine Corner-stones, which vphold (like foure pillars) the
whole frame of the Church. I meane, the first, foure principles of all
Religion: namely, <hi>That there is a God. That there is but one
God. That Iehovah our God, is that one God.</hi> And, <hi>That the
holy Scripture is the word of that God.</hi> These vnder-groundworks,
hath it pleased diuine prouidence, to assigne me for my taske. So
that, whilst other men doe so are aloft, like Eagles in the ayre; I must
creepe heere below, like a worme vpon the earth. But yet, let no man
despise the basenesse of this worke; because it is about the <hi>Basis</hi> of the
Church. For, the worke of the foundation, though it be in sight, the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
worke belonging to the building, yet, is it not the least, but in truth,
the very greatest; as being the whole support and stay of all the rest,
euen of the very highest: A Worke which requireth both the skilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest
head, and the cunningest hand, vnto the doing of it; if it be done
as it ought.</p>
   <p>And therefore, I could haue wished, that some excellent Maister<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workman,
more plentifully abounding, both in leisure, and learning,
would haue taken it vponhim. The worke is due to such:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 10.</note> yea, and our
Church hath store of such (Gods name be praysed for it.) But yet, no
man (that I see) hath set his hand vnto it. Many worke vpon the
walls, to make them firme and strong: many vpon the roofe, to keepe
<pb facs="5"/>
it close and tight: many vpon the pillars, to erect and straighten
them exactly, <hi>ad perpendiculum:</hi> some pariete and smooth it: some
painte and adorne it; some furnish,<note place="margin">Cic. Orat. 3. in Verrem. p. 79.</note> and garnish it with beautifull pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<hi>like apples of gold, in pictures of siluer.</hi> But yet, no man
looketh downe into the ground-worke of it,<note place="margin">Prou. 25. 11.</note> that it be layd so low, as to
reach vnto the Rocke. Whereby there is a space left, for pioners and
vnder-miners, and such like deceitfull workers, which are not able to
breake through the wall, yet do dig vnder the foundation, and so to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert
all. And therefore I haue aduentured vpon this great taske, though
farre vnequall to it; hoping that the the <hi>same Spirit</hi> which hath giuen
me <hi>the will,</hi> will also assist me in the worke, in some measure, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
it. For,<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 13.</note>
      <hi>Sorte diuinaid recte efficere quis{que} potest, ad quod
Musa quempiam incitauit.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plato in Ionc, p. 171.</note> And so I haue followed the aduice of the
Poet:
<q>
         <l>Quin, hortante Deo, magnis insistere rebus</l>
         <l>Incipe—</l>
         <l>Why then, beginne,<note place="margin">Tibul. leb. 4. p. 150.</note> sith ayde from God is sent▪</l>
         <l>Proceede, goe on, dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e forth thy great intent.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A Worke, great indeede: yea, and that of much greater, both</hi> Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie,
and Variety, and Vtility, and Necessity, <hi>then will easily, at
the first, bee conceiued of many: of all which foure, I will giue you a
little taste, in order.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Difficulty</hi> of the worke, ariseth from hence, that this Argument
now intended to be handled by me, is the most deserted part of all <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologie;</hi>
and wherein the fewest <hi>Diuines</hi> haue bestowed their paines.
For, whereas there be but two wayes, to bring men vnto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
and vnderstanding of God (as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> hath well obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued)
namely, <hi>Creatura, and Seriptura,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. lib. 2. de Trin. in proaem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 3 p. 260.</note> the <hi>Creature,</hi> and the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi>
the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Word:</hi> there haue so many men laboured in
this latter, that, for number, almost they be without number: but, in
the former part, so few, that they likewise, in comparison, be number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
too. Some few, I confesse, haue written before me, of this matter:
but none at all in this manner: as I leaue it to be iudged by the wise and
learned. So that, I may truely take vp that excuse for all incident er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,
which Lucretius doth, euen in this very case, that,
<q>
         <l>Auia Pieridum peragro loca,<note place="margin">Lucret. l. 1. P. 34.</note> nullius ante</l>
         <l>Trita solo—</l>
         <l>I walke a way lesse way, with vncouth pace,</l>
         <l>Which yet no former Muse with foot did trace.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
The naturall <hi>Difficulty</hi> of the Argument, hath deterred the most
men from writing vpon it: and the paucitie of such writers, hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
a second difficulty vnto me. Those whom I haue seene to haue
written vpon this Theme (for I goe not beyond the compasse of mine
owne Library) are onely these following. <hi>Aquinas contra Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;
Raymundus de Sabunde, in Theologia naturali; Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardinus
de Causa Dei;</hi> and <hi>Valesius de sacra Philosophia.</hi> But
these foure, dealing onely <hi>Scholastically,</hi> by way of Logicall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
which doe not <hi>influere,</hi> they cannot affect, nor leaue any great
impression in the mind of a man but (as the Orator aptly censureth
such short and sharpe conclusions) <hi>Haec spinosiora, prius vt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teamur
nos cogunt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 1. Tuse. p. 110.</note>
      <hi>quam vt assentiamur. Such thorny and
prickly conclusions of Logique, do rather inforce men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
them, then induce men to beleeue them.</hi> There is further,
<hi>Augustinus Eugubinus;</hi> who in his Booke <hi>de perenni Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi>
hath laboured in this Theme, with singular learning, congesting
out of <hi>Poets, Philosophers,</hi> and <hi>Orators,</hi> an incredible masse of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities
and Sentences. But as the fore-named Authors delt onely by
argument, without any testimony; so dealeth he mostly by testimony,
without any argument. There is yet further, <hi>Ludouicus Viues, de
veritate Fidej Christianae;</hi> and <hi>Philippus Mornaeus,</hi> of the same
both argument and inscription▪ <hi>Zanchius</hi> also, <hi>de Operibus Dej;</hi>
and the <hi>Second Part</hi> of the Booke of <hi>Resolution:</hi> all which haue
done learnedly, in their seuerall kindes. But yet, for those heads, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
in this Book, I doe principally insist, they passe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r them so
sleightly, and perstringe them so briefely, that all of them may be truly
affirmed, to haue beene, by those Authors, rather touched, then hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.
It hath beene mine endeauour, so to temper my writing, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Authorities should lacke their arguments; nor arguments their
Authorities; nor the Reader store of both. And yet in vsing the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
of those fore-named Authors, I haue entertayned this course: that
whatsoeuer any of them hath prolixely handled, that haue I either who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
pretermitted, or (at the most) but lightly touched. What they haue
pretermitted, that haue I sought out (so farre as I could) and more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piously
inlarged. Whereby neither their writings shalbe preiudiced by
mine, nor mine thought a <hi>Plagium</hi> out of theirs: and yet the Reader
be inriched by the store of both of vs. And this hath also bred a <hi>third</hi>
difficulty vnto me. A <hi>fourth</hi> there groweth likewise from the destinate
<pb facs="6"/>
end, and scope of this worke: which is, to compell the Heathens to
preach the truth of Christians; and <hi>Philosophy</hi> to proue the grounds
of <hi>Diuinity:</hi> yea and to inforce, by strength of Argument, both <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi>
and <hi>Epicures,</hi> and <hi>Atheists,</hi> who will not beleeue God in his
word; yet to beleeue him without his word. Which euery wise man will
easily imagine, to be a worke not easie to be done. For, as it is truely
obserued by <hi>Tertullian;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de Testim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> c. 1. p. 84.</note>
      <hi>Magna curiositate, &amp; maiore longe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria
opus est ad studend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, si quis velit ex literis receptissimis
quibus{que} Philosophorum, vel Poetarum, vel quorumlibet sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae
secularis Magistrorum, testimonia excerpere Christianae
veritatis. It is a piece of businesse▪ both of great curiosity, and of
greater memory, and yet of greatest study, to gleane out of the
writings of Philosophers, and Poets, and other secular Authors,
fit authorities, and testimonies, for the proofe of Christiā truths.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now secondly, for the <hi>Variety</hi> of this Worke; that is such, and so
great, as none other could come neare it; if it were handled as it should.
For, this Worke intreateth both of God, and all his Workes; which
containe all those <hi>varieties,</hi> which God and Nature yeeldeth. In <hi>God</hi>
there commeth to be considered, all those diuine properties, which hee
hath adumbrated in any of his creatures; his <hi>Simplicity,</hi> his <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,</hi>
his <hi>Immensity,</hi> his <hi>Eternity,</hi> his <hi>Strength,</hi> his <hi>Wisedome,</hi>
his <hi>Goodnesse,</hi> his <hi>Dominion,</hi> his <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> his <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi>
and his <hi>Omnipraesence;</hi> and such like; thinges incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible
in themselues, but yet such, as may in part be sufficiently
vnderstood, by that shadowy resemblance of them, which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
vnto our soules. In his <hi>Creatures,</hi> there commeth to be discussed,
both the <hi>little World,</hi> with all the faculties of his body, and all the
powers of his mind; and the <hi>great World,</hi> with all his most excellent
and glorious parts; the <hi>Heauens,</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> the <hi>Seas,</hi> and all the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
creatures contained in all these▪ yea and the admirable working
of Gods diuine prouidence, both in <hi>making,</hi> and <hi>preseruing,</hi> and in
<hi>ruling</hi> of al of them. Which (as euery simple man may easily see) be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of the greatest <hi>Variety</hi> that can be. In all which points, I haue
giuen the Reader so much taste as may delight him, yet not to glut him.
For the full handling of them, would both be nauseous vnto him, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
vnto me, and supersluous vnto both of vs; a meere deviation
from the scope of this worke; and in it selfe an attempt, not onely fond,
but also infinite.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
Now thirdly, for the <hi>Vtility</hi> and profit of this Treatise▪ that may
partly be collected from the <hi>varieties</hi> of it. For it is the <hi>Orators</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 3. de. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. pag. 214</note>
      <hi>That those things which carry with them the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
delight, doe commonly carry likewise the greatest profit▪
Pleris{que} in rebus, incredibiliter hoc Natura est ipsa fabricata, vt
ea, quae maximam vtilitatem in se continent, eadem habeant
plurimum, vel dignitatis, vel saepe etiam venustatis.</hi> And hee
giueth for an instance, that great beautie and varietie which we see in
the world: which carrieth also with it, no lesse vtilitie and profit: the
very punctuall instance of this our present purpose.</p>
   <p>But to consider the profit of this our Treatise, absolutely in it selfe,
without any such reference vnto his varieties. Can there possibly be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
more profitable contemplation, either to excite and stirre vp a man
vnto godlinesse, or to incite him vnto thankfulnesse, then religiously
to weigh and pond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r with himselfe, the immensitie of Gods goodnesse,
who hath made both heauen and earth, and all the seuerall creatures
contayned in them both, to serue onely for his vse? This contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
wrought in the Prophet <hi>David</hi> so strongly, that it draue him almost
into an holy extasie; forcing him to breake out into that patheticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation;<note place="margin">Psa. 8. 1.</note>
      <hi>O Lord our Governor, how excellent is thy Name in
all the world. Thou that hast set thy glory aboue the Heauens.
When I consider the Heavens, the worke of thy handes, the
Moone, and the Starres, which thou hast ordayned: What is
man (say I then) that thou art so mindfull of him, or the son
of man, that thou so visitest him?</hi> And marke heere againe, how
the Prophet resumeth his first admiration, by a Poeticall <hi>Epanalep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis</hi>
or reduplication; <hi>O Lord our Governour, how excellent is
thy Name in all the world!</hi> And indeede, this sensible beholding of
<hi>the invisible things of God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 20.</note>
      <hi>by the creation of the world,</hi> if it du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be considered and weighed as it ought, it will minister a more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
instruction vnto our eyes, then any that we commonly receiue in by
our eares. For,
<q>
         <l>Segnius irritant animos demissa per aurem,<note place="margin">Horat▪ lib. de Arte Poet p 170</note>
         </l>
         <l>Quam quae sunt oculis subiecta fidelibus, &amp; quae</l>
         <l>Ipse sibi tradit spectator—</l>
         <l>Those things more slowly doe affect the mind,</l>
         <l>Which eares doe heare, then those which eyes doe find.</l>
      </q>
And erefore this worke (as I hope) will not be without his profit.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
Fourthly, as concerning the <hi>Necessity</hi> of it: Looke what absolute
necessity the work of the foundation hath, vnto all the rest of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;
the same (and no lesse) hath the proofe of these Propositions,
vnto all the other parts of Religion: For let but these foure positions
be substantially proued; <hi>That there is a God: That there is but one
God: That Iehovah our God, is that one God: And that the
Scripture is the Word of that God:</hi> and then all the other parts of
Religion, in the whole Scripture contained, are soundly supported and
vpheld. For then it will follow of it selfe, that <hi>whatsoeuer is in the
whole Scripture prescribed, it ought to be obeyed, as the very
word of God.</hi> But (on the other side) let either all, or any of these po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions
be disproued; <hi>That either there is no God;</hi> or, <hi>That there
is not onely one; or, That I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hovah is not that one;</hi> or, <hi>That
the Scripture is not his word:</hi> and then all Religion must needes
presently fall downe, as an house that lacketh his foundation. So that,
whether we consider the difficulty of this work in respect of the writer;
or the <hi>Variety, Vtility,</hi> and <hi>Necessity</hi> of it, in respect of the Reader:
it will (as I hope) be no labour ill spent, to bestow some time in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
of it.</p>
   <p>And yet I doubt not (courteous Reader) but this my labour and
indeauour will, of some men, be esteemed to be needelesse, and redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant:
that in this so cleere a light and sun-shine of the Gospell, I should
goe about to proue those grounded principles of Religion, which so
long haue beene receiued without all contradiction: the very seeking
to proue the vndoubted truth of them, carrying with it (in shew) a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
doubting of them; at the least wise, a calling of their truth into
question, which hath hitherto beene questionlesse amongst all good and
sound Christians.</p>
   <p>I represent the whole Obiection in his true and proper forme, as it
formerly hath beene represented vnto me by some, neither ill-learned,
nor ill-affected towards me. Whereby I may collect, that from those
which are more strange, or more estranged <hi>Readers,</hi> I may probably
expect that scomme of <hi>Theognetus:</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Laevas didicisti (o nequam) Literas:<note place="margin">Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>naeus. l. 15. p. 500.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Everterunt tuam vitam libri.</l>
         <l>Dum philosophareris, cum coelo acterra es confabulatus,</l>
         <l>Quibus tui sermones minime curae sunt.</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="8"/>Fond man, th'ast spent thy time in vaine,</l>
         <l>Much idle learning thus to gaine:</l>
         <l>Thy bookishnesse hath beene thy bane.</l>
         <l>With heauen and earth thou talk'st I wis,</l>
         <l>And yet thy talke by that, nor this,</l>
         <l>Nor more, nor lesse, regarded is.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>This measure (and no better) I but hardly shall escape, from those
rash and heady persons, who (like <hi>Sannioes</hi>) subsanne all things, but
onely their owne follies: not waighing the moment and nature of things.
For, as <hi>Euripides</hi> very truely obserueth,
<q>
         <l>Indoctis—nova proferens scita,<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urip. in Medea p. 185.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Videberis inutilis, &amp; non sapiens esse.</l>
         <l>Who broacheth ought that's new,<note place="margin">Quicun{que} ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt pro foribus etiamsi quid Doctum cecine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, non repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati sapientes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionem sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unt stultitiae. Clem. Alex. lib. Strom p. 136.</note> to fooles vntaught,<note place="margin">Galen. l. 12. de vsu partium. p. 358.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Himselfe shall iudged be vnwise, and good for naught.</l>
      </q>
Against whom I haue put on Galens iron-resolution, as an armour of
sure proofe: <hi>Non ignorantes hunc librum, &amp; calumnijs &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitijs
lacessitum iri quam saepissime, cum velut infans orpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus
in manus hominum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>briorum prae stultitia &amp; ruditate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciderit:
tamen conamur scribere, gratia illorum paucorum, qui
dicenda audire recte, &amp; iudicare poterunt.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And yet, for the better remouing of the fore-alledged Exception,
and diuerse other of like nature, which might minister any scruple,
either vnto the curious or incurious Reader, I thought good to prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munite
the succeeding Treatise, with this praeceding Preface▪ to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt
out of their minds, all those scrupulous exceptions, which (by
way of diuination) I could forecast would trouble them, touching ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the matter, or the manner of my writing. Vsing in the meane time
the same obtestation vnto my beneuolous Reader, which <hi>Lucretius</hi>
doth to his, in the very like matter:
<q>
         <l>—Vacuas aures mihi,<note place="margin">Lucret. lib. 1. p. 2. 3.</note> &amp; te—</l>
         <l>Semotum a curis adhibe, veram ad rationem:</l>
         <l>Nemea dona tibi studio disposta fideli,</l>
         <l>Intellecta prius quam sint, contempta relinquas.</l>
         <l>To Reason Lend me thine attentiue eares,</l>
         <l>Exempt thy selfe, from mind-distracting cares,</l>
         <l>Lest that which I proiected for thy good,</l>
         <l>By thee reiected be, e're vnderstood.</l>
      </q>
Yea, and the reason, which there is alledged by him, will also not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly
<pb facs="8"/>
serue my turne:
<q>
         <l>Nam, tibi de summa Coeli ratione Deum{que}</l>
         <l>Disserere incipiam: &amp; rerum primordia pandam.</l>
         <l>My purpose is, to treate of Heau'ns high Nature,</l>
         <l>Of All's originall, and of All's Maker.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>First therefore, as concerning the fore-named Exception, <hi>That all
these foure Positions, which are the subiect of this Treatise, be
already amongst vs sufficiently beleeued; and that therefore it
is superfluous to call them now to be proued:</hi> Vnto this Obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
I answer three things. First, that the principall scope and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
of this Booke, is, rather to conuince those that beleeue them not,
then to confirme those that beleeue them. Though <hi>this</hi> also be intended
as a secondary end, as it likewise is, in <hi>the Creatures of God▪</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 20.</note> But
the <hi>prime end</hi> of this Worke, is, to confute all those, which either dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
against Gods <hi>Essence and being,</hi> as the direct <hi>Atheist</hi> doth; or,
against his <hi>Prouidence and gouerning,</hi> as the <hi>Epicure</hi> doth, who
is an indirect <hi>Atheist:</hi> and to proue both of these to be men, not onely
destitute a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all Piety and Religion, but also of common sense and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.
And further, to shew vnto those acute <hi>Naturalists,</hi> who hold it a
seruility to be led with brutish-beleeuing, and will therefore entertaine
no more of Religion then they find to be consonant vnto Reason; that
<hi>here</hi> they may find reason for their <hi>Religion.</hi> All which seuerall kinds
and degrees of <hi>Atheists,</hi> it is not more incongruous for me to confute,
amongst beleeuing <hi>Christians,</hi> then it was for the <hi>Psalmist</hi> to confute
the same,<note place="margin">Psal. 14. 1. &amp;</note> amongst beleeuing <hi>Iewes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 53. 1.</note>
   </p>
   <p>But secondly, I answer, that my conceite is too shallow to sound the
depth of that bottomlesse reason, <hi>That it should not bee lawfull to
prooue those Positions, because they bee already beleeued of
Christians.</hi> For if it were not lawfull to proue those points of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi>
which are now already accepted and beleeued; then (if we will
proue any thing) we must euery day bring forth a new <hi>Creed.</hi> For the
<hi>old</hi> may not be proued, because it is approued. And then were the
writings of the most <hi>Diuines,</hi> both <hi>ancient and recent,</hi> to be reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.
For, what poynt of Diuinity doth any of them proue, in all their
writings, but that which was before admitted, and approued by all good
and sound Christians? Is it not lawfull to prooue the Articles of our
<hi>Creed,</hi> because they be already beleeued? or, is it lawfull to proue all
the rest; and is it not lawfull to proue the first? Is it lawfull to proue,
<pb facs="9"/>
that our Sauionr <hi>was conceiued by the holy Ghost? borne of the
Virgin Mary? suffered vnder Pontius Pilate? &amp;c.</hi> And is it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
to proue that <hi>There is a God? That he is our Father? That he
is Almighty?</hi> and, <hi>That he is the Maker of heauen and earth?</hi>
What strange infelicity is fallen vpon this one Article (which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ground and support of all the rest) that to seeke to proue <hi>it</hi> should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
reprehension, when to proue <hi>all the other</hi> deserueth commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
I cannot reach (I say) the profoundnesse of this Reason.</p>
   <p>But, thirdly, I answer: that it is a false position, That either all, or
any one of these foure fore-named positions, is so generally and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly
beleeued, as that it hath no need, to be proued and confirmed.
For, there be but too too many men that haue their beleefe so vnperfect
in all of them, that it is mingled with much haesitation, doubting, and
wauering: so that, the best of them may say with him in the Gospell,
<hi>Lord,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mar. 9. 24. Plau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Act. 5. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c. 4. p. 547.</note>
      <hi>I beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe:</hi> And with him in the Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<hi>Credo, sed tamen metuo miser.</hi> But yet specially, in the first
point, of beleeuing <hi>That there is a God,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of all the rest the most
vnbeleeued.<note place="margin">Ovid. l. 3. Amor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Eleg. 8. p. 209.</note> For, that which <hi>Ouid</hi> confesseth of himselfe, is also true
in very many men, if they would confesse the truth, as <hi>Ouid</hi> plainely
doth.
<q>
         <l>Sollicitor, nullos esse putare Deos.</l>
         <l>Temptations oft sollicite me,</l>
         <l>To thinke in heart, That Gods none be.</l>
      </q>
Yea and this sollicitation of Sathan,<note place="margin">Alas sometimes I cannot shun, But some p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane thoughts in my minde will runue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 7. day, p. 235.</note> as it hath much preuailed with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse
of the <hi>Heathens:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iust. Mart. Dial. cum Try<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hon. p. 153.</note> so hath it no lesse also, euen with diuerse <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi>
Amongst whom, it is but too true an obseruation which is made
by <hi>Iustin Martyr,</hi> an ancient learned Father, <hi>Dici quidem non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullos
Christianos, esse vero nullius Numinis cultores. That
many men be called by the name of Christians, who yet be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
no better then very Atheists:</hi> though not such as <hi>Diagoras</hi>
and <hi>Theodorus</hi> were, who made (as it were) a profession of their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme;</hi>
yet such as are noted by the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> which say in
their heart,<note place="margin">Ps. 14. 1.</note>
      <hi>That there is no God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Theodoret. Serm 1. De Prouiden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ia. Tom. 2. p. 576</note> Yea and sometimes go further too,
as is noted by <hi>Theodoret. Sunt quidam qui Christianorum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
nomine gloriantur, veritatis autem dogmata palam op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant.
There be some that are called by the name of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
and yet do not onely deny Gods Truth in secret, but also
defie it, and oppugne it in publique,</hi> which commeth not much
<pb facs="9"/>
short of the direct and profest <hi>Atheist.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore it is not <hi>the name</hi> of a <hi>Christian</hi> that can free a man
from <hi>Atheisme;</hi> nor <hi>reciting</hi> the <hi>Articles</hi> of our Christian beleefe
that can mak a true <hi>Beleeuer.</hi> To <hi>beleeue,</hi> is with the heart to assent:
it is not with the tongue to recite.<note place="margin">Isai 29. 13.</note> For, <hi>many draw neere vnto God
with their lippes, whose hearts be farre from him.</hi> Therefore,
<hi>Corde crediture,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 10. 10.</note> is a Christian mans <hi>Character,</hi> printed vpon his
heart, which many men doe lacke, who haue the marke of Christians
printed vpon their fore-heads: notwithstanding both the numberlesse
multitude of preaching, and the cleernesse of the Gospell, as bright as
any Sun shine. For, though it cannot be denied, that there neuer was
in any age, such subtilty of wit, such plenty of learning, and such study
of all things, both Diuine and Humane: Yet must it also be confessed
(if we will confesse the truth) that the greatest part of those excellent
gifts, wherewith God hath beautified and adorned this our age, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the gifts of <hi>Illumination,</hi> than of <hi>Sanctification;</hi> and such as
haue bred with many, rather a verball Religion in their mouthes, then
a reall in their hearts. We may euidently see this, in the practise of
common life: how all the Streets do sound, all Tables and Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>naries
resound, with learned discourses in euery kinde. The best Schooles of
<hi>Athens</hi> were neuer better able, to dispute <hi>de omni scibili,</hi> then many
men now doe almost at euery table. But yet this againe is very worthy
obseruation; that all this sharpenesse of wit, and abundance of learning,
is oftentimes abused, but onely to dispute, and make Obiections against
God. So that he taketh himselfe for the ioylliest fellow, that can shewe
himselfe best able to make some witty Obiection against the Bible: thus
abusing the great gifts of their wit and vnderstanding, euen against
God himselfe, who is the giuer of them.</p>
   <p>Which prophanenesse so scandalized the Romane Orator <hi>Tully,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cic. l. 3. de Nat. Deor. p. 237.</note>
that is draue him almost into another impiety;<note place="margin">Prouidentiam repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, quae ration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n dederit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be vsuros.</note> complaining against
<hi>Prouidence;</hi> that surely in this poynt it was vtterly improuident, in
giuing so great Gifts and Ornaments vnto those men, whom it could
not but foresee would so not ably abuse them.</p>
   <p>Now this is the worst kinde of <hi>Atheisme</hi> of all other, when as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme</hi>
is grounded, not so much vpon <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as it is vpon the
opinion of <hi>Knowledge.</hi> And yet such is the <hi>Atheisme</hi> of this our time.
That which men at the first (like good Christians) receiued with the
simplicity of beleeuing; they now (being growne vnto greater know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge)
<pb facs="10"/>
desire to haue prooued, with the subtilty of disputing: else,
will they beleeue nothing. The greatnesse of mens wits sharpneth
many of them on, to see all things prooued by arguments, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated
vnto sense. The Scriptures (with many) haue lost
their authority: and are thought onely fit for the ignorant, and
idiote: The World now swelling with an opinion of learning, though
it be indeede, in such men, but onely an opinion; yea, and that, a
very false one. For (as the Apostle S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath very truely cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured
them) <hi>Wherein they professe themselues to be wise,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 21. 22.</note>
      <hi>therein
they doe shew themselues to be fooles:</hi> there being nothing more
foolish, then either not to beleeue that there is a God, who yet may
<hi>visibly be seene by the creation of the world;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Verse 20.</note>
      <hi>or, to beleeue
that the world was neuer created, because we see not visibly the
first creation of it</hi> This, though such vaine men doe conceite and
accompt to be their <hi>wisedome:</hi> yet is it indeed their palpable folly:
yea and that not onely in the Apostle <hi>Pauls</hi> iudgement, but also in
the iudgement of the very Heathen Poet, who calleth such mens
doubting, <hi>rationis egestatem, the very beggery of reason.</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Tentat enim dubiam mentem rationis egestas,<note place="margin">Lucret. lib. 5. pag. 227.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Ecquaenam fuerit mundi genitalis origo.</l>
         <l>It's want of reason, or it's reasons want</l>
         <l>Which doubts the minde, and Iudgment so doth daunt,</l>
         <l>That Worlds beginning, mak's men not to graunt.</l>
      </q>
Yea as thicke and grosse a folly, as if a man looking vpon some goodly
building, should professe, hee would not beleeue that it euer had beene
made; because he himselfe did not see the making of it. For, how dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
they?</p>
   <p>Therefore it is but an erroneous opinion, to thinke, that either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
Christians there can be no Atheists; or, that secret Atheists are
not to be convinced, as well as the publique: or, that the principles of
Religion are beleeued of all, by whom they bee confessed: or that they
ought not to be prooued vnto those men, of whom they bee already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued.
All these (I say) be very great errors, but especially the
first. For beside the two fore-named sorts of Atheists, the one both
inword, and heart denying God; the other in word confessing him,
but in heart renouncing him; there is yet a third sort of them (yea and
those euen amongst Christians) who though both in word and in heart
they confesse him, yet doe they <hi>in their workes deny him.</hi> They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb facs="10"/>
there is a God: but they liue, as if they beleeued there were none:
which the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> perstringeth as a reall denying of him.<note place="margin">Titus 1. 16.</note>
      <hi>They
professe they know God, but by workes they deny him.</hi> Yea,
and his censure is approued, euen by the Heathen Poet: who sentenceth
all wicked, and licencious liuers, to bee no better, then a kinde of prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall
Atheists.
<q>
         <l>—Tubulus si Lucius vnquam,</l>
         <l>Si Lupus, aut Carbo,<note place="margin">Cic. l. 1. de Nat. Deor. p 192.</note> aut Neptuni silius,</l>
         <l>Putasset esse Deos, tam periurus, aut tam impius fuisset?</l>
         <l>Lucilius ask's, if any man can dreame,</l>
         <l>That Lucius,<note place="margin">Tubulus.</note> Lupus, Carbo, and their crue,</l>
         <l>Or Neptun's sonne, that impious Polypheme,</l>
         <l>Themselues so periur'd, or so vile would sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>w;</l>
         <l>If they had once, a thought but, that there is,</l>
         <l>A God in Heau'n, who plagues men for their mis?</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Now all these sorts of Atheists, are to bee convinced, and drawne,
<hi>obtorto collo, will they nill they,</hi> vnto God. Which, I hope, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
(I am sure indeauoured) in this Booke. Wherein, the first sort
of those Atheists, which deny <hi>there is a God;</hi> are forc't, by strength of
reason, to confesse that, they denied. The second sort of them, which
confesse there is a God, and yet beleeue it not; are taught to beleeue,
that which they haue confessed. The third sort of them, which both
beleeue, and confesse him, and yet haue no care to worship, or obey
him; are heere taught, to liue as they doe beleeue. So that, this
Booke hath great vse, towards all those sorts of Atheists, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
not these positions. Yea, and no lesse (I hope) likewise, towards
those that beleeue them. For those true and sound Christians, which
both confesse the truth, and beleeue as they confesse, and liue as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,
it notably confirmeth, both in their true faith, and in their good
life. So that it will no way be idle or super<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>luous, neither towards the
Vnbeleeuers, nor yet towards the Beleeuers. Not to them, for infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;
not to these, for confirmation.</p>
   <p>But yet it may bee, that some man will obiect, that Treatises of
<hi>Deuotion</hi> are of much greater profit, and more fitting to the nature
and capacity of the Vulgar: and that therefore these our paines might
more properly and profitably haue bene bestowed vpon such. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
I breifly answere; That indeede there is nothing more generally
wanting, in the practise of our liues, then is the exercise of true <hi>Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
nothing more defectiue in the diuersity of our writings, then
discourses of that kinde. So that this may likewise be confessed, too
truly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o be but a steril part of <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> tilled by very few. But
yet, euen this present worke, which we now haue in hand, if it be well
considered,<note place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stio de Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Dcorum, &amp; ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> &amp; ad moderandam Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>em ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaria. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. l. 1. De Nat. Deor. p. 184.</note> and duly meditated, doth not want his instigation vnto
true deuotion.<note place="margin">Item, vide Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> p. 107. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> For what greater motiue or incentiue can there be, to
inflame the godly Soule, with all faithfulnesse to deuote it selfe, wholy
vnto Gods holy seruice, then seriously to perpend, and to recompte
within it selfe, that God hath made all his seuerall Creatures, to deuote
them onely vnto our vse and seruice? Whosoeuer hath in him any spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckle
of goodnesse, he must needes, by this godly and religious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
be greatly accended vnto true deuoion. Now that point in this
Booke is prolixly layd open. And certes, how the Reader will be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
in the rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing of this Booke, I cannot tell: but, my selfe in
writing of it, was no lesse affected, then was <hi>Tullie</hi> in the writing
of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>De Senecture:</hi> being oftentimes so liuely touched,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> that
I neuer found in my selfe a more quicke apprehension, both of Gods
incomprehensible Maiestie and goodnesse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of Mans most contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible
pusillitie &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> then by this contemplation of God in his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
finding in my self the verity of that obseruation of <hi>Tully;</hi> that
<hi>Est animorum inge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>um{que} naturale quasipabulum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cic. lib. 4. Acad. p. 38.</note>
      <hi>conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio
contemplatioq, Naturae▪ Erigimur, latiores fieri videmur,
humana despicinus; cogitantesq, supera, atque coelestia, haec
nostra, vt exigua &amp; minima contemnimus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for the capacitie of the simpler Readers; all is not written to them;
but the most vnto the learned, who are in most danger, with many
Obiections, vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> these points to be troubled. But yet, there bee many
passages, throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> out the whole Booke, which may easily be conceiued,
euen of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Readers: yea and that euen in the highest points,
which I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> indeauoured to stoop and demitte, euen to the
capacitie of the very lowest, so farre as the nature of the things would
permit. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> may haply bee found true euen in this discourse
also (at the least in respect of the subiect matter handled, though not in
the forme &amp; manner of handling) which S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> affirmeth of the
holy Scripture,<note place="margin">Greg. Epist▪ ad L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>andrum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> that it is, <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>asi Fluuius, &amp; planus, &amp; altus; in quo,
&amp; Agnus ambuler, &amp; Elephas natet. That though there be some
subiects so deepe and profound, that the Elephant may swim in
them: yet be there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> againe, so obuious and shallow, that
<pb facs="11"/>
euen the Lambe may wade ouer them.</hi> And therefore the worke (as
I hope) will not be without his fruite, neither towards the Infidels, nor
yet towards Christians; neither towards the Learned, nor towards
the Vnlearned: which was the doubt of some men (themselues not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned)
as concerning the Subiect and Argument of this Booke.</p>
   <p>It therefore now remayneth, that, hauing giuen satisfaction vnto
such, as haue obiected against the matter of my writing, I should now
likewise indeauour to remoue those Exceptions, which some haply
<hi>may</hi> take against the Manner of it.</p>
   <p>As first, it may be, that some Man, will except; that there is in this
Booke so much <hi>Philosophie,</hi> and so little <hi>Diuinitie.</hi> Whereunto I
breifely answer; that with those Aduersaries, against whom I am cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to deale in this Booke, the <hi>Diuinity</hi> of Christians hath much lesse au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,
then the <hi>Philosophie</hi> of Heathens; naturall Reason a much
higher place, then supernaturall Religion; and the writings of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers</hi>
much greater credit, then the holy Scriptures. So that (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
of the nature of those Aduersaries) there is more cause of exception
that here is so much Diuinity, then that there is so little. And yet euen <hi>for</hi>
this also, there is a iust Apologie: That this is done, <hi>ex abundante,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to confirme those that beleeue, then to informe those that beleeue
not: that so the Booke may not be without his profit, whether it light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the hands of Christians, or of Pagans.</p>
   <p>Some againe (it may be) will except, <hi>That such a multitude of
Testimonies are congested to one purpose.</hi> But that hath many
vses, to the profit of the Readers. For first, The Matter questioned, is, by
multitude of Testimonies more substantially proued. Secondly, though
those Testimonies alledged, be by me often applyed, but to mine owne
present purpose: yet may the learned, Reader make manifold vse of
them, vnto diuers other purposes: and so in their varietie, haue choise
and election to take, or to leaue, as will best serue his turne. So that the
writers <hi>store,</hi> ought not to be accompted the Readers <hi>sore:</hi> if but in this
respect. But thirdly, though many be alledged to one and the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose:
yet may it be obserued, by the indicious Reader, that they doe not
all proceed by one and the same tenor: but that (for the most part) eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
one bringeth some thing that the other had not: which may serue
the attentiue Reader, either for the better confirmation, or the clearer
illustration of the point, then in quaestion. Finally, if they will needs
haue this to bee the writers error; yet may I defend my selfe, with
<pb facs="12"/>
that same excuse, wherewith<note place="margin">Quintil. lib. 10. c. 1. p. 575.</note>
      <hi>Quintilian</hi> defendeth <hi>Stesicorus:</hi> that,
<hi>Id si est reprehendendum, est tamen nisi Copiae vitium.</hi> Which
though it hath made the Booke some what bigger: yet hath it also (I
hope) made it better.<note place="margin">Athenaeus. lib. 3. p. 55.</note> So that I am the lesse fearefull of <hi>Callimachus</hi>
his censure, that, <hi>Magnus Liber, est magno malo par. A great
Booke is little better then a great euill.</hi> Yea and so much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
because in those sentences I haue made choise of mine Authors, not
corrading out of all <hi>promiscue,</hi> and <hi>sine delectu,</hi> but taking only such
as are both ancient, and Classicall, as well <hi>Seculars,</hi> as <hi>Diuines.</hi> In
citing of whose Testimonies, I haue not alledged them all pariter, as they
stand in their Author: but (leauing out all exorbitant and heterogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Clauses, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itted not my purpose) I haue taken onely so much as
was properly incident vnto mine owne ends, and hindered not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text,
and roundnesse of the speech: yet alwayes, with this care, neither
to wrest, nor wrong the sense of the Author.</p>
   <p>Some againe may except, against the citing of mine Authors so par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly;
Booke, Chapter, and Page; as carrying with it, some touch (or
at least, some shew) of Vanitie. But, vnto that I answer that it was not
to ostentate, and make shew of mine owne reading (which it greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth
me to be so little) but to helpe my Reader with it, such as it is:
not envying his profit, but seeking, with all my best endeauour, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
it. And indeed, I haue alwayes esteemed it a great ouersight, yea
and a kinde of vnkindenesse, in any writer, in the citing of his Authors,
to send his Reader to seeke in an indefinite compasse, when as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
can direct him vnto the definite place: by that meanes also, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feating,
the very end and purpose of his owne paines in writing▪ which
is, onely to increase his Reader in all knowledg and vnderstanding. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides,
Whereas in the citing of those Authors, I doe oftentimes allude
but in a word or two, vnto many great Matters, which in the Authors
themselues are set downe more prolixly: this directing of my Reader
vnto the plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> so particularly, will oftentimes serue him in stead of a
Commentarie, storing him to euery purpose, with a great deale of more
matter, then I haue extracted out of the Author.</p>
   <p>And yet, no man is hereby tyed vnto the same edition of the Authors
that by my selfe is vsed. I doe but only direct them, which haue the same
editions, how to make more ready vse of them. As for those that haue
them not, I haue noted, not onely the Author, but the Booke also, and
the Chapter: and so come as neere them, as I could possibly imagine.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
Another Exception may perhaps be also taken: <hi>That Verses bee
sometimes cited, and yet not as verses.</hi> But this may be defended,<note place="margin">Fraz, Poet. pag. 141. Versorum pro versuum.</note>
with that excuse of <hi>Laberius,</hi> that, <hi>Versorum non numerorum
numero studuimus. I therein followed rather the power of the
sense, then the number of the syllables.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Senec. Epist. 101. p. 251.</note> And, with another like, of
<hi>Seneca's,</hi> that <hi>Animis ista scripsi, non auribus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Some againe may except that Greeke writers are not cited in their
owne proper language. Whereunto I answer: First, that the weight of
those Testimonies, which I haue taken out of them, doth seldome, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
rest vpon the proprietie of the Greeke word or phrase: but mostly
vpon the matter, and the sense. Secondly, that if it did: yet the credit
of the Translator hath no lesse authoritie, then any Nomenclator, or
Dictionarie maker, but rather much greater: Because, hee is led vnto
his translation; by exactly perpending the true weight of euery word as
it is in that place vsed, rendring it most properly out of the congruitie
of those circumstances that he hath before considered, both in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teceding
and succeeding passages: which are the best directions, and
cannot be considered by the bare reciter of the words in their seuerall
significations. But thirdly, and lastly (which stoppeth all reply) I haue
cited those Authors, as I had them: contenting my selfe with the vse
of those Booke, which were onely mine owne, and in mine owne posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
not affecting to be curious, either in this, or in any thing else which
tendeth not directly vnto the profit of my Readers.</p>
   <p>Againe it may be obiected; that the Sentences alleadged are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
translated.<note place="margin">Aul. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l. lib. 9. c. 9 p. 124.</note> Whereunto againe I answer: that to the sense they
be alwayes,<note place="margin">Horat. lib. de Art. Poet. p. 169.</note> though, to the words, not alwayes: For, that needs not: in
the opinion of an excellent Criticke And the Poet telleth vs, that hee
may be a faithfull Translator that doth it not.
<q>
         <l>Nec verbum verbo curabis reddere fidus</l>
         <l>Interpres—</l>
         <l>It's not his part, that is the best Translator,</l>
         <l>To render word for word, vnto his Author.</l>
      </q>
But, the Orator telleth vs, that hee cannot be a delightfull Translator
that doth it.<note place="margin">Cie. lib 3. De Fin p. 68.</note>
      <hi>Verbume verbo exprimere, interpretis est indiserti.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, yet an other, <hi>That I haue not alwayes cited them to the
meaning of the Author.</hi> To which I likewise answer: That, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
I produce them, as Testimonies for the confirmation of the point
then in question, I cite them exactly, vnto the Authors meaning. But
<pb facs="13"/>
that is not alwayes my end in alledging them: but, sometimes, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
their words, by way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, rather then of allegation, for the more
commodious expressing of mine owne sense and meaning. A thing very
vsuall and familiar with <hi>Plutarch;</hi> whose character, and forme of stile
I haue (in that point) propounded to imitate.</p>
   <p>Finally, it may be, that some men will except against the publishing
of this first part alone, before the rest be ready: in putting vnto me, the
incurious error of <hi>Curio</hi> the Orator.<note place="margin">Cic. in. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>43.</note>
      <hi>Qui, aliquoties tria cum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posuisset,
aut quarum adderet, aut tertium quaereret. Who often
times, propounding to speake but of three things, commonly,
either added to them a fourth, or else forgat to speak of the third.</hi>
But, for this course of proceeding, I am not without my reason: as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
First the example of very many learned men; whom wee dayly
obserue to practice the same, and to propine vnto their Readers
an assay of their works, to take a tast of them, how themselues are
tasted by them. Secondly, because this first part of the worke hath
growne exceeding great, and beyond mine expectation, beeing
now come vnto the measure and bignes of a Volume. And thirdly, it
had no little moment with me, that diuers of my learnedest and best
affected Friends, haue often importuned mee vnto the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
of it, hastening (in their loue) this vnperfect worke, vnto the
edition; peraduenture, as an vntimely fruit vnto his abortion: but
without peraduenture,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Orat▪ ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> p. 35.</note> vnto that common condition, which is obserued
by <hi>Isocrates</hi> to be fatal, to many Booke. <hi>Vt dum adhuc in mentibus
Authorum inclusi te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eantur, magnam sui expectationem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citent:
sed. perfecti tandem, &amp; alijs oftensi, longe tenuiorem,
quam pro concepta spe, gloriam consequantur. They stirre vp a
greater expec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ation, whilst they are in doing, then they are able
to maintaine, when as they be done.</hi> But yet, the principall ende
and intent of my writing, being onely the good, and profit of my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;
I should greatly wrong, both their curtesie and equitie, to make
any doubt of their fauourable acceptance. Which, if they should not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde,
they themselues should wrong them both. For what can be more
contrarie, both to curtesie, and equitie, then either to speake, or but to
thinke euill of those, that haue spent so much paynes, onely to doe them
good?<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 46. 47. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. ad Corn. Nepo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. p. 7.</note> This were the reward of worse then a Pagan: which I hope to be
farre, from euery good Christian.
<q>Quare habe tibi, quic quid hoe Libelli est.</q>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>Such as it is, I doe willingly permit it vnto thine equall censure:</hi>
desiring nothing more, then that the same minde, towards thine owne
good, may possesse thee, in reading it, that did me, in writing it: and then
I shall not neede to doubt of thy profit by it: Which I will accompt, mine
owne <hi>exceeding great Reward.</hi> And therefore, I conclude this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
with that prayer of <hi>Irenaeus:</hi>
      <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>enaeus l. 3. c, 6. p. 176.</note>
      <hi>Da (Deus) omni legenti hanc
scripturam, cognoscere te quia solus Deus es, &amp; confirmari int te
&amp; absistere ab omni haeretica, quae est sine Deo, &amp; impia senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.
Grant (O Lord) vnto all that shall be readers of this Booke,
to know thee, to be the onely true God▪ and in thee
more and more to be strengthned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed:
and to eschew all the impious
opinions, of</hi> Heretiks, <hi>and</hi>
Atheists▪ <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
<hi>Martin Sarum.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>