<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣REND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD LORD, THE LORD Arch-bishop of CANTERBVRY his Grace, Primate and Metropoli∣tan of all England.</title>
           <author>Field, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121344_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00728</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10858</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121344</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣REND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD LORD, THE LORD Arch-bishop of CANTERBVRY his Grace, Primate and Metropoli∣tan of all England.</title>
                 <author>Field, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the Church : fiue bookes. By Richard Field Doctor of Diuinity and sometimes Deane of Glocester</title>
                 <author>Field, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 906, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD LORD, THE LORD Arch-bishop of CANTERBVRY his Grace, Primate and Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan of all <hi>England.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Reuerend in Christ, the consideration of</hi> the vnhappie diuisions of the Christian world, and the infinite distractions of mens mindes, not knowing in soe great variety of opinions, what to thinke, or to whom to joyne themselues, (euery faction boasting of the pure &amp; sincere profession of heauenly truth, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging to it selfe alone the name of the Church; and fastning vpon all that dissent, or are otherwise min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the hatefull note of Schisme and Heresie) hath made me euer thinke, that there is no part of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge more necessary, than that which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Church. For, seeing the controuersies of Religion in our time, are growne in number so many, and in nature so intricate, that, few haue time and leasure, fewer strength of vnderstanding to examine them; what remaineth for men desirous of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in things of such consequence, but diligently to search out, which amongst all the societies of men in the world, is that <hi>blessed company of holy ones,</hi> that <hi>houshold of faith,</hi> that <hi>Spouse of Christ,</hi> and <hi>Church of the liuing God,</hi> which is <hi>the Pillar and ground of truth;</hi> that so they may embrace her communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, follow her directions, and rest in her iudgement. Hence it commeth, that all wise and iudicious men; do more esteeme bookes of <hi>doctrinall principles,</hi> than those that are written of any other argument; and that there was neuer any treasure holden more rich and precious by all them that knew how to prize and value things aright, than bookes of <hi>prescription against the profane nouelties of Heretiques:</hi> for that thereby men that are not willing, or not able to examine the infinite differences that arise amongst men concerning the faith, haue generall directions what to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and what to avoid. Wee admitte no man, sayth <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>booke of prescriptions,</hi> to any disputation concerning sacred and diuine things; or to the scanning and examining of particular questions of Religion, vnlesse hee first shew vs, of whom he receiued the faith, by whose meanes he became a Christian, and whether hee admitte and hold the generall principles, wherein all Christians do, and euer did agree; otherwise, prescribing against him, as a stranger from the common-wealth of
<pb facs="4"/>
the Israel of God, and hauing no part, nor fellowship in this businesse. But as in the daies of the Fathers, the <hi>Donatists,</hi> and other Heretickes, including the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compasse of <hi>Africa,</hi> and such other parts of the world, where they &amp; their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorts found best entertainment, reiected all other from the vnity of the Church, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them from hope of saluation, and appropriated all the glorious things that are spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of it, to themselues alone: soe in our time, there are some found so much in loue with the pompe and glory of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they feare not to condemne all the inhabitants of the world and to pronounce them to be <hi>Anathema</hi> from the Lord Iesus, if they dissent from that Church, and the doctrine, profession, and obseruations of it; So casting into hell, all the Christians of <hi>Graecia, Russia, Armenia, Syria,</hi> and <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> because they refuse to be subiect to the tyranny of the Pope, and the Court of <hi>Rome:</hi> besides the heauie sentence which they haue passed, against all the famous States and Kingdomes of <hi>Europe,</hi> which haue freed themselues from the Aegyptiacall bondage, they were formerly holden in. These men abuse many with the glorious pretences of antiquity, Vnity, Vniuersality, Succession, and the like; making the simple beleeue that all is ancient which they professe, that the consent of all ages is for them, and that the Bishops succeeding one another, in all the famous Churches of the world, neuer taught, nor beleeued any other thing, than they now doe: whereas it is easie to proue, that all the things wherein they dissent from vs, are nothing else but nouelties, and vncertaineties; that the greatest part of the Christian world hath beene diuided from them for certaine hundreds of yeares; that none of the most famous, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Churches, euer knew, or admitted, any of their heresies; and that the things they now publish, as Articles of faith to be beleeued by all that will bee saued, are so farre from being Catholike, that they were not the doctrines of that Church, wherein they and wee sometimes liued together in one communion, but the opinions onely of some men in that Church, adulterating the doctrine of heauenly trueth, bringing in, and defending superstitious abuses disliked by others, and seruing as vile instruments to aduance the tyrāny of the Bishop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherefore for the discouery of the vanity of their insolent boastings, for the cōfirming of the weake, the satisfying of them that are doubtfull, and that all men may know, that wee haue not departed from the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent faith, or forsaken the fellowship of the Catholicke Church, but that wee haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken a part to hold communion with the whole, (led so to doe, by the most preuailing reasons that euer perswaded men, and the greatest authority on earth) I resolued to communicate to others, what I had long since in priuate for mine owne satisfactien obserued, touching the nature of the Church, the notes whereby it may bee knowen, and the priuiledges that pertaine to it. These my simple labours, most Reuerend in Christ, I thought it my dutie to offer to your Graces censure, before they should present themselues to the view of the world; that so, either finding approbation, they might the more confidently make themselues publike, or otherwise be suppressed like the vntimely fruit, that neuer saw the Sunne. The condition of the times wherein wee liue is such, that manie are discouraged from medling with the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies of Religion, because they are sure (besides the vile slanders, wicked calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and bitter reproches, of the common aduersaries) to passe the censures of those men, who, though they will doe nothing themselues, yet in the height of a proud and disdainefull spirit, with many a scornefull looke, smile at the follies of other mens writings, as they esteeme them. The sinister iudgements of either of these sortes of men, I shall the lesse regard, for that it pleased your Grace so louingly to accept, and soe fauourably to approue these my poore paines, bestowed for the clearing of sundry
<pb facs="4"/>
questions concerning t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rch, which by your direction and appointment <hi>I</hi> first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into. It hath bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he vaunt of the aduersaries of the Religion established amongst vs, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> written many bookes against vs, and none haue beene found to oppose any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>g against them; &amp; that they desire nothing more, then by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or disputing, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ic the goodnes of their cause. But, I doubt not, but this Nationall Church, the gouernment whereof vnder our most gracious Soueraigne, is principally committed to your fatherly care, shall yeeld men more than matchable, with the prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of the aduerse faction: who being animated and hartned by your fauour, &amp; gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by your directions, shall no longer suffer these proud <hi>Philistims,</hi> to defie the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord of Hosts. For though they proclaime their owne praises with loude sounding trumpets, that might haue beene piped with an oaten straw; and though they magnifie themselues, as if they were the only Paragons of the world, and as if all wit, &amp; learning, had bin borne with them, &amp; should die with them: yet whosoeuer knoweth them, will little regard the froath of their swelling words of pride and scorne: seeing when they haue done vaunting, they haue done their best, and that which remaineth is little worth; their allegations being for the most part nothing but falsifications: their testimonies of antiquity, the markes &amp; notes of their ancient forgeries; their reasons, sophismes: their reports, slanders, and wicked calumniations: their threats, the venting of their malice, and powring out of their impotent desires; their predictions, onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifesting what they wish might be, but no way shewing what shall be. In the later daies of our late dread Soueraigne <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous &amp; blessed memory, all their books were nothing but fearefull threatnings of bloody confusions, and horrible dissipations, of Church and common-wealth, which they hoped for, and looked after, soe soone as it should please God to cut off the thread of her blessed life. But, <hi>he that sitteth in heauē hath laughed them to scorne,</hi> and branded them with the marke of false Prophets. For, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is gathered to her fathers in peace, full of daies, and full of honour, &amp; yet they haue not bathed their swords in blood as they desired; but God hath disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed all their purposes, frustrated their hopes, and continued our happinesse. <hi>Iosua</hi> hath succeeded <hi>Moyses:</hi> and <hi>Salomon, Dauid:</hi> and he that disposeth the kingdomes of men, &amp; giueth them to whom he will, hath set vpon the Throne of Maiesty amongst vs, a King of a Religious, Vertuous, and peaceable disposition, to whom he hath giuen a wise and vnderstanding heart, large as the sands of the sea shore, whose delight is in the Law of the Lord, who hath chosen his <hi>testimonies to be his Counsellers;</hi> whose constant resolution in matters of faith and Religion, daunteth the enemies of it; whose admirable vnderstanding in things Diuine, more then for many ages, the world hath found in any of his ranke, giueth vs good assurance, that no frauds of any deceiuers shall euer be able to seduce or misse-lead him: whose blessed Progenie, and Royall issue, maketh vs hope, that the felicity of these vnited kingdomes, shall continue as longe as the Sunne and Moone endure: which whosoeuer desireth, and seeketh to procure, <hi>Peace be vpon him, &amp; vpon the Israel of God.</hi> Thus crauing pardon for this my boldnesse, and humbly beseeching Almighty God, long to continue your Graces hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and prosperous estate, and to make you a glorious instrument of much good to his Church, I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces, in all dutie,
RICHARD FIELD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>