<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121939_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01077</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11191</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121939</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bitter vvaters of Babylon, or The miserable estate of the citizens of Sion : considered by the confusion of all things in this world</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been the <hi>manner</hi> of most of the <hi>Anncient,</hi> in former time; and at this day is retained in the <hi>Church,</hi> as a forme, amongst the best <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anes;</hi> to chuse a text fitted for the <hi>time:</hi> and to speake out of the Scripture appointed for the <hi>day.</hi> Which order if I had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, my text should haue entreated, of mirth and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodie, both in respect of the season of the yeare; and occasion of the feast; for of all seasons, this is most sweete, pleasant, and deliciouse, <hi>Iam floridu aestas, quae spicea serta</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ouid. 2. Meta▪</note>
      <hi>gerit,</hi> Now it is florishing summer, which brings foorth the fragrant flowers: Nay this the merry moneth of May: if the occasion of the feast had ledde me to my text, the matter had been me odious, for by the reuolution of this time euery yeare, is specified vnto vs; the <hi>comfort</hi> which we receiue by that sweete <hi>Comforter,</hi> sent downe by Iesus <note place="margin">Act. 2. 1. 2.</note> Christ vpon the Apostles in visible signes, wherefore the Auncient in their Lythargie did tearme it a <hi>glorious time:</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Missa pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e.</note>
      <hi>gloriosum hunc fecists diem,</hi> was their <hi>Antheme;</hi> And wee obseruing the same in our Church pray the Lord to grant that we may reioice in his holy comfort, in the Collect for <note place="margin">Collect vpon W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>day.</note> the day: either of which, if I had regarded, then my song had been solacious, or a <hi>song of degrees.</hi> But, I consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the iniquities of the time, and knowing that <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nare readie to enlarge their hearts</hi> too much with worldly mirth, and especially about this time of the year, wherfore I haue changed my note into an <hi>Elegiacall</hi> tune, which sounds nothing but weeping, mourning, and lamentation for worldly mirth is like vnto <hi>pure wine,</hi> which not being min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with some other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cour, will draw drunkennesse vpon the receiuer, in like manner <hi>earthly melody</hi> not being tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="2" facs="6"/>
with a meditation of death, or a consideration of a better life, it will drowne the affecter with a greedie desire thereafter, and ouerwhelme him with an obliuion of his Creator: wherefore our Sauiour tooke vp a mournfull song in the midst of the peoples melodie, in his iourney to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem;</hi> and herefore, it is, that I haue chosen a dolefull <note place="margin">Luke. 19. 41.</note> ditty, which I am (by Gods assistance) to read vnto your godly audience, which may restraine our too much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in worldly vanity.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>