<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121333_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01020</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11126</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121333</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deuout contemplations expressed in two and fortie sermons vpon all ye quadragesimall Gospells written in Spanish by Fr. Ch. de Fonseca Englished by. I. M. of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Fonseca, Cristóbal de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 648, 18 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, to seeke thy approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Booke by any
faire &amp; plausi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inductions, were to distrust, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the worth
of it. 'Tis folly to light a Candle to the Sunne, as likewise to praise that,
which in it selfe is all praise worthy. True Vertue needs no Orator to set her
foorth; her owne natiue beautie is so moouing, that outward trappings can
afoord her small aduantage. If the diuine conceits and meditations of
Antiquitie can worke vpon thy Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, I make no doubt but here's enough to
win thee. The whole Booke is nothing but a bunch of flowers collected from out
those pleasant Gardens, which were long since planted by the art and industrie
of those re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Fathers, whom God raised vp for Guardians to his Church,
during hir nonage and minoritie. If the sent of these shall please thee, the
Translator will hereafter furnish thee with the Labors of the same Author vpon
all the Parables.</p>
   <p>Some peraduenture may dislike it, because it was first composed by
a Spaniard; as if <hi>Eliah</hi> should haue refused his meat, because it was
brought him by a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; or that in a curious Fountaine, where there are some
spouts formed like the heads of Serpents, others, like those of Doues, the
water that issued out of either were notall one. The antient Gaules had no
sooner ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the delicious wines of Italy, but a desire tooke them 
<pb facs="4"/> to goe and conquer the Countrey: the like had beene wrought vpon
the Israelites, when some of those, whom <hi>Moses</hi> by the appointment of
God himselfe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Num.</hi> 13.23</note> had sent to view the
fruitfulnesse of the land of Canaan, brought them of the Grapes, Figs, and
Pomegranats, which the soyle affoorded; if others had not marr'd this reall
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration with a vaine suspition of the sons of <hi>Anak.</hi> But what,
shall not the corne be reaped because there's cockle in the field? Shal not the
rose be pluckt because it grows on a Brier? And yet let me tell thee, to
hearten thy aduenture against all needlesse &amp; imaginarie fears, The captiue
here hath her head shorn, and may well be admitted for a true Israelite. Thou
shalt not cry out, <hi>Mors in olla, Death is in the pot</hi>; that little
leafe of <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida</hi> which was in it, is taken out, and the children
of the Prophets may tast of the broth without danger.</p>
   <p>Others it may be, wil condemne it as defectiue, because such
proofes &amp; passages as are alledged out of the fathers are not quoted in the
margent; &amp; indeed they should not haue bin wanting, but that in the Spanish
copy, they were found vpon good perusall (whether through the negligence of the
Printer, or some other default) to be so mistakē, that to haue set them down,
would haue occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned trouble rather than content: but if euer the Booke come
to a second impression, all things shal be added, for the satisfying of thy
desires to the full. Meane while ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this, and let it be thy Christian
ioy, That the lis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Ephramite is heard here to speake as plaine as the
smooth-tongu'd Canaanite; and that there is not so great a distance betwixt
Hierusalem and Samaria, as some imagine. And so I leaue thee to the blessing of
the Highest.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>