<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121088_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14686</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121088</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nine worthies of London : explayning the honourable exercise of armes, the vertues of the valiant, and the memorable attempts of magnanimious minds. Pleasant for gentlemen, not vnseemely for magistrates, and most profitable for prentises. Compiled by Richard Iohnson</title>
                 <author>Johnson, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Humphrey 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, being incouraged through your gentle
acceptance of my <hi>Cynthia,</hi> I haue once more aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured
on your Curtesies: hoping to finde you (as I
haue done hertofore) friendly. Being determined to
write of somthing, &amp; yet not resolued of any thing, I
considered with my selfe, if one should write of Loue (they will
say) why, euery one writes of Loue: if of Vertue, why, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards
Vertue? To be short, I could thinke of nothing, but either
it was common, or not at all in request, At length I bethought
my selfe of a Subiect, both new (as hauing neuer beene written vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
before) and pleasing (as I thought) because Mans Nature (com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly)
loues to heare that praised, with whose pressence, hee is
most pleased.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Erasmus</hi> (the glory of <hi>Netherland,</hi> and the refiner of the Latin
Tongue) wrote a whole Booke, in <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> prayse of Folly.</hi> Then if so
excellent a Scholler, writ in praise of Vanity, why may not I write
in praise of that which is profitable? There are no two Countreys
where Gold is esteemed, lesse than in <hi>India,</hi> and more then in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi>
the reason is, because the <hi>Indians</hi> are barbarous and our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
ciuill.</p>
   <p>I haue giuen <hi>Pecunia</hi> the title of a Woman Both for the termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of the Word, and because (as Women are) shee is lov'd of
men. The brauest Voyages in the World, haue beene made for
Gold: for it, men haue venterd (by Sea) to the furthest part of the
<pb facs="7"/>
Earth: In the Pursute wherof, <hi>Englands Nestor</hi> and <hi>Neptune (Hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi>
and <hi>Drake</hi>) lost their liues. Vpon the Deathes of the which
two, of the first I writ this:
<q>
         <l>The Waters were his Winding sheete, the Sea was made his Toome;</l>
         <l>Yet for his fame the Ocean Sea, was not sufficient roome.</l>
      </q>
Of the latter this:
<q>
         <l>
            <hi>England</hi> his hart; his Corps the Waters haue:</l>
         <l>And that which raysd his fame, because his grave.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Praetorians</hi> (after the death of <hi>Pertinax</hi>) in the election of a
new Emperour, more esteemed the money of <hi>Iulianus,</hi> then either
the vertue of <hi>Seuerus,</hi> or the Valour of <hi>Pessennius.</hi> Then of what
great estimation and account, this Lady <hi>Pecunia,</hi> both hath beene
in the Worlde, and is at this present, I leaue to your Iudgement.
But what speake I so much of her praise in my Epistle, that haue
commended her so at large, in my Booke? To the reading wherof,
(Gentlemen) I referre you.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>