<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣REND FATHER IN GOD, WILLIAM, BY THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE, LORD ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBVRY, PRIMATE OF ALL England and Metropolitan, one of the L L. of his Majesties most Honourable Privy Councell, and Chancell or of the Vniversity of OXFORD.</title>
           <author>Somner, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S121902_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22918</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S121902</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣REND FATHER IN GOD, WILLIAM, BY THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE, LORD ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBVRY, PRIMATE OF ALL England and Metropolitan, one of the L L. of his Majesties most Honourable Privy Councell, and Chancell or of the Vniversity of OXFORD.</title>
                 <author>Somner, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The antiquities of Canterbury. Or a survey of that ancient citie, with the suburbs, and cathedrall : Containing principally matters of antiquity in them all. Collected chiefly from old manuscripts, lieger-bookes, and other like records, for the most part, never as yet printed. With an appendix here annexed: wherein (for better satisfaction to the learned) the manuscripts, and records of chiefest consequence, are faithfully exhibited. All (for the honour of that ancient metropolis, and his good affection to antiquities) sought out and published by the industry, and goodwill of William Somner</title>
                 <author>Somner, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thrale, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 516, 12 pages, 3 folded leaves of plates, coat of arms, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN GOD, <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> BY THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE, LORD ARCHBISHOP OF <hi>CANTERBVRY,</hi> PRIMATE OF ALL <hi>England</hi> and Metropolitan, one of the L L. of his Majesties most Honourable Privy Councell, and Chancell or of the Vniversity of OXFORD.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>May it please Your Grace.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S without the concurrence of divers good reasons to induce me, I had not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to present unto Your <hi>Grace</hi> the following <hi>Discourse:</hi> So I conceive it very fitting, and my bounden duty, to give Your <hi>Grace,</hi> and the world, an Accompt in
<pb facs="3"/>
briefe, of the inducements whereby I have been animated to appeare in this kinde before Your <hi>Grace.</hi> The chiefe whereof hath been, and is, Your <hi>Graces</hi> interest both in the <hi>Author,</hi> and in the <hi>Worke.</hi> In the <hi>Author,</hi> as subsisting in his place and profession, under <hi>God,</hi> chiefly by your <hi>Graces</hi> favour and Goodnesse. In the <hi>Worke,</hi> in a double respect: the one, as it is a Discourse of <hi>Antiquities;</hi> Your <hi>Graces</hi> extraordinary care and cost for the Collection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of all sorts, from all parts, Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Your singular Piety and Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in disposing them to the good and service of the publike; as they are thankfully acknowledged and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily celebrated by all the Lovers of <hi>Antiquities;</hi> so doe they give Your <hi>Grace</hi> an especiall interest to all their Labours who are that way inclined. The other; as it handleth more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Antiquities</hi> of two such <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars</hi> as are of very neere relation to
<pb facs="3"/>
Your <hi>Grace,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> These reasons (may it please Your <hi>Grace)</hi> not to trouble You with more, in all Humility I hope, may prevaile with Your <hi>Grace</hi> for Your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and pardon of this presumption: and though not procure Your <hi>Graces</hi> acceptance and protection of the <hi>Worke,</hi> yet Your excuse of the <hi>Authors</hi> bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, who most humbly craves it at Your <hi>Gracious</hi> Hands: and with his hearty Prayers, both for the long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of Your <hi>Graces</hi> Health and Happinesse here, to <hi>Gods</hi> Glory and the good of His <hi>Church,</hi> and for Your endlesse blisse hereafter, prostrates both Himselfe and His Labours at Your <hi>Graces</hi> Feete with that reverence which becomes</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The meanest of Your <hi>Graces</hi> Servants, William Somner.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>