<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Winton, Ia.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122229_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04224</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Winton, Ia.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorkes of the most high and mightie prince, Iames by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. Published by Iames, Bishop of Winton, and deane of his Maiesties Chappel Royall</title>
                 <author>James, I., King of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 569, 3 pages, portraits (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst the infinite number of great Ʋolumes wherewith the world seemes, as it were, to bee wayed downe, there bee few of them that were written at once, or were at first published toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Writings as they consist of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry natures; so they will beare a diuers maner of Edition. To set foorth an Art by pieces, is to shew you a body dismembred; the one is no more vncomely, then the other is vnproper. To publish a <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> before it be at an end, is to turne the Hower-glasse before it bee runne out; neither of both will giue you a trew taste of the time. But writings of other Natures, Common places and Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, Meditations and Commentaries, as they are for the most part, accidentally taken vp, so they are as occasionally set out: They craue no other birth into the world, then they had conceptions in our braines, singly by vs conceiued, and singly by themselues set out.</p>
   <p>The different maner of <hi>GOD</hi> his setting foorth of his owne Workes, may instruct vs in this point. His diuine Wisedome held one course in his Naturall Workes, an other in his Ceremonialls, Politicalls and Moralls. Jn his Naturalls he made a masse at once, which speedily he diuersified into diuers formes. Hee gaue a kinde of potentiall delineation of all things in that vniuersall matter, which presently hee distinguished into diuers <hi>Species</hi> in
<pb facs="6"/>perfection: But in his Ceremonialls, hee takes another course, he brings not them out of a Masse, but into a Masse: He doeth not out of a <hi>Totum</hi> produce the parts, but out of the parts make vp the whole. For example; Jn the Ceremonialls, first he beginnes with Sacrifice, long after he followes with Circumcision, then hee filleth a Tabernacle with them; at last makes them full vp in a Temple. Jn his Politicalls, hee beginnes with a paternall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in a family, proceeds to an Election of a Captaine in an Armie, as in <hi>Iosuah</hi> and the Judges, perfects it by way of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession in a setled Kingdome, as in <hi>Solomon</hi> and his Successors. Jn his Moralls, hee beginnes with the word out of his owne mouth, proceeds with the <hi>Tables</hi> written by his owne fingers, followes on with the fiue Bookes penned by <hi>Moses,</hi> till hee make vp the <hi>Canon</hi> perfect by a number of succeeding <hi>Prophets.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>What we haue from <hi>GOD</hi> in a president, it may wel beseeme vs to practise; and since his Bookes came out so farre asunder, it is no reproach to any man, though his Workes come not foorth together: for there is a reason for it in vs answerable in some proportion to that of the Workes of <hi>GOD,</hi> for workes of Nature haue their roote from within vs, and bring with them a radicall kinde of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that neuer suffers them to rest, till they haue produced their fruite to perfect forme and perfection: Workes of deliberation and Art, haue their foundation from without vs, and giue vs occasion to worke vpon them, as our phantasies thinke fittest for the present time: Hence proceeds it, that the workes of Nature haue so few errors in them, those of Art so many; They of Nature so constant, they of Arte so variable; they of Nature so perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, they of Art so soone perish; they of Nature so well accepted and approued of all, they of Art accepted or reiected, as it pleaseth the seuerall apprehensions of men to conceiue of them.</p>
   <p>Now, albeit the workes of men be of Errors so full, of nature so different, subiect to so many Jnterpretations, published at so diuers times; Yet hath it bene euer esteemed a matter commendable to collect them together, and incorporate them into one Body, that we may behold at once, what diuers Off-springs haue proceeded
<pb facs="6"/>from one braine, and how various Conceptions the wit of man is able to afford the world. To instance in a few of them beginning a little higher then the writings of ordinarie Men. The seruants of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> are commended in Scripture for collecting together the Sentences of <hi>Solomon. Iesus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> is praised for searching out the Copies of his Grandfathers workes: But prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally <hi>Ezra</hi> is had in great honour for setting in order the whole Bookes of the Old Testament, and deuiding them into Chapters and Ʋerses, which before were caried along in a scroule, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall <hi>Series,</hi> without any distinction at all. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> is reported to haue searched out the Copies of the three former Euangelists, and to haue added his owne for the fourth in that order, as now they are extant. And the Primitiue Church was curious to gather together the Epistles of the Holy Apostles; which, they being not able by reason of persecution perfectly to performe in euery place, gaue occasion to after-times, to call the authority of so many of them into question.</p>
   <p>But to descend; How are we bound to those, who haue laboured in setting out the <hi>Counsells,</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Fathers</hi> together? Jnsomuch, that we thinke our selues as much bound to <hi>Eusebius</hi> and <hi>Hierom,</hi> and of later times to <hi>Peter Crab</hi> and <hi>Erasmus</hi> and diuers others, who haue laboured in that kinde, as wee doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most to the Authors themselues. <hi>Traian</hi> commended <hi>Plutark</hi> for gathering the <hi>Apothegmes</hi> of wise men together. <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Leo,</hi> collected out of all Histories, both in the East and West, one <hi>Corpus Historicum,</hi> which they counted an inestimable Treasure. <hi>Iustinian</hi> by the helpe of <hi>Tribonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> did the like in the Lawes. <hi>Gratian</hi> compiled the Decrees out of the Epistles of <hi>Popes, Councells</hi> and <hi>Fathers. Damascen</hi> collected into one body of Diuinitie, the Sentences of the Greeke <hi>Fathers;</hi> And <hi>Peter Lumbard 400.</hi> yeeres after him by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample did the like in the Latine <hi>Fathers.</hi> And how doe wee labour to recouer Bookes that are lost? The Bookes of <hi>Origen</hi> that amounted to sixe thousand, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> witnesseth, were much laboured for by <hi>Eusebius</hi> and others. The Bookes of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero
<pb facs="7"/>de Repub.</hi> were much sought for by Cardinall <hi>Poole;</hi> and great summes of money haue bene spent to recouer the lost <hi>Decades</hi> of <hi>Liuie.</hi> Wherefore since it hath beene heretofore the practise of all aages, to collect the workes of Men of worth, and preserue them from perishing; to labour much in recouering those that haue bene lost; to giue to euery childe the owne Father; to euery Booke the trew Author: (for there neuer had bene halfe so many birds to haue flowen about the world with false feathers, if euery Author had set out his owne workes together in his owne time,) J hope then it shall not be now a matter of reproofe in a Seruant, to trauaile in the setting foorth of the <hi>Works</hi> of his Master; and for giuing you that together, which before yee could hardly get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder; and for preseruing that in a Masse from perishing, that might easily be lost in a Mite.</p>
   <p>But while I am collecting workes one way, I heare others scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering wordes as fast an other way, affirming, it had beene better his Maiestie had neuer written any Bookes at all; and being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, better they had perished with the present, like <hi>Proclamations,</hi> then haue remayned to <hi>Posterity:</hi> For say these Men, Little it befitts the Maiesty of a <hi>King</hi> to turne Clerke, and to make a warre with the penne, that were fitter to be fought with the Pike; to spend the powers of his so exquisite an vnderstanding vpon pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which had they beene spent on powder, could not but haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled ere this, for the Conquest of a <hi>Kingdome.</hi> For a <hi>King,</hi> say they, to enter a Controuersie with a Scholler, is, as if he should fight a Combate with a Kerne; he doth no more descend from his Honour in the one, then he bringes vpon himselfe Disgrace by the other. And since that Booke-writing is growen into a Trade; It is as dishonorable for a <hi>King</hi> to write bookes; as it is for him to be a Practitioner in a <hi>Profession.</hi> Jf a <hi>King</hi> will needs write; Let him write like a <hi>King,</hi> euery Lyne a <hi>Law,</hi> euery Word a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi> euery Letter a <hi>Mandate.</hi> Jn good trewth, I haue had my eares so oft dung through with these Obiections and the like, as I know not whether I conceiued amisse of my selfe or no, thinking I had more ability to answere these Calumnyes, then I had patience
<pb facs="7"/>to heare them: And therefore hauing so fit opportunity, J shall not let to deliuer my opinion; <hi>Whether it may sorte with the Maiestie of a King, to be a writer of Bookes, or no.</hi> First I could neuer reade, that there was any Law against it; and where we haue no Law, the best is to follow good Examples: And many Diuines are of opinion, that examples that are not contrary to any Precept, doe binde vs in practise, at least so farre; that though they doe not inforce vs to the doing, yet they warrant the deede when it is done; And if Examples will serue the turne, wee haue Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples enough.</p>
   <p>First to beginne with the <hi>King of Kings</hi> God himselfe, who as he doth all things for our good; So doeth he many things for our Jmitation. Jt pleased his Diuine wisedome to bee the first in this Rancke, that we read of, that did euer write. Hee wrote, and the writing was the writing, saith <hi>Moses,</hi> of God; the maner was after the maner of engrauing; the matter was in Stone cut into two Tables, and the Tables were the worke of God written on both sides. <hi>Diuines</hi> hold, that the Heart is the principall Seate of the Soule; which Soule of ours is the immediate worke of God, as these Tables were the immediate worke of his owne fingers. The Stone, the expresse represent of the hardnesse of our heart; the engrauing the worke of God so deepely impressed, that it can neuer be blotted out; the writing, the writing of the Law in our hearts; In two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, for our double duty to God and Man; on both sides to take vp our heart so wholly, that nothing contrary to those Precepts should euer haue any place in our Soules. And certainely from this little <hi>Library,</hi> that God hath erected within vs, is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all our Learning layd; So that people Ciuillized doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themselues depriued of one of the best abilities of nature, if they be not somewhat inabled by writing, to expresse their mindes: And there is no Nation so brutish or Barbarous, that haue not inuented one kinde of Character or other, whereby to conuey to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their inward Conceptions. From these Tables of God, wee may come to the writing of our Blessed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> which we may put in the next place, though not for order yet for Honour. His Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb facs="8"/>Maiestie left behinde him no Monument of writing, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his owne hand in any externall Booke; for he was to induce and bring in an other maner of the writing of the Law of Loue; not in Tables of stone; written not with incke and paper, but in the Tables of our fleshly hearts written by the Spirit of the Liuing God: Yet did he once with his owne finger, write on the Pauement of the Temple of <hi>Ierusalem.</hi> What he writ, J will not now dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusse. <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> saith he wrote this Sentence: <hi>Festucam in oculo fratris cernis, trabem in tuo non vides. Beda</hi> thinkes, he wrote that Sentence that he spake: <hi>He that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sinne, let him cast the first stone at her. Haymo</hi> hath a pretty Conceit: He thinketh, he wrote certaine Characters in the Pauement, which the Accusers beholding might see, as in a glasse, their owne wickednesse; and so blushing at it went their wayes. What euer it was, sure we are, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> would haue false accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations written in dust, to bee troden vnder foote of them that passe by. But howsoeuer, I say, our Blessed <hi>Sauiour</hi> did leaue behind him no writing of his owne hand; Yet we may not deny, but that God in the old <hi>Testament</hi> and our <hi>Sauiour</hi> in the New, haue left vs many bookes of their owne inditements: For all the Bookes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture were written by inspiration; and the Prophets and Apostles were but their <hi>Amanuenses,</hi> and writ onely as they were led and actuated by the Spirit of God: So that we may not make the Author of any of those Bookes any other then God Himselfe.</p>
   <p>The old world before the flood wil afford vs no writings, neither did that aage require them; for the liues of Men of that aage were liuing <hi>Libraries,</hi> and lasted longer then the labors of Men doe in this aage: Yet <hi>S. Iude</hi> doeth insinuate somewhat of the writings of <hi>Enoch,</hi> who though he were not in Stile a <hi>King,</hi> Yet there is no reason to contend with him for that Title; for his Dominion would beare it, standing Heire-Apparent to the greater part of the world. <hi>Origen, Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Augustine</hi> report many things out of the supposititous writings that went vnder his name: And <hi>Iose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> and that <hi>Berosus,</hi> that wee haue, tell vs, that hee erected
<pb facs="8"/>two pillars, the one of Stone, the other of Bricke, wherein he wrote of the two-fold destructions of the world, the one by Water, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Fire: But howsoeuer that be trew, it is very probable, he wrote something of that matter, which though it perished with that world; yet doubtlesse the memory thereof was preserued by Tradition vnto the dayes of the <hi>Apostles.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>J will not here insist vpon the writings of <hi>Moses,</hi> who was not onely a Priest, and a Prophet, but was, as himselfe records, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the people a <hi>King,</hi> and was the first that euer receiued au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie from <hi>GOD</hi> to write in <hi>Diuinitie:</hi> Neither will J insist vpon the Example of <hi>King Dauid,</hi> in whose <hi>Psalmes</hi> and <hi>Himnes,</hi> are resounded out the praises of <hi>GOD</hi> in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; for that J finde nothing that these men writ, but what they writ as the <hi>Scribes</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> acted, as I said euen now, by <hi>GOD</hi> his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and not guided by their owne. Yet I suppose wee may safely collect thus much from them, that if <hi>GOD</hi> had thought it a matter derogatory to the Maiestie of a <hi>King</hi> to bee a Writer, he would not haue made choice of those, as his chiefe <hi>Instruments</hi> in this kinde, who were principalls in that other Order. J would easily beleeue, that such men as haue had the honour to be <hi>GOD</hi> his <hi>Pen-men,</hi> should neuer vouchsafe to write any thing of their owne: for as we hold in a pious opinion, that the blessed <hi>Virgine,</hi> hauing once conceiued by the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> would neuer after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by man; So surely men, that had deliuered nothing but the conceptions of that Spirit, should hardly be drawne euer to set out any of their owne labours. But we see the flat contrary both in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> the one the greatest Iudge, the other the most glorious <hi>King,</hi> that euer that Kingdome had. <hi>Samuel,</hi> who writ by <hi>GODS</hi> appointment, the greatest part of those two Bookes, that beare his name, writ also by his owne accord, a Booke contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Law of a <hi>King,</hi> or Institution of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whereby hee laboured to keepe the <hi>King</hi> as well from declining to Tyrannie, as the people from running into Libertie. <hi>Solomon,</hi> besides the Bookes of Scripture, which remaine, writ many likewise of his owne accord, which are lost: For to say nothing of his <hi>3000. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>his <hi>5000.</hi> Songes, that <hi>ingens opus,</hi> as the <hi>Hebrues</hi> call it, of the nature of all things, Birds and Beasts, Fowles and fishes, Trees and plants, from the Hysop to the Cedar: All these were rather workes to manifest humane wisedome, then Diuine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; written rather for the recreation of his owne spirit, then for the edification of the Church: For I cannot conceiue, but those Bookes would rather haue taught vs the learning of Nature; (for which <hi>GOD</hi> hath left vs to the writings of men) then edified vs in the gifts of Grace; for which hee hath giuen vs his owne Booke. Neither let any man suggest, that these writings, that are lost, and, as they say, were destroyed in the destruction of the Temple by the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> were of the same authoritie, as those that doe remaine: for J can hardly be induced to beleeue, that the writings, that were indited by the Spirit of <hi>GOD,</hi> layed vp in the <hi>Arke,</hi> receiued into the <hi>Canon,</hi> read publikely in the Church, are vtterly perished. Jt is a desperate thing to call, either the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of <hi>GOD,</hi> or the fidelity of the Church in question in this point: For if those, that haue bene, are perished; then, why may not these that remaine as well be lost? which is contrary to our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours</hi> assertion, that one <hi>Iota</hi> shall not perish till all bee fulfilled: Therefore J rather incline to thinke; that what euer was Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, still is, then that any is lost: Neither is this opinion so curious to hold, as the other is dangerous to beleeue; Better it is euer, to argue our selues of ignorance, then to accuse <hi>GOD</hi> of improuidence: But if so much Scripture be lost, as is alleadged, farewell <hi>GOD</hi> his prouidence, farewell the fidelitie of the Church, to whose care was concredited the <hi>Oracles</hi> of <hi>GOD.</hi> Let vs come to the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Kings,</hi> where we shall not incurre any danger of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie; that were so farre from being acted by <hi>GOD</hi> his <hi>Spirit;</hi> that they were more like those Disciples of <hi>Iohn,</hi> that had not heard whether there were an <hi>Holy-Ghost,</hi> or no; that knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>GOD,</hi> though they felt neuer so much of his Goodnesse; that neuer beleeued his Omnipotencie, though they had neuer so much experience of his Power.</p>
   <p>To beginne with the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> whose first Monarch was
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and his chiefe Citie <hi>Babel:</hi> from his time to <hi>Sardana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palus</hi> the last of that Monarchie, there was no <hi>King</hi> amongst them, that gaue himselfe to Letters: for as their Kingdome was founded in Tyrannie, so they laboured to keepe it in Barbaritie; neither must we euer looke to see Learning flourish, where Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie beareth the Standerd; for Learning hath no more a facultie to bring the minde to vnderstanding, then it hath with it a power, that workes the will to libertie; neither of which, can euer consist with Tyrannie: And therefore it is no wonder, that this aage affoorded no learned <hi>Kings:</hi> for in that State, which continued thirteene or foureteene hundred yeeres, yee can scarce reade of a learned man: Therefore let either <hi>Histories</hi> or <hi>Poets</hi> paint that out for a Golden aage, as they please, there was neuer any aage, that hath left so little memory of the Golden tincture of their Witts.</p>
   <p>After the time of <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Phull, Tig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath-Philasar</hi> and <hi>Salmanasar,</hi> of whom mention is made in Scripture, and to whom, as it is thought, <hi>Ionas</hi> preached, and with whom some of the <hi>Prophets</hi> were conuersant, when as these <hi>Kings</hi> came into the land of <hi>Israel,</hi> as they did in the dayes of <hi>Menahem,</hi> who gaue to <hi>Phul-Belochus</hi> a thousand Talents of Siluer for a Tribute; And in the dayes of <hi>Hezechiah</hi> came <hi>Salmanasar</hi> and besieged <hi>Samaria</hi> three yeeres, and caried away a great part of the people of the Kingdome of <hi>Israel:</hi> From that time forward, their <hi>Kings</hi> gaue themselues to Letters; insomuch as in the dayes of <hi>Nabucodonolor,</hi> who set vp the Monarchy of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> within one hundred yeeres of <hi>Salmanasar King</hi> of the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> learning was in great estimation, and the <hi>Kings</hi> Court was a Schoole for the best witts of the Kingdome to be bred in, that they might bee able to stand before the <hi>King</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with all learning and vnderstanding. And if <hi>Stories</hi> do not intollerably deceiue vs; <hi>Daniel</hi> and his companions instructed fiue great Monarches, as in the trew knowledge of <hi>GOD,</hi> so in the vnderstanding of all excellent Arts and Sciences; Namely <hi>Nabuchodonosor, Euilmerodack, Baltazar, Darius</hi> of the
<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>Medes,</hi> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> of the <hi>Persians:</hi> And it were no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to proue the trewth of this out of <hi>Daniel</hi> himselfe.</p>
   <p>Come to the <hi>Persians,</hi> who conuersed more with the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as with <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah, Zachary, Malachy</hi> and the people that were in captiuitie; we shall finde them giuen much to Letters. <hi>Cyrus</hi> the first Monarch is recorded to haue written large <hi>Commentaries</hi> of all his diurnall Actions: amongst those Books are found, saith <hi>Esdras,</hi> the <hi>Edicts</hi> of reducing of the <hi>Iewes</hi> to their Countrey: He wrote diuers Letters for the same purpose to all the chiefe Cities of <hi>Asia;</hi> some whereof, we haue in the <hi>11.</hi> of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus,</hi> Chap. the first. Many things likewise are reported to haue bene written of <hi>Artaxerxes, Darius,</hi> and some others of those Monarches, as wee may partly conceiue by the <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Bookes of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and more by the Apocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal-<hi>Esdras,</hi> who reports it to haue bene a custome of those <hi>Kings,</hi> so much to delight in learning, and in the sayings of wise men, that they vsed for an exercise in their greatest Solemnities, to haue so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne <hi>Orations</hi> made in the presence of the <hi>King</hi> and State, of sundry purposes, which, whoso performed to the liking of the <hi>King,</hi> was rewarded with the highest Preferments, that so mighty a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch could aduance them vnto.</p>
   <p>Come we to the <hi>Graecians;</hi> and there we shall finde Learning in the Tropicke of <hi>Cancer</hi> at such a height, as it neuer was before, nor euer, that we read of, since. And surely it is worth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing, that when that extarordinary Diuine Light went out, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning came in; and the ende of the <hi>Prophets</hi> was the beginning of the <hi>Poets:</hi> The last of the diuinity of the one, the first of the Philosophy of the other: for from the end of the Captiuity till the Comming of our <hi>Sauiour Christ,</hi> the space of foure hundreth yeares and more, in which there was no Prophet, that euer J reade of, there were so many <hi>Orators, Poets</hi> and <hi>Philosophers</hi> of such singular giftes in all kindes; as wee are onely their Schollers since, and can neuer attaine to the Excellency of our Master. Jn this time <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was as famous for his Learning and writings, as he was for his Victories: He wrote to <hi>Antipater</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>of all his owne Actions in <hi>Asia</hi> and in <hi>India,</hi> as <hi>Plutark</hi> reports in his Life. <hi>S. Ciprian</hi> in his Tractate of the vanitie of Jdoles, saith, that <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great wrote <hi>Insigne Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to his Mother; wherein he signifies vnto her, how it was tolde him by a certaine <hi>Egyptian-Priest,</hi> that all the Gods of the Gentiles had bene but men. And <hi>S. Augustine</hi> also in his twelft Booke <hi>De ciuitate Dei</hi> makes mention of other of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Alexander</hi> to <hi>Olimpias</hi> his Mother about the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the Monarchies.</p>
   <p>Amongst the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Syria, Antiochus</hi> surnamed <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> writ many Bookes, and sent them into <hi>Iudea,</hi> about changing the Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Iewes</hi> into the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the <hi>Grecians;</hi> The principall heades of his Bookes may be found in the Bookes of <hi>Machabes</hi> and in <hi>Iosephus.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Romans,</hi> which of their <hi>Emperours</hi> did not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his fame by Letters? <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> besides many other things, writ his <hi>Commentaries</hi> after the example of <hi>Cyrus. Octauius,</hi> as <hi>Suetonius</hi> reportes, writ many <hi>Volumes, The historie of his owne life, Exhortations to Philosophie, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Verses, Epigrams, Tragedies</hi> and diuers other things; of whom I will only relate two <hi>Stories</hi> not impertinent to my purpose. He is reported to haue bene a very diligent searcher out of all such Bookes, as appertayned to the <hi>Roman-Ethnick-Religion.</hi> All the Bookes <hi>Fatidicorum,</hi> of <hi>Fortune-tellers,</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from approued Authors both of <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> he cast in the fire, to the number of two thousand: Onely he reserued the writings of the <hi>Sibills,</hi> but with that choise, as hee burnt all such of them as he thought to bee counterfeit. J relate this <hi>Story</hi> the rather, for that J thinke it were a good President for our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> to follow, to make a diligent search of all good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Authors; As for all Hereticall <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> slaunderous Libells and impertinent writings, to commit them to <hi>Vulcane:</hi> for one of the maine meanes of corrupting this people in point of <hi>Religion,</hi> proceeds from the free vse of reading of all kinde of writings without any restraint.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>The other <hi>Storie</hi> of <hi>Augustus</hi> is that famous <hi>Inscription</hi> of his, which he made to be set vp in the <hi>Altar</hi> of the <hi>Capitoll</hi> to our <hi>Sauiour Christ;</hi> of which <hi>Nicephorus</hi> makes mention; as also <hi>Suidas</hi> in the word <hi>Augustus. Caesar Augustus</hi> being proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the first <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> hauing done many great things and achiued great Glory and felicity; came to the <hi>Oracle</hi> of <hi>Apollo,</hi> &amp; offering vp a <hi>Heccatomb,</hi> which is of all other the greatest <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> demaunded of the <hi>Oracle,</hi> who should rule the <hi>Empire</hi> after his decease; receiuing no answere at all, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp an other Sacrifice, and asked with all, how it came to passe, that the <hi>Oracle</hi> that was wont to vse so many wordes, was now become so silent? The <hi>Oracle</hi> after a long pause, made this answere:
<q>
         <l>Me puer Hebraeus, Diuos, Deus ipse gubernans</l>
         <l>Cedere sede iubet, tristemque redire sub Orcum:</l>
         <l>Aris ergo dehinc tacitus abscedito nostris.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Emperour</hi> receiuing this answere, returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in the <hi>Capitoll</hi> the greatest <hi>Altar</hi> that was there, with this <hi>Inscription: Ara primogeniti Dei.</hi> Surely, our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus,</hi> in whose dayes our Blessed <hi>Sauiour Christ Iesus</hi> is come to a full and perfect aage: As hee was borne in the dayes of the other, studying nothing at all to know, who shall rule the Scepter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him (for God be praised, he is much more happie then was <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> in a Blessed <hi>Posterity</hi> of his owne) but indeauoring, that <hi>CHRIST</hi> his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> may euer Reigne in his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> hath consulted all the <hi>Oracles</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and hath found in them, that there is but one onely <hi>Altar</hi> to be erected to the onely Sonne of <hi>GOD,</hi> who is Blessed for euer; and therefore hath set himselfe and bestowed much paines to bid that Man of Sinne, <hi>cedere sede,</hi> and <hi>redire sub Orcum,</hi> that hath erected so many <hi>Altars</hi> Athenian-like, to vnknowne Gods, making more prayers and <hi>Supplications</hi> to supposed <hi>Saints,</hi> then euer the other did to Gods they knew not. But to returne, <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Caesar,</hi> that had so much wickednesse in him, had this
<pb facs="11"/>good in him, that hee writte many good Bookes. <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports, hee writ so many Bookes in <hi>Greeke,</hi> as that hee erected a Schoole of purpose in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> called after his owne name, and caused his Bookes to be read yeerely in it: He writ in <hi>Latine</hi> likewise <hi>43.</hi> Bookes, contayning a Historie from the murther of <hi>Caesar</hi> to his owne time. There would bee no ende of the reporting of the writings of the Heathen <hi>Emperours.</hi> That one example of <hi>Constantine</hi> amongst the Christian <hi>Emperors</hi> shall suffice: <hi>Eusebius</hi> hath written curiously his Life, and is not sparing to report of his Learning; How many <hi>Orations</hi> and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses he made, exhorting his Subiects and seruants to a good and godly life; How many nights hee passed without sleepe in Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Diuinitie;</hi> His Speeches in the beginning and ende of the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Nice;</hi> That fomous <hi>Oration, Ad Sanctorum coetum,</hi> pronounced in <hi>Latine</hi> by him Selfe, after translated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Greeke by diuerse, doe shew, how much Glory hee gayned by Letters.</p>
   <p>From these great Monarches abroad, giue mee leaue a little, to descend to our owne <hi>Kings</hi> at home. <hi>Alphredus</hi> King of the <hi>West-Saxons,</hi> translated <hi>Paulus Orosius, S. Gregorie De pastorali cura,</hi> and his <hi>Dialogues</hi> into the <hi>English</hi> tongue: He translated likewise <hi>Beda</hi> of the Actes of the <hi>English,</hi> and <hi>Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius de consolatione Philosophiae, Dauids Psalmes,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things: Hee writ besides a Booke of Lawes and <hi>Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> against wicked Judges: Hee writ the sayings of <hi>Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and a singular Booke of the fortune of <hi>Kings,</hi> a collection of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> and a <hi>Manuel</hi> of <hi>Meditations.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ethelstanus</hi> (or <hi>Adelstan,</hi> as our <hi>Stories</hi> call him) <hi>Rex Anglorum,</hi> as <hi>Baleus</hi> calls him, caused to be translated the Bible out of <hi>Hebrew</hi> into <hi>Saxon,</hi> and writ himselfe a Booke of <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> the Constitutions of the <hi>Cleargie,</hi> corrected many olde Lawes, and made many new.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>King Edgar</hi> writ to the Cleargie of <hi>England</hi> certaine <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions</hi> and <hi>Lawes,</hi> and other things.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Henrie</hi> the first, the yongest Sonne of the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> was
<pb facs="12"/>brought vp in the <hi>Vniuersitie</hi> of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> and excelled so in the knowledge of all Liberall Arts and Sciences, that to this day he doeth retaine the name of <hi>Beau-Clerke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Achaius</hi> King of the <hi>Scots,</hi> writ of the Acts of all his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors. And <hi>Kenethus</hi> King of the <hi>Scots,</hi> writ a huge <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume</hi> of all the Scottish <hi>Lawes,</hi> and like an other <hi>Iustinian,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them into a <hi>Compendium.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Iames</hi> the first writ diuers Bookes both in <hi>English</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Ʋerse: He writ also, as <hi>Baleus</hi> saith, <hi>De vxore futura.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight writ of the <hi>Institution</hi> of a <hi>Christian man,</hi> and of the <hi>Institution</hi> of youth: Hee writ also a defence of the <hi>7. Sacraments</hi> against <hi>Martin Luther;</hi> for which hee was much magnified of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and all that partie; Jnsomuch as hee was stiled with the Title of <hi>Defensor fidei</hi> for that worke: And trewly it fell out well for the <hi>King,</hi> that hee writ a Booke on the <hi>Popes</hi> side; for otherwise, he should haue them raile on him for his writings as freely, as they reuile him for his Actions. For he writ two Bookes after that; the one <hi>De auctoritate Regia contra Papam;</hi> the other <hi>Sententia de Concilio Mantuano,</hi> as well written for the Stile and Argument, as the other is: But because they seeme to breath an other breath, there is no Trumpet sounded in their praise.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt, though his dayes were so short, as he could not giue full proofe of those singular parts that were in him; yet hee wrote diuers <hi>Epistles</hi> and <hi>Orations</hi> both in <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine:</hi> He wrote a Treatise <hi>De fide</hi> to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Somerset:</hi> He wrote a History of his owne time, which are all yet extant vnder his owne hand, in the <hi>Kings Library;</hi> as M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>Patrick Young,</hi> his Maiesties learned and Industrious <hi>Bibliothecarius,</hi> hath shewed mee; And which is not to bee forgotten, so diligent a hearer of <hi>Sermons</hi> was that sweet <hi>Prince,</hi> that the notes of the most of the <hi>Sermons</hi> he heard, are yet to bee seene vnder his owne hand with the <hi>Preachers</hi> name, the time, and the place, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumstances.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> our late <hi>Soueraigne</hi> of blessed memory,
<pb facs="12"/>translated the prayers of <hi>Queene Katherine</hi> into <hi>Latine, French,</hi> and <hi>Italian:</hi> Shee wrote also a Century of <hi>Sentences,</hi> and dedicated them to her <hi>Father.</hi> J haue heard of her Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Salustius;</hi> but I neuer saw it: And there are yet fresh in our memories the <hi>Orations</hi> she made in both the <hi>Vniuersities</hi> in <hi>Latine;</hi> her entertayning of <hi>Embassadors</hi> in diuers Languages; her excellent Speaches in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereof diuers are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant at this day in Print. And to come a little neerer his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie;</hi> The <hi>Kings Father</hi> translated <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> into <hi>English;</hi> And the <hi>Queene</hi> his <hi>Maiesties Mother,</hi> wrote a Booke of Ʋerses in <hi>French</hi> of the <hi>Institution</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> all with her owne hand, wrought the Couer of it with her needle, and is now of his <hi>Maiestie</hi> esteemed as a most pretious <hi>Iewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore since wee are compassed about with such a Clowd of <hi>Witnesses</hi> (albeit these are but a little handfull in comparison of the infinite multitude, that might be produced,) Since we haue the examples of all the Mightie-men of the <hi>World,</hi> euen from the beginning thereof vnto this day; who haue striuen as much to get a Name for their writings, as fame for their doings; haue affected as much to be counted Learned as Ʋictorious; and to be reputed of, as much for their wise Sayings, as for their worthy Deeds; Why should it bee thought a thing strange in this time, that his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie,</hi> whom <hi>GOD</hi> hath adorned with as many rare perfections of Nature and Arte, as euer he did any that wee read of, (I except such as were Diuinely inspired) should lend the world a few leaues out of the large <hi>Volumes</hi> of his <hi>Learning?</hi> J commend the wisedome of our Aduersaries, who hauing assayed all meanes, the wit of man is able to inuent, to incline his <hi>Maiestie</hi> to like of their partie; and finding by all their Tricks, they haue got no ground, would at last put his <hi>Maiestie</hi> to silence, and gaine thus much of him, at least; that since he will doe nothing for them; yet that he would say nothing against them. Therefore they cry out against his <hi>Maiesties</hi> writing, and vpbrayd him more for that hee doeth write, then they doe for any thing that hee hath written: Jt is ynough to wonder at, that <hi>Rex scribit.</hi> These people are wise in
<pb facs="13"/>their generation, and haue learned by long experience; that as the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>CHRIST</hi> is the Gospel of peace, so it hath bene from the beginning spread more by the Pennes of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> then by the power of <hi>Princes;</hi> more propagated by the sweet writings of the ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> then it could bee suppressed by the seuere Edicts of <hi>Emperours;</hi> and of late, their Kingdome hath bene more shaken by a poore Monke, then it hath bene able to recouer by the helpe of Mighty <hi>Monarches.</hi> Therefore since the writings of poore Schollers haue so raised the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and so discouered the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of Jniquitie; they do well to feare what may follow vpon the Writings of so great a <hi>King.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>They liue securely from bleeding by his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Sword; but they are not safe from being blasted by the breath of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Bookes. Jf they could bring it about therefore, to calme and quiet his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Spirit from working vpon them that way; as they see his <hi>Maiesties</hi> sweetnesse to bee farre from drawing of their bloods the other way, they would deeme it a greater Conquest, then all the conuersions of the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West-Indies</hi> they tell vs so many tales of: For they looke vpon his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Bookes, as men looke vpon <hi>Blasing-Starres,</hi> with amazement, fearing they portend some strange thing, and bring with them a certaine Influence to worke great change and alteration in the world: Neither is their expectation herein deceiued; for we haue seene with our eyes, the Operation of his <hi>Maiesties Workes</hi> in the Consciences of their men so farre, as from their highest <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claue</hi> to their lowest <hi>Cells,</hi> there haue bene, that haue bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted by them; and that in such number, as wee want rather meanes to maintaine them, then they minds to come to vs. But to conclude this point, that <hi>Kings</hi> may write; Giue mee leaue to offer you this Meditation.</p>
   <p>How many are the wayes that men doe inuent to perpetuate their Memorie! Insomuch, that mortall-men haue made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues Gods, when they were dead, that they might be adored, as if they were aliue. Wherein, is the <hi>Impetus</hi> of Nature so strong,
<pb facs="13"/>as in the affection that propogates to <hi>Posteritie?</hi> Wherefore serue Pictures, but to continue our features? Why doe men bestow so much cost in sumptuous Buildings, but to leaue a <hi>Monument</hi> of their Magnificence? To what end doe we erect Holy-houses and Hospitalls, but to possesse mens mindes with the Deuotion of our Soules? And shall wee blesse a <hi>King,</hi> when wee behold him in his <hi>Posteritie!</hi> Shall wee admire his features, when wee contemplate them in his <hi>Pictures!</hi> Shall we wonder at his <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence,</hi> when we gaze vpon it in his stately <hi>Edifices!</hi> and may wee not as well bee rauished, when wee see his sharpe Wit, his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Judgement, his infinite Memorie, his Excellent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in his admirable <hi>Writings?</hi> Certainely it is a peruersnes to esteeme a man least, for that whereby hee liues the longest; to value him more for the outward worke of his hand, then for the inward operation of his minde; to esteeme him more for that which instructs but little, then for that which shall edifie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. What now remaines of <hi>Caesar</hi> so famous as his <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries?</hi> What of <hi>Cicero,</hi> as his <hi>Orations?</hi> How comes <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> to be of more authoritie then <hi>Alexander? Seneca,</hi> then <hi>Nero?</hi> The Triumphes and Ʋictories of the one are vanished; the Ʋertues of the other remaine in their perfect vigour: And though all other <hi>Monuments</hi> by time consume and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; yet these by time, gaine strength and get authoritie; and euer the more ancient, the more Excellent.</p>
   <p>Hauing now deliuered my opinion, that J thinke it neither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull nor inconuenient for a <hi>King</hi> to write, but that he hath the Liberty that other men haue, if hee can get the leysure; to shew his abilities for the present, to perpetuate his Memory to <hi>Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> to aduance his praise before his owne People, and gaine Glory from others; but especially to giue <hi>Glory</hi> vnto <hi>GOD.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>J will craue leaue to descend to an other Consideration: for it may be, there will not be so much fault found with a <hi>King</hi> for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as for the matter or Subiect whereof he treates: For <hi>Persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of their eminent Degree and <hi>State,</hi> must not spend their paines on poore purposes; nor write so much to try their witts
<pb facs="14"/>on triuiall thinges, as to winne themselues Honor by the Excellency of their subiect. Jndeed, if I were worthy to aduise a <hi>King,</hi> hee should meddle very sparingly, and but vpon important Causes, with <hi>Polemicalls:</hi> Hee should not often fight but in the field; for put the case a <hi>King</hi> writ neuer so modestly, that there be not in a whole Booke one word <hi>ad hominem,</hi> nor any touch of his Aduersary in any personall infirmity; yet J know not how it comes to passe, that in all Controuersies, a solide answere to an argument, is a very sufficient occasion to make an Aduersary wonderfull angrie. And so long as there are diuersity of Opinions, there will neuer want matter for Confutations. And in these Replications the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of a <hi>King</hi> is more exposed and lyes more open, then the person of a poore Scholler can doe; for as he is a farre greater marke, so he may farre more easily be hit: And though they misse him and can hit vpon nothing iustly to bee reprehended in him; yet they doe thinke it <hi>Operaepretium,</hi> to make a Scarre in the face of a <hi>King;</hi> Whereas on the contrary, if a <hi>King</hi> doe write of <hi>Piety</hi> or <hi>Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> compile a <hi>History,</hi> giue <hi>Precepts</hi> of <hi>Policy,</hi> handle Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, or treate of some rare Experiences of Nature; wee doe in these things commend his Iudgement, admire his parts without any euill cogitation against his Person. There can hardly be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a more viue Example in this case, then is to be found in the <hi>Writings</hi> of his <hi>Maiestie.</hi> When the <hi>King</hi> had published his <hi>Basilicon-Doron,</hi> a Booke so singularly penned; that a Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granat is not so full of kernells, as that is of Excellent <hi>Counsells:</hi> What applause had it in the world? How did it inflame mens minds to a loue and admiration of his <hi>Maiestie</hi> beyond measure; Insomuch that comming out iust at the time his <hi>Maiestie</hi> came in, it made the hearts of all his people as one Man, as much to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him for Religion and Learning, as to obey him for Title and Authoritie; and gaue vs then a taste, or rather the first fruits, of that we haue since reaped a plentifull Haruest of, by his <hi>Maiesties</hi> most prudent and Gracious Gouernment ouer vs. The like I may say of his <hi>Maiesties Demonologie;</hi> a rare peece for many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Experiments, both in <hi>Diuinitie</hi> and Naturall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophie.
<pb facs="14"/>Jn these, there was nothing heard of, but Sunne-shine and faire-weather; euery countenance sweet and smiling vpon them: But as soone as his <hi>Maiestie</hi> dealt against the <hi>Pope,</hi> tooke the <hi>Cardinall</hi> in hand, made the world see the vsurped power of the one, and Sophistry of the other; Good Lord, what a stirre we had; what roaring of the wilde Bulls of <hi>Basan,</hi> what a commotion in euery Countrey; Jnsomuch, that I thinke, there is scarce a People, Language or Nation in <hi>Christendome,</hi> out of which his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath not receiued some answere or other; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by way of resuting, or at least by rayling: So that, had not the <hi>King</hi> contemned and made himselfe sport and recreation by such kinde of Reuelling, rather then bene mooued to passion; It could not haue bene but a marueilous perturbation to a <hi>Prince</hi> of so exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site sense and vnderstanding. But what of all this? Shall wee wish his <hi>Maiestie</hi> had not fought with beasts at <hi>Ephesus,</hi> stopped the roaring of the <hi>Bull,</hi> nor encountered the <hi>Cardinall?</hi> Trewly when J thinke vpon the wonderfull abuses, and Hyperbolicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath receiued from these men; I am some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of that minde: But when on the other side, J consider his <hi>Maiesties</hi> zeale for to maintaine the cause of <hi>GOD</hi> and Right of <hi>Kings;</hi> his singular dexteritie to doe it; the blessing of <hi>GOD</hi> that hath followed vpon his so doing of it; I cannot but change my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and bee of another minde. And the better to induce you to bee of my minde; I will make vnto you a trew Relation of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> entering into this businesse, and then leaue it to your consideration; whether there were not a <hi>Diuine hand,</hi> that led his into it, or no. Jt is the Speach of our Blessed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> that there is nothing hid, that shall not be knowne; and what is spoken in darkenesse, shall be heard in the Light: This his <hi>Maiestie</hi> as himselfe confesseth, found trew in the comming foorth of one of his Bookes; and I thinke it may bee found as trew in the comming foorth of some other of them. For after the <hi>Pope</hi> had put forth his <hi>Breues,</hi> and the <hi>Cardinall</hi> had sent his Letters to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priest; the one to enioyne the People not to take the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> affirming they could not take it with safety of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation;
<pb facs="15"/>the other to reproue the Arch-priest for that hee had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, and to draw him to a penitencie for so foule a Lapse: His <hi>Maiestie</hi> like as became a Prudent and a Religious <hi>Prince,</hi> thought it not meete, that these things should passe for current, but that it was expedient his People should know, that the taking of this <hi>Oath</hi> was so farre from endangering their Soules, as that it intended nothing but ciuill Obedience, and without touching any point of their conscience, made the <hi>State</hi> secure of their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. To performe this worke, his <hi>Maiestie</hi> thought the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Winchester</hi> that then was, a very fit man, both for his sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Learning, as for that he had long laboured in an Argument not much of a diuers nature from this: Whereupon his <hi>Maiestie</hi> calling for penne and incke, to giue my L. of <hi>Winchester</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, how and in what maner to proceed in this Argument, I know not how it came to passe; but it fell out trew, that the <hi>Poet</hi> saith,
<q>
         <l>— Amphora coepit</l>
         <l>Institui, currente rota, post vrceus exit.</l>
      </q> For the <hi>Kings</hi> Penne ranne so fast, that in the compasse of sixe dayes, his <hi>Maiestie</hi> had accomplished that, which hee now calleth his <hi>Apologie;</hi> which when my Lord of <hi>Canterburie</hi> that then was, and my Lord of <hi>Elie</hi> had perused, being indeed deliuered by his <hi>Maiestie</hi> but as briefe Notes, and in the nature of a Minute to bee explicated by the <hi>Bishop</hi> in a larger Ʋolume; yet they thought it so sufficient an Answere both to the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> as there needed no other: Whereupon his <hi>Maiestie</hi> was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, to giue way to the comming of it foorth, but was pleased to conceale his Name: And so haue wee the <hi>Apologie</hi> beyond his <hi>Maiesties</hi> owne purpose or determination.</p>
   <p>After that the <hi>Apologie</hi> was out, his <hi>Maiestie</hi> diuerse times would bee pleased to vtter a Resolution of his; that if the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Cardinall</hi> would not rest in his answere, and sit downe by it; take the <hi>Oath</hi> as it was intended for a point of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and Ciuill Obedience; Hee would publish the <hi>Apologie</hi> in his owne name with a <hi>Preface</hi> to all the <hi>Princes</hi> in <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>wherein hee would publish such a Confession of his Faith, perswade the <hi>Princes</hi> so to vindicate their owne Power, discouer so much of the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of Jniquitie vnto them; as the <hi>Popes Bulles</hi> should pull in their hornes, and himselfe wish he had neuer medled with this matter. The <hi>Cardinall</hi> contending against the <hi>Apologie,</hi> his <hi>Maiestie</hi> confirmed his Resolution, and with the like Celerity, in the compasse of one weeke, wrote his <hi>Monitory-Preface:</hi> for as <hi>Hirtius</hi> said of <hi>Caesars Comentaries, Qua foelicitate</hi> they were done, let others iudge; but <hi>Qua celeritate,</hi> J can tell: And being so written, published it and the <hi>Apologie</hi> in his owne Name; and made good his word, sent it to the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> and all the <hi>Kings</hi> and free <hi>Princes</hi> in <hi>Christendome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now hauing made this Relation, wherein J haue deliuered nothing but trewth; Let me offer vnto you some few things worthy Consideration.</p>
   <p>First, that vpon the comming foorth of that Booke, there were no <hi>States,</hi> that disauowed the Doctrine of it in that point of the <hi>Kings</hi> power; And the <hi>Venetians</hi> mainetained it in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and put it in Execution; The <hi>Sorbons</hi> maintained it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in <hi>France.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, their owne writers, that opposed it, so ouerlashed, as they were corrected and castigated of men of their owne Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Becanus</hi> his Booke corrected by the <hi>Cardinalles</hi> of <hi>Rome; Bellarmines</hi> Booke burnt in <hi>Paris; Suarez</hi> his Answere burnt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in <hi>France.</hi> As for the Raylers, I leaue them to God his Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whose hand hath bene vpon the most of them.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Confession of faith, hath bene so gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally approued, as it hath conuerted many of their partie: And had it not bene (as J haue bene informed by diuerse) for the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> many more would easily haue bene induced, to subscribe to all in that <hi>Preface.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Fourthly, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> haue by his <hi>Maiesties Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,</hi> had a more cleare insight, and a more perfect discouery into the Iniury offered them by the <hi>Pope</hi> in the point of their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Power, then euer they had; Jnsomuch, as that point was
<pb facs="16"/>neuer so throughly disputed in <hi>Christendome,</hi> as it hath bene by the occasion of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Booke.</p>
   <p>Fiftly and lastly, for the point of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> I haue heard many confesse, that they neuer saw so much light giuen to that <hi>Mysterie,</hi> neuer descerned so much trewth by the vniforme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Text, and strength of Interpretation of places, as they haue done by his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Booke. So that, though Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies be fitter subiects for Schollers ordinarily, then for <hi>Kings;</hi> Yet when there was such a necessitie in vndertaking, and such a successe being performed; I leaue it to the world to iudge, whether there were not a speciall hand of <hi>GOD</hi> in it, or no. Now since I haue begunne with this point of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> J will make bolde to proceed a little with his <hi>Maiesties Paraphrase</hi> vpon the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> wherein that Treatise of <hi>Antichrist</hi> is principally grounded.</p>
   <p>His <hi>Maiesties</hi> singular vnderstanding in all points of good Learning is not vnknowne: But yet aboue all other things, <hi>GOD</hi> hath giuen him an vnderstanding Heart in the Interpretation of that <hi>Booke,</hi> beyond the measure of other men: For this <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase,</hi> that leades the way to all the rest of his <hi>Maiesties Workes,</hi> was written by his <hi>Maiestie</hi> before hee was twenty yeeres of aage; and therefore iustly in this Ʋolume hath the first place, the rest following in order according to the time of their first penning. Anciently <hi>Kings</hi> drempt dreames, and saw visions; and <hi>Prophets</hi> expounded them: So with <hi>King Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Ioseph</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> So with <hi>Nabuchodonosor</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> in <hi>Babylon.</hi> Jn this aage, <hi>Prophets</hi> haue written Ʋisions, and <hi>Kings</hi> haue expounded them. <hi>GOD</hi> raised vp <hi>Prophets</hi> to deliuer his People from a temporall captiuitie in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> by the Jnterpretation of the one; And <hi>GOD</hi> hath in this aage stirred vp <hi>Kings</hi> to deliuer his People from a Spirituall <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> by the Interpretation of the other. It is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruable thing, that <hi>GOD</hi> neuer made his People any great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, but he added vnto his promise a famous <hi>Prophecie.</hi> Three great promises we reade of, that runne through all the Scriptures.
<pb facs="16"/>The first of the <hi>Messiah;</hi> the second of the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> the third of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of Heauen: To these three promises, are reduced all the <hi>Prophecies.</hi> Of the promise of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> prophecied all the <hi>Prophets</hi> from the fall of the first <hi>Adam,</hi> to the comming of the second: Of the promise of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> prophecied <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Ioseph,</hi> and the rest, from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to the possessing of it by <hi>Iosuah</hi> and the children of <hi>Israel:</hi> Of the promise of the Kingdome of Heauen, made by our <hi>Sauiour CHRIST',</hi> prophecied the <hi>Apostles;</hi> principally <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in the Reuelation. Now though all were to lay hold on the promises; yet few were able to vnderstand the <hi>Prophecies.</hi> And surely, though all the people of <hi>GOD</hi> are to lay hold on the promises of that Glorious <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> described in that Booke; yet few are able to vnderstand the <hi>Prophecies</hi> therein contained, comprehending in them a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>History</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> euen from the destruction of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> till the consummation of the whole world. Yet this I thinke, I may safely say; That <hi>Kings</hi> haue a kinde of interest in that Booke beyond any other: for as the execution of the most part of the <hi>Prophecies</hi> of that Booke is committed vnto them; So it may be, that the Interpretation of it, may more happily be made by them: And since they are the principall Instruments, that <hi>GOD</hi> hath described in that Booke to destroy the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> to consume his State and Citie; I see not, but it may stand with the Wisedome of <hi>GOD,</hi> to inspire their heart to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it; into whose handes hee hath put it to excute, vntill the <hi>LORD</hi> shall consume both him and it with the Spirit of his mouth, and shall abolish it with the brightnesse of his comming: For from the day that <hi>S. Iohn</hi> writ the Booke to this present houre; I doe not thinke that euer any <hi>King</hi> tooke such paines, or was so perfect in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> as his <hi>Maiestie</hi> is; which will easily appeare by this <hi>Paraphrase,</hi> by his <hi>Maiesties Meditation</hi> on the <hi>20.</hi> Chap. and his <hi>Monitorie Preface.</hi> Jt was my purpose to haue past through all his <hi>Maiesties</hi> Books; to haue expressed the Argument and the occasion of their writing; But I find by that J haue already
<pb facs="17"/>said, I should be ouer tedious vnto you. This therefore in generall; They are all worthy of a <hi>King,</hi> and to be kept to Posterity: For if <hi>Ouid</hi> could imagine, that no time should eate out the memory of his <hi>Metamorphoseis,</hi> which were but fictions; J hope no time shall see an end of these Books, that carry in them so much diuine trewth and light. And as in this first worke of the <hi>Paraphrase,</hi> his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath shewed his <hi>Piety;</hi> So in this last <hi>Pearle</hi> (I meane <hi>his Maiesties Speach in the Starr-Chamber</hi>) his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath shewed his <hi>Policy:</hi> The first sheweth, hee vnderstands the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>GOD;</hi> this last, that hee as well apprehends the State of his <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in this <hi>World:</hi> The first sheweth him to haue a large Portion in that of Heauen; and this last sheweth him to haue a great Power and experience in these <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> hee hath on earth. Therefore, let these men, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light so much in Detraction and to vilify him, whom <hi>GOD</hi> hath exalted; and to shed his blood, whose Soule <hi>GOD</hi> hath bound vp in the Bundle of life; Let them, J say, write what euer the Subtilty of the olde <hi>Serpent</hi> can put into their heads, or the Malice of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> infuse into their hearts; Let them speake, what the poyson of <hi>Aspes</hi> is able to put into their lippes; they are not all able to make his <hi>Maiestie</hi> to appeare lesse then he is, nor to shew, that euer they had of theirs a <hi>King</hi> so accomplished. It is trew, that wee haue not had many <hi>Kings</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome</hi> of our Profession: But for those we haue had, this <hi>Iland</hi> of ours neuer saw the like, either for partes of Nature, giftes of Learning or Graces of <hi>Piety.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The little time of life, that God lent to <hi>King Edward,</hi> must needs lessen his prayses; But neuer did there appeare beginnings of more rare perfection, then in him.</p>
   <p>The length of <hi>Queene Elizabeths</hi> dayes, together with the felicity of her time, was not only a Glory to her owne People, but a wonderment to the World, euen our Aduersaries, as <hi>Moses</hi> said, being <hi>Iudges.</hi> And praysed be <hi>GOD,</hi> the present time passeth a long with the like felicity and much more Securitie: for let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a little, for the Glory of <hi>GOD</hi> and encouragement of his
<pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>Maiestie,</hi> to goe on in his happie Course begunne, the Blessings of <hi>GOD</hi> we receiue by him; And then let our Aduersaries tell vs, whether we be a miserable People or no, as some of late haue gone about to perswade vs. Neither doe J stand in feare of any mans reprehension; for J will speake nothing but trewth, and I haue my <hi>President</hi> from <hi>GOD</hi> his owne Booke; wherein the good Actes of euery good <hi>King</hi> are to their eternall praises trewly recounted.</p>
   <p>First to beginne with <hi>Religion,</hi> as the Generall to the Armie: Of all Gods Blessings wee haue it without any alteration or change contynued vnto vs. His <hi>Maiesties</hi> first Care was for the Confirmation of the Gospell: for at his <hi>Maiesties</hi> first comming in; who knowes not the endeauours of men, to haue made a change, either to the <hi>Papists,</hi> or to the <hi>Puritanes?</hi> His <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie</hi> therefore, to quiet the <hi>State</hi> and Peace of the Church, called a Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court;</hi> where passing ouer the one, as being neuer in his heart to giue the least way vnto; He so tempered the other, as the Harmony hath bene the better euer since.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Religion</hi> thus ratified; His <hi>Maiesties</hi> next Care was for the Translation of the <hi>Bible,</hi> it being the ground of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: His <hi>Maiestie</hi> was desirous his People should haue it in as much perfection, as the Jndustrie and Labors of the best Learned were able to afford it them.</p>
   <p>Hauing done what was necessary for the Spirituall part of the Church, his <hi>Maiestie</hi> tooke into consideration the Temporal State thereof: No sooner came the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but finding what spoile had bene made of the Lands thereof in the tyme of his <hi>Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors,</hi> by a libertie they had to take the Landes of the Church for a longer Terme then others could doe; Cut himselfe off from that libertie, and equalled himselfe to a common person in the taking of any State in the Churches Landes.</p>
   <p>When his <hi>Maiestie</hi> had done this in <hi>England,</hi> he looked backe into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and reforming the State of the Church there, as farre as in his <hi>Princely-Wisedome</hi> he thought conuenient for the time; restored the <hi>Bishops</hi> there, as to their Spirituall <hi>Keies;</hi>
      <pb facs="18"/>so to their temporall <hi>Estates,</hi> though it were to the great losse and dammage of his owne Reuennue and <hi>Crowne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>From <hi>Scotland</hi> his <hi>Maiestie</hi> came to <hi>Ireland,</hi> that forlorne <hi>Kingdome</hi> both for Temporall and Spiritual estate, till be looked into it: There his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath reduced the <hi>Bishoppricks,</hi> not only to their old Rents; but added vnto them many new <hi>Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues;</hi> so that many places there are answerable to the best Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings here: Neither hath his Care bene onely on these high places of the Church, but hath descended to the lowest in the same, hauing both protected the <hi>Benefices</hi> from being raysed to any higher Taxe, and hindred all courses, that might giue his Cleargie mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station or trouble.</p>
   <p>His <hi>Maiesties Bountie</hi> hath not bene wanting to Colledges and Hospitalls, hauing parted with his owne Tenures, to giue them power of larger Indowments; whereby there hath bene works of more sumptuousnes and cost done in his <hi>Maiesties</hi> time, then there hath bene in any one aage before.</p>
   <p>J may not forget one thing, that since his <hi>Maiesties</hi> comming to this <hi>Crowne,</hi> he hath neuer put into his Coffers the meane prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitts of any Ecclesiasticall liuing, but hath bene a <hi>Fidus-Deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarius,</hi> and euer giuen them to the next Jncumbent.</p>
   <p>Let me descend a little from these workes of <hi>Piety</hi> to <hi>Peace.</hi> Neuer hath there bene so vniuersall a Peace in <hi>Christendome</hi> since the time of our <hi>Sauiour Christ,</hi> as in these his Dayes: And I dare say, as much, if not more, by the procurement of his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie,</hi> then by any other earthly meanes in this world. A <hi>Peace</hi> (to let forraigne partes passe) so entertayned at home; that in his <hi>Maiesties</hi> three <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> apt enough by constitution, and not vnaccustomed by practise to be at variance, there hath bene no Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill dissension at all. With <hi>Peace GOD</hi> hath giuen vs Plentie: So that, if Peace and Plenty haue not made vs too too wanton, I know not what wee want. Neither is there any crying out for lacke of <hi>Iustice</hi> in our <hi>Courtes;</hi> for neuer was there Iustice ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred with more liberty from the <hi>King,</hi> nor more vprightnes from the Judges; And yet in the free dispensation of <hi>Iustice,
<pb facs="18"/>Mercie</hi> did neuer more triumph. If this bee to bee miserable, J know not what on earth they call Happinesse: <hi>GOD</hi> continue these still vnto vs; and then, let them call Happinesse, what they please.</p>
   <p>But I know wherefore all is miserable; because there is no more Mercy shewed to their <hi>Catholiks.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>J will put it as a <hi>Crowne</hi> vpon all his <hi>Maiesties Mercies:</hi> There was neuer <hi>King,</hi> that had so great a cause giuen him, that euer tooke so little bloode, extending his Mercy to all, that were not personall workers in that <hi>Powder-Plot:</hi> And before that you had hatched that Monster, neither was the person or purse of any your reputed Catholicks touched. And since that time, you may doe well to complaine of your Miseries; but the Church and Comonwealth both, doe trauaile and groane vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of your disobedience: But the worst J wish you, is, that at length by his <hi>Maiesties</hi> long <hi>Patience,</hi> you may bee drawne to Repentance; for as we are come out from you, lest we should bee partakers of your plagues; so we pray for you, that you may come in to vs, that you may be participants of our felicities.</p>
   <p>To Conclude this <hi>Preface: GOD</hi> hath giuen vs a <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>GOD</hi> aboue all things gaue <hi>Solomon</hi> Wisedome; Wisedome brought him peace; Peace brought him Riches; Riches gaue him Glory. His wisedome appeared in his wordes and <hi>Workes:</hi> his Peace, he preserued by the power of his Army: His riches he ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, as by his Reuennue, so by the Trade of his Nauie: His Glory did accrue from them all. Now, as in these, <hi>GOD</hi> exalted him beyond all the <hi>Kings</hi> that euer were, or should be after him; So had he in other things Humiliations not farre behind the proportion of his Exaltations; the fearefullest fall, that the Scripture affords an Example of; the most vnchast life and immoderate excesse of <hi>Women,</hi> that we read of; the weakest Posterity for Wisedome and Gouernment, that we finde in all the Line of his Succession. <hi>GOD</hi> would haue it so, that he should no more be set out, as a Type of the <hi>Glory</hi> of his owne <hi>Sonne</hi> in the felicity of his State one way, then he would haue him proposed as a patterne of Humane
<pb facs="19"/>frailty an other way. Therefore, though we may not approach him in his Typicall State; yet <hi>GODS</hi> Name be blessed, that hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs to goe farre beyond him in his personall Condition: For we haue already, blessed be <hi>GOD,</hi> seene the Constancie and perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his <hi>Maiesty</hi> in his Holy Profession, without any <hi>Eclipse</hi> or Shaddow of change, longer then we are well able to deduce the whole life and reigne of <hi>Solomon.</hi> We haue not the Daughter of <hi>Pharao</hi> an Idolatrous <hi>King;</hi> nor feare we strange women to steale away his heart from the Seruice of <hi>GOD:</hi> But a <hi>Queene,</hi> as of a <hi>Royall,</hi> so of a Religious Stocke, professing the Gospell of <hi>Christ</hi> with him; A <hi>Mirrour</hi> of trew Modestie, a <hi>Queene</hi> of Bounty, both beloued and admired of all his People: A <hi>Posterity</hi> that we need not feare for folly in the one Sexe, nor for leuitie in the other; Both which made <hi>Solomon</hi> speake so much, (as the <hi>Iewes</hi> say) in his <hi>Prouerbes,</hi> of a foolish sonne, because his owne was not wise, and of wanton Women, because he feared the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his owne Daughters. But <hi>GOD</hi> hath left his <hi>Maiestie</hi> a <hi>Sonne;</hi> a <hi>Prince,</hi> as in outward <hi>Liniaments,</hi> so in inward <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments,</hi> (I need say no more) an <hi>Alter-Idem,</hi> a second-Selfe; A <hi>Daughter,</hi> a <hi>Princesse</hi> of that Piety, singular vertue and Modestie; as makes her both beloued at home and admired abroad. J haue done: Only I desire the <hi>Readers</hi> of these <hi>Workes,</hi> to pray to <hi>GOD,</hi> that as he hath so farre aduanced vs, as to bestowe vpon vs, with the Heauenly Treasures of his trewth, the riches of his earthly <hi>Iewels</hi> in so <hi>Sacred</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> so admired a <hi>Queene,</hi> so hopefull a <hi>Prince,</hi> so vertuous a <hi>Princes;</hi> He would for his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies sake, for his Sonnes sake, continue this the Light of his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance vpon vs in them and their <hi>Posterity,</hi> till the comming of that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which neuer shall haue end. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, IA. WINTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>