<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all true hearted English men
dwelling in their native soile.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122422_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69292</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7751</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122422</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all true hearted English men
dwelling in their native soile.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A record of some worthy proceedings: in the honourable, wise, and faithfull Howse of Commons in the late Parliament</title>
                 <author>England and Wales, Parliament, House of Commons</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all true hearted English men
dwelling in their native soile.</head>
   <p>HOwsoever (my deare country-men) it is mine
hap to abide on this side the seas; yet I cannot
but hearken after the prosperitie of my gracious
Soveraigne, &amp; naturall countrey, especially in the
Parliament time. I am not (indeed) in any such e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
place▪ as where I may be sure to have a
perfect relation of all remarkeable affaires: yet by
my diligent indevour, I obteyne (in time) more
probable intelligence, than many of you doe. Of
which the love of my countrey compelleth to make
some present vse, occasioned by a Publication (for
not one word thereof is in the Kings name) dated
31. December last. Wherein the worthiest house of
Commons that ever was, is covertly traduced for
spending long time, and great charges, and yet
failing an earnest expectation of a good conclusion
for the Ease, and Freedome of his Maiesties sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.
I could not therefore but indevour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
(as I may) the heart-burning which (I feare)
that publication may occasion between the King
and his Commons, and 2. to make it appeare that
no house of Commons had ever a greater zeale for
the ease &amp; freedome of the subiects than the late
house had. The former, by demonstrating that the
sayd covert imputation is not the Kings, but the
pen-mans. For whereas Proclamations (in deed)
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
speake in the first person, as thus, Our subjects;
&amp;, We are resolved, that publication speaketh in
the third person thus, His Maiesties subiects; &amp;,
His Maiestie is resolved. Therefore it was not
penned by his Maiestie. Againe, How can close
suggesting the said imputation to be cause of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving
the Parliament agree with that which is
expresley said, That his Maiesty, for many good
considerations knowne to himselfe determined to
dissolve, &amp;c? Doth not this shew, that the over
large preamble of that publication is the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,
&amp; onely the body thereof was by the Kings
direction? Moreover, In a Proclamation dated
24. September last, his Majesty findeth fault
with former proclamations, in regard of their
penning. Which sheweth, that, when his Majesty
hath signified his mind touching the substance of a
proclamation; he doth not alwayes review the
penning thereof. Therfore it may be supposed, that
he did not peruse the penning of the publication.
So that I think it may be well concluded, that
the said imputation is not the Kings, but the
pen-mans.</p>
   <p>As for the Zeale of the commons in parliament
for the ease, &amp; freedome of the subjects, let that
appeare by that which is here published. Onely I
suppose it not amisse to remember, that in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
session of the late parliament, there passed
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
these billes in the house of commons. 1. An act
for the better observing and keeping holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
day, or Sunday. 2. An act against such, as
cōming to church, doe refuse to receive the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the Lords supper. 3. An act for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding
of a learned, &amp; godly Ministery. and 4.
An act to inable suspended, and deprived Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
to sue, &amp; prosecute their appeales. I remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
these, because that worthy Knight, or burgisse
(whose speach is here recorded) doth not speak
of them; Intending (belike) to mencion no other
billes, but such as passed in the house of commons,
in the fourth, that is, the last session of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
I say, The last, because the fifth cannot be
accompted a session, seeing nothing was concluded
therein, the Speaker, sundry mornings before the
house met togither adjourning the same from day
to day, til the parliament was prorogued, &amp; there
dissolved. Well, I pray God; that, whensoever
we shall haue an other parliament, Counties, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and burroughes may not be moved by letters
from such common-wealth-men, as the pen-man
of the said publication is feared to be, to chuse such
Knights and burgisses, as will have less Zeale for
the ease and freedome of the subjects, than had the
Knights, and burgisses of the late parliament.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>