<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORfull. Sir EDVVARD BARKHAM, Sir MARTIN LVMLEY, Sir CVTH∣BERT HACKET, and Sir MAVRICH ABBOT Knights; And the Worshipfull, HENRY GARAVVAY Esquire, Aldermen of this Honourable Citie:</title>
           <author>Freake, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122937_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72111</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11346</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122937</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORfull. Sir EDVVARD BARKHAM, Sir MARTIN LVMLEY, Sir CVTH∣BERT HACKET, and Sir MAVRICH ABBOT Knights; And the Worshipfull, HENRY GARAVVAY Esquire, Aldermen of this Honourable Citie:</title>
                 <author>Freake, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrines and practises of the Societie of Iesuites : In two bookes. The first, containing their grounds and intentions, discovered by two of their owne societie, the Reverend Paulus Florenius, Doctor and professor of Divinitie, and Christianus Francken, professor of philosophy, both in the Imperiall Schoole of Iesuites at Vienna. The second, containing a detection of the secret designes and bloody proiects of that societie of later yeares; especially, since their first designes for disturbing the sate [sic] of Germanie. And may serue as a warning for vs of this iland, and these times whereinto wee are fallen. By W.F. an vnworthy minister of the Gospell of Iesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Francke, Christian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gibbs, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36, 4, 39-62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Book industry, catalogues and inventories</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<seg rend="sup">full</seg>. Sir EDVVARD BARKHAM, Sir MARTIN LVMLEY, Sir CVTH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT HACKET, and Sir MAVRICH ABBOT <hi>Knights; And the Worshipfull,</hi> HENRY GARAVVAY <hi>Esquire, Aldermen of this Honourable Citie:</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">With the <hi>Master, Wardens,</hi> and <hi>Assistants</hi> of the right Worshipfull Companie of <hi>Drapers; W. F.</hi> wisheth all such Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings in this Life, as may fit them for the blessed fruition of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Life.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Proverbe is not more antient then true:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Tunc tua res agitur, paries quum proximus ardet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>When our Neighbours house is on fire, it is high time to prouide for the safetie of our owne: This present Age wherein wee liue, and the distressed estate of our Neighbours and Brethren in Religion fallen vpon them within these few yeares past, by the Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villian plots of that pernicious brood of Incendiaries stiled <hi>Iesuites,</hi> gaue mee occasion to make vse of this Proverbe, and called to my consideration the present danger of our owne State except some course were spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly taken to bring to light these concealed proiects of that Societie, which now wee may be assured they haue
<pb facs="26"/>in agitation against vs of this Nation in generall, and of this City more in particuler. Which thing I haue not found any so ready a way to performe (to the best of mine vnderstanding) as by propounding vnto our Nation a president of their practises of late yeeres, <hi>Vt exemplo alieno discamus,</hi> that we may see by their dealings with others, what measures our selues may in all probability expect from them. This president you shall find in this following discourse, wherein you may see as in a perfect Mirror, their Consultations for the disturbing of the States of <hi>Germany,</hi> taken aboue XX. yeeres agoe, their plottes vpon the particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, and seuerall Princes, discouered to that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before their Councels were brought into Action, had that Nation beene either so wise or so happy, as to haue taken notice thereof in time, and to haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated that brood of <hi>Vipers</hi> before they were grown vp to Maturity: All which, I haue thought it my bounden duty to divulge for the good of our Nation, that being forewarned, they may arme themselues in time against the growing Mischiefes, and to Dedicate more particularly this part thereof to your Worships in token of my due respect and ready willingnesse to doe any seruice to your Worships in particular, and to this Worshipfull Societie in generall, which may fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compasse of the abilitie of him, who resteth till death, for the good and happy estate of your Worships, and this Worshipfull Company, a daily Petitioner at the throne of Grace, in the best prayers and indeauours of.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>A weake Minister of the Gospell of CHRIST, and a free Brother of the</hi> Drapers <hi>Company: WIL: FREAKE</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>