<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Good Reader,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122637_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72064</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10926</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122637</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Good Reader,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian knight compiled : by Sir VVilliam VViseman Knight, for the pvblike weale and happinesse of England, Scotland, and Ireland</title>
                 <author>Wiseman, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 7, 1, 39, 1, 41, 3, 75, 3, 83, 15 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Good Reader,</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Haue heard of a discourse the other yeare, betweene two Frenchmen, the one a Souldier, the other a Ciuilian, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the vices of their times, and country. The Souldier was the Duke de <hi>Mercury,</hi> a right noble, and vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Captaine, late Lieftenant gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to the Emperour, against the Turk in Hungarie, and yet a great enemy to Duells. The Ciuilian was a Companion of his, and vndertooke against <hi>coueting,</hi> as it appeares by the Preamble following. And I am sorie wee haue no more of theirs, but the Preamble; since the times, and vices be as well ours as theirs. What the rest of their method was, J haue not seene, but by the qualitie of their persons, &amp; by their learning we may imagine. The argument could not be but profitable, and J set downe, what I thinke probable to come neerest their meaning, and the good of our nation; and I speake English to English. For heere is first set vp the marke, or white, which wee must all shoote at, and is done in two Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Paranaeticall</hi> to heauen-ward, The one shewing vs our way thither, The other our happines, when we come there. Here are secondly discouered two potent impediments in our way, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our sight, and leuell: and these are our <hi>Irascible,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscible</hi> parts. The abuse whereof is touched in two <hi>Charges;</hi> the one shewing the iniustice of <hi>Duell:</hi> the other our common iniustice in buying, and selling, and neglect of common good. And lastly, here be two <hi>Homages,</hi> or <hi>thanks-giuings</hi> to God.
<pb facs="3"/>The one of a Soule truely conuerted, the other of one proceeding in his grace, with signes of both. There be many things here delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be thought of, nothing hard to be done, and wee shall blame our selues most desperately, if we haue not done. Read there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beseech thee, and make vse of It; which if thou doe, thou wilt finde much comfort; and if all doe, they will make as flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing a common-wealth as euer was. There will scarce be any poore in it, or any vnquietnes. Kings will glorie in their Subiects, and Subiects in their Soueraigne, and all in each other, as it is in Heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>