<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND WOR∣thy Gentleman, Sir IOHN LEVINTHORPE Knight perpetuall Happinesse and Content.</title>
           <author>Jones, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122017_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04616</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14735</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND WOR∣thy Gentleman, Sir IOHN LEVINTHORPE Knight perpetuall Happinesse and Content.</title>
                 <author>Jones, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A musicall dreame. Or The fourth booke of ayres : the first part is for the lute, two voyces, and the viole de gambo; the second part is for the lute, the viole and foure voices to sing: the third part is for one voyce alone, or to the lute, the basse viole, or to both if you please, vvhereof, two are Italian ayres. Composed by Robert Iones</title>
                 <author>Jones, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Waterson, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentleman, Sir IOHN LEVINTHORPE Knight <hi>perpetuall Happinesse and Content.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne vnto your wel deseruing selfe, Right VVorshipfull, that not long since I tooke my <hi>Ultimum vale,</hi> with a resoluing in my selfe, neuer to publish any workes of the same Nature and Fashion, whereupon I betooke me to the ease of my Pillow, where <hi>Somnus</hi> hauing taken possession of my eyes, and <hi>Morpheus</hi> the charge of my senses; it happened mee to fall into a Musical dreame, wherein I chanced to haue many opinions and extrauagant humors of diuers Natures and Conditions, some of modest mirth, some of amorcus Loue, and some of most diuine contemplation; all these I hope, shall not giue any distaste to the eares, or dislike to the mind, eyther in their words, or in their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all sounds, although it is not necessarie to relate or diuulge all Dreames or Phantasies that Opinion begets in sleepe, or happeneth to the mindes appar<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And continuing long in this my dreaming slumber, I began to awake, and vpon my eyes vnclosing, I bethought my selfe, being full awaked, aduising in my mind, whome to elect and chuse as a Patrone for the same, I was easily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited to make choice of your VVorship, as one to whome I necessarily ought both loue and duety, And howsoeuer I might feare that you wil not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, yet in that Nature hath inriched you with more then ordinarie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in this Art, beeing a witnes of that Loue which you haue alwayes affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Musicke, I emboldened my selfe the rather to present it vnto you. Accept it then (good Sir) as a Token of vnfained Loue, and a debt worthily due vnto you for your many fauours done to him that is</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your Worships commaund.
ROBERT IONES.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>