<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122177_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16316</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3227</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122177</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A cordiall for Christians in the time of affliction. Or, A sermon preached at Kethering Lecture by Master Robert Bolton, Bachelour of Divinity, and sometimes fellow of Brasen-nose Colledge in Oxford. Published by I.S</title>
                 <author>Bolton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 27, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S nothing in the world makes a man so <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 17. 11.</note> truely <hi>noble</hi> as Religion: So nothing to the world makes a man more <note n="b" place="margin">Acts 28. 22. John 15 19. Wisdom 2. 18</note> liable to opposition and dis grace. And our mighty God that governes in wisdome, and ever hath an <note n="c" place="margin">1 Peter 5. 7</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speciall care of his people, suffers that so to be for some such ends as these. 1 That the <note n="d" place="margin">Hosea 5. 13 1 Peter 4. 13</note> graces of Gods Children may shine, the rust being scoured off. 2 That their incense offrings in their severall duties being broken and beaten <note n="e" place="margin">Genesis 8. 20</note> may smell the more. 3 That their obedience may be discerned by the purblind world not to be mercinary, but from some in ward principle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to nature, &amp;c. Now for the poore persecuted Saints to follow this way of Gods<note place="margin">g 1 Cor. 4. 12</note> providence <note n="f" place="margin">1 Chro. 29. 17</note> kindly to obey with a willing yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
         <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>

rather then to be angry at them. <note n="t" place="margin">Acts 28. 26</note>They see onely with a naturall eye: If a man looke upon GODS wayes onely with the eye of Reason they are <hi>foolishnesse</hi> to him; and sure if a man looke upon GODS Word and Workes through the false glasse of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wisedome, he cannot but imagine the thing promised in the one and in agitation in the other impossible so to be effected as promised for his childrens good. If a man had only so looked<note place="margin">2 Kings 20 11</note> upon the <note n="u" place="margin">Exodus 14. 22</note>
      <hi>Sunne standing still in Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiahs time,</hi> or upon the <note n="x" place="margin">Iudges 5. 20</note>
      <hi>Sea</hi> when the bottome became <hi>drie,</hi> and the <hi>waters</hi> stood as <hi>walls</hi> on each side; or upon the <note n="y" place="margin">Exodus 13. 21</note>
      <hi>Starres</hi> that <hi>fought</hi> in their courses against <hi>Sisera:</hi> Or u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on the <note n="z" place="margin">Daniel 3 22, 23, 27.</note>
      <hi>fiery Pillar</hi> which was sent to the <hi>Israelites,</hi> would they have thought these should bee a meanes to preserve GODS chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and destroy the Enemies. Little<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 11. 31</note> did <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iant men of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my thinke when they bound the <hi>three children in their clothes</hi> to cast them into the <hi>hot fiery fornace</hi> that the same fire thus prepared should <hi>burne</hi> and <hi>destroy</hi> them, and burne only the bonds to set <hi>free</hi> the poore persecuted Saints not
<pb facs="3"/>
once to hurt either <hi>body</hi> or <hi>garment,</hi> but to be a means to bring them to greater honour amongst their Persecutors. O the infinite wisedome of our good GOD that can put such understanding into sencelesse creatures thus to distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the precious and the vile, him that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth GOD and him that serveth him not more clearely then the Divell and naturall men can discerne: Now therfore to cleare the Eye of Faith which onely <note n="b" place="margin">Acts 16. 23</note> discernes such things and to helpe thee to get support against any such Faintings or the least grumbling at such a providence, which is unbeseeming a <hi>Paul</hi> (though in Prison with sore sides) for Religion.</p>
   <p>1. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Prayer a worke,</hi> which workes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in Heaven and earth, because that sets GOD a worke for us that is the hearer <hi>of Prayers</hi> and that he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ps his servants out of severall <hi>Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Afflictions</hi> when they pray by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 6. 26</note> wonders for them rather then they shall rest subject to continuail pressures of wicked men.</p>
   <p>2. Set <hi>Faith a</hi> worke, a hard duty I confesse, it being easier to obey then beleeve aright. Faith being the <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 26. 6, 7</note> worke of GOD, Obedience
<pb facs="4"/>
without Faith being the work of man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me intreat of thee to use the meanes that GOD affords, either to helpe thee out or <hi>comfort</hi> thee in <hi>affliction,</hi> as if thou hadst no promise: And yet so beleeve and depend u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on the promise for thy being helped out or upheld in the <hi>affliction,</hi> as if thou hadst no means at all to look after, that GOD may have all the honour from thee, and then certainly He that gives a being to his promises and a blessing to the means will prosper thee in the use of them: which of his <hi>Mercy</hi> he grant to us all for the LORD CHRISTS sake,</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>