<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122082_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21219</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7575</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122082</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The suruay or topographical description of France : with a new mappe, helping greatly for the surueying of euery particular country, cittye, fortresse, riuer, mountaine, and forrest therein: collected out of sundry approued authors: very amply, truly, and historically digested, for the pleasure of those who desire to be throughly acquainted in the state of the kingdome &amp; dominion of France</title>
                 <author>Eliot, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 103, 1 page, folded plates, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THou seest before thine eies (gentle Reader) the face of the florishing Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> whose lustre and glorie at this present is a little eclipsed and dymmed by the cyuill dissention and bloudy broiles that a long time haue afflicted it. I knowe many famous Cosmographers haue in their maps described the country in ample sort, vnto whom an ancient Historiographer gaue the first and greatest light▪ I mean <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> who in his learned and eloquent Commentaries of <hi>France</hi> did so excellently well that all the writers in the world, and lay all their pens and wits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in that matter, cannot doe so well againe, or once come neare him, considering the time that he wrote was so long agone. Amongst other that haue written since of the country and people of <hi>France, Be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>le-Forests</hi> hath not deserued the lest praise for his Collections out of sundry good and approued Authours, published concerning this matter. Now thou hast also here of vs a breif Topographicall description of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> gathered out of many of the later writers not to bee neglected, wherein are exactlye and briefly described their Regions, Prouinces, Citties▪ Castels, and Fortresses, the commodities of euery soyle, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Inhabitants, their auncient and moderne maners, lawes▪ rights and customes, with diuers other thinges coincident to the same, and verye meete to bee knowne in such an Historie. To bee breif I shall not neede to write at large of the Country in this place, for that thou shalt bee informed thereof most amply by one that can sett it downe in better manner then I. I will speake a worde or two of <hi>Paris,</hi> the capitall City and metropolis of all <hi>France,</hi> an vniuersity whose fame is spread through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all <hi>Europe</hi> for the famous Scholes of learning therein, and I thinke it to bee beside one of the most populous Cityes in the world. The number of whose Inhabitants is of many millyons, and to make shorter, is, as it were another world, or rather as one said of ancient Rome, an <hi>epitome</hi> of the world: with the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> is invested at this present <hi>Henry the Fourth</hi> lyneally descended from <hi>Saint Lodouicke,</hi> who is now vp in Armes with the princes of his bloud roiall for his title and right vnto the Crowne: Remarked for the most heroicall and magnanimous Kinge, fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the most victorious and invincible warriour that euer vnsheathed sword
<pb facs="3"/>
for a Kingdome: hauing bine personally present and fought more then fourteene or fiueteene pitched fields, and had victorye on his side at them all. So that I thinke if we seeke amongst all the Empires of the <hi>Assyrians, Persians, Grecyans, Romans, Almans, Iewes, Tartarians and Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> and ouer all the face of the whole world beside, we cannot find a king of a greater race and more noble courage then this: hauing had xxviii. kinges in his house before him and all in line masculine of his fathers side: His mother being the heire and yssue of a Queene, whose mother was sister to <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> excelled in wit, learning and haughty courage of a woman all other Christian Princesses that euer had liued before her. And if there be any that will contradyct me concerning the kings roiall parson or his ancient ofspring and descent, to compare it to some base, poore and ignoble Family, he is lesse able to speake of the royal, high, ancient &amp; noble families of Christendome, then frogs and rats are to discourse of the greatnes, height, essence, beauty and admirable operations of the <hi>Sunne:</hi> and for his country if there be any that will empeache the goodnes and beautie thereof, to say that it is not so fruitfull nor so pleasant, nor so well furnished and replenished with all thinges that are to be desired in such a flourishing kingdome (Peace only excepted which the God of heauen send downe vpon them spedily) he is no more able to dispute of a Country then a Mole or a Mouse of the man in the Moone. For his Royall person, and noble progenie his very enimyes and al the world shalbe iudge. And for his kingdome and country <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Saluste</hi> Seigneur of <hi>Bartas,</hi> a man of that nation to whome credite may woorthily bee giuen in such a matter: whose verses in praise of his natiue soile in his second day of his second weeke, I haue translated thus out of <hi>French</hi>:
<q>
         <l>O Fruitefull <hi>France</hi>! Most happy Land, happy and happy thrice!</l>
         <l>O perle of rich <hi>Europaean</hi> bounds. O earthly Paradice.</l>
         <l>All haile sweete soile! O <hi>France</hi> the mother of many conquering knights,</l>
         <l>Who planted once their glorious standards like triumphing wights,</l>
         <l>Vppon the banckes of <hi>Euphrates</hi> where <hi>Titan</hi> Day-torch bright.</l>
         <l>Riseth, and blouddy swordes vnsheathd where <hi>Phebus</hi> drounds his Light,</l>
         <l>The Mother of many artist-hands whose workemanship most rare</l>
         <l>Dimmes <hi>Natures</hi> workes, and with her fairest flowers doth compare.</l>
         <l>The Nurse of many learned wits who fetch their skill diuine</l>
         <l>From <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Greece,</hi> from <hi>AEgipt</hi> farre, and ore the learnedst shine,</l>
         <l>As doth the glymmering-Crimsin-dye ouer the darkest gray:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Titan</hi> ore starres, or <hi>Phaebus</hi> flowers ore marigolds in May.</l>
         <l>Thy flouds are Ocean Seas, thy Tounes to Prouinces arise,</l>
         <l>Whose ciuill gouerment their walls hath raisd to lofty skies.</l>
         <l>Thy soile is fertill-temperate-sweete, no plague thine aire doth trouble,</l>
         <l>Bastillyons fower borne in thy bounds: two Seas and mountains double,</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="3"/>The <hi>Crocodile</hi> fierce-weeping-teares annoyeth not thy maine,</l>
         <l>The speckled-race of crawling Serpents hant not thy domaine,</l>
         <l>Not in one Acre of thy land that cursed seede is seene,</l>
         <l>Backs-venimous-winding to and fro t'infect thy medowes greene,</l>
         <l>The <hi>Tigre</hi>-swift of-foote prayes not within thy mountaines hollow,</l>
         <l>Nor hungry-soming ore thy Plaines inrag'd his chace doth follow.</l>
         <l>No <hi>Lions</hi> in thy desarts lurke: no <hi>Sea-horse</hi> monster rumbling,</l>
         <l>Swymmes to thy maine, and steales thine infantes vnder waues them tumbling</l>
         <l>If in thy streaming- riuers-rich-swift-gliding be not rold</l>
         <l>The golden sands mong Pibble-stones, nor ore of massiue gold:</l>
         <l>Yf Siluer pure dropping from downe thy mountaines be not found,</l>
         <l>And euery step <hi>Perle, Ruby, Diamond, Grenate</hi> on thy ground,</l>
         <l>In contre-chaung thou art as rich in woade, in wolle, in wines,</l>
         <l>In Salt pits, Sindon fine good Graine: which are sufficient mines</l>
         <l>To make thee farre and neere renound of earthly Kingdomes Queene.</l>
         <l>Tis only Peace, thou lackst. Alas! O God whose Eyes haue seene</l>
         <l>Our blessinges and our miseries, thine Eyes of mercy glance</l>
         <l>Vppon our present State and quench the flames consuming <hi>France:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Sweete father turne our stormes to calmes: Thy heauy hand retyre,</l>
         <l>Hide quickly in thy Quiuer all the Arrowes of thine Ire.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Thou canst not Gentle reader desire to knowe any more of this country then this excellent poet hath told thee, cōcerning they great treasures, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and pleasures thereof, wherein it is worthely to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other countryes vnder the scope of the heauens. Thou seest first with what worthy and honorable titles hee saluteth this rich and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing territory: then speaketh of the great numbers of warryours, famous Artists, and men of great learning that it hath brought forth and bred. Nexte setteth downe the Scituation of the Countrey: to wit: that it is bounded towards the west and the North with the huge <hi>Ocean</hi> Sea: &amp; to the Southward with the <hi>Mediterrane</hi>: being full of diuers riuers or rather litle seas, passing and runninge euerie way cleane thorow the mayne: the names whereof are: The <hi>Rosne</hi>▪ the <hi>Saone, Dordone, Loyre, Marne, Seyne,</hi> and <hi>Oyse</hi>: besides a great number of others smaller and yet verie famous to: It hath her cities▪ as <hi>Paris, Tholouse, Roan, Lions, Bourdeaux,</hi> and many other wich are more populous then so many dutchies, Countries and whole prouinces. The fortresses at this day are fayrer, more in number and better fortified then euer before. As for the Ciuility of the people, I leaue that to the iudgment of the stranger that hath liued there. The ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Country is almost incredible: the ayre is temperat euery where. For rampires and walles it hath the two seas: and likewise the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines called the <hi>Alpes</hi> towards <hi>Italie</hi>: and the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> mountaines to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>Spaine,</hi> beside it is exempt from all venimous, cruell and rauish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="4"/>
beastes, as <hi>Crocodyles,</hi> and other monstrous Serpents, which spo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e the country of <hi>AEgypt</hi> and diuers other partes of <hi>Africa.</hi> If it haue not mines of Gold and Siluer, precious Stones and perles, yet hath it in cont re-exchang other mines of farre greater commoditie and neuer to be searched to the botome: to wit: lynen clothes: woade, wolles, salte, corne and wine: The wadd and salte are found in <hi>Languedock:</hi> salte is founde also in the Country of <hi>Guienne</hi>: wolles in <hi>Prouince</hi> and in <hi>Beausse,</hi> where is also wheate in abondance: wine in diuers partes, and in all prouinces except fower or fiue great prouision of two or three of these commodityes: The poete hath remarked the principall thinges whereof great trafficke is made into forraine and neighbour nations from <hi>France.</hi> This then might suffice to learne that nation to acknowledge the great gifts of God and bee thankefull for the same. And seing they haue so many benefits, to knowe what they want, and to aske it at his hands that can giue it. So also with my hart I can wish to this kingdome (that whilome was so flourishing) and I hope all good christians wish the same, a florishing, firme, ciuill, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aigned and christian Peace, the band of true vnity and concord to indure amongst them for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>