<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his honoured friend and Kinsman, Mr. LEVVES ROBERTS, Merchant.</title>
           <author>E., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122012_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10821</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21094</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his honoured friend and Kinsman, Mr. LEVVES ROBERTS, Merchant.</title>
                 <author>E., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The merchants mappe of commerce : wherein, the universall manner and matter of trade, is compendiously handled. The standerd and currant coines of sundry princes, observed. The reall and imaginary coines of accompts and exchanges, expressed. The naturall and artificiall commodities of all countries for transportation declared. The weights and measures of all eminent cities and tovvnes of traffique, collected and reduced one into another; and all to the meridian of commerce practised in the famous citie of London. By Lewes Roberts, merchant. Necessary for all such as shall be imployed in the publique affaires of princes in forreigne parts; for all gentlemen and others that travell abroad for delight or pleasure, and for all merchants or their factors that exercise the art of merchandizing in any part of the habitable world</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 12, 223, 3, 116, 119-202, 205-262, 2, 192, 22 pages, 2 plates (1 folded), portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <pb n="1" facs="7"/>
      <head>To his honoured friend and Kinsman, Mr. LEVVES ROBERTS, <hi>Merchant.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>HOw ere our ruder Countrey-men despise</l>
         <l>The Mysteries of <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Merchandise;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>With whom 'tis counted Learning but to know</l>
         <l>The price of <hi>Runts,</hi> how <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Cattell</hi> goe:</l>
         <l>Such as (for COINE) doe onely understand</l>
         <l>That which with them doth passe from hand to hand:</l>
         <l>And as for <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Measures,</hi> find no ground</l>
         <l>For any other thanthe <hi>Yard</hi> and <hi>Pound:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>So as thy BOOKE, to these that judgement lacke,</l>
         <l>Seemes of lesse use then an old <hi>Almana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ke:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>How ere (I say) their ignorance incline</l>
         <l>To make <hi>wast paper</hi> of this <hi>Worke</hi> of thine;</l>
         <l>Yet please t'admit one from thy native Clime,</l>
         <l>And of thy Blood too, to speake truth in Rime.</l>
         <l>A <hi>verse</hi> protects not falshood, and a Lye</l>
         <l>Is not excus'd by being good <hi>Poetrie;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That's but to sinne more wittily, and be</l>
         <l>Guiltie of a more quaint impietie:</l>
         <l>Such praise You'd scorne; and (though the <hi>vice</hi> of <hi>Time</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Make Sin in <hi>prose,</hi> but Courtesie in <hi>rime)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Your better thoughts would ne'r with patience brooke</l>
         <l>That any damne himselfe to praise your BOOKE.</l>
         <l>Ile then bring no fain'd <hi>Eulogies</hi> t'invite</l>
         <l>The thrifty <hi>Buyers</hi> colder Appetite;</l>
         <l>Or (like a begging <hi>Prologuist)</hi> forespeake</l>
         <l>A faire Applause, for feare the <hi>Author</hi> breake:</l>
         <l>No thy <hi>Composures</hi> farre transcend that fate,</l>
         <l>And scorne alike the Vulgars <hi>love</hi> and <hi>hate.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>They that (like Thee) refus'd no paine or toyle</l>
         <l>With forreigne <hi>Trade</hi> t'enrich their <hi>Native soile,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And (like discreet <hi>Camelions)</hi> can comply</l>
         <l>With each Mans <hi>humor</hi> for <hi>Commoditie:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That have read <hi>Kingdomes</hi> over, and can tell</l>
         <l>What Men, for Letters put together, spell;</l>
         <l>And understand too even the most perplext</l>
         <l>And hidden meaning of that darker <hi>Text:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>These and these onely are allow'd to bee</l>
         <l>The equall <hi>Iudges</hi> of thy BOOKE and THEE.</l>
         <l>And sure Thy <hi>merit</hi> cannot want <hi>it's</hi> meed;</l>
         <l>For <hi>doing well's</hi> rewarded in the <hi>deed.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>M. E.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="2" facs="8"/>
      <head>To my honoured friend and Cousin, <hi>Mr. LODO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVICKE ROBERTS</hi> Merchant, upon his <hi>BOOKE.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>STeel'd was his Courage, and undaunted Minde</l>
         <l>Who first spread <hi>Sailes</hi> to catch the nimble <hi>winde;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Culling the stately <hi>Pines</hi> from lofty <hi>Woods,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>To cut a passage through the <hi>raging Floods:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>The hazard of this Enterprize did make</l>
         <l>Thee this laborious <hi>Taske</hi> to undertake;</l>
         <l>To make that way familiar, which before</l>
         <l>Was full of doubt; that where feare kept the doore</l>
         <l>Security might enter, and men now</l>
         <l>Through <hi>Neptunes</hi> field safely might drive their <hi>Plough</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Our <hi>English Merchants</hi> justly may stile thee,</l>
         <l>Not onely <hi>Typhis,</hi> but their <hi>Mercurie:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>For, how each Countrey doth to others prize</l>
         <l>The value of its <hi>Native Merchandize;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>What profit such COMMERCE to us may bring,</l>
         <l>Their Rites, and how the Image of our KING</l>
         <l>In <hi>forreigne Climates</hi> is preferd before</l>
         <l>Exotick <hi>Princes,</hi> stampt in the same <hi>Oare,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Thou in this little VOLVME dost contrive;</l>
         <l>That <hi>Merchants</hi> seeing them (through perspective)</l>
         <l>Discharge their <hi>Factors;</hi> for thy BOOKE alone</l>
         <l>Seemes a sole FACTOR for our NATION.</l>
         <l>CAMBRIA rejoyce; hereafter thou maist write,</l>
         <l>I bore the MAN, who lent the <hi>World</hi> this light.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>F. H.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>To my loving and much honoured Cousin, <hi>Mr. LEVVES ROBERTS</hi> Merchant, upon his <hi>MERCHANTS MAPPE</hi> of <hi>COMMERCE.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>MY praise is bootlesse, and to discommend</l>
         <l>Is fitter for a Slanderer then a Friend;</l>
         <l>For my small judgement in this <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Gaine</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Makes both my <hi>verdict</hi> and my <hi>Censure</hi> vaine:</l>
         <l>
            <pb n="3" facs="8"/>
Yet I've perusd thy BOOKE, and there have seene</l>
         <l>A <hi>Worke</hi> of wonder; and though have not beene</l>
         <l>Farr from my <hi>Native home;</hi> yet now I find</l>
         <l>The <hi>Worlds worth</hi> clos'd within thy knowing <hi>Minde;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>I see the <hi>Riches</hi> of each Countries <hi>soyle</hi>
         </l>
         <l>By this thy <hi>Art</hi> brought home, without our toyle;</l>
         <l>I find the <hi>Rarities</hi> of each Place and Towne</l>
         <l>Brought to our view with ease, and thou hast drawne</l>
         <l>All forreigne COINES to <hi>Ours,</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> to <hi>theirs;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Their <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Measures</hi> too, to us appeares</l>
         <l>All but One thing; thy most industrious hand</l>
         <l>By this thy skill, ha's crowned thus this Land</l>
         <l>With strange <hi>Outlandish wealth,</hi> which shall commend</l>
         <l>Thy <hi>worth</hi> to after Times; and I, thy friend</l>
         <l>And <hi>Kinsman,</hi> glory shall that this thy Fame</l>
         <l>Hath thus rais'd up a WORKE t'outlive thy <hi>Name.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>ROBERT ROBERTS <hi>of Llanvair</hi> in <hi>Anglesey.</hi>
         </signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>Ad Ingeniosum exactissimi hujus operis Authorem, D<seg rend="sup">m</seg>
         <hi>Lodovicum Roberts,</hi> Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem <hi>Londinensem.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>MVltatuo (fateor) debentur carmina Libro,</l>
         <l>Qui dedit ingenij tot monumenta tui.</l>
         <l>Siste pedem, nec vade for as Mercator ad <hi>Indos:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Huc ades, his paucis discere multapotes.</l>
         <l>Spargitur his folijs nummus peregrinus, et Aurum,</l>
         <l>Argentum, Aes, varijs sculptamoneta modis.</l>
         <l>Aspicerem, legem, placidâ brevitate docentur,</l>
         <l>Artificis, patriae, gloria, fama, decus.</l>
         <l>Vade Liber, plausuque volent <hi>(Lodovice)</hi> labores:</l>
         <l>Primadabunt merit is praemia digna tuis.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <head>Ad LECTOREM.</head>
         <l>QVisquis eris (Lector) Librinè supprime laudem,</l>
         <l>Ingenuum dices, si legis artis opus.</l>
         <l>Qui flocci pendes, tentes componere tale.</l>
         <l>Da sibi quod tibivis: Lector, Amator eris.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>GVLIELMVS ROGERS.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="4" facs="9"/>
      <head>To the eminently deserving Author, <hi>Mr. LEVVES ROBERTS.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>TWere needlesse sure to fixe a <hi>Poem</hi> heere</l>
         <l>To draw the taken READER in by th'Eare;</l>
         <l>'Tis cheape to praise the <hi>Author;</hi> we commend</l>
         <l>No <hi>worth</hi> i'th <hi>Worke</hi> by that, but <hi>love</hi> toth' <hi>Friend;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And (by an open way of Flattery) make</l>
         <l>The <hi>Worke</hi> approved for the <hi>Authors</hi> sake:</l>
         <l>So, (though we loath) the thick-lipt <hi>Nurse</hi> wee kisse</l>
         <l>For the <hi>Babes</hi> sake, that by her nourish't is.</l>
         <l>Thy <hi>Genius,</hi> that first stampt a <hi>worth</hi> on This,</l>
         <l>Above <hi>its Reader,</hi> or <hi>its Praiser</hi> is;</l>
         <l>And we may make a doubt, whether best takes,</l>
         <l>The <hi>Coine</hi> thou speak'st of, or the <hi>Coine</hi> thou makst;</l>
         <l>And live indebted, that thou hast brought hither</l>
         <l>To us, the <hi>Trade</hi> of all the <hi>World</hi> together:</l>
         <l>And (as i'th' <hi>Worlds</hi> MAP spacious <hi>Kingdomes</hi> lie</l>
         <l>Deciphered by small <hi>Atomes</hi> to our eye)</l>
         <l>So the great <hi>Worth</hi> in every <hi>Page</hi> by Thee</l>
         <l>Exprest; is richer then a MONARCHIE.</l>
         <l>Live, live to <hi>Fame;</hi> and may its truth to You</l>
         <l>Make mee a POET and a PROPHET too.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>THO: BEEDOME.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>Ad clarissimum virum D. <hi>Lodovicum Roberts</hi> Civem <hi>Londinensem,</hi> linguarum modernarum artisque Mercatoriae scientissimum; Chartam Mercatoriam edentem.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>QVid dignum <hi>Lodovice</hi> tibi, quid pectorepromam,</l>
         <l>Quo possim merito solvere digna tuo?</l>
         <l>Carmina quid canerem, dulces imitantia Musas?</l>
         <l>Carminasunt Libris inferiora tuis.</l>
         <l>Laudibus eveherem? tua pura modestia pellit:</l>
         <l>Notaloquor. Laudes respuis ipse tuas.</l>
         <l>Desistam meliùs. Reliquos tu pande labores.</l>
         <l>Laus <hi>Chartae Mercis</hi> nulla sat esse potest.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>HENRY GARTHWAITE.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="5" facs="9"/>
      <head>To his worthy Friend, and loving Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servant, the AVTHOR.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>TIs an old custome that this Age hath got,</l>
         <l>To praise their <hi>friends</hi> in <hi>print,</hi> Ile praise thee, not</l>
         <l>Because I am thy <hi>friend;</hi> onely Ile tell</l>
         <l>The World, the WORKE which thou hast done so well</l>
         <l>Speakes both thy <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>praise; it</hi> cannot misse,</l>
         <l>Those that are not thy <hi>friends</hi> must needs praise <hi>this;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>This thy COMMERCE, <hi>Child</hi> of thine <hi>Industrie,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Joyning both POLES in neere <hi>affinitie,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Nurse</hi> of thy Countries <hi>honor,</hi> and by which</l>
         <l>Onely, all <hi>Kingdomes</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> grow rich;</l>
         <l>And (by the <hi>Currant</hi> of a <hi>mutuall Trade)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Thou shewst how <hi>happie</hi> all the <hi>Earth</hi> is made.</l>
         <l>Let others praise Thee; yet in the degree</l>
         <l>Of <hi>Vertue,</hi> live belov'd by <hi>W. B.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>Ad charissimum Fratrem D<seg rend="sup">m</seg>
         <hi>Lodovicum Roberts</hi> Civem <hi>Londinensem.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>QUas <hi>Phoebus</hi> merces terris adspersit Eois,</l>
         <l>Et quas occiduis aspicit ipse locis:</l>
         <l>Quicquid produxit Zephyrus, tu quicquid et Eurus,</l>
         <l>Antiquus quicquid et novus orbis habet,</l>
         <l>Collig is in fascem: numismata millia centum;</l>
         <l>Mille tibi merces; cambia caecapatent.</l>
         <l>Perge beare tuos foeliciprole cerebri,</l>
         <l>Utraquevix tant as <hi>India</hi> jactat opes.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>TASSS.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="6" facs="10"/>
      <head>To my ever loving friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> LEWES ROBERTS Merchant, upon his MAP of COMMERCE.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>CAll up the ancient Bards and let them praise</l>
         <l>This Brittaines skill not known in former dayes,</l>
         <l>For then <hi>Astraea</hi> fled and left the land,</l>
         <l>But now's return'd with Ballance in her hand,</l>
         <l>And teacheth out of <hi>Roberts</hi> new found treasure,</l>
         <l>To know the World throughout by Weight and Measure.</l>
         <l>First then lets weigh the man, weigh his good will,</l>
         <l>Then weigh our words, so shall we speake none ill.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>Charles Fetiplace.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>To his friend <hi>Mr. LEWES ROBERTS</hi> MERCHANT.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>SOme <hi>Merchants</hi> travaile without rest,</l>
         <l>From North to South, from East to West,</l>
         <l>To gaine their wealth; which home they bring</l>
         <l>To fill their chests; or with full wing</l>
         <l>Profusely spend it here in pleasure,</l>
         <l>With health, time, credit and their treasure.</l>
         <l>But thou, experience having taught,</l>
         <l>That what is buried comes to naught,</l>
         <l>Here largely shewes by course of Trade,</l>
         <l>The <hi>Merchants</hi> MAP, COMMERCE to ayd;</l>
         <l>And so by spending gathers more</l>
         <l>Than they that basely hide their store.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>Ralph Hanson.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="7" facs="10"/>
      <head>To his much Honoured friend <hi>Mr. LEWES ROBERTS</hi> Merchant, upon his <hi>MAP of COMMERCE.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg n="1">
         <head>1.</head>
         <l>WHen that the portall of this goodly frame</l>
         <l>Was first presented to my greedy eyes,</l>
         <l>(Before I saw the Master-builders name)</l>
         <l>Me thought it was a promising Frontispiece:</l>
         <l>And then desires did kindle in my brest,</l>
         <l>To enter further and to view the rest.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="2">
         <head>2.</head>
         <l>But looking longer on that beauteous Porch,</l>
         <l>I spied insculp'd on the outside building,</l>
         <l>The Authours name, that like a burning torch</l>
         <l>Did set on flame my pristine ardent longing:</l>
         <l>By that the builder of the worke I knew;</l>
         <l>How could I then but thirst for further view?</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="3">
         <head>3.</head>
         <l>I crav'd admittance, 'twas a needlesse suite,</l>
         <l>(The Arts (they say) are called liberall;)</l>
         <l>Assoone as entred I was strucken mute,</l>
         <l>And made my moane to th' Muses severall:</l>
         <l>They promis'd ayde; but yet when I had done,</l>
         <l>They said 'twas lighting tapers to the Sunne.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="4">
         <head>4.</head>
         <l>Loe here I met with many sacred Arts,</l>
         <l>Which keepe their Courts and usuall residence;</l>
         <l>At <hi>Ox</hi> and <hi>Camber</hi> those two famous Marts,</l>
         <l>Partaking most of their munificence.</l>
         <l>These franckly sent this Architect a piece,</l>
         <l>To beautifie his curious Edifice.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="5">
         <head>5.</head>
         <l>Me thought I saw them sadly to lament</l>
         <l>The adverse fortune of so brave a Wight,</l>
         <l>That was not to their learned mansions sent,</l>
         <l>Ne'r could his Starrs have wrought him worser spight:</l>
         <l>But yet to conquer their malignities,</l>
         <l>Th'enricht his Thesis with their dignities.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="6">
         <pb n="8" facs="11"/>
         <head>6.</head>
         <l>Here did I see with strange variety</l>
         <l>The great Colosse of the terrestriall Globe,</l>
         <l>Brought by the Art of rare Geographie,</l>
         <l>Within the compasse of a paper robe;</l>
         <l>So rich the forme and so compendious,</l>
         <l>As strucke amazement in my wondering Muse.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="7">
         <head>7.</head>
         <l>I further look'd and saw with admiration</l>
         <l>Th'exact composure of two matchlesse lights,</l>
         <l>They serve not onely for the contemplation</l>
         <l>Of men Merchantile, but of Gentile spirits;</l>
         <l>The one descries the paths of <hi>merchandize,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>The other shewes Exchanges mysteries.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="8">
         <head>8.</head>
         <l>I've read of <hi>Drake</hi> and <hi>Martin Forbesher,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Whose manly faces all the Poles did see,</l>
         <l>With others famed for the Globes surrounder,</l>
         <l>Their worths have sweld the Worlds great History:</l>
         <l>I honour much those Heroes memory,</l>
         <l>Asmuch I loathe the staine of flattery.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="9">
         <head>9.</head>
         <l>But my opinion freely Ile expresse,</l>
         <l>And thinke that none will judge it Heresie;</l>
         <l>That of the World in this MAP of COMMERCE,</l>
         <l>This age shall finde more rare discovery:</l>
         <l>For here that Massy Ball and all its <hi>traffique</hi>
         </l>
         <l>At once is seene, as through a perfect optique.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg n="10">
         <head>10.</head>
         <l>Goe on (brave wit) and let the World possesse</l>
         <l>Some further fruit of thy wel-tempred braines:</l>
         <l>Though Critiques snarle, it matters not a rush;</l>
         <l>Honour and thankes attend thy matchlesse paines.</l>
         <l>The unborne Babe that shall a <hi>Merchant</hi> be,</l>
         <l>Shall honour in this worke thy memory.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>I. H.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="9" facs="11"/>
      <head>To the no lesse <hi>ingenuous,</hi> then really <hi>industrious Gentleman,</hi> Mr. LEWES ROBERTS, <hi>Merchant;</hi> and one of the COMMITTEES for the <hi>East-India</hi> COMPANY:</head>
      <p>Vpon his <hi>Booke</hi> intituled, THE MERCHANTS MAPPE OF COMMERCE. With an <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madversion</hi> to the <hi>Reader,</hi> and <hi>Allusion</hi> to <hi>the time of the first</hi> Impression, <hi>being the beginning of this present Yeare;</hi> MDCXXXVIII.</p>
      <lg>
         <l>HAd I (by frequent <hi>Traffique</hi> on the BVRSE)</l>
         <l>Beene verst i'th' <hi>notes</hi> of <hi>Mercantile Discourse,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>In proper <hi>Accents</hi> heere I might set forth</l>
         <l>Some faire Expression of Thy <hi>pregnant WORTH;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Or rais'd a TROPHEE to Thy <hi>vertuous</hi> NAME,</l>
         <l>Of equall <hi>PARR,</hi> to Thy <hi>Deserving FAME:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>But, (having onely <hi>touch'd</hi> APOLLOS <hi>Lyre)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Grant me yet roome amongst this <hi>numerous Quire:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And, (as I am) accept of what I bring,</l>
         <l>A <hi>Posie</hi> meane for such an <hi>Orient</hi> RING,</l>
         <l>A RING for every MERCHANT meet to weare,</l>
         <l>Though vast in <hi>Compasse,</hi> as the <hi>Orbique Sphaere:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Thy <hi>Booke</hi> I mean, the MAP OF faire COMMERCE,</l>
         <l>That takes <hi>Circumference</hi> ore the UNIVERSE.</l>
         <l>Where first, (as to the life) I finde displaid <note place="margin">1.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Due <hi>Method,</hi> and materiall <hi>forme</hi> of TRADE;</l>
         <l>The <hi>STANDERDS</hi> value secondly, injoynes</l>
         <l>Of PRINCES to observe their <hi>currant</hi> COINES: <note place="margin">2.</note>
         </l>
         <l>The third, COINES <hi>reall,</hi> and <hi>imaginarie,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Accompts, Exchanges;</hi> and wherein they varie: <note place="margin">3.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Fourthly, COMMODITIES for <hi>Transportation,</hi>
            <note place="margin">4.</note>
         </l>
         <l>The various <hi>sorts</hi> of every severall NATION:</l>
         <l>Fifthly, of TOWNES and CITIES <hi>eminent,</hi>
            <note place="margin">5.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Their <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Measures</hi> to the full extent:</l>
         <l>Lastly, reducing all to One, (by <hi>This)</hi>
            <note place="margin">6.</note>
         </l>
         <l>LONDONS COMMERCE, our faire <hi>Metropolis.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Rare MERCHANT of the MVSES! may I call</l>
         <l>Thee <hi>Merchant?</hi> or Great FACTOR <hi>Generall?</hi>
         </l>
         <l>This <hi>Proofe piece</hi> of Thy <hi>Service</hi> for the rest,</l>
         <l>May well oblige <hi>Them</hi> to Thy deare <hi>behest;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <pb n="10" facs="12"/>
For, of Thy equall sure no AGE can boast,</l>
         <l>That bringst Us <hi>Traffique</hi> home from every <hi>Coast;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Rat'st the <hi>Commodities,</hi> the <hi>Coines,</hi> the <hi>Measures;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And sum'st (in fine) a very <hi>Masse</hi> of <hi>Treasures.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Go on, and prosper in Thy faire <hi>Designes;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>May these <hi>elaborate</hi> and <hi>experient Lines</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Add to those <hi>honourd</hi> PAIRE of CITIE-SAGES,</l>
         <l>That shall receive <hi>them</hi> to <hi>their</hi> PATRONAGES.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Meane while, (and to transmit my free <hi>Applause</hi>
         </l>
         <l>READER, to <hi>Thee</hi> (without <hi>collaterall</hi> cause)</l>
         <l>Of th' AVTHORS <hi>Worth;</hi> not hereby to prefer</l>
         <l>This MERCHANTS MAPP, (as do's the <hi>Stationer,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>For his owne <hi>private profit)</hi> but for <hi>Thine,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>To whom Our AVTHOR do's His <hi>Worke</hi> resigne)</l>
         <l>This I infer; <hi>It</hi> ha's no PRESIDENT</l>
         <l>For THEORIE; and to make <hi>equivalent</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Thy <hi>practique Part;</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> here bequeaths</l>
         <l>A VOLVME, not more <hi>continent</hi> of <hi>Leaves,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Then <hi>various fruitfull Matter;</hi> which his <hi>toyle</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Ha's brought Thee <hi>home</hi> from every <hi>forreigne Soyle;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And (as deepe <hi>speld</hi> in GEOGRAPHIQVE <hi>Arts)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Ran smooth division o're the WORLD in <hi>Parts;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Searching the <hi>bowels</hi> of each <hi>Kingdomes</hi> STATE:</l>
         <l>And not alone of TRAFFIQVE <hi>there</hi> relate;</l>
         <l>But <hi>Customes, Habits, Strength,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Deckt in so new HISTORIQVE <hi>Ornament;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That <hi>heere</hi> Thou mayst with <hi>ease</hi> and <hi>pleasure</hi> see</l>
         <l>The <hi>Rate</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of every MONARCHIE.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Nor need'st Thou yet demand for <hi>whom</hi> is made</l>
         <l>This faire <hi>Commerciall</hi> MAPP, this <hi>Mapp</hi> of <hi>Trade:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>To <hi>All</hi> 'tis needfull; specially for <hi>Those</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That most for <hi>Travaile</hi> shall <hi>themselves</hi> dispose;</l>
         <l>Or <hi>those</hi> who would employ or <hi>them</hi> or <hi>theirs</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Ith' <hi>publique way</hi> of PRINCES great <hi>Affaires;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Or <hi>any,</hi> who for <hi>private</hi> RECREATION,</l>
         <l>Make (by <hi>conceit)</hi> continuall <hi>Transmigration:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>In fine, (and chiefe) for <hi>All</hi> that <hi>exercise</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Ith' <hi>spacious</hi> WORLD the <hi>Art</hi> of MERCHANDISE.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Since now, for <hi>generall Good</hi> (as't may appeare)</l>
         <l>This HARVEST comes i'th' <hi>entrance</hi> of the YEARE;</l>
         <l>(As to so MANY <hi>usefull;) Many</hi> bee</l>
         <l>The <hi>future</hi> BLESSINGS shall be <hi>shour'd</hi> on THEE:</l>
         <l>Yea, <hi>All</hi> (in part) <hi>Thy</hi> LABOVRS to <hi>requite)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Blesse <hi>that New-</hi>YEARE brought <hi>this new</hi> WORKE to <hi>light.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>MATHEW RHODES.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="11" facs="12"/>
      <head>In praise of my friend the Author, and his <hi>BOOKE. To the READER.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>IF thou would'st be a <hi>States-man,</hi> and survay</l>
         <l>Kingdomes for information; heres a way</l>
         <l>Made plaine, and easie: fitter far for thee</l>
         <l>Then great <hi>Ortelius</hi> his <hi>Geographie.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>If thou would'st be a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> in more</l>
         <l>Then title onely; this MAP yeelds thee store</l>
         <l>Of Observations, fit for Ornament,</l>
         <l>Or use, or to give curious eares content.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>If thou would'st be a <hi>Merchant,</hi> buy this Booke:</l>
         <l>For 'tis a prize worth gold; and doe not looke</l>
         <l>Daily for such disbursements; no, 'tis rare,</l>
         <l>And should be cast up with thy richest ware.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>READER, if thou be any, or all three;</l>
         <l>(For these may meet and make a harmonie)</l>
         <l>Then prayse this Author for his usefull paines,</l>
         <l>Whose aime is publike good, not private gaines.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>Iz. Wa.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>
         <hi>SAMUEL VVILLIAMOT,</hi> to his ever honour'd Brother in law the Authour.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>THis learned <hi>Issue</hi> of thy <hi>teeming Braine</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Cals me not UNCLE; yet let me obtaine</l>
         <l>The <hi>Nurses</hi> usuall freedome, to embrace it,</l>
         <l>And shew it my best <hi>love,</hi> though 'twill not grace it</l>
         <l>For though new borne, <hi>it</hi> speakes as if <hi>it</hi> were</l>
         <l>The Sonne of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> or <hi>Vlysses</hi> Heyre.</l>
         <l>Thy <hi>worth</hi> to praise, were fitter <hi>Homers</hi> Quill</l>
         <l>Then my rude <hi>Verse;</hi> yet here accept my will.</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>S. WILLIAMOT.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb n="12" facs="13"/>
      <head>To my ever loving friend Mr. <hi>LEWES ROBERTS Merchant,</hi> upon his <hi>MAP of COMMERCE.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>THough many know much; yet we seldome finde</l>
         <l>Spirits so free, and profitably kinde,</l>
         <l>T'impart what or the industry, or sweat</l>
         <l>Of a whole <hi>Life-time,</hi> could observe, or get;</l>
         <l>Like cunning STATISTS enviously prone</l>
         <l>To keepe all <hi>Secrets</hi> of their <hi>Art</hi> unknowne;</l>
         <l>Out of a feare that some (lesse-witted) may</l>
         <l>(Meeting their <hi>Rules)</hi> become as wise as they.</l>
         <l>But friend, thy <hi>Candor's</hi> such, I dare acquit</l>
         <l>Thee of that malice, by thy labour'd <hi>Writt:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And must commend thy <hi>judgement</hi> too, in <hi>this,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That fix'd thy <hi>Fame</hi> on such a <hi>Piramis,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>As, (but the WORLD) 't had mist a <hi>Basis,</hi> great</l>
         <l>And vast enough, whereon to plant <hi>its</hi> seat:</l>
         <l>And, (if my <hi>Word</hi> may passe) this <hi>glori's Thine,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Men <hi>sayle</hi> by all MAPPES, but must <hi>thrive</hi> by <hi>Thine.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>W. Lewis.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="dedication">
      <head>To his deare Brother in law, Mr. <hi>Lewes Roberts,</hi> Merchant, <hi>on his MAP OF COMMERCE.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>SHould I write in thy <hi>praise,</hi> it would bee thought</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Friends</hi> will <hi>commend,</hi> although the <hi>Worke</hi> be nought;</l>
         <l>No, I will leave it to each READERS mind,</l>
         <l>To judge the WORKE as hee the <hi>worth</hi> shall find:</l>
         <l>And if they say this MAPP is not <hi>done well,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Bid him that blames <hi>it,</hi> bring <hi>its parallel.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>R. HILL.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <head>To my most deare Father <hi>Mr. LEWES ROBERTS</hi> Merchant.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>A Fathers <hi>love</hi> may well excuse</l>
         <l>The weaknesse of my <hi>Infant Muse,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Yet ('mongst the rest that praise thy <hi>Pen)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>As last admit mee say,<hi>—Amen.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>GABRIEL ROBERTS.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>