<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The vtilitie of this Story.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122167_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A67922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11225</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122167</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The vtilitie of this Story.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Actes and monuments of matters most speciall and memorable, happenyng in the Church : with an vniuersall history of the same, wherein is set forth at large the whole race and course of the Church, from the primitiue age to these latter tymes of ours, with the bloudy times, horrible troubles, and great persecutions agaynst the true martyrs of Christ, sought and wrought as well by heathen emperours, as novve lately practised by Romish prelates, especially in this realme of England and Scotland. Newly reuised and recognised, partly also augmented, and now the fourth time agayne published and recommended to the studious reader, by the author (through the helpe of Christ our Lord) Iohn Foxe, which desireth thee good reader to helpe him with thy prayer</title>
                 <author>Foxe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 305, 307-373, 373-1221, 1223-2110, 2112-2154, 32 pages, 5 woodcut inserts, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>The vtilitie of this Story.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eyng the worlde is replenished with such an infinite multitude of bookes of all kinde of matters, I may séeme (perhaps) to take a matter in hand superfluous and needles, at this present to set out such Uolumes, especially of hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, considering now a dayes the world is so greatly pestered, not only with su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous plenty therof, but of all other treatises, so that books now seeme rather to lacke Readers,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Multitude of bookes lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
      </note> then Readers to lacke bookes: In which multitude of bookes I doubt not, but many doe both perceiue, and inwardly bewayle this insatiable bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of many now a dayes both in writing and printing, which to say the truth, for my part I do as much lament as any man els beside: and would therefore no man should thinke that vnaduisedly or with rashnes I haue attempted this enterprise, as one being not onely doubtful, but also both bashfull and feareful within my self for setting the same abroad. And why? first I perceaued howe learned this age of ours is in reading of bookes, neither could I tell what the secret iudgementes of readers woulde conceaue, to see so weake a thing, to set vpon such a weighty enterprise, not sufficiently furnished with such ornamentes able to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the perfection of so great a story, or sufficient to serue the vtility of the studious: and the delight of the learned. Which abilitie the more I perceiued to be wanting in me, the lesse I durst be bold to become a writer.</p>
   <p>But agayne on the other side, when I weyed with my selfe what memorable Actes and famous doynges this latter age of the Churche hath ministred vnto vs by the patient suffringes of the worthy martyrs: I thought it not to be neglected, that so precious Monumentes of so many matters, meet to be recorded and regestred in books, should lie buried by my default vnder darkenes of obliuion. Me thought somewhat was to be sayd of them for their well deseruing, and something agayne of our partes for benefites by them receaued. But aboue all other thinges nothing did so much styrre me forward hereunto, as the dilligent consideration and speciall regard of the common vtilitie which euery man plentifully may receaue by the reading of these Monuments or Martyrologe which histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as I haue taken in hand chiefly for the vse of the English Church: so haue I framed it in that tongue which the simple people could best vnderstand.</p>
   <p>Nowe if men commonly delite so much in other Chronicles which intreate onely vpon matters of pollicye, and reioyce to beholde therein the variable euentes of worldlye affayres, the Stratagemes of valiaunt captaynes, the terrour of foughten fieldes, the sacking of Cities, the hurlye burlies of Realmes and people. And if men thinke it such a gaye thing in a common wealth to committe to history such olde antiquities of thinges prophane and bestow all theyr ornamentes of wit and eloquence in garnishing the same: how much more then is it meete for Christians to conserue in remembraunce the liues: Actes and doynges, not of bloudy warriours, but of myld and constant Martyrs of Christ, which serue not so much to delight the eare, as to garnish the lyfe, to frame it with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of great profite, and to encourage men to all kinde of Christian godlines? As first by reading thereof wee may learne a liuely testimony of Gods mighty working in the life of man, contrary to the opinion of <hi>Atheistes,</hi> and all the whole nest of <hi>Epicures.</hi> For like as one sayd of <hi>Harpalus</hi> in times past, that his doyngs gaue a liuely testimony agaynst God, because he being so wicked a man escaped so long vnpunished: so contrariwise in these mē we haue a much more assured and playne witnes of God both in whose liues and deathes appeared suche manifest declarations of Gods diuine working, whiles in such sharpnes of tormentes we behold in them strength, so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant aboue mans reach, such readines to aunswere, such patience in imprisonment, suche godlines in forgeuing, cherefulnes so couragious in suffering, besides the manifold sense and feeling of the holy ghost which they in their liues so plentifully tasted in theyr afflictions,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Comparison be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene worldly soldiours and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> the soldiours of Christ.</hi>
      </note> as in readyng of theyr letters euidently we may vnderstand. Ouer and besides this, the milde deaths of the sayntes do not a little auayle to the stablishing of a good conscience: to learne the contempt of the world, and to come to the feare of God. Moreouer, they confirme fayth, encrease godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, abate pride in prosperitie, and in aduersitie do open an hope of heauenly comfort. For what man reading the misery of these godly persons, may not therein as in a glasse behold his owne case, whether hee be godly or godles. For if God geue aduersitie vnto good men, what may eyther the better sort promise themselues, or the euill not feare? And whereas by reading of prophane storyes we are made perhaps more skilfull in warlike affayres: so by reading of this we are made better in our liuinges, and besides are better prepared vnto like conflictes, if by Gods permission they shall happen hereafter more wiser by theyr doctrine, and more steadfast by theyr example.</p>
   <p>To be short, they declare to the world what true Christian fortitude is, and what is the right way to conquere which standeth not in the power of man, but in hope of the resurrection to come, and is nowe I trust at hand. In consideration whereof, me thinkes I haue good cause to wish, that like as other subiectes: euen so also Kinges and Princes, which commonly delite in heroicall stories, would diligently peruse such Monumentes of martyrs, and lay them alwayes in sight, not alonely to read, but to follow, and would paynt them vpon theyr walles, cups, ringes and gates. For doubtles suche as these: are more worthy of honour thē an hundreth <hi>Alexanders, Hectors, Scipions</hi> and warlike <hi>Iulies.</hi> And though the world iudgeth prosperously of thinges, yet with God the true iudge, certes such are to be reputed in deede, not that kill one an other with a weapon, but they which being rather killed in Gods cause, do retayne an inuincible constancie agaynst the threates of tyrantes and violence of tormentours. Such as these, are the true Conqueroures of the world, by whome we learne true manhoode, so many as fight vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Christ, and not vnder the world. With this valiantnes did that most milde Lambe and inuincible Lyon of of the tribe of <hi>Iuda</hi> first of all go before vs, of whose vnspeakeable fortitude we heare this prophetical admiration: <hi>who is this</hi> (sayth he) <hi>which walketh so in the multitude of hys strength</hi>?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esay.</hi> 63.</note> Forsooth the high sonne of the high God, once conquered of the world, and yet conquering the world after the same maner he was conquered.</p>
   <p>The like daunce did all hys other Martyrs follow, to whome the auncient antiquitie of the Churche did attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute so great honour, as neuer king or Emperour could purchase in this world with all theyr images, pillers hie spires, triumphes, temples, and all theyr solemne feastes. In probation whereof we see with what admiration, and almost superstition, not onely the memory, but also the reliques of those good Martyr's were receaued &amp; kept amongest the auncient Christians. We haue also for witnes the learned Hymnes and Songes of <hi>Prudentius</hi> and <hi>Nazienzene,</hi> wherewith <hi>Pindarus</hi> did neuer so much set out hys triumphes of <hi>Olympia</hi> and <hi>Nemea.</hi> I neede not here rehearse the learned Orations of eloquent <hi>Cyprian, Chrysostome, Ambrose.</hi> and <hi>Hierome,</hi> who neuer shewed theyr eloquence more, then when they fell into the commendations of the Godly Martyrs?</p>
   <p>Whereby it is manifest, what estimation in times past was attributed to Martyrs: with what gratulation, reioyce, myrth, and common ioy the afflictions of those godly, dying in Christes quarrell, were sometime receiued
<pb facs="23"/>
and solemnised, and that not without good reasonable cause. For the Churche did well consider howe much she was beholding to theyr benefites, by whose death she vnderstoode her treasurés to encrease. Now then if Martyrs are to be compared with Martyrs, I see no cause why the Martyrs of our tyme deserue any lesse commendation, then the other in the primatiue Churche, which assuredly are inferiour vnto them in no poynt of prayse: whether we view the number of them that suffered, or greatnes of theyr formentes, or theyr constancie in dying, or also consider the fruite that they brought to the amendment of posteritie, and encrease of the Gospell. They did water the truth with theyr bloud,<note place="margin">
         <hi>A comparison betweene the Martyrs of the Primitiue Church and of the latter Church.</hi>
      </note> that was newly springing vp: so these by theyr deathes restored it agayne, being sore decayed and fallen downe. They standing in the forewarde of the battell, did receaue the first encounter and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of theyr enemies, and taught vs by that meanes to ouercome such tyranny. These with like courage agayne like old beaten souldiours did winne the field in the rereward of the battayle. They like famous husbandmen of the world did sow the fieldes of the Church, that first lay vnmanured and wast: these with fatnes of their bloud did cause it to battell and fructifie. Would to God the fruite might be speedely gathered into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arne, whiche onely remayneth behinde to come.</p>
   <p>Now, if we ascribe such reputation to Godly preachers (and worthely) which diligently preache the Gospell of Christ, when they liue notwithstanding by the benefite of tyme, without all feare of persecution: howe muche more reasonable cause haue we to prayse and extoll such men as stoutly spend theyr lyues for the defence of the same? All these premisses duely of our partes considered and marked, seeing we haue found so famous Martyrs in this our age, let vs not fayle then in publishing and setting forth their doings, lest in that poynt we seeme more vnkinde to them, then the writers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> primitiue Church were vnto theirs. And though we repute not theyr ashes chaynes, and swerdes in the stede of reliques▪ yet let vs yeld thus much vnto theyr commemoration, to glory the Lord in hys Saintes, and imitate theyr death (as much as we may) with like constancy, or theyr liues at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> least with like innocency. They offered theyr bodies willing, to the rough handling of the tormentors. And is it so great a matter then for our part, to mortifie our flesh, with all the members thereof? They neglected not onely the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and glory of the world for the loue of Christ, but also their liues: and shal we then keepe so great a styrre one agaynst an other, for the transitory trifles of this world? They continued in patient suffering, when they had most wrong done vnto them, and when theyr very heartes bloud gushed out of theyr bodyes: and yet will not wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue our poore brother, be the iniury neuer so small, but are ready for euery trifling offence to seeke hys destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cut his throat. They wishing well to all men, did of theyr own accord forgeue theyr persecutors: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought we, which are now the posteritie and Children of Martyrs, not to degenerate from theyr former steps, but being admonished by their examples, if we cannot expresse theyr charitie toward all men, yet at lest to imitate the same to our power and strength. Let vs geue no cause of offence to any. And if any be geuen to vs, let vs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome it with patience, forgeuing and not reuenging the same. And let vs not onely keepe our handes from shedding of bloud, but our tongues also from hurting the same of others. Besides, let vs not shrinke if case so require, martyrdome or losse of lyfe, according to their example, to yeld vp the same in the defence of the Lordes flocke. Whiche thing if men would do, much lesse contention and busines woulde be in the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen now is. And thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the vtilitie and fruit to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of this history.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>