<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122018_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08216</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18550</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122018</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Comoedia : A worke in ryme, contayning an enterlude of myndes, witnessing the mans fall from God and Christ. Set forth by HN, and by him newly perused and amended. Translated out of Base-almayne, into English</title>
                 <author>Niclaes, Hendrik</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bohmberg (van Bohmbergen), Nikolaus, pseud.?</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Cologne</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface</head>
   <head type="sub">To the good-willing Reader; whose Heart and Thoughts, loueth Spirit and Lyfe; be Health and Saluation.</head>
   <p n="1">BEholde and consider, how that now in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> last Tyme, the Loue is appeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vppon the Earth with her Safemak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-seruice / to the Lyfe of Men, in the Godlynes: also com vnto vs Little and Humbleones, for to minister thesame: and how that{reversed ;}
<note place="margin">☜</note>in the Beleeuing and Obeying of the Requyring of thesame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Loue; the verytrue
<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.8.b</note> Light of Lyfe, and the vpright Beeing of <hi>Iesu Christ,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> risen-vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs
<note n="b" place="margin">2. Corin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.a.</note> in our Hearts. With the which, and in the which / the vpright Beeing of the pure
<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 22.c. Luk. 1.f. Eph. 1.4.b.</note> Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes of God the Father the vpright Beeing of the true Ioye and
<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 2 b.</note> Peace of <hi>Iesu Christ</hi> the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Beeing of the true euerlasting Lyfe of the Loue or holy Gost and the vpright Beeing of our inwarde Mynde, is likewyse {reversed ;}by Gods Grace; inherited of vs.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> Through which Grace that is thus chaunced vnto vs from the vncouered
<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.b 2. Cor. 3.b.</note> Face of God and <hi>Christ,</hi> wee doo {reversed ;}through the Loue and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyring of her Seruice; call and bydd all Louers of thesame vpright Beeing,
<note n="f" place="margin">Math. 22.a. Luk. 14.b</note> therunto / for that they mought all {reversed ;}through the Requnring of our gracious Seruice of Loue; enter into the verytrue
<note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 31.d. Heb 5.10 c</note> Sainetnary of thesame vpright Beeing and so
<pb facs="3"/>haue their fellowshipp with Vs. For through thatsame Sainctuary of God {reversed ;}being com vnto vs in the Spirit; wee
<note n="h" place="margin">1. Ioh 1.a.</note> haue our fellowshipp with God the Father with the Lorde <hi>Iesu Christ</hi> and with the Holy Gost and all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Holyones of God, in the Kingdom of the Heauenly Beeing
<note n="i" place="margin">Apost. 12.21.a.</note> full of all Bewty of the Spirituall and heauenly Goodes. Of which Kingdom also, wee do publish a ioyeful
<note n="k" place="margin">Mar. 14.b Apo 14.2.</note> Message, to the Spreeding-abrode of thesame, in all the Worlde / for a Testimony vnto all People, that the Coming of thesame vpright and verytrue Beeing, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Consummation</hi> [namely, the Whole Somme or Fulfilling] of all Thatt / which is
<note n="l" place="margin">Act 3 c. Ephe. 1.b.</note> written touching the Godlynes in <hi>Iesu Christ.</hi> and touching the Daye of the Declaring of all thesame.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> For thissame Daye
<note n="m" place="margin">Mal. 4.a.</note> of the great Light from Heauen {reversed ;}wherin it is all declared and brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Vs, what soeuer is of God and of <hi>Christ;</hi> is the true Daye of Loue / which the God of Heauen hath heertofore / when Hee commanded all Men, in euery Quarter / to Repent, appoynted to be a
<note n="n" place="margin">Act. 17.c.</note> Day of his Iudgment: and hath also {reversed ;}out of his Grace and mercifull Loue / towardes all People that haue a desyer to doo his Will; made-knowen vnto Vs with thesame / the first
<note n="o" place="margin">Math. 3.2.16 c. Luk. 13.14.c. Act. 2.3.c.</note> Entrance into the peaceable Waye
<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 4 h. Mat 19 e.</note> that reacheth to the euerlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyfe. and the verytrue Trueth of God,
<note n="q" place="margin">Iohn. 8.c</note> that maketh free: and nakedly declared the euerlasting Lyfe, as a verytrue Light of vpright Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and brought the Sweetnes of the louely Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God vnto Vs, in all Loue / wherby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>now likewyse in the last tyme / Gods vpright Righteousnes / vnto the Goodwillingones: and {reversed ;}in the Requyring of the Loue; to make all that knowen
<note n="r" place="margin">Ephe 3.a. Colo. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> vnto them, which extendeth ther-vnto.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> Forasmuch now therfore / as that this Daye of the great Light from Heauen, is com vnto Vs, in the Obeying of the Requyring of the Loue / so perceaue wee now also in thesame Daye, and it shall likwyse in thesame, becom knowen {reversed ;}in the Spirit; vnto all Louers of the Trueth, that ther is no Waye / easyer, more peaceable, nor ioyfull to walke-in, then the Waye of Peace / which vnder the Obedience of the Loue, is taught
<note n="s" place="margin">Esa 2.a. Luk. 1.g.</note> and poynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed - on out of the gracious Woorde of the Lorde (but yet is it loued of Fewe: and much lesse knowen and
<note n="t" place="margin">Math. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> walked-in:) neither-yet also that ther-is any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, more sweete or louely, then the Lyfe of the Loue, which proceedeth out of God, and that is inherited in the Seruice of Loue: yet is thesame {reversed ;}through Ignorance; disdayned of Many. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>that-cause it remayneth likewyse couered
<note n="v" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.b.</note> or hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den before Many.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> Which Misunderstanding, or ignorant
<note n="x" place="margin">Ephe. 4.b</note> Blyndnes, the Man hath inherited / decause that hee is more inclyned to the
<note n="y" place="margin">Esa. 59.b. Rom. 5.b.</note> Estrainging from his God and to the Declyning from the Requyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Loue / then to liue in his God or to be obedient vnto him in the gracious Woorde of his Loue. For-that-cause also, the Man loueth much-more, his vayne and corrupted Lyfe, which hee himself taketh-on {reversed ;}the which notwith standing is nothing but
<note n="z" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>9.a.</note> troublesom and deadly vnto him;
<pb facs="4"/>then the louely Lyfe of Peace, wherunto God
<note n="a" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.a.</note> hath cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ated and loued the Man: and so hee cleau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth-vnto or followeth much-more, his taken-on knowledg,
<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1.c. Colo. 2.c.</note> Self-wisdom, and manly Learning / proceeding out of the Flesh / then the Trueth of Lyfe, which is witnessed
<note n="c" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Pet. 1.c.</note> out of the Mouth of God, or brought-forth by God.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> BVt the greatest Darknes and erring Blyndnes, wherwith the Man is most<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all captiued is this: That hee himself taketh-on
<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1.c.</note> a knowledg so arrogantly / and so perswadeth himself, that hee vnoweth somthing of the godly Things / ereuer that God
<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 14.c.</note> with his <hi>Christ</hi> / haue his Dwelling or a liueing
<note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 4.c.</note> Foorme in him: For veryly / all the Mans Knowledg and Vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, together with all his Descerning or Perceau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Trueth / ought to stand
<note n="g" place="margin">Ephe. 3.c.</note> grounded in the liuing God and in his <hi>Christ</hi> or woorde of Lyfe: and not to take on him / any-maner of Knowledg of the godly Things / without God or his <hi>Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7.</hi> But seeing now, that it standeth not so with many Men: as also that they do not {reversed ;}vnder the Obedience of the Loue; giue-ouer themselues good-willingly to the Incorporation
<note n="h" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hn. 15. Rom. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.a.</note> vnto God and <hi>Christ,</hi> nor-yet stand submitted therunto: but that they all for the most part / do respect and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their owne goodthinking
<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>9 Ier. 7 9 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.13 18.</note> Knowledg / for the Trueth / Therfore is likewyse all the Knowled and Discerning therof / proceeding out of the Lye, and out of the Deuill / 
<note n="k" place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> the Father of Lyes: and
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>all their Wayes that they walke in / 
<note n="l" place="margin">Sap. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> are meere Errour and Darknes.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8.</hi> THerfore is the goodthinking Knowledg of the Trueth, or the knowledg of the godly Things ▪that one taketh on him / without the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Moorde or the Incorporating to thesame / or
<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> before the Appeering or Comming of <hi>Iesu Christ</hi> and of the Kingdom of God; the most hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Spirit
<note n="n" place="margin">act. 12.13.17.</note> of the false Prophets / which sedu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceth the Man most-of-all, and bringeth him into Errour: and maketh him biynde touching the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Vnderstanding of God, and touching the true Discerning of the Lyfe and of the euerlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Trueth.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <hi>9.</hi> For ther-through the Man turneth himself awaye from the right Waye of the louely and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lyfe and Peace: and hee falleth or strayeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a By-waye of the vngodly and deadly Beeing: wherin ther cometh vnto him, manye
<note n="o" place="margin">Esa 59. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Sap. 5.a.</note> Troubles and Calamities, many Miseries, Paynes, and greefs of Heart, and many Afflictions and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered Thoughts, all which do stretch to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction: and so hee walketh in the
<note n="p" place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> tedious Wayes, which are full of Darknesse, and do leade to the
<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 7.b.</note> Condemnation.</p>
   <p n="10">
      <hi>10.</hi> O Yee Deerly-beloued, seeing now that I / through the Light of Lyfe {reversed ;}which is apeered
<note n="r" place="margin">2. Cot. 4.a.</note> in my Heart / out of the heauenly Trueth; do see and percaeue all the Mans Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitee and Misery,
<note n="s" place="margin">Esa. 13.a. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and all the Aduersitee that is comming vppon him [namely, through his Blyndnes and erring Darknes, and through all
<pb facs="5"/>the Vnquietnes and Misunderstanding,
<note n="t" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>om. 7.b.</note> wheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>under hee {reversed ;}through his taken-on Knowledg; is captiued and bounde, and wherunto he hath ▪wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; geeuen-ouer himself] So am I greatly moued with Compassion towardes the erring Man / for his ignorant Blyndnes cause / and very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much troubled and combred in my Heart, about him: and haue for-that-cause {reversed ;}to thend that I mought happly by som meanes, bring him to
<note n="y" place="margin">Esa. 59.b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 3.c.</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Knowing of himself, and of his Errour; witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and figured-out, and setfoorth in Ryme ▪euen out of harty Loue; this Inuention of an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude / of the Mans Fall, of his Errour, and of the taking-on of his Owne-wills Chooseing / for that hee, or eneryone that heareth or readeth thesame / shoulde ▪ther-through; euidenly vnderstande and consider, which is the cause of the Mans Vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and what Vanitee or Foolishnes, the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men do take-on of themselues, to their great Burdening: and wherwith they do bring themselues into muth Calamitee and Greefe against one-another. All the which / is playnly shewed and testifyed ▪in enterlude-maner; in this Inuencion of a Playe of Myndes.</p>
   <p n="11">
      <hi>11.</hi> Concerning which Inuention of thissame Plane: wheerin small clerckly-skyll is sheewed; I shall desyer of the good-willing Reader / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hee will not stumble therat, because thesame is so playne a Worke: nor - yet reiect or dispise {reversed ;}therfore; the groundly Signification or the <hi>Substance</hi> therof.</p>
   <p n="12">
      <hi>12.</hi> For it is not brought-foorth or witnessed / for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>howe or commendaeion of artificiall Skill of
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>Rethorick: but much-rather / 
<note n="x" place="margin">Ephe. 4.a</note> to further all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde in the Loue / for to shewe euenso through the same Playe, how that the Children of Men haue turned them awaye from the louely
<note n="y" place="margin">Sap. 1.b.</note> Lyfe of the Kingdom of God / and from the
<note n="z" place="margin">Gal. 3.a.</note> Trueth of <hi>Iesu Christ:</hi> and how that they like wyse, are turned vnto themselues seduced
<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 1.c. Ephe. 4.b.</note> by their owne Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg blynded in their Vnderstanding and {reversed ;}tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Vnregarding, and Good-thinking; are falne into much Diuision and many Errours. Because that they shoulde then {reversed ;}through the Knowing of their Estrainging from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; turne them agayne vnto God, and to the Kingdom of God and his
<note n="b" place="margin">Esa. 1.e. 55 Ier. 3.4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Eze. 18.33. Ioel. 2.e</note> Righteousnes and liue in all Loue and Peace.</p>
   <p n="13">
      <hi>13.</hi> WHerfore {reversed ;}yee Deerly-beloued; haue a good regarde to the Intent and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentation of thissame Playe: and note well / how that the Fall of Man, and his Distruction, as likewyse his Opinion or Good-thinking / is witnessed and shewed in thesame Playe (as well in the Wisdom of his Scripture-learnednes, as in his Playnes or Simplenes) so shall yee then {reversed ;}with small labour; vnderstande or perceaue / how that the
<note n="c" place="margin">Esa. 5.c. Ier. 7.11.c 13.a.</note> Goodthinking hath {reversed ;}with his Misunderstanding; gotten the Superioritee, and raigneth euery wheare, ouer the Children of Men: euen as well ouer the Wyse of the Worlde
<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 12.15.23. 1. Cor. 1. Act. 7.22.23.24.</note> and Scripture-learnedones {reversed ;}which bost them of the Knowledge of the Trueth, and of the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Vnverstanding; as ouer
<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 5.a.</note> the Little and
<pb facs="6"/>Simpleones, or Ignorant-sort / which must be ledd, taught, and instructed.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <hi>14.</hi> Now when ye haue looked into and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood all thissame / so may ye then likewyse / see and vnderstand rightly and according to the Trueth / by what meanes the
<note n="f" place="margin">Esa 59 b.4. Esd. 6 c 14.b.</note> Trueth of God hath remayned so vnknowen and in secret among the Children of Men the vpright
<note n="g" place="margin">Math. 24.</note> Loue, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en so colde, among many the true Gighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / so vtterly forsaken and the Vnitee of Peace or all Concord and Loue / bin so rent, broken, or deuided: and by what Middlewall it cometh-to-pas / that all the Worlde is so full of Falshod: and that also therthrough / all Hipocrisye,
<note n="h" place="margin">Oze 4 a Rom. 1 c.</note> Lyes, and Deceit / and all Slaundering, Enuye, Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye, and subtill Falshood, with al-maner of Vnrighteousnes, is com-in
<note n="i" place="margin">4. Es 14.b Mat. 24.b.</note> and beareth-swaye ouer the whole Worlde.</p>
   <p n="15">
      <hi>15.</hi> By meanes wherof likewyse / many good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing Heartes and Louers of the Trueth, are falne into great Greef-of mynde: and that cheef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because then do euidently see the Abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and the Confused-estate, the Errours, and the Distruction of Men / and yet vnderstand not from whence the Corruptions are com / nor how they are to be amended / or how the Children of Men are to be ridd from them. The which Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding {reversed ;}to the Reformation of all Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; is taught and inherited, in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyaltie of the Loue of <hi>Iesu Christ,</hi> and in the mostholy Seruice of thesame.</p>
   <p n="16">
      <hi>16.</hi> And now, for to open, out of the mostholy
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>Seruice of the Loue of <hi>Iesu Christ;</hi> the right Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of thatt wherof is spoken / so haue wee brought-foorth and set-out this Mytered<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of the spirituall Vnderstanding {reversed ;}to a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceablenes, for the Louers of the Trueth, and for the Disciples of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Loue / as also for all young Youth, that submytt them vnder the Loue and her Seruice / wherby to procure in them all; with thissame; a Delytfull-likeing towardes the true Beeing: and for that they shoulde all likewyse / recreate themselues one-with-another / in the Knowledg
<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Ephe. 1.c.4.b.</note> of the godly Trueth: Also for to witnesse and bring-to-light euery wheare {reversed ;}in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Playe; the Lyfe of the inwarde Kingdom of God (the which is a
<note n="l" place="margin">Iohn. 1.2.</note> Light / that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared from the Beginning, to be a Lyfe vnto the Man) or the Knowledg of thesame: As likewyse to discouer ther-through, the Mans Foolishnes, and his cleauing to the Danitee. And how that hee; through his owne good-thinking Wisdom; is captiued, and becometh yet dayly captiued with thesame.</p>
   <p n="17">
      <hi>17.</hi> BEsydes this, wee haue also, to a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Recreating of the good-willing Heartes; ordayned in Myter, certen effectuall Refraynes and Rondels / as likewyse an A. B. C. / the tenn Commaundementes of God / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Twelue Articl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of the Christian-fayeth / with also certen good Lessons and Prayers: and haue likewyse set-foorth certen Canticles or Songes / to thend to drawe all young Youth somuch-the-more-willingly to the Obedience of the Requyring of the
<pb facs="7"/>Seruice of Loue / because that they all which loue the Trueth / mought stedfastly beleeue the holy and godly Vnderstanding / that floweth out of the Heart of Loue and Mercy / and mought; in the Knowledg of the Requyring of God; be illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated with the Light of the louely Cleernes of thesame Vnderstanding: and also that all those (which; out of a good meaning; are yet in Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and haue fastened or seduced themselues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a strainge Foundation, with-out our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munialtee of Loue) mought com to a Discerning or Knowledg of themselues turne them to God and his mercifull
<note n="m" place="margin">Esa. 55.a Ezec. 18.d Ioel. 2.b.</note> Loue and submytt them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diently / to the Requyring of the Seruice of Loue / wherby to be taught then, in the holy and godly Vnderstanding of the Loue, and to becom vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in the
<note n="n" place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Mistery of the Kingdom of God / and to comprehende with holy Vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing / from whence, and in what an vpright Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing / the Kingdom of God appeereth or cometh vnto vs.</p>
   <p n="18">
      <hi>18.</hi> For the Coming of the
<note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 17.c</note> Kingdom of God, cometh not to pas with outward Apparance / as that men may saye: Lo, heere
<note n="p" place="margin">Math. 24.</note> or theare it is. For beholde: The Kingdom of God and the Lyfe of the heauenly Beeing, is inwardly
<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> with in Vs. Those which haue
<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 13. Luk. 8.a.</note> Eares to heare, let them heare: and whoso hath Mysdom, let him take-holde of Vnderstanding.</p>
   <p n="19">
      <hi>19.</hi> HEer-withall; as with an Assistance to the Loue, and to the Doctrine of her Seruice; O ye Louers of the Trueth / ye bee all
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>called and bidden, to the Grace of the liueing God to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cleernes of the Kingdom of Heauens and to the
<note n="s" place="margin">Luk. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1. Cor. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Table of <hi>Iesu Christ,</hi> or Supper of the
<note n="t" place="margin">Apo. 19 b.</note> Lambe / for to eate of the liuing
<note n="v" place="margin">Iohn. 6.c</note> Bread of Heauen, with God and his <hi>Christ,</hi> in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the God of Heauens / and to drinke the liueing Water
<note n="x" place="margin">Iohn. 4.b Esa. 55.a. Apo. 22.a.</note> of the holy Spirit of Loue: as also to liue eternally, with God and all his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyones.</p>
   <p n="20">
      <hi>20.</hi> The Power of the liueing Woorde, and the true Light of the holy Spirit of the Loue of <hi>Iesu Christ,</hi> vouchsafe to shyne about you all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer you from the
<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Death of Sinne seperat you from all Self-wysdom and Good-thinking leade you into the Obedience of the Requyring of the gracious Woord and his Seruice of Loue: and establish you in Gods Trueth / to thend that ye may rightly vnderstand and know / wherin the Saluation of Men, the vpright Lyfe, and the euerlasting Ioye and Rest, standeth comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or grounded.</p>
   <p n="21">
      <hi>21.</hi> Heer-vnto {reversed ;}yee Deerly-beloued; apply dil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently all your Hearts / that your Lyues
<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 15.b.</note> Rest, and your Ioye, maye be perfect.</p>
   <trailer>O Yea: that com-to-pas euenso.</trailer>
   <trailer>Amen:</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>