<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable, right Reue∣rend, right Worshipfull, or whatsoever he be or shall bee whom I hereafter may call Patron.</title>
           <author>Hausted, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122568_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72254</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12935</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122568</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable, right Reue∣rend, right Worshipfull, or whatsoever he be or shall bee whom I hereafter may call Patron.</title>
                 <author>Hausted, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rivall friends : A comoedie, as it was acted before the King and Queens Maiesties, when out of their princely favour they were pleased to visite their Vniversitie of Cambridge, upon the 19. day of March. 1631. Cryed downe by boyes, faction, envie, and confident ignorance, approv'd by the judicious, and now exposed to the publique censure, by the authour, Pet. Havsted Mr. in Artes of Queenes Colledge</title>
                 <author>Hausted, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Robinson, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right <hi>Honourable,</hi> right <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend,</hi> right <hi>Worshipfull,</hi> or whatsoever he be or shall bee whom I hereafter may call <hi>Patron.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou do'st deale with the <hi>crackt Chambermaid,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Or in <hi>stale Kinswomen</hi> of thine own do'st trade,</l>
   <l>With which <hi>additions</hi> thou do'st set to sale</l>
   <l>Thy <hi>Gelded Parsonages,</hi> or do'st prevaile</l>
   <l>With thy <hi>despayring Chaplaine</hi> to divide</l>
   <l>That which should be <hi>entire,</hi> for which beside</l>
   <l>Perhaps hee payes thee too, know that from thee</l>
   <l>(Beest thou <hi>Squire, Knight,</hi> or <hi>Lord,</hi> or a degree</l>
   <l>Aboue all these) nor I, nor yet my booke</l>
   <l>Does craue protection, or a gentle Looke:</l>
   <l>But if there be a man, (such men bee rare!)</l>
   <l>That 'midst <hi>so many sacrilegious,</hi> dare</l>
   <l>Be <hi>good</hi> and <hi>honest,</hi> though he be <hi>alone,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>With such a zeale, such a devotion,</l>
   <l>As th'old <hi>Athenians</hi> were wont to pay</l>
   <l>Vnto their <hi>vnknowne God,</hi> I here doe lay</l>
   <l>My <hi>selfe and booke</hi> before him, and confesse</l>
   <l>That such a <hi>Vertue</hi> can deserue no lesse.</l>
   <l>Reade it (faire Sir) and when thou shalt behold</l>
   <l>The <hi>Vlcers</hi> of the time by my too bold</l>
   <l>Hand brought to light, and <hi>lanch'd,</hi> and then shalt see</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Vice</hi> to his face <hi>branded</hi> and told <hi>that's hee,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Incircled safe in thine owne goodnesse sit,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>Vntouch'd by any line, and laugh at it.</l>
   <l>'Twas made to <hi>please,</hi> and had the <hi>vicious Age</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Beene <hi>good</hi> enough, it had not left the <hi>Stage</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Without it's <hi>due Applause:</hi> But since the <hi>times</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Now bring forth men <hi>enamour'd</hi> on their <hi>crimes,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And those the greater number, 'twere <hi>difeafe</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To thinke that any thing that <hi>bites</hi> should <hi>please.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Had it beene borne a <hi>toothlesse</hi> thing, though <hi>meane,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>It might haue <hi>past,</hi> nay might haue <hi>praysed</hi> beene:</l>
   <l>But being a <hi>Satyre</hi>— no. Such straines of Witt</l>
   <l>Are lik'd the <hi>worse,</hi> the <hi>better</hi> they are writ.</l>
   <l>Who euer knew one deepe in loue, commend</l>
   <l>A Song though ne're so good, so aptly pend,</l>
   <l>Set to the choycest note <hi>Musick</hi> affords,</l>
   <l>Sung by as choyce a <hi>Voice,</hi> if that the words</l>
   <l>Contained nothing else but a <hi>disgrace</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Vnto his Mistris and her <hi>borrowed face?</hi>
   </l>
   <l>O happy Age! ô wee are fallen now</l>
   <l>Vpon <hi>braue times,</hi> when my <hi>Lords wrinckled brow</hi>
   </l>
   <l>(Who perhaps labour'd in some <hi>crabbed Looke</hi>
   </l>
   <l>How to get farther into'th <hi>silk-mans booke,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Not <hi>minding</hi> what was <hi>done,</hi> or <hi>said</hi>) must stand</l>
   <l>A <hi>Coppy,</hi> and his <hi>Anticke</hi> front command</l>
   <l>The <hi>censure</hi> of the <hi>rest,</hi> to <hi>smile</hi> or <hi>frowne,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Iust as his <hi>squeesed</hi> face cryes <hi>vp</hi> or <hi>downe:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>When such as <hi>can judge right,</hi> and <hi>know</hi> the Lawes</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Comaedy,</hi> dare not <hi>approue,</hi> because</l>
   <l>My <hi>Ladies Woman</hi> did forget to bring</l>
   <l>Her Sp— and therefore swor't a <hi>tedicus thing.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>But <hi>(knowing Sir)</hi> rancke not your selfe with these</l>
   <l>That <hi>judge not</hi> as things <hi>are,</hi> but as they <hi>please.</hi>
   </l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Peter Hausted.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>