<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE LIFE OF ABRAHAM ORTELL, COSMOGRAPHER TO PHILIP THE SECOND, LATE KING OF SPAINE, written first in Latine by Francis Sweert of Antwerpe, his familiar and louing friend, and now translated into English by W. B, as great a louer of his learning and vertues.</title>
           <author>Styles, Christopher</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122301_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08536</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18855</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122301</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE LIFE OF ABRAHAM ORTELL, COSMOGRAPHER TO PHILIP THE SECOND, LATE KING OF SPAINE, written first in Latine by Francis Sweert of Antwerpe, his familiar and louing friend, and now translated into English by W. B, as great a louer of his learning and vertues.</title>
                 <author>Styles, Christopher</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Theatrum orbis terrarum Abrahami OrtelI Antuerp. geographi regii. = The theatre of the vvhole world: set forth by that excellent geographer Abraham Ortelius</title>
                 <author>Ortelius, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                            <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Norton, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Norton, John 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6 pages, 25, 25 par.-3 par, 26-42, 46-55, 55 par.-3 par 56-115 plates, 4 pages, ix plates, 2 pages, plates 'x', 2 pages, plates 'xj xij', 4 pages, xiij-xiiij plates, plates 'xv xvj', 2 pages, xvij-xxxiiij plates, 2 pages, xxxv-xl, 2 plates, 2 pages, 3 plates, 8 pages, portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="account">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE LIFE OF ABRAHAM ORTELL, COSMOGRAPHER TO PHILIP THE SECOND, LATE KING OF SPAINE, written first in Latine by <hi>Francis Sweert</hi> of Antwerpe, his familiar <hi>and louing friend, and now translated into English by</hi> W. B, <hi>as great a louer of his learning and vertues.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He stocke of the ORTELS flourished not long since, and liued in good state and credit at Auspurg in Bayern, (<hi>Augustam vindelicorum,</hi> the Latines called it.) From that family came WILLIAM ORTELL, who about the yere of our Lord 1460 left his natiue country, and seated himselfe in Antwerpe, (at that time one of the famousest Mart-townes of the world) where he did many notable things worthily deseruing great commendation: among which that is most memorable, that of his owne proper cost and charges he caused a goodly crosse of free stone to be set vp without the Emperours gate, in that place where the malefactours are vsually woont to be executed and put to death. Beneath this crosse, at the base or foot of the same, stood Mary and Iohn, and beside them, a little farther off, hung the two theeues; the one vpon the right hand and the other vpon the left, vpon their seuerall gibbets. This <hi>William</hi> died vpon the seuenth day of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary in the yeere of our Lord God 1511, and was buried in the cloisters of the Franciscane Friers in Antwerpe, leauing his sonne LEONARD ORTELL sole Executor, and heire, not only of his goods and substance, but also of his vertues and good qualities: For they report that he was a man so deuout and religious, that it was an hard matter to finde him from his booke, serious meditation on heauenly matters. This <hi>Leonard</hi> maried ANNA HER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVAYERS, and by her had issue two daughters, and one some named ABRAHAM, (whose life we heere pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to describe) borne vpon the second day of Aprill, in the yeere of our Lord God 1527. Hee was euen in his child-hood of singular towardnesse, great capacity and passing quicke conceit, and, that which is very strange in youth, hee was neuer giuen to the reading of any trifles or idle vanities. Wherefore his father purposing to make him a scholar, began first himselfe to instruct him priuatly at home in his owne house in the Latine and Greeke tongues: (For the old man was very learned in both these languages.) But see how these good purposes were soon crossed by the vntimely death of his most louing and kinde father! who departing this life, in the yeere of Christ 1535, left this his sonne to be further informed and taught abroade by strange schoolemasters, whose care and diligence to profit him, whatsoeuer their learning were, was nothing so great and painfull: notwithstanding euen vnder these he made such profit in the Artes and liberall Sciences, that he was not much inferiour to the best of his degree and time: For, as I said before, no vaine pleasure, or trifles, pastimes (which commonly are the ouerthrow of many yongue men) could euer with-draw him from his setled purpose, or alienate his minde from his booke. Yet his greatest delight and commendation consisted in the knowledge of the Mathematicall sciences, which for the most part he studied and practised without an instructor, or teacher, atteining, only by his owne paines and industrie, to the great admiration of others, euen to the vnderstanding of the greatest and deepest mysteries of the same. In the thirtieth yeare of his age, hauing many great matters in his head, and loathing to liue idly at home in his owne natiue country, he began to entertaine a conceipt of trauelling into diuers and sundry forreine parts and countries of the world. To Frankford vpon the Main, by reason of the great Marts or Faires, there held at two seuerall times euery yere, he went very often. In the yeere of our Lord 1575, he went with <hi>Iohn Viuian</hi> of Valence, a Marchant, but a great louer of learning, and <hi>Hierome Scoliers</hi> of Antwerp, to Leige, Trier; Tungren and Mentz: of which iourney and peregrination of theirs, there is at this day a booke of his exstant in print, wherein he hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly described the particulars obserued by them. In the yeere of Christ 1577, with <hi>Immanuël Demetrius</hi> of Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe, hee trauelled beyond the Seas, into England and Ireland. Italy, that nource of great wits, that worker of strange woonders, that mother of reuerend antiquities and ancient monuments, hee visited thrise. The third time that he went thither, which was in the yeere 1578, he went in company of <hi>George Houfnayle</hi> of Antwerp, who was so excellent a painter that he was greatly esteemed and beloued of the illustrious princes, <hi>Albert</hi> and <hi>VVilliam,</hi> Dukes of Bayern: of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> Duke of Austrich; yea and of <hi>Rudolphus</hi> himselfe, at that time Emperour of the Germanes. But this his consort, to the great greefe of his friends and such as loued his singular qualities, left his life at Prage in Bohemia, vpon the thirteenth of Ianuary in the yeere of our Lord, 1600. This man was woorthy of longer life, if the Fates would respect men for their great parts and excellent vertues. But so it is, that Death, like as the sythe in Haruest, cutteth downe, without distinction, aswell the yongue as old. There was nothing either in Germanie or in France, that was woorth the seeing, that this our authour had not seene and viewed with a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorious and iudicious eie. At length, hauing ouercome so many tedious and toilsome trauels, he returned againe to Antwerpe his natiue soile. There and then he began to apply himselfe to benefit succedent ages, to write of
<pb facs="3"/> those countries by him viewed and seene, to set out in Charts and Mappes diuers places both of Sea and Land vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to former ages, to describe the tracts and coasts of the East and West, South and North neuer spoken of nor touched by Ptolemey, Pliny, Strabo, Mela or any other historiographer whatsoeuer: and lastly to bend all his forces to the framing of that his THEATER, which now is beheld and read with such admiration and applause of all men: in which worke of his he was so generally well liked and approued of all, that Philip the Second, that renowmed King of Spaine, graced him with the honour and title of <hi>The Kings Cosmographer.</hi> He wrot also his GEOGRAPHICALL TREASVRE, a very learned and pleasant worke, in which the ancient names or appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, (yea and oft times the new, by which they are now called and knowen at this day,) of Mountaines, Hils, Promontories, Woods, Ilands, Hauens, People, Cities, Townes, Villages, Seas, Baies, Creekes, Straights, Riuers, &amp;c. are at one view instantly to be seene. Moreouer, out of ancient coines, for the benefit and delight of such as are louers and studious of antiquities, he set out The HEADS OF THE GODS AND GODDESSES, which afterward were illustrated with an historicall narration or discourse done by Francis Sweert the yonger. In the yeere of Christ 1596, he set forth THE IMAGE OF THE GOLDEN WORLD, that is, A treatise descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the life, Maners, Customes, Rites and Religion of the ancient Germans, collected and gathered out of diuers and sundry old writers of both languages. By these his labours and trauels he hath gotten and purchased vnto himselfe an immortall name and credit amongst the learned of all sorts. In company he was of an excellent dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete cariage, passing courteous, merry and pleasant. Such was his singular humanity, that it was strange to see how he did winne and retaine the loue and fauour of all men wheresoeuer he became. His enemies he chose rather to ouercome with kindnesse, or to contemne them then to reuenge himselfe of their malice. He did so much hate vice, euen in his owne kindred, that he rather reuerenced vertue in his enemies and strangers. Vaine questions, and subtill disputations of diuinity, or matters of religion, as dangerous and pernicious, hee did alwaies greatly detest and abhorre. A deepe in-sight and sound iudgment in any kinde of matter, he preferred before glosing elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and quaint termes. Present aduersity and daungers he alwaies endured with more patience then feare of such as were comming on and neere at hand: and those which were bitter, more easily then such as were doubtfull and vncertaine of euent. He was a man which in his life time did set as little by himselfe as any man could: For he neuer set his minde much vpon the wealth of this world, or ought of those things in the same, hauing alwaies in memory that his learned poesie CONTEMNO ET ORNO, MENTE, MANV, <hi>I scorne and trimme, with minde, with hand.</hi> For surely this man was led with some heauenly spirit, which did so with-draw his minde from those earthly cogitations, that he neuer tooke any thing in his life more vnkindly then when he was drawne from his bookes, which he alwaies preferred before all other things in the world beside. These great learned men follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were his familiar friends, and such as he did greatly loue and reuerence. In Spain <hi>Benedictus Arias Montanus,</hi> that great linguist and graue Diuine; and the reuerend father <hi>Andrew Schotte,</hi> borne in Antwerp, a learned Iesuite. In Italy, <hi>Fuluius Vrsinus, Franciscus Superantius,</hi> and <hi>Iohannes Sambucus.</hi> In Germany, <hi>Gerard Mercator,</hi> that famous Cos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mographer, <hi>Iames Monaw, Marke Velser, Ioachim Chamberlin, Ionas Grutterus</hi> of Antwerp, and <hi>Arnold Milius.</hi> In France, <hi>Petrus Pithoeus,</hi> and others. In the Low-countries, <hi>Iustus Lipsius, Laeuinus Tormencius, Nicolaus Rockoxius, Cornelius Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Balthasar Robianus, Ludouicus Perezius, Iohannes Brantius</hi> a ciuillian, recorder to the state of Antwerp, <hi>Iohannes Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> secretarie to the same city, <hi>Francis Raphalengius, Christopher Plantine, Iohn Moret, Philip Gally, Otho Venius</hi> that famous painter, and <hi>Francis Sweert</hi> the yonger. In England, <hi>Humfrey Lloyd,</hi> the only learned courtiour of his time, and <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Camden,</hi> now Clarenceux, the painfull and iudicious antiquary of our land. With all these and many other he was familiarly acquainted. To these he wrot often, and from these he often receiued most kinde and louing let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. He was a great student of antiquities, and searcher out of rare and ancient things. He had at home in his house, Images, Statues, Coines of Gold, Siluer and copper both of the Greeks, Romans and others: Shelfishes brought from India and our Antipodes: Marble of all kinde of colours: Torteises shelles of such wonderfull big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that tenne men, sitting round in a circle, might eate meat out of them at once: Others againe so little and narrow, that they were skarce so bigge as a pinnes head. His Library was so maruellously well stored with all sort of Bookes, that his house might iustly haue beene termed, A shoppe of all manner of good learning, vnto which men flocked from diuers places, like as in former times they did to Plato's Academy, or Aristotle's Lyceum. This <hi>Ernest</hi> and <hi>Albert,</hi> returning conquerour from the battaill at Hulsten, with other great Princes, and men of all sorts, came in troops to see and behold. While he was thus busied, and hauing now liued aboue threeskore and eleuen yeeres, he fell sicke in Iune in the yeere of our Lord 1598, and growing euery day worse and worse, at length, he yeelded to nature and died vpon the 28 day of the same moneth. The Physicians affirmed that he died of an vlcer of the reines, which Hippocrates writeth will hardly euer be cured in old men. He was of stature tall and slender; the haire of his head and beard was of a yealow colour. His eies were gray, and his forehead broad. He was very courteous and affable. In serious businesses he was very graue and sober, but without any shew of arrogant dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine: in mirth and iesting he was as pleasant, yet with that moderation, that all was guided by the rules of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian piety and modesty. This deceased bachelour, Anna Ortell, a virgine his sister, who liued not long after this her brother Abraham, (for she died in the yeere of Grace 1600) caused to be buried and intombed in Saint Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaëls, the Abby of the Praemonstratenses in Antwerp. He might well want the honour of a gorgeous and costly tombe, who by the generall consent of all men, had for his rare and singular vertues deserued an euerlasting fame and reputation. Francis Sweert, the yonger, gathered together the mournefull verses of those poets and friends of his, which did bewaile his death, set them foorth, and dedicated them to the State and citizens of Antwerp. Iustus Lipsius, at the instant request of his heires, and for a perpetuall memoriall of their constant loue and friendship wrote that Epitaph which is in capitall letters ingrauen vpon his tombe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>