<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Introduction.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122568_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72254</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12935</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122568</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Introduction.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rivall friends : A comoedie, as it was acted before the King and Queens Maiesties, when out of their princely favour they were pleased to visite their Vniversitie of Cambridge, upon the 19. day of March. 1631. Cryed downe by boyes, faction, envie, and confident ignorance, approv'd by the judicious, and now exposed to the publique censure, by the authour, Pet. Havsted Mr. in Artes of Queenes Colledge</title>
                 <author>Hausted, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Robinson, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Introduction.</head>
   <stage>Being a <hi>Dialogue</hi> betwixt <hi>Venus, Thetis,</hi> and <hi>Phoebus,</hi> sung by two Trebles, and a Base. <hi>Venus</hi> (being <hi>Phosphorus</hi> as well as <hi>Vesper</hi>) appearing at a window aboue as risen, calling to <hi>Sol,</hi> who lay in <hi>Thetis</hi> lap at the East side of the stage, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noped with an azure curtaine: at the first word that <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> sung, the curtaine was drawne, and they discovered.</stage>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>DRowsie Phoebus come away,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And let out the long'd for day,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Leaue thy Thetis silver breast,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And ope the casements of the East.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Tis Venus calls, away, away,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The waking mortals long for day.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Thetis.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>And let them long, tis just and right</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To shut them in eternall night,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Whose deeds deserue no day; lye still,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Arise not yet, lye still my Sun,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>My night begins when thou art gone.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>He wooe thee with a kisse to come away.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>And I with fourtie for to stay.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>I'le giue to thee the faire</hi> Adonis <hi>speare</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>So thou wilt rise:</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>And I to keepe thee here</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Will giue a wreath of pearle as faire</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>As ever Sea-Nymph yet did weare.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Tis Thetis wooes thee stay, O stay, O stay.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>Tis Venus wooes thee rise, O come away.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Phoebus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>To which of these shall I mine eare encline?</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>Vnto the vpper world repayre.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>O no, I'le binde him in my flowing haire.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Phoebus.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>But see fond Mortalls how they gaze</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>On that same pettie blaze?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Thetis <hi>adieu, I am no longer thine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>I must away, For if I stay,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>My Deity's quite undone,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They will forget t' adore the rising Sun.</hi>
      </l>
      <stage>
         <hi>Heere</hi> Phoebus <hi>arises from</hi> Thetis <hi>lap, and speakes.</hi>
      </stage>
      <l>But what new spectacle of wonder's this?</l>
      <l>And haue I lost my wonted <hi>Majestie</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Where with I use to strike a generall blindnesse</l>
      <l>Through all the <hi>Starres?</hi> unto what height of pride</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>Are they aspir'd, that thus with <hi>open</hi> eyes</l>
      <l>They dare <hi>out-face</hi> mee? Call out a powerfull raye</l>
      <l>And make those saucie sparkes confesse that all</l>
      <l>Their lustre is a debt they owe to me.</l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus sings.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>Gently, gently, God of light,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Profane not powers that are knowne</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To bee greater then thine owne:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Here is not a fire doth shine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>That is beholding unto thine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They are of</hi> themselues <hi>divine.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Phoebus speaks.</speaker>
      <l>And blesse them all the Gods. But how come I</l>
      <l>To be so blinde to day? so dull? so heavy?</l>
      <l>I know them now; Hayle fayrest <hi>Albions King,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Liue still the <hi>envie of the world;</hi> and thou</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Resplendent Goddesse,</hi> to view whose glorious face</l>
      <l>I haue oft times in my swift course stood still;</l>
      <l>Be all propitious to thy wish'd delights.</l>
      <l>And since ye haue vouchsaf'd your gracious presence</l>
      <l>Here at the <hi>Muses Groue,</hi> command their <hi>Patron,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Who here stands prest to serue yee.</l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus sings.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>Will hee obey?</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Phoeb. speaks.</speaker>
      <l>Or else let <hi>Daphne</hi> frowne,</l>
      <l>Or Phaeton resume my Chariot.</l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Venus sings.</speaker>
      <l>
         <hi>Then in their names I doe command thee heere</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lord of the yeere,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To entertaine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>This goodly Traine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Call backe that day of mine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The sprightly Valentine.</hi>
      </l>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Phoeb. speaks.</speaker>
      <l>Command me kill a <hi>Python,</hi> or recall</l>
      <l>The <hi>Lion</hi> or the <hi>Crabb:</hi> thou art too modest</l>
      <l>In thy requests; tis done, and for to add</l>
      <l>A greater honour to this day, behold</l>
      <l>I will recall those few spent minutes too</l>
      <l>Which haue runn out since I appear'd, I'le back,</l>
      <l>And fetch new rayes that amorous <hi>Valentine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>This morning may brighter then euer shine.</l>
      <stage>At Phoebus his going in, the Chorus sing these two last lines.</stage>
      <stage>
         <pb facs="7"/>
         <hi>After the</hi> Dialogue, <hi>enter a Boy.</hi>
      </stage>
      <p>Ha ha he, here be fine feats. (I hope we shall haue a ballad made o'nt before night) ha ha he, the Sun must lay aside all his busines, &amp; be at leasure (forsooth) to fetch back S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
         <hi>Valentines</hi> day for thē, ha ha he. In faith Gentlemen I pity ye, y'ar like to haue a goodly <hi>Comoedy</hi> here, <hi>Plautus</hi> his Captiues translated, or some such thing I warrant ye: why your Poet cannot endure a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and there are likely to be sweet raptures where the <hi>Muse</hi> is not <hi>amorous</hi> and <hi>sanguine.</hi> But let me see, now I think o'nt, Ile go fetch him out to ye, &amp; ye shall laugh at him most miserably, &amp; the Ladies too; troth do, he deserues it. He has hired me this <hi>Valentines</hi> morning, (for so ye must suppose it) to lead him out hood-winkt with a black scarf, into the fields, because he would not see a woman. But Gods me! what haue I forgot? I should haue had mine eares stretch'd for it if I had miss'd it. Yee must suppose the <hi>Scene</hi> too to be here in England at a country village. Some low homely slight stuffe 'twill be, I doubt: pray heavens he does not heare me. And here's an other dainty absurdity too (which I care not much if I tell yee) concerning their cloathes, which as far transcend the condition of the persons, as the court does the country. But that they hope the Court will excuse, for had it not bin here, they had bin forc'd (they say) to keepe the true <hi>decorum.</hi> But to my charge whom I left at the doore, till I had discover'd whether the coast were cleare. Come sir, now you may venture, you haue a prospect as barren as an Eunuches chin.— O me! why hee's run away. I'le be whipt if he has not smelt out my plot of exposing him to your view. — But heere comes the <hi>Prologue,</hi> he perhaps brings some newes of him; I'le leaue yee to censure his <hi>legs</hi> and <hi>cringes.</hi>
      </p>
      <stage>Exit Boy.</stage>
   </sp>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>