<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>R. VVilles Preface vnto the Reader, wherein is set downe a generall summe as it were of the whole worke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122069_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">649</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122069</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>R. VVilles Preface vnto the Reader, wherein is set downe a generall summe as it were of the whole worke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of trauayle in the VVest and East Indies, and other countreys lying eyther way, towardes the fruitfull and ryche Moluccaes : As Moscouia, Persia, Arabia, Syria, Ægypte, Ethiopia, Guinea, China in Cathayo, and Giapan: vvith a discourse of the Northwest passage... Gathered in parte, and done into Englyshe by Richarde Eden. Newly set in order, augmented, and finished by Richarde VVilles</title>
                 <author>Anghiera, Pietro Martire d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jugge, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 466, 6 leaves, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>R. VVilles Preface vnto the Reader, wherein is set downe a generall summe as it were of the whole worke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His greate and large bolume consisteth principally of foure partes, agreeable vnto those foure corners of the worlde, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the skilfull seamen and merchauntes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers of late yeeres haue chiefely tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled, and yet specially are wont to resorte. The first part conteyneth foure Decades, written by <hi>P. Martyr,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The first part, the first Decad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> a learned &amp; graue counseller of Charles the Emperour fifte of that name, concernyng the Spanyardes voyages Southwestwarde, &amp; theyr famous exploites doone in these newly discouered partes of the worlde, the whiche vsually wee now call the west <hi>Indies.</hi> Hereunto haue we added <hi>Gonza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Eerdinandus Ouiedus</hi> breefe historie touching the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, so that the first part of our volume hath fiue particular bookes. In the first whereof cap 1.2.3 4 and 5. <hi>P. Martir</hi> describeth <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbus</hi> first and second nauigations and discoueries of certaine Ilandes made by hym specially and his brother. In the 6. chapter or booke thereof (for both names we finde) is set foorth <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> third voiage, and the discouery of <hi>Peru,</hi> in the maigne west <hi>Indish</hi> lande. In the seuenth, his troubles both in the west <hi>Indies,</hi> and retourne into Spaigne with his brother, being both priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The 8. is of <hi>P. Alfonsus</hi> voyages that same way. In the 9. are declared the trauailes of <hi>Vincent</hi> and <hi>Peter Pinzoni,</hi> and other Spaniards likewise thither from <hi>Palos.</hi> The 10. is a conclusion of the whole Decade, with particuler mention of some special no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties, &amp; <hi>Colūbus</hi> fourth voiage beganne. So that in the first De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade you haue historically set downe the discouerye of the west <hi>Indies,</hi> taken in hande about the yeere of our Lorde .1492. by <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbus</hi> and his companions, vntill the yeere 1510. as <hi>P. Martir</hi> witnesseth fol. 8. 43 47. and 54. This worthy trauayler and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full seaman died at <hi>Validolid</hi> in Spaigne. <hi>An. dom.</hi> 1506. as <hi>Lopez</hi> reporteth cap. 25. in his generall historie <hi>de las Indias.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The second Decade conteyneth <hi>Peru</hi> matters,<note place="margin">The second Decade.</note> entituled by <hi>P. Martir, Creditus Cortinens,</hi> that is, a continent or maigne lande, as
<pb facs="8"/>
in deede it is of it selfe with the rest of <hi>America,</hi> in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as Europe, Affryk, &amp; Asia, be one continent or maigne lande vnited togeather. In the fyrst and seconde chapters of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade, shall you reade the voyages of <hi>Fogeda</hi> and <hi>Nicuesa,</hi> to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riena.</hi> In the thyrd, <hi>Colmenaris</hi> trauayles, <hi>Nicuesa</hi> his death, and the <hi>Indishe</hi> kyng <hi>Comogrus</hi> beneuolence: In the fourth, <hi>Vasquez Nunnez</hi> doynges in <hi>Vraba</hi> gulfe. His conquest of rebellious Barbarian kyngs in the fifte. In the syxt <hi>Quicedus</hi> &amp; <hi>Colmenaris</hi> ambassage out of <hi>Dariena</hi> to <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> and the religion of king <hi>Commendator</hi> in <hi>Cuba.</hi> The seuenth booke conteineth <hi>Petrus Arias</hi> iorney to <hi>Paria</hi> in <hi>Peru.</hi> The .8. the dissention betwixt the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes and Portugales for theyr boundes, and makyng of fyue Bishops in these newely founde partes of the worlde. In the 9 are shewed the ryuers of <hi>Darien,</hi> and philosophically the causes of so great waters there. That countrey is described in the .10 and the extreme hunger, abydden by the companions of <hi>Nicuesa,</hi> set forth.</p>
   <p>In the fyrst, second, and thyrd chapters of the thyrde Decade, is conteyned an abridgement of <hi>Vascus Nunnez</hi> relations,<note place="margin">The third Decade.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his voyage to the south sea, for it lyeth south from <hi>Darien,</hi> vsually termed nowe a dayes <hi>Mar del zur,</hi> and may also be called the wyde east Indyshe Ocean. The discouery thereof made by <hi>Nunnez,</hi> the kyng subdued by hym, especially kyng <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grus</hi> christenyng by the name of Charles, and the wynnyng of kyng <hi>Tumanama</hi> or <hi>Tubanama</hi> and his countrey. In the fourth chapter shal you fynd <hi>Columbus</hi> fourth vyage, began <hi>An. do.</hi> 1502 to the mayne west Indyshe lande, with the description of some part therof, lying betwyxt our Atlantike or westerne Ocean, and the aforesayde <hi>Mar del zur,</hi> as <hi>Vraba,</hi> and <hi>Beragua.</hi> In respecte of the history and course of yeeres, this booke myght haue been placed before the seconde Decade, but it shoulde seeme that these reportes came no sooner to. <hi>P. Martyr</hi> his handes, wherefore he began this fourth booke ryght well thus. I was determined. &amp;c. The fyfth booke conteyneth. <hi>P. Arias</hi> iorney mentioned dec. 2 lib. 7. to the north syde of <hi>Peru,</hi> wherein <hi>Carthagena</hi> and <hi>S. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> two famous hauens, do stande, with a description of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and people thereof. In the syxt you haue a disputation touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the Leuant streame or easterne surge of the sea, the discouery
<pb facs="8"/>
of <hi>Baccalaos</hi> done by <hi>Cabot. P. Arias</hi> arriuall in Darien, the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of. <hi>S. Maria antiqua</hi> there, with other fortresses, finally the commodities and vnwholesomnesse of <hi>Darien.</hi> In the .7 8. &amp; .9 bookes, shal you haue a description of <hi>Hispaniola, Cuba,</hi> and other Ilandes thereabout, done by <hi>Andreas Moralis.</hi> And in the .10 shall you reade of the Ilande <hi>Diues</hi> in <hi>Mar del zur,</hi> of the kyng therof subdued by <hi>Andreas Moralis,</hi> of <hi>Pearles</hi> &amp; the finding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of <hi>Petrus Arias</hi> Captaynes doinges agaynst the Caniballes, of the Barbares fowlyng, &amp; the manner of the geatheryng of gold in <hi>Dariena.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The fourth Decade, for so was it named in the Spanyards edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of.<note place="margin">The fourth Decade.</note>
      <hi>P. Martyr</hi> his woorkes set forth at <hi>Alcala</hi> in Spayne <hi>An. do.</hi> 1530. though the <hi>Basile</hi> and <hi>Cullen</hi> printers haue entituled it, <hi>De insulis nuper inuentis,</hi> that is, of Ilandes lately found out, to wyt, after <hi>Columbus</hi> voyages: this booke I say was by. <hi>P. Mar.</hi> culled out of the Indian registers, conteynyng speciall notes that seemed vnto hym most meete to be publyshed: as the disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of certayne Ilandes and creekes, namely <hi>Iucatan</hi> (done by <hi>Fernandes</hi> of <hi>Corduba</hi> &amp; his companions) <hi>Cozumella,</hi> the Ilands of Sacrifice, the Ilandes of women, the prouince <hi>Coluacan</hi> and <hi>Palmaria</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>Iohn Gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>alua</hi> &amp; his felowes: the <hi>Iucaians</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie and discouery of <hi>Florida</hi> made by those Spanyardes which <hi>Diegus Velasquen</hi> sent out of <hi>Cuba,</hi> and <hi>Ferd. Cortesius</hi> fyrst naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, wherein he conquered <hi>Potanchana</hi> in newe Spayne, the death of <hi>Valdiuia,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> execution of <hi>Vascus Nunnez,</hi> king <hi>Muteezūa</hi> his presentes to Charles the Emperour, his bookes, letters, and superstitions, finally the ruine of <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> and vtter decaye thereof, if heede shoulde not be taken in tyme.</p>
   <p>Last of al <hi>Gonzalus Ferdinandus Ouedus</hi> historie conteineth in .18. seuerall chapters (eche one whereof hath his proper title) a briefe declaration of the west Indysh nauigation, of the metals the which are found in those lately discouered lands, of the maners of the people, rites, customes, and cerimonies, of the beastes, foules, byrdes, wormes, fyshes, seas, riuers, sprynges, trees, plantes, hearbes, &amp; diuers other thinges that are engendred there both on the land &amp; in the water. To this haue we added certaine speciall reports of new Spaine or <hi>Mexico,</hi> of <hi>Peru</hi>▪ of <hi>Rio de la Plata,</hi> &amp; the countrey lying therunto, of the lands <hi>Laborador</hi> &amp; <hi>Baccalaos,</hi> with the discoueryng of <hi>Florida.</hi> And thus muche for the fyrst part of this volume.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>The seconde part of this worke appeareth what it is, by the title thereof set downe.<note place="margin">The seconde part.</note> Fol. 230. to wyt, a discourse to proue that there is a passage to the <hi>Moluccaes</hi> by the northwest, the whiche presently. <hi>M. Cap. Furbisher</hi> attempteth, with certayne reportes of the prouince <hi>China</hi> in <hi>Cathayo,</hi> where he hath to strike in his voyage, and thyrdly of <hi>Giapan,</hi> and other Ilandes by the way. The whiche seconde part, wherein matter concernyng the northwest is handled, is so muche the shorter, by how much the fyrst part seemed ouerlong: besydes that the particularities of this corner of the worlde are not yet so throughly knowen, but that other writers shal doubtlesse in more ample maner employe theyr labour therein after the returne of our northwesterne tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylers. The which I wyshe to be most happie and prosperous, as they most valiantly &amp; painefully, to the renowne of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe nation, do shewe to haue taken it in hande.</p>
   <p>In the thyrd part shal you fynd a discription of the northea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne frosty seas and kingdomes lying that way: as <hi>Moscouia, Schondia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The thyrde part.</note> or <hi>Denmarke, Groenlande, Islande, Laponia, Norway, Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi>▪ or <hi>Swethlande, Bothnia,</hi> and <hi>Gothlande:</hi> out of <hi>Zeiglerus, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Iouius, Haiton,</hi> and <hi>Sebastian</hi> free lord or Baron of <hi>Herbestein,</hi> with the countreys as well north and northeast beyond <hi>Moscouia,</hi> namely <hi>Petzora, Iuhra,</hi> and other prouinces of the Tartars: as also the voyages made through <hi>Moscouia</hi> by the merchauntes of London into <hi>Persia,</hi> conteinyng many speciall thynges woorth the knowledge, both of the countrey it self, the commodities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the manners of the people, and the priuiledges graunted vnto our merchauntes by the <hi>Sophie</hi> or <hi>Shaugh</hi> the <hi>Persian</hi> kyng.</p>
   <p>Finally in the fourth part are set downe our merchauntes voyages into <hi>Guinea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The fourth part.</note> and the other parcelles of Affrike lying towardes the Southeast, <hi>Lewes Vertomannus</hi> nauigations into Egypte, <hi>Ethiopia, Arabia, Syria, Persia,</hi> and east <hi>India,</hi> euen to the fruitefull <hi>Moluccaes,</hi> with the prices of drugges and other wares brought from thence. Whereto for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, haue we added partly out of <hi>Maximilian Transiluanus</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wrytten vnto the Cardinall of <hi>Saltzburge,</hi> and partly out of <hi>P. Martyrs</hi> other woorkes, that famous nauigation made round about the whole world: the contention betwixte the Portugales and Spanyardes for the <hi>Moluccaes,</hi> &amp; the decydyng thereof by
<pb facs="9"/>
Pope Alexander the syxt: and last of all the abridgement of. <hi>P. Martyrs</hi> foure last Decades, wherein especially that noble and gloryous conquest of <hi>Mexico</hi> is wrytten. Generally this much of the foure partes of this large volume. The lesser parcelles and speciall matter conteyned in eche part, you haue so exactely rehearsed in the table of the Decades. Fol. 173. and in the resy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the whole woorke before eche chapter so euidently set downe, that any particular table thereof at al the reader greatly needeth not, if so be that he be able to remember in what region of the worlde, East, West, North, or South, that be, the which he looketh for.</p>
   <p>Nowe concernyng. R. Edens owne doynges, syncerely to say what I thynke, and curteousely to yeelde hym that due prayse the whiche worthyly these his labours deserue, yet not to flatter hym neither, where any faulte hath ben committed: as hyghly he was to be commended for Englyshyng so straunge, so wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, so profitable histories as these are, nothyng inferior to the bookes of auncient writers, far exceedyng the multitude of foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysh commentaries and friuolous translations, to to licentiousely vsed in our tyme: So may the gentle reader forbeare his ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syghte, in so great a woorke, where some Spanyshe prouerbe, harsh latine phrase, or vncleane speache may seeme hardly Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshed, or any rashe note to shame the texte. I woulde excuse hym for translatyng the dayes by the latine names, as Fol. 12. <hi>Non. April.</hi> thus. At the Nones of Apryll. <hi>item,</hi> 3. <hi>Idus Octobris.</hi> thus. The thyrd daye of the Ides of October. <hi>item. Fol.</hi> 17. <hi>tertio Kalend. Maij.</hi> thus. The thyrd daye before the Kalendes of Maye: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng in deede, the fyfth daye of Apryll, the .13. day of October, the 29. of Aprill: but therein it shoulde seeme that he folowed his owne humor, for he obserueth the same phrase of transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng throughout. <hi>P. Martyrs</hi> whole worke. Many of his Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe woordes cannot be excused in my opinion for smellyng to much of the Latine, as <hi>Dominators. Fol</hi> 5. <hi>Ponderouse. Fol.</hi> 23. <hi>Ditionaries. Fol.</hi> 25. <hi>Portentouse. Fol.</hi> 28. <hi>Antiques. Fol.</hi> 31. <hi>des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picable. Eol.</hi> 387. <hi>Solicitate. Fol.</hi> 76. <hi>obsequiouse. Fol.</hi> 90. <hi>homicide. Fol.</hi> 390. <hi>imbibed. Fol.</hi> 395. <hi>Destructiue. Fol.</hi> 276.
<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>Prodigious.</hi> Fol. 279. with other such lyke: in the steede of Lords, weyghtie, subiectes, wonderfull, auncient, lowe, carefull, dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, manslaughter, drunken, noysome, monstrous. &amp;c. the which faultes he confesseth in other his owne verses, wrytyng thus of hym selfe.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>I haue not for euery worde asked counsayle</l>
         <l>of eloquent Eliot, or Sir Thomas Moore:</l>
         <l>Take it therefore as I haue intended,</l>
         <l>the faultes with fauour may soone be a mended.</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>