<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printers to the friendly Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122012_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10821</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21094</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printers to the friendly Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The merchants mappe of commerce : wherein, the universall manner and matter of trade, is compendiously handled. The standerd and currant coines of sundry princes, observed. The reall and imaginary coines of accompts and exchanges, expressed. The naturall and artificiall commodities of all countries for transportation declared. The weights and measures of all eminent cities and tovvnes of traffique, collected and reduced one into another; and all to the meridian of commerce practised in the famous citie of London. By Lewes Roberts, merchant. Necessary for all such as shall be imployed in the publique affaires of princes in forreigne parts; for all gentlemen and others that travell abroad for delight or pleasure, and for all merchants or their factors that exercise the art of merchandizing in any part of the habitable world</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 12, 223, 3, 116, 119-202, 205-262, 2, 192, 22 pages, 2 plates (1 folded), portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="355"/>
   <head>The Printers to the friendly Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, it is found true by daily experience, that one hand doth oftimes ease many mens labour, &amp; as often (it must be granted) that many hands give ease to one mans paines, and makes, as the Proverb sayes, light worke; the first Assertion the Author hath made good in this Tract by his paines in your behalfes, the last, wee desire you to make good in his right, for being not well acquainted with the subject, and his publique and private affaires not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting his daily and continuall attendance at the Presse, may occasion the let slipping of some Errors, which unwillingly have past the Correctors hand, our will, and his knowledge, therefore wee entreat you lovingly to amend them where they are found, and courteously to accept both of ours and his good will and endcavours therein, so shall you encourage us to doe better hereafter, and endeavour so farre to please you in the future, that wee may make some satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to him for the Errors now committed, and rest ingaged to you for your love and courteous acceptance of our paines and care taken therein.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>