<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right worshipfull Master Alexander Nowell Deane of the Cathedrall Church of Sainct Paule in Lon∣don: Continuance of health &amp; all things pros∣perous in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Ludham, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122044_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68093</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11758.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122044</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right worshipfull Master Alexander Nowell Deane of the Cathedrall Church of Sainct Paule in Lon∣don: Continuance of health &amp; all things pros∣perous in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Ludham, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practise of preaching, otherwise called the Pathway to the pulpet : conteyning an excellent method how to frame diuine sermons, &amp; to interpret the holy Scriptures according to the capacitie of the vulgar people. First written in Latin by the learned pastor of Christes Church, D. Andreas Hyperius: and now lately (to the profit of the same Church) Englished by Iohn Ludham, vicar of Wethersfeld. 1577. Herevnto is added an oration as concerning the lyfe and death of the same Hyperius: which may serue for a president to all the learned men of his calling in our tyme</title>
                 <author>Hyperius, Andreas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 181, 19 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right worshipfull Master Alexander Nowell Deane of the Cathedrall Church of Sainct Paule in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: Continuance of health &amp; all things pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>HAuing accomplished &amp; gone through with all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyning to the edition of this former Booke, (right worshipful) It was my hap to light vpon this Oratiō p̄ened in good &amp; pure Latine by Wigandus Orthius, as concerning the life &amp; death of the famous and worthy man D. Andrew Hyperius, author &amp; cōposer of the same Booke. Which whē I had once reade ouer, and finding it to be both pleasaunt &amp; profitable, by reason as wel of the varietie of mater as also of the aptnes of the phrase &amp; holesōnes of the argumēt, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing againe that it might minister no small occasion to the Reader, whereby the better to like, not onely of this, but of all other the workes of this most excellēt writer: I could by no meanes satisfie my selfe, till such time as I had turned the same into our English tongue, and placed it (as a thing seuerall by it selfe) in the later ende of this volume. The thing it selfe (I graūt) is smal, but if the substance of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be considered, it may seeme (peraduenture) to be (I will not say great but) such as neither the Reader shall haue cause to repent him off in reading, nor I cause to forethincke mee off in writing [Sed vino vendibili non est opus suspensa hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera,] Howbeit why I haue bene so bolde to put it foorth vnder the title of your name, as you (purchāce) may maruaile, so haue I to render some reason. First I was moued vnto it by the example of the penner of this Oration, who causing it to be fixed in the later ende of a worke begon &amp; not fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by the Author thereof D. Andrewe Hyperius, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led The Method of Diuinitie, dedicateth the same to his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry friende and Scholemaster, Master Iohn Princierus. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly I was induced so to do by the likenes &amp; resemblāce of the persons: that is to say, of D. Andrew Hyperius, and D. Alexander Nowell: the one a famous Superintendente in Marpurge, a Citie of high Almayne, the other a most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Deane of the Cathedrall Church of S. Paule in Londō: the one renowmed after his death for his rare gifts of learning
<pb facs="3"/>&amp; godlines of life, the other yet liuing with no lesse comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datiō, as well as for his manifold knowledge in thinges diuine and humayne, as also for his singuler ornaments of Curtesye, Affabilitie, Modesty &amp;c. The one a Mirrour of his time for his notable frugalitie &amp; sobriety, the other a spectacle of our age for his boūtifulnes and good hospitalitie. But I cannot prosecute this point so far as I iustly might, considering tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> neither is it any part of my purpose to set foorth your prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses (otherwise then by occasion) neither (I am sure) conceyue you any pleasure at all in hearinge of them: seeing you are wont to ascribe al praise &amp; glory vnto god alone, &amp; vnto mā nothing but shame &amp; confusion. The third thing that alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me to the doing of it, was the consideration of the neere friendship &amp; familiaritie that remaineth betwene your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship &amp; that Reuerend father, my Lord of Londō: wherby I thought it not amisse (cōsidering my dutie to both) to ioyne and lincke you together (as in one bande of amitie) so in one littell volume. Fourthly and lastly, I was stirred or rather cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled herevnto, as well by the certaine report of your rare benignitie towardes all men, and especially poore Scollers &amp; ministers of the Church, as also by infallible experience of that bountifull Curtesy, which naturally is ingenerate in you, &amp; floweth (as a man would say) euen vnto those with whom you are smally acquainted. For which causes as you cannot be but greatly beloued of all in general &amp; of mee in speciall, so couet I againe (by some meanes) to testifie the gratefull signification of my good meaning in this behalfe, which I cannot otherwise doe then by this simple demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of my good will and ready obseruance toward you. This only remayneth, that you (according to the goodnes of your nature) accept my doinges in good part: esteeming ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this litle what a great deale more meaneth, then by the smalnes of the gift to misconstrue the mind of the giuer. <hi>Vale Integerime vir: et Deus opt. Max. Dominationem tuam quam din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissime incolumem seruet, domis{que} suis eximijs eandem indies augea., locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletet, diteseat.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Wethersselde <date>the .xxviii. of May. 1577.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>¶ <hi>Your worships alwayes most humble in the Lorde,</hi> Iohn Ludham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>