<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>☞ The aucthors prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1540</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122112_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00884</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10996</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122112</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>☞ The aucthors prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The boke of husbandry·</title>
                 <author>Fitzherbert, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1540</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 90 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>☞ The aucthors prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>It ista questio.</hi> This is the questyon, Whervnto is euerye manne ordeyned. And as Iob saythe, <hi>Homo nascitur ad la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borem, sicut auis ad volan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> That is to saye, a man is ordeyned and borne to do labour, as a bird is ordeyned to flye. And the apostle saythe, <hi>Qui non laborat, non manducet: Debet enim in obsequio dei laborare, qui de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eius vult manducare.</hi> That is to saye, he that laboureth not, shulde not eate, and he ought to labour and doo goddes warke, that wyll eate of his goodes or gyftes, The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is an harde texte after the lyterall sence. For by the letter, the kynge, the quene, nor all other lordes spirituall and temporal shuld not eate, without they shuld labour, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che were vncomely, and not conuenyente for suche estates to labour, But who that redeth in the boke of the moralytes of the chesse, shal therby perceyue, that euerye man, from the hyest degree to the lowest, is set and ordeyned to haue labour and occupation, and that boke is deuyded in .vi. degrees, that is to saye, the kynge, the quene, the byshops, the knightes, the iudges, and the yomenne. In the whiche
<pb facs="3"/>
boke is shewed theyr degrees, theyr aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytyes, theyr warkes, and theyr occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and what they ought to do. And they so doynge and executynge theyr auctorytyes, warkes, and occupatyons, haue a wonders great study and labour, of the whiche aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytyes, occupations, and warkes, were at this tyme to longe to wryte. Wherfore I remytte that boke as myn auctour therof: The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che boke were necessary to be knowen of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry degree, that they myghte doo and ordre them selfe accordynge to the same. And in so moche the yomen in the sayde moralytyes and game of the chesse be set before to labour, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, and maynteyne all the other hyer esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, the whiche yomen represent the common people, as husbandes and labourers, therfore I purpose to speake fyrste of husbandrye.</p>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>