<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Gonzalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus, of the west Indies.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122069_Fr3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">649</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122069</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Gonzalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus, of the west Indies.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of trauayle in the VVest and East Indies, and other countreys lying eyther way, towardes the fruitfull and ryche Moluccaes : As Moscouia, Persia, Arabia, Syria, Ægypte, Ethiopia, Guinea, China in Cathayo, and Giapan: vvith a discourse of the Northwest passage... Gathered in parte, and done into Englyshe by Richarde Eden. Newly set in order, augmented, and finished by Richarde VVilles</title>
                 <author>Anghiera, Pietro Martire d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jugge, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 466, 6 leaves, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb n="185" facs="195"/>
   <head>❧ Gonzalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus, of the west Indies.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>R. E. To the Reader.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough among dyuers which haue written of the Ocean and VVest Indies, there is none to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Peter Martyr of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleria, in declaryng by phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophicall discourses the secrete causes of naturall affectes, both as touchyng the lande, the sea, the starres, and other straunge workes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: yet forasmuch as of later dayes those coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys haue been better knowne and searched, and dyuers such particuler and notable thinges founde, as are conteyned in the histories of later writers, among the number of whom, Conzalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus (whom learned Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus compareth to the ancient writers) is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the chiefe, I haue therefore thought good to ioyne to the Decades of Peter Martyr, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne notable thinges which I haue geathered out of his booke, intituled the Summarie or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of his generall hystorie of the west Indies, written in the firme lande of the same, in the citie of Sancti Maria Antiqua in Dariena (where he dwelt &amp; was gouernor many yeeres) and dedicated to Themperours maiestie, as may appeare by the Epistle folowyng.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>