<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122521_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5871.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122521</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Present remedies against the plague : Shewing sundrye preseruatiues for the same, by wholsome fumes, drinkes, vomits and other inward receits; as also the perfect cure (by implaisture) of any that are therewith infected. Now necessary to be obserued of euery housholder, to auoide the infection, lately begun in some places of this cittie. Written by a learned physition, for the health of his countrey</title>
                 <author>Learned phisition</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>FOR as much as the force and infection of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diseas called the Plague or Pestilence, hath heretofore beene too well knowne and felt in sundrie places of this Realme: and considering that it hath of late begun to increase in many chiefe Citties and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous places; I thought it good to publish to you in time, sundry preseruatiues against the said disease, the better to defende those that are in health, from the infection of the diseased: And also to cure those that are any way infected, grieued, or troubled with the same. And to this I was imboldened, the rather for that it was written by a very learned and approoued Phisition of our time, who desireth more the health of his Country, than by discouering his name seeme vaine glorious to the world. Accept the same I pray you in good part, and thanke God for the Phisitions paines, who hath his desire if it may doe but that which he wisheth: namely expel sickenes, and increase health to this Land. Which God for his mercie sake, prosper and preserue from all plagues and dangers for euermore, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>