<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To his louing Nurie the Christian Church of Eng∣land. I. VV. a member and minister of the same, vvisheth peace in Christ, and continuance of his glorious gospell, euen to the vvorlds ende.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122025_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15127</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25427</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To his louing Nurie the Christian Church of Eng∣land. I. VV. a member and minister of the same, vvisheth peace in Christ, and continuance of his glorious gospell, euen to the vvorlds ende.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a certen libel intituled, An admonition to the Parliament, by Iohn VVhitgifte, D. of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Whitgift, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 246, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To his louing Nurie the Christian Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. I. VV. a member and minister of the same, vvisheth peace in Christ, and continuance of his glorious gospell, euen to the vvorlds ende.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here bee diuers thinges, &amp; especially fiue, that whē I first tooke this labour in hande, had almost vtterly dissuaded me from the same.</p>
   <p>First, bycause I doe with all my hart hate contention and strife, and especially in matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, among such as professe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> selfe same Gospell.</p>
   <p>Secondly, for that I feared gretly least some slander might redounde to the Gospell by this open contention, séeing that God is not the authour of contention or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, but of peace.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, I doubted whether this kinde of dealing by writing, might minister matter to the common aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries of the Gospell, to reioyce and glorie, and to flatter them selues the more in their damnable errors.</p>
   <p>Fourthly I, greatly suspected the slanderous reportes of the backbiter and of the vnlearned ton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue▪ the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
bycause he loueth to speake euill, and heare euill of all those that be not in all pointes inclinable to his phansie, whereof I haue great experience, being my selfe most vniustlye slandered by that viperous kinds of men: the other, bycause they be not able to iudge of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies according to learning and knowledge, and therefore are ruled by affection, &amp; carried hedlong with blind zeale, into diuers sinister iudgementes &amp; erronious opinions.</p>
   <p>Lastlye, bycause I knowe sundrie (in all respectes) worthie men, much more able to deale in suche matters, than I am.</p>
   <p>But when I considered my dutie towardes God, to his Churche, and to our most gracious Lady and soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Elizabeth hir Maiestie (by whose ministerie God hath giuen his Gospell frée passage vnto us) y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first stoppe and hinderaunce was answered. For I thought that, that dutie ought not to be omitted for any such cause, séeing God and not man, shall be my Iudge: and also that not he which defendeth the truthe, and confuseth errours, but he that impugneth the truthe, and spreddeth sectes, is the authour of contention.</p>
   <p>Likewise when I remembred y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> it was no new thing to haue contentions, sectes, &amp; schismes in the Churche of Christ, (especially when it enioyeth externall peace) and that we had manifest examples therof from time to time, (first in Peter, &amp; Paule. <hi>ad Gala.</hi> 2. Paule &amp; Barnabas, Acto. 15: then in the Churche of the Corinthians. 1. Cor. 1. and .3. Afterwardes betwixt the orientall Church &amp; occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall Church, touching Easter &amp; such like matters: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Bishops of Aphrica and the Bishops of Italie, for rebaptising of heretikes: &amp; sundrie times, yea vsuallie in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> external peace of the church, as may be more at large séene in Eusebius, <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>eccle. histo. ca.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 24.25.26. <hi>&amp; li.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Likewise in Ruffinus <hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. In Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zom. <hi>Li.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 4. In Basilius magnus <hi>epist.</hi> 61. <hi>ad fratres &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
Episcopas in accidente: &amp; epist.</hi> 69. and in sundrie other auncient and learned histories and writers.</p>
   <p>For the second point I was satisfied, for I thought, that, that could be no slander to this Church which by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Sathan hath bene practised in all Churches euen synce the ascention of Christ.</p>
   <p>Thirdly when I perceiued y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> these men against whome I nowe write, did agree with the aduersaries in defacing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> state of religion, the order of cōmon prayers, the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, the sacramentes, the kind of gouermēt. &amp;c. vsed and allowed in this realme of England, and that in as oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious &amp; spitefull manner as the aduersaries do: likewise that they séeke to ouerthrow the selfe same pillers of this Church with the aduersaries (although not by the selfe same meanes) I thought that the confutation and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of the one should be the confutation &amp; ouerthrow of the other, and therefore the aduersaries to haue small cause in déed of reioycing.</p>
   <p>Against backbiters, slanderers, and vnlearned tongs, I shall by Gods grace arme my selfe with pacience, for their taulke is no sufficient cause for a man to absteyne from dooing his dutie.</p>
   <p>To conclude, I, (although the vnworthiest and vnmée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test of a great nūber) was bold to take vpon me this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise, partly to shew, that the booke called the Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is not such, but that it may easily be answered, and especially to satisfie mine owne cōscience: for I cōsidered that if no man had taken vpon him y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enuie of the cōmon sort, in withstanding the enterprises &amp; procéedings of the Anabaptists whē they began in Germanie, Anabaptisme had ouerrunne those Churches &amp; vtterly destroyed them.</p>
   <p>These were the reasons that satisfied the former ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, and especiallye moued me to take vppon me this labour: wherewith, if I can also satisfie others, I haue my desire: if not, yet haue I done my dutie, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
<pb facs="4"/>
mine owne conscience. And for asmuche as the matter toucheth the state of the whole Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, I thought it most méete to dedicate this my booke, rather vnto the same generally, than to any one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer member thereof: protesting that if I haue affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any thing therein, that by learning and good reasons may be proued erronious, I will reforme the same, for I wholly submit it to the rule of Gods worde, and the iudgement of those that he learned, discrete, &amp; wise. The Lord blesse the (o deare spouse of Christ) with the continuance of his Gospell, of the Quenes Maiestie, and of godlye peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>