<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his much respected friends, the MERCHANTS of ENGLAND in generall, and to the courteous READER, whom it may concerne.</title>
           <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122012_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10821</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21094</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his much respected friends, the MERCHANTS of ENGLAND in generall, and to the courteous READER, whom it may concerne.</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The merchants mappe of commerce : wherein, the universall manner and matter of trade, is compendiously handled. The standerd and currant coines of sundry princes, observed. The reall and imaginary coines of accompts and exchanges, expressed. The naturall and artificiall commodities of all countries for transportation declared. The weights and measures of all eminent cities and tovvnes of traffique, collected and reduced one into another; and all to the meridian of commerce practised in the famous citie of London. By Lewes Roberts, merchant. Necessary for all such as shall be imployed in the publique affaires of princes in forreigne parts; for all gentlemen and others that travell abroad for delight or pleasure, and for all merchants or their factors that exercise the art of merchandizing in any part of the habitable world</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 12, 223, 3, 116, 119-202, 205-262, 2, 192, 22 pages, 2 plates (1 folded), portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To his much respected friends, the</hi> MERCHANTS of ENGLAND in generall, and to the courteous READER, whom it may concerne.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was not ignorant, <hi>(Right worthy friends)</hi> when first I undertooke this <hi>taske,</hi> and busied my selfe to compasse this <hi>Worke,</hi> how difficult it would prove to bee in it <hi>selfe;</hi> what slender furtherances I had to accomplish the <hi>same;</hi> and how weak my own abilities were to give <hi>it</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: yet notwithstanding all these obstacles, when I had duely considered the generall want <hi>thereof,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefit and commoditie that would redound <hi>thereby,</hi> especially to those of my owne profession (if <hi>it</hi> might bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or in some measure truely perfected) I resolved (conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the silence of those of better indowments) to take <hi>the same</hi> in hand, and cheerfully and willingly layed both my hand to the <hi>Worke,</hi> and my shoulder to the burthen, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting and gathering with laborious industry, and industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous labour all those principall points and heads, as might ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conduce to the accomplishment of <hi>the building,</hi> or any way further my intended <hi>fabrique:</hi> So that by my continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all toyle, and search after fit and apt materials, I hoped that at length a good issue would crowne my indeavors, and finish this my intended undertaken <hi>taske.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But after long and tedious inquisition, I found that the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I sailed in this <hi>Ocean,</hi> the vaster were my desires, and the fewer were my furtherances to my wished <hi>Port;</hi> so that
<pb facs="5"/>
perceiving the <hi>Worke</hi> thus to increase upon me, beyond my expectation and first purpose, I was constrained (with the wind-scanted <hi>Seaman)</hi> to cast about againe, and limit my selfe to a narrower scantling; for that to doe it at large, and as the matter punctually required, was farre beyond the reach of my knowledge; yet because I could not doe as I would, I resolved to doe as I could, and thereupon begun againe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve these my first scattered Collections into a lesser mould, and reduce my first thoughts and observations into such a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond limit and order, as might best befit my experience, and the compasse to which now I had confined it; conceiving that as my intentions (ioyned to my labour and paines herein) tended onely to the good of others, and principally of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> and their actors, that reside or negociate in forreigne parts, so they will in requitall be induced to have a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <hi>thereof,</hi> as a reward to mee, for the benefit that shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to them by <hi>the same,</hi> excusing those errors which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure the better experienced may by triall find in the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall of this <hi>Worke,</hi> and the defects which my ignorance hath inforced me to let passe, which by reason of the diversitie and rarity of the matter the same is most subject unto, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because I have beene constrained oftentimes in this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert</hi> to travell without a certaine <hi>guide,</hi> and not seldome to navigate by anothers <hi>Compasse,</hi> having not in any Language or Countrey met with any <hi>Author,</hi> that could either totally conduct me, or truely rectifie my steps when I went astray; yet I must confesse I met with some that shot at the marke I aymed at; but it was at randome, and came not home to my proposed blanke; and I found <hi>some</hi> that tooke up stuffe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on trust, and a <hi>second</hi> followed <hi>him,</hi> and a <hi>third</hi> that <hi>second,</hi> and heere (not able otherwise to contradict nor amend) I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so became a follower of theirs; some againe I observed to have borrowed from others, of which number I may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt the Collections of <hi>Claud Bojer Lionois,</hi> of <hi>Gio: Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> of <hi>Iacob Cartolano,</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> of <hi>Gio Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiste Zuchetta</hi> a <hi>Genovois,</hi> of Mr. <hi>Malines</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> our owne Countreymen, and some others, who againe gave addition to what they had in this nature gathered; but all
<pb facs="5"/>
these (though by their indeavours meriting due commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) yet satisfied not throughly my curiositie, nor the earnest desire I had to bring this <hi>Worke</hi> to a more absolute perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: therefore in this case I was furthered by some friends, whose <hi>Starre</hi> led mee when I was benighted, and whose <hi>Candle</hi> lightned me, when otherwise I should have stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; by which meanes, and my owne old twelve yeares collections, during my aboade and imployment in many parts of the World, I have at last by due sounding of the <hi>Channell,</hi> safely sailed over the <hi>Ocean</hi> afore-mentioned, and brought my <hi>Barke</hi> to an Anchor in <hi>her</hi> desired <hi>Harbour;</hi> and I hope so well observed the depths, shoulds, rocks and sands thereof, that he that navigates after me, and by this my <hi>Mapp,</hi> shall bee secured from all dangers, and thereby bring his accompts to that wished <hi>Port,</hi> that may prove both to his owne profit and Commoditie.</p>
   <p>Now <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> having thus then understood with what industry and care the materials of this <hi>Edifice</hi> hath beene collected, what paines hath beene used to bring <hi>it</hi> to this conclusion and perfection, and having truely weighed the benefit arising <hi>thereby;</hi> all these I conceive are effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all inducements to challenge a faire acceptance from you: yet notwithstanding all these reall arguments I cannot denie, but the <hi>Worke it selfe</hi> may not onely suffer in the opinion of the censorious, but be also subject to the verdict of the judicious, both in the <hi>forme, manner, method</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> thereof, which I shall easily be brought to acknowledge, though as easily I might alleadge, that had not my younger yeares been drawne by adverse fortune or crosse fate, from the study of <hi>Arts</hi> to the studie of <hi>Marts,</hi> I might peradventure have delineated this <hi>Mapp</hi> with more curious colours, illustrated <hi>it</hi> with more diversity of pleasing objects, and adorned <hi>it</hi> with some more delightfull varietie; but proceeding thus from the Pen of a <hi>Merchant,</hi> from whom such excellencies cannot be expected, <hi>it</hi> may the rather find a favorable construction from the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous of my profession, and from the learned of what Art soever, to whose judgement and candid censure, I shall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly submit both my selfe and these my <hi>Labours;</hi> and for
<pb facs="6"/>
those whose tender appetite cannot relish <hi>it</hi> in that nature as <hi>it</hi> is, and who are ignorant of my paines <hi>herein,</hi> it will not be judged to be a point of ill manners in mee to tell them, that this <hi>method, forme,</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> was prescribed me by the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity and consequence of the <hi>Worke</hi> in hand, and by the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thusiasme</hi> of my owne fancie, which I conceived in some sort I was bound a little to please, partly to ease the burthen I endured in the <hi>building,</hi> and principally to adde some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and pleasure to the toyle I underwent in rearing the <hi>same.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now as touching the <hi>Structure it selfe,</hi> many motives have induced mee to lay the foundation <hi>thereof</hi> upon the knowledge of <hi>Geographie,</hi> and upon the use of <hi>Mapps</hi> and <hi>Sea-Cards</hi> in generall, so delightfull, profitable and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to the <hi>Merchant,</hi> that it cannot be by him that would be accompted such a <hi>one,</hi> neither neglected nor omitted. The principall parts thereof I have touched, so farre only as conduced to the enlightening of the <hi>matter</hi> in hand, and to the generall understanding of the insuing <hi>Tract:</hi> from hence (for method sake) I was inforced to a cursory <hi>survey</hi> of the foure principall parts and divisions of the <hi>World,</hi> according to moderne Authors; from this I descend to the <hi>Empires, Kingdomes,</hi> and particular <hi>Provinces</hi> of each of them; and thence to the <hi>eminent</hi> and most <hi>noted Cities,</hi> and <hi>Townes</hi> of Traffique therein, whose scituation I have superficially run over, and in some sort, observed the most remarkable <hi>passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> as have presented themselves within the compasse of my <hi>reading;</hi> and for matter of <hi>Trade,</hi> I have in the first place ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the <hi>naturall artificiall Commodities</hi> therein found; then the <hi>Coines</hi> there in use and <hi>currant,</hi> with the <hi>value</hi> and <hi>denomination</hi> thereof, and the <hi>species</hi> wherein <hi>Merchants</hi> do there frame and regulate their <hi>accompts</hi> by, also the <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Measures</hi> of those places, together with their <hi>Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and how these are found to be calculated amongst the <hi>Italians,</hi> who are accounted the most expert <hi>Bankers</hi> and <hi>Exchangers,</hi> with all other fit instruments and materials, as at this day is found practised in the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Merchandizing,</hi> in all the parts of the habitable <hi>World.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
And in conclusion, I have added a Table of the <hi>longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> and <hi>latitude</hi> of all these <hi>eminent</hi> places of <hi>Traffique,</hi> not onely thereby to satisfie the curious, but the better to guid the inquirer to any such <hi>Citie</hi> or <hi>Towne</hi> sought for: In the rest, I have (following the example of many <hi>Merchants)</hi> shewed the <hi>worst</hi> first, and the <hi>best</hi> last; I meane declared the particulars of the <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>America,</hi> as the least and worst knowne unto us; then of <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Asia,</hi> and <hi>last</hi> of all <hi>Europe,</hi> as the <hi>best,</hi> and best knowne to us, and according to my <hi>Title</hi> included and concluded all, within the <hi>famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of London</hi> where we abide, which ever with all grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes as the place of my Education in the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,</hi> I am obliged to honour.</p>
   <p>And to conclude, in all this <hi>Worke</hi> my ambition still hath prompted me to an indeavour of pleasing all <hi>Merchants</hi> in generall, and (if I may not bee thought to judge too favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of this <hi>Child</hi> of my owne <hi>braine)</hi> I may be induced to beleeve I shall hereby please not onely the most, but also the most ingenuous. I am confident, were my <hi>Labours</hi> truely scand, my <hi>indeavours</hi> might challenge that thankes I expect; and he that knowes both my publique and private imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may well answere for me, and excuse the defects or omissions, that may by further triall peradventure be found herein; and if in the future I find <hi>this</hi> acceptable, I may yet bee incouraged to publish some other <hi>Workes,</hi> which in this kind I have hewen out to your profit and commoditie: till when, and ever, I remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A welwisher of your prosperities; LEWES ROBERTS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>