<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS ADMO¦NITION TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122236_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14624</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24931</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122236</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS ADMO¦NITION TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mariners mirrour : wherin may playnly be seen the courses, heights, distances, depths, soundings, flouds and ebs, risings of lands, rocks, sands and shoalds, with the marks for th'entrings of the harbouroughs, havens and ports of the greatest part of Europe: their seueral traficks and commodities: together wth. the rules and instrume [n] ts of nauigation. First made &amp; set fourth in diuers exact sea-charts, by that famous nauigator Luke Wagenar of Enchuisen and now fitted with necessarie additions for the use of Englishmen by Anthony Ashley. Heerin also may be understood the exploits lately atchiued by the right Honorable the L. Admiral of Engla [n] d with her Maties. nauie: and some former seruices don by that worthy knight Sr. Fra: Drake</title>
                 <author>Waghenaer, Lucas Janszoon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haslop (Hassellup), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>230 pages, maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS ADMO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>NITION TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Reendly Reader, forasmuch as all skilfull and experienced in the art of</hi> Nauigation, do well know, that certein of the sandy coastes and shoares, as also diuerse mouthes &amp; entries of riuers, aswell of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Frizeland,</hi> as of <hi>Yutland</hi> (which in old time was called <hi>Cimbrica Chersonesus</hi>) and of other countries, are moueable, &amp; haue not alwaies their being in one self place, as in these Tables or Chartes, rightly, fitly &amp; faithfully they are set down: I could do no lesse then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish the thereof, that thou mightest diligently obserue and marke them by these Mappes, as thinges most necessarie to be regarded. For it is perfectly knowen to all Pilots and Masters, that, by force of tempests and violence of boisterous windes, huge heaps of sand are so dispersed, that at length they are made euen with the plaine Sea-shore. VVhich <hi>Keteldune</hi> of <hi>North Holland,</hi> the yle <hi>Busk</hi> or <hi>Corensand,</hi> lying betwixt <hi>Lawers</hi> and <hi>Scilla,</hi> neere the shore of <hi>East Frizland,</hi> and the better part of <hi>Ameland</hi> in this our age, do most euidently &amp; certeinly bewray. For these Sand-hils are in such sort blowen abroad and scattered, that at this day they can scarcely be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaued, nay they do scant differ in shew from the plaine low shore: especially <hi>Buske</hi> or the Isle of <hi>Corensand,</hi> which hath been so notably metamorphosed, that in a raging and wrought sea it is quite ouerflowen at an high water. In like maner all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Pilots do vnderstand, that, by force and violence of outragious stormes (which cause most mighty and ouerth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wart billowes) diuerse sandy entraunces and Chanels of the Sea alongst the foresayd coastes, are sometimes choaked with sandes, and sometimes do shift their seate. VVherfore by the lawe of the Sea, such places are expresly forbidden to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered without sounding: and therefore they are called VVaters of Pilotage. I haue obserued and marked these strange chaunges of late yeres, both in the <hi>Maze</hi> and elswhere: and therfore do find this most true, that for the former causes, many hauens are decayed, and many are altered, as the olde <hi>Ripe-deep in Yutland</hi> doth sufficiently manifest the same: which hauing had his chanell heretofore betweene <hi>Rim</hi> and <hi>Manu,</hi> hath it now welneere two leagues more Northward betweene <hi>Manu</hi> &amp; <hi>Fanu.</hi> But these onely may suffice for examples sake. And although all these and such like alterations, which haue hitherto beene found, are with great care faithfully corrected and reformed by me in the pourtraicts and descriptions of these Sea-Cardes: yet could I not omit this my well meaning and sincere admonition for two causes: First, that by these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples thou mightest vnderstand, that vpon the like causes, the like chaunges may happen: next that the vnskilfull and especially the enuious backbiter and carper, may haue no matter to cauill, nor occasion to carp: seeing that things to come, and vncerteine, can by no meanes possible, bee perfectly described. And for that it is but too apparant, how much euell speach, hatred and enuy preuayle in this our wretched age. I haue thought good to rehearse briefly in this place the beginning and progresse of this my labour. First I endeuoured by all my studie, paines, diligence and care to draw the generall Sea-Cardes, and the other particuler plots, exactly and faithfully, (as became mee) and in the most faultlesse forme that I could: because on them both the liues and goods of such as traficke and trauill by Sea do depend. VVhereby it came to passe, that many yeres since (be it spoken without enuie) they haue been so highly accoumpted of: that I was ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly required and oftentimes importuned, of diuerse skilfull Pilots and Masters in these countries, besides many princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and rich Marchants, and owners of ships, to print and publish the same, for the furderance of salfer sea-faring, &amp; the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe and benefit of the inhabitants of <hi>Holland, Zealand</hi> and <hi>Frizland,</hi> which most of all vse traffique by Sea. At that time for many causes, I yeelded not to their requests: specially for that my meane abilitie was not sufficient to defray so great expēse. But at length, ouercome by the importunat suite of Mariners, Masters, and Marchants: but chiefly by reason of my sincere loue and affection towards the commonweal, and posteritie: with the continuall instance and exhortation of many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, of qualitie &amp; iudgemēt which egged me on, and, both with promises and performance, holpe &amp; furthered the worke: I set vpon it with a cheerefull minde, and incessant labour: And printed the first part of this Mariners Mirrour, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth the whole western Nauigation, to wit, of the coastes of <hi>Fraunce, England, Ireland, Scotland, Spaine, Portugall &amp;c.</hi> &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished it in the yere of our Lord. 1583. being dedicated to the most famous Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> of happy Memorie, who tooke no small delight therin: and of his great bountie bestowed large allowance towards the finishing of the worke begun. VVherefore presently I betooke my selfe to the second part: beyng aduertised in the meane time, by the skilfullest Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotes, Masters, and Mariners, with how great commendation the first part was receiued, and how profitable it was found, for all such as trauayle by Sea: which I leaue to bee remembred of others.</p>
   <p>Moreouer I was enformed by many Pilots of good credit, with how great good-liking these Sea-Cardes were recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in many other countries &amp; kingdoms: namely by these most famous and learned men <hi>Io. Dowza Baron</hi> of <hi>Nortwick,</hi> and M. Doctor <hi>Maelson</hi> who this last yeare were Embassadours for the States of the vnited Prouinces of the low countries, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the most renowmed Queene of England: where a booke of these Sea-cardes was presented at the Counsell table, by the moste Noble Lorde, <hi>My Lorde</hi> Charles Howard, <hi>Baron of Effingham, Lorde Admirall of England,</hi> and was esteemed by the chief personages of that graue Counsell, worthy to be translated and Printed into a language familiar to all Nations, that it might bee both read and vnderstood of all. VVherefore from that time, I purposed with my selfe, to performe the same, assoone as I might. Shortly after I printed and published th'other part of this <hi>MIRROƲR,</hi> which cōprehendeth the whole Nauigation of the <hi>German, Scottish</hi> and <hi>North Ocean,</hi> as also of the Northeast and <hi>Baltik Sea.</hi> This I dedicated to the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Westfrizland,</hi> who gratiously and thankefully receauing it, rewarded mee with such recompence as whilest I liue I shall neuer be able to deserue. This encouraged mee, vpon the former reasons, to procure, that the descriptions of these Cardes might be translated into Latine: to th'end, that, al nations, which vnderstand that language, might reape both profit and pleasure out of the same: hoping that it will be very profitable vnto all those which are studious in the knowledge of Nauigation, and no lesse acceptable to al courteous readers, who may take likyng therof &amp; accept of this my labour in thankefull manner.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell,</salute>
      <dateline>From <hi>Einchusen.</hi>
         <date>1586.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>