<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reuerend Father in GOD, Thomas Morton Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of Couentrie and Lietchfield, I. F. wisheth grace in this life, and glorie in the world to come.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122635_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01022</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11128.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122635</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reuerend Father in GOD, Thomas Morton Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of Couentrie and Lietchfield, I. F. wisheth grace in this life, and glorie in the world to come.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Apostles catechisme : consisting of sixe articles, plainly expounded; very profitable for all, but especially for the benefite of the vnlearned and those that desire more knowledge. By Iohn Foorthe, minister of the Word of God</title>
                 <author>Foord, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 71, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reuerend Father in GOD, <hi>Thomas Morton</hi> Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of <hi>Couentrie</hi> and <hi>Lietchfield,</hi> I. F. wisheth <hi>grace</hi> in this life, and <hi>glorie</hi> in the world to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS the holy Ghost hath both recorded in the sixt Chapter of the Epistle to the Hebrewes, that short Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme, which the Apostles in their dayes taught those whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the faith of Christ, &amp; also left the same to the Churches for all future times: I not doubting but that the euidence of the text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. and 6.1. Will iustifie this to bee the Apostles Catechisme, haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to propound and expound
<pb facs="3"/>the same as the Lord hath inabled mee, hoping thereby to whet vp their gifts, which are better able to adorne and enlarge it; to iustifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catechismes, which differing from this in words, agree with it in substance; and to propound it as a paterne or an example for imitation, that they which of themselues are alreadie forward, may be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to proceede, and those which are somewhat slacke, may bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked diligently to plant the first principles in the hearts of those that are vnder their charge, and so yong plants may grow vp in their youth, and become worthie instruments in Church or Common-wealth, as God shall appoint. This small Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise I haue presumed to dedicate to your Lordships for these reasons. First, because you are able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of the matter handled herein. Secondly, because it hath beene
<pb facs="3"/>publikely taught to youth in your Lordships Dioces. Thirdly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I haue great cause to giue some testimonie of heartie thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to your Lordships great fauour, which I haue lately found at your hands. And desiring the small te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie may bee accepted in good part, I cease at this present. <hi>Iune</hi> 5. 1623.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>