<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Presace of the Authour vnto Titus pomponius Atticus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122136_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18823</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5294</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122136</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Presace of the Authour vnto Titus pomponius Atticus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The worthye booke of old age othervvyse entituled the elder Cato : contayning a learned defence and praise of age, and aged men: writen in latine by that father of eloquence Marcus Tullius Cicero, and now englished. VVherunto is annexed a recitall of diuerse men that liue long. With a declaracion of sundrye soortes of yeares, and the diuersitie betwene the yeres in the old time, and our yeares nowe adayes. Anno. 1569</title>
                 <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64, 7 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Presace of the Authour <hi>vnto Titus pomponius Atticus.</hi>
   </head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>O Tytus, if I ease thee of that paine,</l>
         <l>And heauie charg vvhich doth the sore annoy,</l>
         <l>And makes thine hart ful pensiue to remain,</l>
         <l>Shal I herein my laboure vvell employe?</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>For in speaking vnto the (friend Atticus) I maye vse the same verses and woordes, whiche that auncient and worthie Potte, more fully fraughted vvith honestye, and faithful dealing, than vvith vvorldly pelfe and rychesse, vseth, in coumforting the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble Flaminius: albeit I am vvell assured, that thou art not so disquieted night and day, vvith pensiuenes, care, and sorovve, as Flaminius vvas: for I knovve thy paei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente sufferaunce of all chaunces and brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Fortune, and the vvell stayed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thy mynde. And I do ryghte vvell vnderstande hovve that thou haste broughte hoome vvythe thee frome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, not onelye thy Surrename, to bee
<pb facs="8"/>called Atticus, but also gentle behauioure, courtesie, and prudence. Yet canne I not othervvyse thynke, but that, novve and then asvvel as I, thou arte sore vexed and troubled in minde, for the tyrannous oppressions and greuous enormities novv in our common vvealthe perpetrated and comitted. The consolation vvherof is so great, that it can not in this litle booke be fully declared, and therfore I vvil defer it, vntill an other time more conuenient. At this presēt time, I thought it best to vvrit som litle Treatise vnto the, cōcerning Old age: because I vvould faine haue both thee and my selfe, to be eased of this heauie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, which is commune and indifferēt to me asvvell as to thee, (I meane Olde age,) vvhich novve already is either come vpon vs, or els ere it be longe, (we maye be assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) will catche holde on vs. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I know well that thou doest and wilt take the same modestlye, and as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a wise man to do, pacientlye, euen as thou arte in all other thynges accustomed.</p>
   <p>But vvhenne as I purposed vvythe my selfe to vvrite somevvhat in prayse and commendacion of Olde age, I deemed and
<pb facs="8"/>iudged the most vvorthy, vnto vvhom my laboure and studie in this behalfe myght be dedicated, vvhiche boothe of vs, mighte ioyntlie and commonly vse for our coum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and contentacion. As for my part, I promise thee, I toke such singuler pleasure and delectacion in the compilinge of this Booke, that it did not onelye vtterlie take avvaie al the encombraunces and discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of mine Olde age from mee: but rather made the same vnto me pleasaunt, ioyfull, and delectable. Therefore Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie canne neuer be sufficientlye praised, so muche as the vvorthinesse and dignitie thereof requireth: vvhose preceptes and rules vvho so euer obayeth, maye passe the vvhole time of his age, and runne the full race of this life, vvithoute anye yrkesome griefe or trouble. VVhat other vtilities and commodities it bringeth, I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in manye other of my Bookes at large declared and meane hereafter manie times and often therof to make ample discourse and mencion. But this Booke of Old age, I haue sent vnto thee: vvherein the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and superioritie of the disputacion is not geeuen to olde Tithonus as Aristo
<pb facs="9"/>Chius did in his Booke, least in suche a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fable the vvhole discourse should bee the lesse esteemed among the Readers: but I attribute the chyefe dignytie of it vnto the Old grayheaded sage Marcus Cato, to thende the Treatise shoulde haue moore estimation credite and authoritie. And I introduce as speakers, Laelius and Scipio, frankly and familierlie talking vvith him, and muche meruailinge to see him, so pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlie and easelie to tolerate his old age, and vvhat aunsvveares hee made to theim again. VVhom if thou thinke more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlye heare to dispute, then in his ovvne vvoorkes he vvas accustomed, impute the cause to his skilfulnes in the Greeke ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, vvhereof it is vvell knovven that in his Olde age he vvas very studious. But to vvhat purpose should vve make any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preamble? for al that vve haue to say concerning Olde age, the talke and dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion of Cato himselfe shall manifestlye declare.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>