<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OPERIS COMMENDATIO.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122236_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14624</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24931</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122236</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OPERIS COMMENDATIO.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mariners mirrour : wherin may playnly be seen the courses, heights, distances, depths, soundings, flouds and ebs, risings of lands, rocks, sands and shoalds, with the marks for th'entrings of the harbouroughs, havens and ports of the greatest part of Europe: their seueral traficks and commodities: together wth. the rules and instrume [n] ts of nauigation. First made &amp; set fourth in diuers exact sea-charts, by that famous nauigator Luke Wagenar of Enchuisen and now fitted with necessarie additions for the use of Englishmen by Anthony Ashley. Heerin also may be understood the exploits lately atchiued by the right Honorable the L. Admiral of Engla [n] d with her Maties. nauie: and some former seruices don by that worthy knight Sr. Fra: Drake</title>
                 <author>Waghenaer, Lucas Janszoon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haslop (Hassellup), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>230 pages, maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
      <head>OPERIS COMMENDATIO.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>RIMVS inexpertis nauim qui credidit Austris</l>
         <l>Tiphys, &amp; ignotis remos lentauit in vndis,</l>
         <l>Saepe vado illisam confregit in aequore puppim;</l>
         <l>Saepe errore viae, vel tempestatibus actus</l>
         <l>Praecipiti prensas amisit turbine naues.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Permare securi vitam nunc quaerite Nautae.</l>
         <l>Tutum iter, ac placidos vobis dant aequora cursus,</l>
         <l>Auspicio liquido: notis iam vela licebit</l>
         <l>Portubus insinuare: imi iam forma profundi,</l>
         <l>Et vada se tangi patiuntur lumine claro:</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Ingenio tota ista tuo laus debita &amp; arti,</l>
         <l>Gnaue AVRIGARI, qui tam bene direxisti</l>
         <l>Per freta morigero volitantem flamine currum,</l>
         <l>Quàm si vsurpatum manibusque &amp; poplite vtroque</l>
         <l>Oceani fundum ac breuia omnia perreptasses.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Quinetiam, ne quid pelagi scrutator Eoi,</l>
         <l>Aut Aquilonaris desideret; è mare sese</l>
         <l>Vt quaeque ostendat regio procul, ostendisti.</l>
         <l>Clarius in SPECVLO nec se Venus ipsa tuetur,</l>
         <l>Tota in charteolo quàm sese hîc aequore Tethys.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Macte, ô, Nereïdum thalamos qui intrare repostos,</l>
         <l>Ausus, &amp; attonitas trahere ad spectacula phocas,</l>
         <l>Delphinumque subire domos. tibi caerula Prothêi</l>
         <l>Alludunt armenta; tuis Matuta gubernis</l>
         <l>Summittit fasces; te prono gurgite Doris</l>
         <l>Et mulcet rauco Tritonia buccina cantu;</l>
         <l>*Squammigenis vix nota Tesce Colao. COL â dum certius ipso</l>
         <l>Exploras adyta, ac Tethydis secreta recludis.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Quò mihi Cymmerios, &amp; subterranea Regna</l>
         <l>Damnatos{que} geli scopulos, duce MAGELLANO,</l>
         <l>Visere, &amp; intactos Austri penetrare recessus?</l>
         <l>Quò Stygios tentare Lacus? Apage Argonautas</l>
         <l>Hesperios: satis, extremâ, mî, haerere Celocis</l>
         <l>Parte tuae; satis est, Tabulas ex ordine pictas</l>
         <l>Spectantem, Arctoi posituram discere Nereî,</l>
         <l>Et nosti conuexa Poli. Quis nouit? an olim</l>
         <l>RIPHAEI hinc quoque se retegant, LVCA indice, MONTES</l>
         <l>Pacatos vbi HYPERBOREOS videamus, Iberas</l>
         <l>Quò necdum vlla rates Cynosura aut Linea duxit.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>THE SAME ENGLISHED IN PRAYSE <hi>OF THE VVOORK.</hi>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Iphis,</hi> who first set sayle to the windes which blasted yet vntried,</l>
         <l>And first bended his oares, in streams which waued yet vnknown▪</l>
         <l>Oft did he bruze his keele, on shoalds, and oft vpon hard rockes,</l>
         <l>Oft by the course not kept, or mayn-storme mightily driuing,</l>
         <l>VVith furious whirlewinds, his ships made wrack in a tempest.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Now Mariners henceforth at Sea may ye liue very carelesse,</l>
         <l>For that a saulfe iourney cleered from daungerous extreames,</l>
         <l>Is for ye prepared. For now may ye into good harbour</l>
         <l>Hale euen at pleasure now doth lo the forme othe mayn-deepe,</l>
         <l>And all shoalds proffer themselues to be cleerly beholden.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>All this prayse is dew to thy witt, to thy paines, to thy charges,</l>
         <l>Ingenious <hi>VVagener,</hi> which hast so worthily guyded,</l>
         <l>That VVagon on Mayn-sea which winds cause flie to the compasse:</l>
         <l>As if vpon thy both hands and knees with curious insight</l>
         <l>Strongly thy selfe hadst crept, and searcht out th' <hi>Ocean</hi> althrough.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Moreouer vnlesse that perauenture a Searcher of East-seas,</l>
         <l>Or Northren passage, should want any thing that he searcheth:</l>
         <l>Thou shewst each Region farr of, what sort it ariseth.</l>
         <l>Nor <hi>Venus</hi> in Mirrour could view her selfe any cleerer,</l>
         <l>Then <hi>Tethys</hi> in this Glasse may well discerne her apeeraunce:</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Hold on amayn valiant courage with vertue auanced,</l>
         <l>Thou that durst the secreat closet of Seagoddeses enter,</l>
         <l>And draw th'astonished Sea-calues to the gaze to behold thee.</l>
         <l>And lodge with <hi>Dolphins</hi> in the deep: thee th'azured whole skulls</l>
         <l>Of <hi>Proteus</hi> pasture reuerence: <hi>Matuta</hi> the Sea-queene,</l>
         <l>Yeelds thee vp her Regiment: <hi>Lady Doris</hi> stoopes lo thy handmayd,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Neptunes</hi> Musicien studieth with his horne to delight thee:</l>
         <l>VVhiles thou a more certein searcher then <hi>Cola</hi> the straunge-fish</l>
         <l>Searchest out th'entries scant known to the Meyny o fishes,</l>
         <l>And openest th'hidden secreats of th'old <hi>Lady Tethys.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>VVhat profit in searching darke realms, sited vnder horizon:</l>
         <l>And Rocks condemned to be pincht with a frost neuer ending:</l>
         <l>Or to go with <hi>Magelan</hi> to the South sea passages vtmost.</l>
         <l>VVhat profit in <hi>Styx</hi> lake? Ile none of your <hi>Argos</hi> auenturs</l>
         <l>
            <hi>VVestern</hi> discouerers: tis enough for mee t'haue a corner</l>
         <l>In this swift carauell to behold these Tables in order:</l>
         <l>And learne how <hi>Northern Nereus</hi> hath spred many braunches.</l>
         <l>And what in our regiōs th'heights are: who knows whither oneday</l>
         <l>This <hi>Lukes</hi> discouerie shall rayze those <hi>Riphean hil-topps</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Where the <hi>Hyperborean</hi> long-liud people are to be found out:</l>
         <l>Though thither yet no star, nor lead, hath led any <hi>Spaignard.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>