<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122314_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03207</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13327</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122314</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hierarchie of the blessed angells : Their names, orders and offices the fall of Lucifer with his angells written by Tho: Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 622, 10 pages, illustrations (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Generous Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not need to apollogise before-hand, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the height of the subiect, or the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of handling this Worke; when the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of euery Tractat can speake for the one; and a direct proceeding in the course proposed, for the other. Remembring the French Prouerbe,
<q>
         <l>Qui edefie en publick place,</l>
         <l>Faict maison trop haut on trop basse.</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>Who builds ith' way where all passe by,</l>
         <l>Shall make his house too low or hye.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>I haue exposed my selfe a subiect to all censures, and entreat the Reader not to vndertake me with any sinister prejudice. For my hope is, if he shall fairely trace me in that modest and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full course which I haue trauelled, he may say in the conclusion, <hi>Facilius currentibus, quam repentibus lapsus.</hi> For I professe my selfe to be so free from all arrogance and ostent, that, <hi>Vt caveam timen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, tuta pertimesco.</hi> My <hi>Iuvenilia</hi> I must confesse were sutable to my age then, for being a childe, I spake as a childe; but Maruritie hath since better instructed me: remembring that excellent Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Sophocles, Si Iuvenis luxuriat, peccat; si senex, insanit.</hi> Nor forgetting that of <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philosopher, <hi>Ante senectutem curan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, benè vivere; in senectute, benè mori.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue proposed vnto you Good Angels and Bad; the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the one, still continuing in their created Puritie; the refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie rebellion of the other, damning themselues to all eternity. In the reading of which, I entreat you to take into your conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that wholesome obseruation of Saint <hi>Chrisostome, Natura rerum sic est, vt quoties bonus malo conjungitur, non ex bono malus melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,
<pb facs="4"/>
sed ex malo bonus contaminetur, sic vnum pomum malum facilè centum bonos corrumpti; at centum mala nunquam vnum corruptum efficiunt bonum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Further, to expect any new conceits from old heads, is as if a man should looke for greene fruit from withered branches. But as <hi>Time</hi> the producter of all things, though he be aged himselfe, is euery houre begetting somthing new; sowe, on whose heads he hath cast such a snow, as no radicall or naturall heate can melt, in imitation of him, (who as sure as he knowes vs borne, will as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prouide vs buriall) will neuer suffer our braines to leaue working, till our pulses cease beating. But howsoeuer the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our working be, so the matter which is wrought vpon be worthy, the value of the subiect dignifieth the invaliditie of the Vndertaker. And thus I take my leaue of thee with this gentle admonition,
<q>
         <l>Heu heu, dij mortalibus nectunt malum,</l>
         <l>Quando bonum videt quispiam &amp; non vtitur.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thin<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,
<hi>THO. HEYWOOD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>