<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the vnderstan∣ding Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122586_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03400</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13521</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122586</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the vnderstan∣ding Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole aphorismes of great Hippocrates prince of physicians: faithfully translated into English for the benefit of such as are ignorant of the Greek &amp; Latine tongs : VVhereunto is annexed a short discourse of the nature &amp; substance of the eye, with many excellent &amp; approued remedies for the cure of most the diseases thereof. With an exact table shewing the substance of euery aphorism</title>
                 <author>Hippocrates</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Redmer, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 198, 6 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>I</hi> Doubt not (gentle Reader) but thou art very well acquainted with the hardnes of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, and how vneasie it it is to translate a Greeke Authour into our english tongue, that it should car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that grace and elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as in the original. For as a fruitfull tree being remoued out of a fertile soyle, into a barren, doth
<pb facs="7"/>
rather wither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnfruitfull, then to bring forth such and the like kinde of fruit as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly it did; so dooth it happen with a diuerse translation: so that the first translation cannot haue the grace of the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, nor a second tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, that of the first, but must needs seem more harsh and barraine then the first: So I feare me it will happen with these A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorisms, which were first written in Greeke by the Authour, and after in latine, and now as thou seest in English. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="7"/>
if thou dost finde any faults committed, or anie mistaking in the translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, my request is that thou wilt rather winke at a small fault, vntill it may be amended, then to carpe with <hi>Zoilus,</hi> and doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thy selfe. Well, what the labour hath beene to the Translator, <hi>sapientum sit iudicium;</hi> this I am sure, it is for thy profit if thou list, and for the benefit of all such as doe not vnderstand eyther greeke or latine. And if thou accept of this worke kindely, thou mayst haue it hereafter in better fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion,
<pb facs="8"/>
and perhaps with a Comment. In the meane time vse these, and let the Translator haue thy good word: and so fare thou well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>