<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122560_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18933</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5351</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122560</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The converted Iew or Certaine dialogues betweene Michæas a learned Iew, and others, touching diuers points of religion, controuerted betweene the Catholicks and Protestants. Written by M. Iohn Clare a Catholicke priest, of the Society of Iesus. Dedicated to the two Vniuersities of Oxford and Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Clare, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 65, 64-421, that is 124, 2, 155, 1, 141, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="79"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="79"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ICHAEAS, after the Disputation had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>D. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers,</hi> touching Romes chang in Religion; (through which he was first made Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke and in short tyme after made Priest.) trauelleth into many Countries, to see their Vniuersities, and places of learning. At the length he arriueth in <hi>England;</hi> where from visiting of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> he cometh to <hi>Oxford.</hi> Then he findeth <hi>D. Reynolds, Ochinus,</hi> and <hi>Neuserus.</hi> They mooue him to become Protestant. He answereth, that the want of performace of the Prophecies, touching the Visibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Christs Church, in the Protestant Church, induceth him besides other reasons to continue Catholicke. Hereupon they all begin a Disputation touching the <hi>Visibility of the Protestant Church,</hi> for former ages; prefixing therto (by mutuall consent) a short Discourse of the Necessity of a continuall Visibility of the true Church. <hi>Michaeas</hi> so fully displayeth the insufficiency of the pretended Instances of Protestants, and of all other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments vrged for proofe thereof, That insteed, of <hi>Michaeas</hi> being to be made a Protestant by this Disputation; <hi>Ochinus,</hi> and <hi>Neuserus,</hi> as not acknowledging the present Roman Church to be the true Church, and seing the Prophecies, not to be fulfilled in the Protestant Church, do finally come to this point, to wit, absolutely, and openly to affirme, that the Church of Christ (as not hauing the Prophecies accomplished in it, which were foretould to be performed in the true Church of God touching it Visibilitie) is a false Church, and that our Sauiour Christ was a Seducer. Hereupon they both protest, that, from that tyme forward they do renounce the Christiā fayth, and do embrace the Iewish Religion; and so teaching Circumcision, and reuiuing the Old law, they do turne blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
<pb facs="80"/>
Iewes or Turks. <hi>Michaeas</hi> and <hi>D. Reynolds</hi> do vse vehement perswasions to them, to the contrary; but their words preuayle not; and so the disputatiō breaketh off. What courses <hi>Ochinus</hi> and <hi>Neuserus</hi> do after take for their spreading of Iudaisme, is hereafter set downe: And all the passages of their Reuolt are manifested, partly out of their owne wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and partly from the acknowledgment of diuers learned Protestants: so as their Apostacy is not feigned, but true and reall.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>