<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE LIFE of Hypocrates.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122586_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03400</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13521</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122586</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE LIFE of Hypocrates.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole aphorismes of great Hippocrates prince of physicians: faithfully translated into English for the benefit of such as are ignorant of the Greek &amp; Latine tongs : VVhereunto is annexed a short discourse of the nature &amp; substance of the eye, with many excellent &amp; approued remedies for the cure of most the diseases thereof. With an exact table shewing the substance of euery aphorism</title>
                 <author>Hippocrates</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Redmer, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 198, 6 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb facs="112"/>
   <head>THE LIFE of Hypocrates.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ypocrates</hi> by the testimony of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> was the son of one <hi>Heraclides:</hi> but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affirm him to be the sonne of Asclepius, borne and brought vp in the Isle <hi>Cos.</hi> His master and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structor was the great Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras. Hee was by his nature inclined to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: for he hated, loathed
<pb facs="113"/>
and abhorred all pomp &amp; worldly pleasures, and the vse of venerie. Hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained all his scholers by an oath to vse silence and secrecie, modesty, affabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, and humilitie as wel in manners as apparell. He restored the science of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke; beeing lost for the space almost of fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres, euen from the time of <hi>Esculapius.</hi> Hee was in body and stature very little; but fayre, and exceeding well fauoured. He had a good and strong head: he went slowely and softly: he was verie pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue and of few words: he
<pb facs="113"/>
was no great eater nor glutton: hee liued nintie fiue yeeres, and vsed often this sentence; <hi>Hee that wil liue in liberty, let him not desire that which he cannot obtaine: and hee that woulde haue that which hee desireth, let him desire nothing but that which hee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi> In like manner, He that would liue in peace in this mortall life, let him conforme himselfe to him who is inuited to a feast, who giueth thankes for all that is set before him, and grudgeth not at any thing which is omitted. He liued
<pb facs="114"/>
about the times of <hi>Elia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim,</hi> of <hi>Malachi,</hi> of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reno &amp; Socrates.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="114"/>
   <pb facs="115"/>
   <pb facs="115"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>