<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE FIRST EPISTLE OF DOCT. CONRADVS GESNERVS before his History of Foure-footed-Beastes, concer∣ning the vtility of this STORY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122276_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13820</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122276</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE FIRST EPISTLE OF DOCT. CONRADVS GESNERVS before his History of Foure-footed-Beastes, concer∣ning the vtility of this STORY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of foure-footed beastes : Describing the true and liuely figure of euery beast, with a discourse of their seuerall names, conditions, kindes, vertues (both naturall and medicinall) countries of their breed, their loue and hate to mankinde, and the wonderfull worke of God in their creation, preseruation, and destruction. Necessary for all diuines and students, because the story of euery beast is amplified with narrations out of Scriptures, fathers, phylosophers, physitians, and poets: wherein are declared diuers hyerogliphicks, emblems, epigrams, and other good histories, collected out of all the volumes of Conradus Gesner, and all other writers to this present day. By Edward Topsell</title>
                 <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 757, 15 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE FIRST EPISTLE OF DOCT. CONRADVS GESNERVS before his History of Foure-footed-Beastes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vtility of this <hi>STORY.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL PHILOSOPHY (most worthy accomplished men,) is in euery part excellent good, most beautifull, and most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the loue and honor of all mortall men, which are her Clyents and Loue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, (as all wise and excellent men haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) in euery age. But because the wits of men do differ, as education, conuersation, custome, and the profit of life and liuing, and peraduenture many other causes, do make many varieties of opinions in vs, which do possesse humaine minds; with very many preiudices, not onely in learning and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but almost in euery thing; from hence therfore it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to passe, that some do follow one part of learning which they altogether propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to themselues, or for the occasion, and profit of the present estate of their affaires.</p>
   <p>So is it with me, that I euen from a child, being brought vp of a kins-man (practitioner of Physicke) haue tasted from my youth the loue of that profession: And although I had a little conceiued the knowledge of diuers things in the encrease of my age, yet I left off the study of physicke, (more then was meete,) because I would not continue ouer long therein; yet afterwards I returned again vnto the former study thereof, the care of house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould affaires requiring the same at my handes. But when I considered the greate affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Science with naturall Phylosophy, and that not any one can be accounted an excellent or learned Physitian, which hath not drawne (as it were from a Fountaine) his first instruction from bookes of nature; I diligently began to peruse the writings of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers, which haue disputed or debated of things pertaining to nature: In which those things did chiefely delight me, which did handle or intreat concerning mettals, plantes, and liuing creatures, and that for two causes. First of all, because there may bee had of those things a more true &amp; certain knowledge then of vnperfect or mixed bodies or Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and certaine other things, too learned or curious or far remoued from sence, or such like, that a man can neuer hope for any sufficient knowledge of them, by any reason or sence.</p>
   <p>Afterwardes because their knowledge and contemplation did not onely pertaine to phisick, but also to minister and to gouerne euery thing peculiar, as other arts which were much more profitable and necessary.</p>
   <p>Therefore I spent much time in this study, so that in spared or borrowed houres, and as often as I did desire to recreate my selfe from other studies or businesses, I very desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously turned to them many yeares, accepting them for my onely pleasures and ioyes, which houres the common sort of men, and euen very many learned men, do idlely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse in walking, playing, and drinking.</p>
   <p>And although I haue considered and obserued very many thinges concerning Plants, and other things, not seene and considered before me, or at least-wise brought to
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/>
light of no man before, therefore it would seeme lesse necessary at this present to write of them, seeing that many do euen to this day write learnedly and profitably concerning plants; <hi>Geor: Agricola,</hi> a man worthy of great praise, hath most learnedly and profitably written concerning mettals: wherefore I applyed my mind to the History of foure-foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted-beastes handled lightly in our age, and onely in partes. But when that I saw I should profit but little, except I should adioyn the Histories of those that haue trauailed in other countries, to these priuate studies, and gathering of our owne. I went first of all to some points of the Germans, (but not many) and by and by after, I did adde thereunto mine owne trauailes into Italy, not onely for this cause, but for the honor of my <hi>Bybliothaeca,</hi> that I might reckon vp all kind of writers therein for the further honor thereof: But if I had met with any <hi>Mecoenas,</hi> or had had further ability, or my fortunes greater, I had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed further, both by Sea and land, into far remote places, for the enlarging of the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both of beasts and plants, for the benefit of all posterity, although I am in my selfe a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weake and sickly man. But because that was not lawful, by reason I wanted sufficient meanes, I haue done that which I could, and haue got also some friendes vnto me out of diuers regions or parts of Europe, with whom after I communicated my purposes, they returned vnto me sundry discriptions of strange beasts, and the moderne names of vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar beasts in many languages, with their pictures and the true formes. In the meane time I did not only sit still and turne ouer books, but gaue my selfe diligently to enquire of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Country-man or trauailer, a perticular and exact obseruation of the nature of euery beast: and for this cause I conferred with strangers of other nations, which by any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion either were resident among vs, or passed accidentally through our country, &amp; made of their relation the most diligent notes that I could gather, conferring them with olde writers, and comparing one with another, till I had digested the perfection of my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted story, and the method thereof for the drawing of it into a perfect body.</p>
   <p>And thus by little and little the worke or volume increased, not only by my great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile and paines, but also to my great cost and charge, considering my poore and needy estate: when I thought that it was growne great enough (for if all things grow infinite and endlesse) then I disposed it to be printed and published to the world, least that by defering the diuulgation thereof vnder colour to learne moe thinges, that might happen to mee, which befalleth all men (namely Death) and so I should by my owne modesty or backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, not onely ouerthrow my owne labours, but also depriue well deseruing men, of the vniuersall benifit to be reaped by this story. Then I determined first of all to begin with the story of foure-footed-beasts, such as are not generated in parts and vnperfectly as it were in an Egge, but perfectly and totally together in the dams belly, because they were not onely the most worthy, principall, and excellent, among all the creatures of this World next vnto men, but also, because their naturall parts of body and disposition, do most of all resemble mankind. And of the residue, namely, such as are conceiued out of Egges, either foure-footed, or Birds, or Fishes, or Serpents, or reptiles, (if God permit) we will entreat perticularly in another Tome by itselfe. And thus much for the order, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, occasion, and edition of this worke.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifit of this story to phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke.</note>But some man will inquire the cause and reason of so great a labor and study, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of me what fruites, profit, and benefit, can come by this History? To whom I make this answere: First, the knowledge of this naturall part of Phylosophye, is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary and profitable to Physicke, and that many waies; First, for that many beastes are vsed for meate, nourishment, and medicine, and for that cause are not only applied out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but inwardly to the body of man: &amp; then more particularly, because about four-footed-beasts which breed in their own kind, for because of the similitude they carry with mankind in body and affections, they suffer many diseases in common with vs, which are cured by euery heard-man and leach in the fields: and also the beasts themselues do offer many profitable medicines for the cure of men; which the skilful Phisitian must borrow from them, if he wil be perfect in his art, and conscionable in his profession. But if that a man bee wounded or poysoned by serpentes, Lyzards, creeping creatures, or by the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of any foure-footed-beast in his madnesse, or by fishes, or by eating them in meat, wherein the Phisitians skill is required, to shew the cause and cure of such a wounde,
<pb facs="8"/>
where shall he find better direction, then to be informed of the particular venom that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hid in euery beast by nature, which thing we haue endeuored to explaine in this our Treatise. Moreouer there are many necessary obseruations about meate, drinke, sleepe, watching, quietnesse, and perturbation of affections in men, and other naturall motions whereby health is to be preserued, the perfectest rules and examples thereof are to bee drawen from bruit beasts, vnto the vse of men.</p>
   <p>And I haue proued by the inspection into this knowledge, that herein is layed the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest foundation of Medicine, either by drawing it from those things which do naturally flow and fall from the beasts, or that which they suffer and endure, or else from those things which they haue obserued to be in them; for it more safe and without impiety, to make tryall of a new Medicine vpon a beast, rather then vpon a man. And lastly, seeing diuers Medicines arise out of euery part of euery beast almost, all which we haue recited in one place Methodically together, and part after part, heereby the Physitian shall reape this commodity, that when he hath any beast in his hand, by looking into this worke he shall find what part he ought to reserue for medicine, and also to what sicknesse it is to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. And after the same maner may euery man chuse his meat, and know by this treatise what is most, and what is least nourishable, and agreeable to the nature of man. And if it pleased me to rehearseal that commeth into this catalogue about vtility of beasts, I would shew you how many arts and occupations of men, do raise maintenance and sustentation from beasts, both to sell them for mony, and also to take them for meate: as the Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which follow the waters, taking for food such fishes as by the ordinance of God, are ordained for that purpose.</p>
   <p>They which are Grasyers and keepe cattell of all sorts, liue vpon their changing, fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, feeding, and selling. Those which make Butter and Cheese, whereof there are many in the Mountaines of <hi>Heluctia,</hi> liue only vpon that labour, and therefore the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Kye, Oxen, Asses, Elkes, Reyners, Camels, and diuers other beastes, is most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for these men, from whom they draw Milke, and therefore good to maintaine and preserue their health. There be some Horse-leaches, Cowe-leaches, Oxe-leaches, and such like for this purpose. There be that liue only vpon the Marchandizes of their skins, as Tawyers, Glouers, Curriers, Shoomakers, and Breast plate-makers of Leathers, Sadlers, Leather-sellers, Purse-makers, and such like.</p>
   <p>Some againe haue an Art to dresse the skins with their haire and wooll vpon them, for garments. Some liue by keambing, shearing, spinning, clothing, and making sundry ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries out of wooll, Goats haire, and Camels haire. For the vse of the cattell aliue, I might be endlesse to shew all, first the husbandmen vse Oxen and Asses, the vse of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Mules, both for trauaile and plowing, and carriage. The Art of riding commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable for all sorts of men, both in peace and warre, not onely for great Princes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches, but for euery Cittizen: many things are vsed for buildings which canot be drawn or brought together, but by Oxen, Horsses, Mules, Asses, Camels, Elephants, Reyners, Elkes, and such like. Who knoweth not the vse of Dogges, for they keepe Houses, and cattell, and they attend, guard, and defend men: they hunt wilde beasts, they driue them away, or kill, or retaine them to the hand of man, that he may be conqueror of them. In fine, the knowledge of beasts is profitable to many arts, sciences, and occupations, which may be better perceiued, by the particular practize and application of him that is studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thereof, then by any other meanes.</p>
   <p>But in the worke it selfe, it shalbe manifested what vse and commodity ariseth out of euery beast, what remedies, or Medicines, what for garmentes, what for meate, what for carriage, what for prognostication of euill weather, what for pleasure and pastimes; so as we shall not need to prosecute these parts in this present Epistle.</p>
   <p>Also there want not instructions out of beasts, by imitation of whose examples, the liues and manners of men are to be framed to another and a better practise, which thing is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested by learned and wise men, but especially by <hi>Theodorus Gaza,</hi> who discourseth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in his Praeface vpon the bookes of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> of the partes of creatures; whose wordes we will recite in the Epistle to our Reader.</p>
   <p>But if I should shew at large and copiously, how many things may be collected out of
<pb facs="9"/>
the knowledge of beasts for familiar and houshold affaires, I might be infinite: but seeing I haue already shewed how necessary they bee for husbandry, for meat, for carriage, and such like, it must be vnderstood that all those commodities belong to this part of Occo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominall profit.</p>
   <p>The like I may say of the pleasure in their contemplation; for although all their vtilities cannot be knowne, and in many thinges they are not beneficiall to men, yet if a man be skilful and haue any vnderstanding, he shal be much delighted by looking into the natures of beasts, by consideration of the many and infinite differences among them, whether he respect their body, or their minds, or their actions: for what is more wonderfull then the voice or extemporall song of many Birdes, who although they be far distant and remote from vs, and will not abide our presence for natural fear of death, yet is not the eleborate deuise of musicall and artificiall numbers, measures, and voyces of men comparable vnto them. <hi>Pliny</hi> that Star and ornament of his time, spendeth a great deale of labour in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the Nightingale. And what man withall his witte, can sufficiently declare and proclaime the wonderful industrious minds of the little Emmets and Bees, moued almost with no bodies, being silly things, and yet indued with noble and commendable qualities, in deformed members; so that I might conclude, that there is not any beast which hath not onely somthing in it which is rare, glorious, and peculiar to himselfe, but also some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is deuine.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I may seeme a foole, to handle these things in a Praeface which are copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously discoursed in the whole worke. <hi>Aristotle</hi> maketh it a true property of a Noble, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and well gouerned mind, to be more delighted with the rare, plesant, and admirable qualities of a beast, then with the lucre and gaine that commeth thereby.</p>
   <p>For it is a token of a filthy, beastly, illiberall, and wretched mind, to loue no more then we can reape commodity by. There be very many things which do not yeald any profit to the possessors or owners, but only please them, &amp; allure their minds by outward form and beauty, so do the most pretious stones, as Adamants, Topazyes, Iacynthes, Smaradgs Chrysolytes, and many such other thinges; by the wearing whereof, no man is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red either from sicknesse or perill (although some superstitious persons put confidence in them for such vertues) but haue crept into the fauour and treasures of men, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause like earthly stars they shine and glitter in the eies of men, resembling the resplendant glory and light of heauenly bodies, and other vse they haue none: and in the meane time, he that should prefer free-stones fitted and squared for buildings, or else Whet-stones, or Mil-stones, and such like, which are most necessary for priuate vse and commodity, yet doe they seeme vile in comparison of others; and that should prefer all of them before one of the other, he should be acounted no wiser then <hi>Aesops</hi> Cocke: and if he should but equall them in price and estimation in like sort, he should be iudged an egregious blocke or foole; and yet the best of these are without life, without spirit, immoueable, and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. For this cause there is none of the creatures but deserue, a far more admiration and esteeme; and among liuing creatures, all those which containe noble spirits in base and vile bodies, without apt Organs and instrumentes for the better mouing of their bodies: For as in clocks we admire the lesser more then the greater, so ought we to admire the les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser narrow bodies indued with such industrious spirits, more then the greater, broader, and larger beasts: for all workemen do shew more art, skill, and cunning in the small and little price of worke, then the greater.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Solinus</hi> writeth, that <hi>Alexander</hi> the great had <hi>Homers Illiads</hi> writen in Parchment, so close together, that it might be contained in a Nut-shell. The like admiration was there of the exile and curious small works of <hi>Myrmicidas</hi> the <hi>Milesian,</hi> and <hi>Callicrates</hi> the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> for they made Chariots so small, that they might be couered with and vnder a flye, and in the brim thereof they wrote two exameter verses in Golden letters. And of <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, Solinus</hi> writeth, that hee made little Emmets out of Iuory so artificially, that it could not be discerned from the liue ones: euen so, nature hath stroue and strained, to excell more in these vile creatures of no reputation, then in greater and nobler creatures. There is nothing that consisteth of matter and forme, but that one of them is worthyer, and the other vile; and therefore the body and the soule in man, haue the respect of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="9"/>
and the soul is the form, because of the power of mouing▪ sences, and actions: where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore when we see all these powers, as it were predominant in a little creature that hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most no body (as the outward proportion of Emmets and Bees) what shal we thinke? but how admirably is it able to worke without the matter in the forme alone, shewing it in a kind of visible nakednes, to be seene without the help of corporall Organs; and therefore they are not set before vs like sports &amp; pastimes to reioyce at, but as honorable emblems of Diuine and supernaturall wisedome. For if we admire the little body of a man, because he beareth the most glorious ymage of all thinges in his proportion, and the ymage of God in his soule and minde, then certainely next to a man, wee ought to admire these beasts, which do so resemble man, as man doeth the eternall and liuing God, creator of them and him. <hi>Pliny</hi> vnskilfully calleth nature the common parent of al creatures, which indeed is the infinite maiesty of God; yet he writeth effectually, that there was no liuing creature made onely for this cause, that it should eat, or that it should satiate and satisfie other, but also it was ordained to be bred and brought foorth for sauing Arts; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ingrafted euen in the bowels and intrals of deafe and dumbe things.</p>
   <p>Now for the creatures which are profitable to men, as sheep, Oxen, Horses, and such like, when we looke vppon them, wee cannot onely admire the wisedome and power of God in their creation, but also we ought to giue hereby thanks to his maiesty for their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and conseruation in their seuerall kinds and orders, for the vse and behoofe of men. And for those things which are altogither vnprofitable to men, we ought to woonder as much at their vilenesse, as they want of profitablenes: For those admirable gifts and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers are not common to all little beasts, as we see they are in Elephants, Lyons, Camels, &amp; such other, for then we should wonder at them the lesse; but yet in som of the litle ones there are farre more excellent properties then in any of the greatest. Consider with what art and indrustry the Bee frameth her Combe, and the Emmet storeth her nest, and tell me if the wit and eloquence of man, be able sufficiently to expresse and praise it? Beside, their perpetuall concord, dilligence, and agreement in the administration, gathring, and spending of all their store, inso much as eyther they seem to be deriued from nature or els from a deep reach of wit, reason, and vnderstanding: neither are they the lesse admirable if we grant that these vertures are not natural and proper, nor proceeding from reason &amp; wil, for they are no lesse the strange or stranger worke of God: For what a Diuine thing is it, that these beasts attaine to that vpon a sudden, without instruction and teaching, and therefore by instinct and a kind of reuelation which men do not attaine in long exercise, practise &amp; study? These are assuredly euident testimonies of diuinity (for the Lord is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous in al his works, either in nature, or reason &amp; wil, or contrary to both, without al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceeding mean, for al these haue dependance vpon his pleasure. For how can his Diuine power, wisedome, and goodnesse, euer be absent from the world, (I meane from man the prince of the world) when such excellent gifts are made visible in little beasts, that euerie day perish and are corrupted easily, and ingendered againe by their owne putrifaction, so as they neuer faile in kind, euen those that are so smal &amp; little in body, that they can scarse be seen by the eies of man? these things are to me vnanswerable argumēts of the presence and power of God: for that they moue and bee in action it proceedeth of his power, in that they vse their sences, and there by follow and attaine those things which are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them, and avoyd al hurtful things contrary to their nature, because they build them houses and places of habitation, make prouision for their food and victuals it proceedeth of his wisedome; but in that they nourish their young ones, &amp; loue one another in al out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, liuing in flocks togither, as if they had knowledge of society, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnanimously to their work and labour, it is likewise a token and visible emblem of his goodnes. The first cause therefore of these virtues, or whatsoeuer you wil cal them, <hi>Idea,</hi> or Original, must needs be the absolute example of God the Creator.</p>
   <p>And wee must not suppose, that his most excellent Maiesty hath proponed these pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes vnto vs by chance or rashly, without purpose of this end; that it should be to vs as cleare as the light (<hi>Omnia diuinitatis esse plena</hi>) that all things are full of his Diuinity: see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that a <hi>Sparrow lighteth not on the ground without his will</hi>: And the poet saide: <hi>God is in the middest of Beasts, Men, Markets, and Sea.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>And heere I cannot containe my selfe from relating the words of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> for I trust that no man will blame me, if I alledge and write any thing truely and fitly, although it be in another mans words: for it is not to be regarded who saith, but what is sayed or spoken.</p>
   <p>Thus therefore he writeth: <q>Among those creatures which are lesse acceptable to our sences, nature which is the common mother of all, hath ordained many delightes and pleasures in them, for men which vnderstand their cause or can reason of their Natures liberally: for this thing is absurd and farre from all reason, that because we cannot looke vppon the ymages and vpper faces of creatures and naturall thinges, painted and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, without we also behold in them the wit and Art of the Painter, and that therefore we can take lesse pleasure in the worke, for the Worke-mans sake.</q>
   </p>
   <q>
      <p>For if we can attaine to the true causes, we shall no lesse kisse and imbrace the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the very actions of naturall thinges, with woonderfull diligence and ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity: and for this cause it is a base thinge to despise the nature and constitution of the smaller and viler beasts, fit for Boyes and childish minds; for there is not any work of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein there is not some wonderfull thing, therefore that is true which <hi>Heraclitus</hi> sayed to them that followed him vnto a hot-house, wherein he sat to warme his body, and when he perceiued that they were affraid to come in, he cryed out vnto them, that they should abstaine &amp; forbeare to enter boldly, because <hi>Ne hinc quidem loco desunt dij immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis:</hi> That euen in this place you shall finde the immortall Gods.</p>
      <p>And this rule must be followed in looking into the nature of Beasts: for we ought to enter into their consideration without feare or blushing, seeing the operation of nature is euery where very honest and beautifull, for therein is nothing done inconsideratly, and without a true end, but all things aduisedly for a certain and determinat purpose, and this purpose doth alway containe both goodnes and honesty.</p>
      <p>But if any man be so Barbarous, as to thinke that the beasts and such other, creatures, cannot affoord him any subiect woorthy of his contempaltion, then let him thinke so of himselfe likewise; for what ignoble basenesse is there in bloode, flesh, bones, vaines, and such like? Doth not the body of man consist thereof? And then how abhominable art thou to thy selfe, that doest not rather looke into these which are so neere of kinde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee?</p>
   </q>
   <p>
      <q>And I may adde as much of them, that reason of matter without forme, or vse forme without matter, as of a house without the sides, or of a vessell without the best part; and and so is he that looketh vppon one part of nature and not the whole: or on those things which cannot be seuered from the substaunce,</q>
      <hi>Thus farre Aristotle,</hi> whose wordes I haue expressed at large, because as we haue borrowed all his substance, and inserted it into our discourse, so I thought it not good to omit his preface.</p>
   <p>Seeing these thinges are thus, we cannot but thinke that euery story of a beast is like a seuerall Hymne, to praise the Diuine wisdome and goodnes, from which as from a pure euer-springing-fountaine, proceed and flow all good, beautifull, and wise actions: First, thorough the heauenly spirits and degrees of Angels and celestial bodies: afterward tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the minds of men, beginning at the highest, and so proceeding to the lowest, (for euen in men the giftes and graces of God differ,) and from men to other creatures that haue life or sence; as to plants and inanimate bodyes, so as the inferiors do alwaies so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselues to the imitation of the superiours, euen as their shaddowes and resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaunces.</p>
   <p>And in these doth Diuinity descend, first to supernaturall things, and then to things naturall: and we must turne saile and ascend first by things naturall, before we can attaine and reach thinges supernaturall. In the meane time Diuinity it selfe remaineth one and the same, without change and alteration, notwithstanding the manifold increasings and decreasings of all these creatures, which it vseth but as Glasses and Organs; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuersity both of matter and forme, it shineth and appeareth in one and other more or lesse, euen as we see in our owne bodies, whose soule is disseminated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery part and member, yet is there a more liuely representation thereof in one part and member, then in another, and the faculties more visibly and sensibly appeare
<pb facs="10"/>
in the vpper then in the neather partes; But yet with this difference, that the soule is so ioyned to the body, as with a kind of Sympathy it suffereth harme and ioy with the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect wherein it is circumscribed, but none of these things do happen to the Diuinity: for it is so communicated to creatures, as it neither is any part or matter, or forme of them; nor yet can be affected by any thing the creature suffereth, nor yet included in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but yet is in all, and ouer all, and without all, and aboue all, compassing, filling, and surpassing heauen and earth: infinite and impossible, and concluding the whole World, visible and inuisible.</p>
   <p>And truely these thinges surpasse all the wit of man, for we are not able with thought, and much lesse with wordes, to expresse it, and yet we ought not to be deterred for any cause from the consideration and contemplation thereof, but rather after we haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the same, with all humility to acknowledge his power, and to view all the helps for our infirmitimes: to admire his wisedome, and endeuour thereby to amend our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and encrease our knowledge: and in conclusion, to beate downe our pride and malice, by praysing and extolling his grace and goodnesse. For being thus affected and conuersant, in beholding these neather and backer partes of God, confessing with thankes giuing that all these thinges doe proceede from his Diuinity, we cannot stay but ascend vppe higher, to the worker himselfe, vsing all thinges in this life but as Prickes and Spurres, for occasion and admonitions to thinke vppon and reuerence the prime Author.</p>
   <p>For we haue continuall neede in this World to be put in mind and incited to the study and contemplation of heauenly thinges: and so we shall leaue all these things behind vs after this mortal life ended, and by the help of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, who by his onely death hath prepared for vs a way to the kingdome of ineffable glory, where we shall partake with the forepartes, and most cleare reuelation of the vnspeakeable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty of God for this is the end of our life, for which we were created, and also the scope and conclusion of all naturall knowledge of the works of God.</p>
   <p>And least that any man should thinke that these thinges are ours, or the heathen Phylosphers sayings, and cannot be defended out of the sacred and supreme Testimony of holy Scriptures, I will also adde some few sayings recorded in the booke of God. First of all therefore, when in the beginning of the World God was about to create man, who was to vse al things, and to behold them in this World as it were in a Theater, he created all kind of Beastes and creatures before man, that he might bring him into a house fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished and adorned with all thinges necessary and delectable: Afterward he brought into his presence all the creatures to bee named by him, which the Scripture recordeth for excellency sake, (for it is no doubt but he named all thinges that should continue to the Worldes end) yet expressely there is no mention but of liuing creatures, as Fishes, Foules, Cattell, and creeping things; that so they might be submitted and vassalaged to his Empire, authority, and gouernment: which thing least it should seeme but a proud coniecture, it is againe repeated in the blessing that God pronounceth to man and all his posterity; and againe after the floud vnto <hi>Noah</hi> and his Childeren. <hi>Euery beast</hi> (saith God) <hi>shall be afraid of you, both the Beastes of the earth, and the Foules of heauen, and what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is bred in the earth, or brought forth in the Sea; all are yours, whatsoeuer liueth and moueth it is permitted to you for meate.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And before when the floud was at hand, God commaunded <hi>Noah</hi> to suffer all beastes that could not liue in the Water to enter the Arke, and of Foules and cleane Birds seuen of a kind, of impure, couples; to the intent that as for man they were at first created, and produced out of the earth, so hee would that man should concerue their kindes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contempt of them that were vncleane beasts.</p>
   <p>Furthermore in the booke of Kings, we read of <hi>Salomon,</hi> that God gaue him such wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that he excelled all the wise and learned men of the world, and among other fruits and tokens of that wisedome there is remembred his parables three thousand, his verses aboue fiue thousande, his History of plantes from the high Caedar, to the Hysope stalke, and lastly his discourse of Beasts, Birds, Fishes, and creeping things. <hi>What is man</hi> (sayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>that thou shouldst so remember him, or the sonne of man, that thou shouldst visite him.
<pb facs="11"/>
Thou hast set him ouer the works of thy hands, and hast set all things vnder his feet: Oxen sheep, Foules, Fishes, and whatsoeuer moueth in the Waters.</hi> And the same King and prophet in another place. <hi>Psal.</hi> 148. <hi>Praise the Lord, Dragons and all deepes, ye wilde beasts and creeping creatures.</hi> But how can Beastes praise the Lord? Or how could they vnderstand the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets exhortation? Surely, therefore we are commaunded to praise God for them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing his goodnesse and wisedome in all these beastes which hee produced for the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this present world.</p>
   <p>And because of these creatures the works of God, the Apostle S. <hi>Paule</hi> in the Epistle to the Romans, Chapt. 2. telleth the Ethinckes that they are vnexcusable before God, for that they knew him by the creatures of his works, and yet did not glorifie him as God, neither were gratefull: <hi>For the inuisible thinges of God, as his eternall power and wisedome are seene by the creation of the World.</hi> And lastly in the History of <hi>Iob.</hi> Ch. 38, 39. you shall find a large discourse to <hi>Iob</hi> from the Lords owne mouth, concerning many beasts. And these thinges may bee spoken, concerning the excellency and dignity of the History of beasts, whereunto I will adde some examples of the most famous men and Kings of the world, to shew what account they made of this learning: and so I will conclude this Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</p>
   <p>First what account heereof was made by Alexander the great, may be gathered by that which Pliny writeth, for he saith, that he being enflamed with the desire to know the beasts and natures of creatures, appointed <hi>Aristotle</hi> (that infinite learned man) to write his books of creatures, commaunding many thousands, both in Asia and Graecia, which exercised Hunting, Hawking, Fishing, or that kepte Parkes, Heards of cattell, Fish-ponds, or any cages or other places and groues for Birds, to be at the commaund of the said <hi>Aristotle</hi> if neede were, to supply his desires in the knowledge of beastes; So that whatsoeuer was knowne in the whole world, might not be vnknowne to him: by whose helps (Pliny affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,) that hee wrote first the volumes, which hee saith he had abridged, to shew to the World in a short view the fruites of those desires, of the most Noble amonge all Kings.</p>
   <p>When <hi>Aristotle</hi> had finished this story and offered the same to King Alexander, hee offered him for his paines fovre hundered tallents; saying that it was a Kings gift to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward such a knowledge; wherein, beside other parts of learning, Riding, Hunting, Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and Fishing, which were Princely sportes were deciphered. But if Alexander were now aliue, he would wonder, that among innumerable other princely bounties which he conferred and bestowed vpon the World, there should bee none that so encreased his honor and continueth his fame, as this one worke, although it bee contemned among many vulgar, base minded men; for he ouercame almost all the kingdomes of the world, and builded great Citties, but his owne kingdom soon after becam distracted, and rent in foure peeces, and so deuolued, one part to the Romans, and other parts to other Kings, the Citties are either ouerthrowne, or the names chaunged, or inhabited by Barbarous people, altogether vnlearned, that doe not so much as now remember or acknowledge who was there first founder.</p>
   <p>Also there haue perished the bookes of many writers that compiled his History, and set forth his valiant actes and renowned fortunes, so that of many, there scarce remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth one or two. But the History of beastes and other creatures, which was made at his cost and charges, hath runne through many ages and beene preserued for a thousand and nine hundered yeares, to the great glory and commendation both of the King, and the writer <hi>Aristotle.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And he is not more honored for his liberality toward the Phylosopher for his worke among posterity, but also the fruite and vtilitye thereof to all ages, hath beene greater then any that arose from the kingdomes that he got, or the battailes that he wan; for how can posterity account that beneficiall to them, which the men of that age found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be so hurtfull and full of calamity?</p>
   <p>Many thousandes of men perished onely for the pleasure of one ALEXANDERS ambitious desire of raygning, many Common-wealthes were chaunged, Regions
<pb facs="11"/>
and countries wasted, and many publicke and priuat miseries followed, as is vsuall where warre ouerturneth kingdomes. Therefore I say againe, he neuer did any thing in all his life, whereby he wan so great fame and renowne, then by being first of all the occasion to <hi>Aristotle,</hi> to vndertake the labour, and then afterward a liberall rewarder thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Petrus Gillius</hi> writeth, that all the stories of creatures were either compiled by Kings, or else dedicated to Kings; for to omit others who were diligent in heards, and curious enquirers into the natures of beasts, <hi>Iuba, Hieron, Attalus, Philometor,</hi> and <hi>Archelaus,</hi> wrot many thinges of the force and nature of creatures. <hi>Opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anus Anazarbensis</hi> (a most learned Poet) when he had finished his poems of the creatures, he dedicated them to <hi>Antoninus,</hi> the Sonne of the Emperour <hi>Seuerus</hi>; for which, hee was bidden to aske what he would: and whereas he was but a banished man, he asked liberty to dwell againe at home in his owne Country, which he not onely obtained, but also receiued for euery verse a peece of Gold worth a Noble, and there were in his two poems, about fiue thousand and eight hundered verses: for which cause the learned Poet in ioy of such a reward, wrote his verses in Gold, bycause he saide he would haue it worthily called a Golden Poem. Of this kind he wrote two, one of hunting, and another of fishing.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>C. Plinius Secundus</hi> wrote a story of the World, wherein he writeth but briefely of all thinges in the World, and yet largely and copiously of plants and beasts, and so dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to the Emperor <hi>Vespasian,</hi> for which hee was alway deare and familiar vnto him. <hi>Auicen</hi> being an excellent Physitian and a counseller of estate to <hi>Vzirus</hi> a King of <hi>Persia,</hi> for which dignity many called him a Prince, yet he disdained not to write of beastes, and to interpret <hi>Aristotle</hi> in many of those books. And this is no maruaile that so many of the ancientes did thus magnifie the knowledge of all kindes of creatures, seeing as <hi>Varro</hi> writeth, they were almost all Sheapheards, Goate-heardes, Neat-heards, and therefore they said that their flocks had Golden fleeces, for the commodity they found in them, as <hi>Atreus</hi> at <hi>Argos,</hi> and <hi>Aeetes</hi> at <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lchos.</hi> Who is he but he knoweth that the Roman peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had their originall from Sheapheards? Who knoweth not that <hi>Faustulus</hi> the Nurse of <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Remus,</hi> was a Sheapheard? And this was an argument hereof, because that they builded their citty for Sheapheards, that they appointed amercements by Oxen and Sheepe, and that they stamped their Mony with such pictures: and how many names are there among the Romans deriued from cattell and sheep, as <hi>Ouinius, Caprillus, Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Taurus,</hi> and sur-names also, as <hi>Annij, Caprae, Statilij Tauri,</hi> and <hi>Pomponij Vituli.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We reade in holy scripture that <hi>Abraham</hi> was onely rich in cattell, and that King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did keepe his fathers flock, and hereunto also belongeth, that the most wise and great men among the ancients were students in Anatomy, and the dissection of parts of mens bodies, instituting children therin from their first learning of letters; Now no man think that they fetched this knowledge from the partes of mens bodies at the beginning, but from beastes, as Dogs, Apes, Swine, and such other, wherewithall they were exercised as in rudiments and grounds, that they might be more prompt, ready, and experienced in the bodies of men. And among other <hi>Marcus</hi> the Roman Emperor was most skilfull and studious in this science of Anatomy, and the Egyptian Kings did the like with their owne handes. <hi>Boethus,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Sergius,</hi> two Roman Consuls, and other principall men, were auditors to <hi>Galen. Thus farre Conradus Gesner.</hi> In the next Epistle he discourseth to the reader of his method and order obserued in his books, and also of other necessary things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this History, which I haue thought good also to insert into this place.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>