<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧THE TABLE AND❧ Kalender, expressing the ordre of the Psalmes and Lessons, to be sayed at Matyns and Euensong, throughout the yeare, excepte certayne proper feastes, as the Rules folowing more plainlye de∣clare.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122894_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72693</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16270a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122894</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧THE TABLE AND❧ Kalender, expressing the ordre of the Psalmes and Lessons, to be sayed at Matyns and Euensong, throughout the yeare, excepte certayne proper feastes, as the Rules folowing more plainlye de∣clare.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of the common prayer : and administracion of the sacramentes, and other rites and ceremonies of the Churche: after the vse of the Churche of England</title>
                 <author>Church of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, clvii, 1 leave, tables, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧<hi>THE TABLE AND</hi>❧ Kalender, expressing the ordre of the Psalmes and Lessons, to be sayed at Matyns and Euensong, throughout the yeare, excepte certayne proper feastes, as the Rules folowing more plainlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</head>
   <div type="order_of_Psalter_readings">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>❧<hi>THE ORDRE</hi>❧ how the Psalter is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee redde.</head>
      <p>THe Psalter shalbe red through, once euery Moneth, &amp; because that some Monethes be longer then some other be: it is thought good, to make thē euen by this meanes.</p>
      <p>To euery Moneth, as concernyng this purpose, shalbe appointed iust .xxx. dayes.</p>
      <p>And because Ianuary and Marche hath one daye, aboue the sayed nombre, and February whiche is placed betwene them bothe, hath onely .xxviii. daies, February shall borowe of either of the Monethes of Ianuary and Marche one daye, and so the Psalter whiche shalbe red in Februarye, muste bee begon the laste daye of Ianuary, and ended the first daye of Marche.</p>
      <p>And whereas Maie, Iuly, August, October, and December, haue .xxxi. dayes a piece, it is ordred that thesame Psalmes shall bee redde the last daye of the saied Monethes, whiche were red the daye before: so that the Psalter maye bee begon agayne the first daye of the next Monethes ensuing.</p>
      <p>Now to know what Psalmes shalbe red euery daye, looke in the Kalendar the nombre that is appointed for the Psalmes, and then finde thesame noum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre in this Table, and vpon that noumbre shall you se, what Psalmes shalbee sayd at Matyns, and Euensong.</p>
      <p>And where the .C.xix. Psalme is deuided into .xxii. porcions, and is ouer long to bee red at one tyme: it is so ordred that at one tyme shall not bee red a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue .iiii. or .v. of the saied porcions, as you shall perceiue to bee noted in this Table.</p>
      <p>And here is also to be noted, that in this Table, and in al other partes of the seruice, where any Psalmes are appoincted, the nombre is expressed after the greate Englishe Bible, whiche from the .ix. Psalme vnto the .C.xlviii. Psalme (folowyng the diuision of the Ebrues) doeth vary in nombres from the comō Latyn translacion.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="calendar_of_Psalter_readings">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <p>
         <table>
            <head>❧<hi>A TABLE FOR</hi>❧ the ordre of the Psalmes, to be sayed at Matins and Euensong.</head>
            <row>
               <cell cols="2">¶Matins.</cell>
               <cell rows="31"> </cell>
               <cell>¶Euensong.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>i</cell>
               <cell>i.ii.iii.iiii.v.</cell>
               <cell>vi.vii.viii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>ii</cell>
               <cell>ix.x.xi.</cell>
               <cell>xii.xiii.xiiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>iii</cell>
               <cell>xv.xvi.xvii.</cell>
               <cell>xviii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>iiii</cell>
               <cell>xix.xx.xxi.</cell>
               <cell>xxii.xxiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>v</cell>
               <cell>xxiiii.xxv.xxvi.</cell>
               <cell>xxvii.xxviii.xxix.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>vi</cell>
               <cell>xxx.xxxi.</cell>
               <cell>xxxii.xxxiii.xxxiiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>vii</cell>
               <cell>xxxv.xxxvi.</cell>
               <cell>xxxvii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>viii</cell>
               <cell>xxxviii.xxxix.xl.</cell>
               <cell>xli.xlii.xliii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>ix</cell>
               <cell>xliiii.xlv.xlvi.</cell>
               <cell>xlvii.xlviii.xlix.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>x</cell>
               <cell>l.li.lii.</cell>
               <cell>liii.liiii.lv.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xi</cell>
               <cell>lvi.lvii.lviii.</cell>
               <cell>lix lx.lxi.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xii</cell>
               <cell>lxii.lxiii.lxiiii.</cell>
               <cell>lxv.lxvi.lxvii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xiii</cell>
               <cell>lxviii.</cell>
               <cell>lxix.lxx.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xiiii</cell>
               <cell>lxxi.lxxii.</cell>
               <cell>lxxiii.lxxiiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xv</cell>
               <cell>lxxv.lxxvi.lxxvii.</cell>
               <cell>lxxviii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xvi</cell>
               <cell>lxxix.lxxx.lxxxi.</cell>
               <cell>lxxxii.lxxxiii.lxxxiiii.lxxxv.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xvii</cell>
               <cell>lxxxvi.lxxxvii.lxxxviii.</cell>
               <cell>lxxxix.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xviii</cell>
               <cell>xc.xci.xcii.</cell>
               <cell>xciii.xciiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xix</cell>
               <cell>xcv.xcvi.xcvii.</cell>
               <cell>xcviii.xcix.c.ci.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xx</cell>
               <cell>cii.ciii.</cell>
               <cell>ciiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxi</cell>
               <cell>cv.</cell>
               <cell>cvi.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxi</cell>
               <cell>cvii.</cell>
               <cell>cviii.cix.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxiii</cell>
               <cell>cx.cxi.cxii.cxiii.</cell>
               <cell>cxiiii.cxv.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxiiii</cell>
               <cell>cxvi.cxvii.cxviii.</cell>
               <cell>cxix. Inde .iiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxv</cell>
               <cell>Inde .v.</cell>
               <cell>Inde .iiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxvi</cell>
               <cell>Inde .v.</cell>
               <cell>Inde .iiii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxvii</cell>
               <cell>cxx cxxi cxxii cxxiii cxxiiii cxxv</cell>
               <cell>cxxvi.cxxvii.cxxviii.cxxix.cxxx.cxxxi</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxviii</cell>
               <cell>cxxxii.cxxxiii.cxxxiiii.cxxxv.</cell>
               <cell>cxxxvi.cxxxvii.cxxxviii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxix</cell>
               <cell>cxxxix.cxl.cxli.</cell>
               <cell>cxlii.cxliii.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>xxx</cell>
               <cell>cxliiii.cxlv.cxlvi.</cell>
               <cell>cxlvii.cxlviii.cxlix.cl.</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="order_of_Scriptural_readings">
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>
         <hi>THE ORDRE</hi> howe the rest of holy Scripture (beside the Psalter) is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee redde.</head>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The olde Testamēt.</note>THe old Testament is appoynted for the first Lessons, at Matins and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uensong, and shal bee redde through euery yere once, except certain bokes and Chapiters, whiche bee least edifying, and might best be spared, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are left vnred.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The newe Testamēt.</note>The newe Testament is appoynted for the second Lessons, at Matins and Euensong, and shalbe red ouer ordrely euery yere thrise, beside the Epistles and Gospelles: except the Apocalips, out of the whiche there be onely certain Lessons appoynted vpon diuerse proper feastes.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Lessons.</note>And to knowe what Lessons shall bee red euery daye: finde the daye of the Moneth in the Kalendar folowyng: and there ye shal perceiue the bookes and Chapiters, that shalbe red for the Lessons, bothe at Matins and Euensong.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Proper Psalmes.</note>And here is to be noted, that whensoeuer there be any proper Psalmes or Lessons, appoynted for any feast, moueable or vnmoueable: thē the Psalmes and Lessons appoynted in the Kalendar, shall bee omitted for that tyme.</p>
      <p>Ye muste note also that the Collect, Epistle, and Gospel, appoynted for the Sundaye, shall serue all the weeke after, except there falsome feast that hath his propre.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The Leape yeare.</note>This is also to bee noted, concernyng the leape yeares, that the .xxv. day of February, whiche in leape yeares is coumpted for twoo dayes, shall in those twoo dayes, alter neither Psalme nor Lesson: but the same Psalmes and Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, whiche be sayed the first daye, shall serue also for the seconde daye.</p>
      <p>Also, wheresoeuer the beginning of any Lesson, Epistle, or Gospel is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, there ye must begin at the beginnyng of the Chapter.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>