<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epilogue vnto the
Reader.</title>
           <author>Turberville, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122514_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14016</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24324</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epilogue vnto the
Reader.</title>
                 <author>Turberville, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of faulconrie or hauking : for the onely delight and pleasure of all noblemen and gentlemen: collected out of the best aucthors, asvvell Italians as Frenchmen, and some English practises withall concernyng faulconrie, the contentes whereof are to be seene in the next page folowyng. By George Turberuile Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Turberville, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 371, that is 370, 6 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <pb facs="191"/>
   <head>The Epilogue vnto the
<hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>LO Reader here, the ende of this my booke,</l>
      <l>Though not the ende of my good will and loue,</l>
      <l>Bestowe thy paynes hereon a while to looke,</l>
      <l>As I imployed my head for thy behoue:</l>
      <l>It shall suffice if thou do not reproue</l>
      <l>This slender worke, compilde for thy delight,</l>
      <l>VVhose friendly looke my labour shall requight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I count my toyle and trauayle but a game,</l>
      <l>I deeme the dayes not long or spent amisse,</l>
      <l>If so I may vnto thy fancie frame</l>
      <l>This booke of mine which all of Hawking is,</l>
      <l>Than which there can be founde no better blisse</l>
      <l>In my conceyte to such as loue the glee,</l>
      <l>And force the fieldes where brauest pleasures bee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I must confesse, my Hammers haue but hewde</l>
      <l>That royall Rocke, which others founde of yore,</l>
      <l>I do but tread the pathe which others shewde</l>
      <l>Vnto their friendes, to make their skill the more:</l>
      <l>I but translate a garment made before:</l>
      <l>VVhich if I do with gallant shape to vewe,</l>
      <l>I deeme as much as if I made a newe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For harde it is to stalke in others steppes,</l>
      <l>He thinkes himselfe a thrall that marcheth so:</l>
      <l>He iumpes in ioy that at his pleasure leapes,</l>
      <l>And is not forst in others feete to go:</l>
      <l>Nothing more leefe than libertie you knowe,</l>
      <l>VVhich no translatour hath I vndertake,</l>
      <l>Vnlesse that he his Authours sense forsake.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhich vaunt I dare, I seldome here haue done,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Zforcino</hi> knowes, and can controll me then,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="192"/>Italian borne, whose booke I ouerronne,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Giorgies</hi> eke compilde with learned pen,</l>
      <l>Assuredly these two were skilfull men,</l>
      <l>And wist full well what Hawkes and hawking ment,</l>
      <l>And all things else that further this intent.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To <hi>Tardiffe</hi> eke the Frenchman, I appeale,</l>
      <l>To <hi>Malopyn,</hi> and <hi>Mychelyn,</hi> cunning wightes,</l>
      <l>Let <hi>Artelowche</hi> be witnesse howe I deale,</l>
      <l>In fielde affayres, or else in riuer flights,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Cassyan</hi> eke who well of hawking wrytes:</l>
      <l>All these I wishe as Iudges in the case</l>
      <l>VVhere I corrupt or alter any place.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Some men perhappes will wonder that I wrote</l>
      <l>Of stately Hawkes, and byrdes of rare delight,</l>
      <l>And blazde it out but in so base a note,</l>
      <l>As scarce will please the gallant Courtiers sight,</l>
      <l>VVho weyes no golde that is not burnisht bright:</l>
      <l>His curious eare but hardly will dygest,</l>
      <l>Sweete Musickes sound, that is not of the best.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For mine excuse and for my simple pen,</l>
      <l>To answere thus, I feare I shall be faine,</l>
      <l>Sith charge of Hawkes committed is to men,</l>
      <l>That nobles serue for yearely hire, and gaine,</l>
      <l>(VVho are not fine but homely mates and plaine)</l>
      <l>My purpose was, to set them downe the trade,</l>
      <l>To man their Hawkes, and howe they might be made.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For Peeres (I knowe, and you must needes agree)</l>
      <l>Regarde no more but onely to beholde</l>
      <l>The fleeing Hawkes, their ioy is but to see</l>
      <l>The haughtie haggarde worth hir weight in golde,</l>
      <l>To slay the sowle at brooke with courage bolde,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="192"/>VVith Hawkes they neuer deale in other sort,</l>
      <l>Their seruants feede, and they enioy the sport.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhich if be so, the lowe and playnest stile</l>
      <l>Doth best agree the Falconers minde to fitte,</l>
      <l>To carpe it fine with those that haue no guile,</l>
      <l>A ieast it were and signe of slender witte,</l>
      <l>The wryters ought the readers vaine to hitte.</l>
      <l>This was the cause I wrote my booke so plaine,</l>
      <l>I tolde it earste, I tell it nowe againe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The modest minde I knowe, will rest content,</l>
      <l>VVith this excuse, and brooke mine answere well,</l>
      <l>Of other some perhappes I shall be shent.</l>
      <l>VVhose sullen breasts vvith secrete enuie swell,</l>
      <l>VVho pleaseth all deserues to beare the bell.</l>
      <l>But if the Courtier fancie this my booke,</l>
      <l>I scorne the prowde disdaynfull Momus looke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Falkners farewell, at pleasure do peruse</l>
      <l>These leaues and lines, eche picture and eche page.</l>
      <l>Readers adue, I haue no farther newes,</l>
      <l>I can but wish you auncient Nestors age,</l>
      <l>Vnto whose doomes my wrytings here I gage:</l>
      <l>To cure your Hawkes or make your cunning more,</l>
      <l>If ought be here, I clappe my handes therefore.</l>
      <l>My Muse, and I, haue done the best we can,</l>
      <l>To learne you howe your Hawkes to lewre and man.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>George Turberuile.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Liuor, edax rerum, tu{que} inuidiosa vetustas, Omnia destruitis.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>