<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of Water-works.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122341_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05657</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1577.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122341</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of Water-works.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mysteryes of nature, and art : conteined in foure severall tretises, the first of water workes the second of fyer workes, the third of drawing, colouring, painting, and engrauing, the fourth of divers experiments, as wel serviceable as delightful: partly collected, and partly of the authors peculiar practice, and invention by I.B</title>
                 <author>Bate, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Church, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 14, 2, 15-112, 16, 121-192, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Art and architecture</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Of Water-works.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been an old saying amongst
Philosophers, and experience doth
prove it to be true, <hi>Non datur vacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi>
that is to say, Nature will not
admit of any vacuity, or emptinesse. For some
one or other of the Elements, but especially
Ayre, and Water doe insert themselves into all
manner of concavities, or hollownesses, in, or
upon the earth, whether they are such as are
formed either by Art or Nature. For the one it
is so obvious, and manifest, as that it needs not
any proofe at all. As for the other, I shall make
it manifest unto you by easie demonstration.
Let there be gotten a large vessell of glasse, or
other, having besides the mouth another
hole (though but a little one) at the top: poure
water into the vessell by a tunnell thrust into
the mouth of it, and you shall finde that as the
water runneth into the vessell, a winde will
<pb facs="5"/>
come forth of the little hole, sufficient to blow
out a candle being held over it. This proveth,
that before the water was poured into the vessell
(though to our sight it appeared to bee empty)
it was full of ayre, which forced out of the ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell
as the water ran in; and the reason hereof
is, because the water is by nature of a massie, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till,
substance; and the ayre of a windy, light, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporative
nature: The knowledge of this, with
the rarifaction of inclosed ayre, is the ground
and foundation of divers excellent experiments
not unworthy the knowledge of any ingenious
Artist whatsoever.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>