<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122229_Bo1_8_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04224</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorkes of the most high and mightie prince, Iames by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. Published by Iames, Bishop of Winton, and deane of his Maiesties Chappel Royall</title>
                 <author>James, I., King of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 569, 3 pages, portraits (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S euery humane body (deare Countrey men) how wholesome soeuer, is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding subiect, or at least natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclined to some sorts of diseases, or infirmities: so is there no Common-wealth, or Body-politicke, how well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, or peaceable soeuer it be, that lackes the owne popular errors, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally inclined corruptions: and therefore is it no wonder, although this our Countrey and Common-wealth, though peaceable, though wealthy, though long flourishing in both, be amongst the rest, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the owne naturall infirmities. We are of all Nations the people most louing, and most reuerently obedient to our Prince, yet are we (as time hath often borne witnesse) too easie to be seduced to make Rebellion vpon very slight grounds. Our fortunate and oft proued valour in warres abroad, our heartie and reuerent obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our Princes at home, hath bred vs a long, and a thrice happie peace: Our peace hath bread wealth: And peace and wealth hath brought forth a generall sluggishnesse, which makes vs wallow in all sorts of idle delights, and soft delicacies, the first
<pb n="212" facs="128"/>seeds of the subuersion of all great Monarchies. Our Cleargie are become negligent and lazie, Our Nobilitie and Gentrie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall, and sold to their priuate delights, Our Lawyers couetous, Our Common people prodigall and curious; and generally all sorts of people more carefull for their priuate ends, then for their mother the Common-wealth.</p>
   <p>For remedie whereof, it is the Kings part (as the proper Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician of his Politicke-bodie) to purge it of all those diseases, by Medicines meete for the same: as by a certaine milde, and yet iust forme of gouernment, to maintaine the Publicke quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and preuent all occasions of Commotion: by the example of his owne Person and Court, to make vs all ashamed of our slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gish delicacie, and to stirre vs vp to the practise againe of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest exercises, and Martiall shadowes of Warre; As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise by his, and his Courts moderatenesse in Apparell, to make vs ashamed of our prodigalitie: By his quicke admonitions and carefull ouerseeing of the Cleargie, to waken them vp againe, to be more diligent in their Offices: By the sharpe triall, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere punishment of the partiall, couetous and bribing Lawyers, to reforme their corruptions: And generally by the example of his owne Person, and by the due execution of good Lawes, to reforme and abolish, piece and piece, these olde and euill grounded abuses: For this will not be <hi>Opus vnius diei,</hi> but as euery one of these dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, must from the King receiue the owne cure proper for it, so are there some sorts of abuses in Common-wealths, that though they bee of so base and contemptible a condition, as they are too low for the Law to looke on, and to meane for a King to interpone his authoritie, or bend his eye vpon; yet are they corruptions, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as the greatest of them. So is an Ant an <hi>Animal,</hi> aswell as an Elephant: so is a Wrenne <hi>Auis,</hi> aswell as a Swanne, and so is a small dint of the Tooth-ake, a disease aswell as the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Plague is. But for these base sorts of corruption in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, not onely the King, or any inferiour Magistrate, but <hi>Quilibet è populo</hi> may serue to be a Phisician, by discouering and impugning the error, and by perswading reformation thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="213" facs="128"/>And surely in my opinion, there cannot bee a more base, and yet hurtfull, corruption in a Countrey, then is the vile vse (or rather abuse) of taking <hi>Tobacco</hi> in this Kingdome, which hath mooued mee, shortly to discouer the abuses thereof in this following little Pamphlet.</p>
   <p>Jf any thinke it a light Argument, so is it but a toy that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon it. And since the Subiect is but of Smoke, J thinke the fume of an idle braine, may serue for a sufficient batterie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst so fumous and feeble an enemie. Jf my grounds bee found trew, it is all J looke for; but if they cary the force of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion with them, it is all J can wish, and more then I can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. My onely care is, that you, my deare Countrey-men, may rightly conceiue euen by this smallest trifle, of the since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of my meaning in greater matters, neuer to spare any paine, that may tend to the procuring of your weale and prosperitie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>