<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Christians baptized in the name
of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the
holy Ghost, dwelling or abyding in
Fraunce, greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122384_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17705</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4448</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122384</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Christians baptized in the name
of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the
holy Ghost, dwelling or abyding in
Fraunce, greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sermons of M. Iohn Caluin, vpon the Epistle of S. Paule too the Ephesians. Translated out of French into English by Arthur Golding</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                            <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 347, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>To all Christians baptized in the name
of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the
holy Ghost, dwelling or abyding in
Fraunce, greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a wondrous matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r right deerly bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
brethren, how all of vs glory in our
Baptim, and yit consider not all with one
accord what that marke importeth of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
owne nature, namely by following the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
of him that is the author of it. For
no doubt but if wee did so, wee should all
ioyne toogither in one holy consent too
woorship the onely one God in spirit and
truth, and to acknowledge Iesus Christ
for our onely Sauyour, Aduocate, Mayster, yea and Lord, as touching
the gouernment of our soules and consciences: and wee would take his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nely woord for our wisdome, guyde, and rule of our whole lyfe, and
specially of his seruice, without mingling of the inuentions of mans
brayne with it, how great antiquitie or countenance so euer they
seeme too haue. Yea, and for the outward gouernment and visible
order of the Church, wee would hold vs to that which our Lord Iesus
Christ in whose name wee were Baptyzed, hath shewed thereof too
his Apostles, and by them inioyneth the whole world too followe euen
vntoo the last day. And certeynly then should the straunge confuzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and diuisions ceasse which are too bee seene in Christendome, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
those are the cause, which will not harken vntoo God, and yeeld full
authoritie too his woord, which fault shalbee layd too their charge at
the iudgment of God, vnlesse they turne a new leafe. The Lord and
Father of mercie graunt them grace so too doo, according as sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
is made too him for them, in all holy assemblies where he is
called vppon according too his will, in the onely name of Iesus Christ.
That is the thing which wee desire: For heere the cace concerneth
not the bringing in of some newe deuyce, after the fancie of men, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
stryue wee too make the victorie fall vppon mens sides, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
they bee, as some surmyze: but that God and his woord may haue
the vpper hand ageinst all abuses, superstitions, and lyes of Satan, and


<pb facs="13"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> we may all toogither giue glory too our God, confessing that both
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and our fathers haue ouershamefully forgotten him, insomuch
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> haue not folowed his holy Lawe, but haue bowed asyde both
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> the ryght hand and too the left. And truly whensoeuer we reade
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> woord in a tung that wee vnderstand, or heare it preached and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>clared purely: he allureth vs too him, too make the lyke acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>gedment.
And he hath doone so much in these late yeeres by stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ng
with his mercie ageinst the malice of the world, that dyuerse
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue returned intoo the ryghtway, whom others yea euen of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rees
doo followe styll anew. But yit is not that ynough, vnlesse th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
residew which haue hithertoo bin deaf or asleepe, doo bethinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
too awake in good earnest, and too haue eares too heare, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
sayeth Iesus Christ. Therefore wee intreate and exhort them too it
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Gods name, that they may discharge themselues of the promis
whereuntoo their Baptim dooth secretly bynd them, as hath bin sayd.
And too further them therein, besydes the lyuely voyces of the trew
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inisters, and other bookes conteyning faythfull expositions of the
Scripture: wee offer them heere the Sermons of <hi>M. Iohn Caluin</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
the Epistle of the Apostle Saint Paule too the Ephesians, where
(as wee hope) they shall haue matter too fare the better by, for the
playner vnderstanding of the things, which they shall eyther heare
preached, or reade alone by themselues afterward. Too mak long
rehersall of things that myght bee alledged in commendation of the
doctrine herein conteyned, or of the manner of teaching vsed by the
Author, which is both simple and familiar, and yit neuerthelesse full
of authoritie and force: it is not now needfull. For wee bee sure that
such as seeke Gods honour and their owne saluation, shall in reading
them, perceyue that the Author had none other meaning with him:
and that shall euen the malicious sorte themselues bee driuen to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
confesse, spyte of their hartes. Wherefore too conclude, ryght deare
brethren which shall meete with this book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, wee pray you new agein,
too giue eare too our God and too his sonne our Mayster, who by his
seruant and excellent minister of his Church, declareth the things
which his holy Apostle had long ago preached with lyuely voyce, and
afterward compyled breefly in wryting for vs, and all that shall com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
after vs too the worldes end. And of what degree soeuer you bee or


<pb facs="14"/>
haue bin, shrinke not backe, forasmuch as it is God that speaketh, who
hath loued vs so d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arely, that he hath not spared his owne sonne, but
hath giuen him too death too redeeme vs from death, and from the
vayne traditions of our fathers: Come on therefore, and let vs all
serue our God with one accord, walking in the wayes which he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
vs, and forsaking our owne, (that is too say, all that disagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
with the rule of his woord,) and making all his giftes too
serue too his glory. And in so dooyng wee shall bee Christians
both in name and deede: wee shall discharge our selues
of our promise made in Baptim: wee shall see good
agreement in Christianitie: and wee shall serue
for a good example too the Iewes and
Turkes, which are yit enemyes too
Christendome. So bee it, So
bee it, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your brethren in our Lord, The
causers of these Sermons too
bee brought to lyght.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>