<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most hygh and myghtie prince Charles, the fyft o that name, Emperor of Rome, Kyng of Spaine, &amp; of the two Cicilies, of both the sydes of the streyght of Faro, Kyng of Hierusalem and Hungarie, Duke of Burgonie, and Earle of Flaunders, Lord and inheritour of the firme lande and Ilandes of the VVest Ocean. &amp;c. Gon∣zalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus, his most humble seruaunt, wysheth health and perpetu∣all felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122069_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">649</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122069</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most hygh and myghtie prince Charles, the fyft o that name, Emperor of Rome, Kyng of Spaine, &amp; of the two Cicilies, of both the sydes of the streyght of Faro, Kyng of Hierusalem and Hungarie, Duke of Burgonie, and Earle of Flaunders, Lord and inheritour of the firme lande and Ilandes of the VVest Ocean. &amp;c. Gon∣zalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus, his most humble seruaunt, wysheth health and perpetu∣all felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of trauayle in the VVest and East Indies, and other countreys lying eyther way, towardes the fruitfull and ryche Moluccaes : As Moscouia, Persia, Arabia, Syria, Ægypte, Ethiopia, Guinea, China in Cathayo, and Giapan: vvith a discourse of the Northwest passage... Gathered in parte, and done into Englyshe by Richarde Eden. Newly set in order, augmented, and finished by Richarde VVilles</title>
                 <author>Anghiera, Pietro Martire d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jugge, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 466, 6 leaves, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="196"/>
   <head>To the most hygh and myghtie prince Charles, the fyft o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that name, Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> Kyng of Spaine, &amp; of the two Cicilies, of both the sydes of the streyght of <hi>Faro,</hi> Kyng of <hi>Hierusalem</hi> and <hi>Hungarie,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgonie,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> Lord and inheritour of the firme lande and Ilandes of the VVest Ocean. &amp;c. <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zalus Ferdinandus Ouiedus,</hi> his most humble seruaunt, wysheth health and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thinges which principally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue and mayntayne the workes of nature in the memories of men, are hystories and bookes composed of the same: among the whiche certes those are esteemed most true and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentyke, which haue been wrytten by wyttie and expert men, well trauey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the world, as faythfull witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of such thinges as they haue partly seene, and been partly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by credible persons. Of this mynde and opinion was Plinie, who better then any other aucthor hath written in .xxxvii. bookes all that parteyneth to the naturall historie, conteyned all in one volume, dedicated to <hi>Vespasian</hi> Themperour: Wherin, as a prudent historiographer, he declareth such thinges as hee had heard, attributing the second authoritie to such as he had redde in aucthours that wrote before him: And thyrdly ioyned to the same hystorie, such thinges as he him selfe had seene, as most certayne testimonie. Whose example I folowyng, will in this my breefe summarie, reduce and represent to your maiesties memorie such thinges as I haue seene in your Empyre of the West Indies, aswell in the Ilandes as in the firme lande of the Ocean sea, where I haue serued now more then twelue yeeres in the place of surueyer of the golde mynes, by the commaundement of the Catholyke kyng <hi>Don Fernando,</hi> the fyft of that name, and graund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father vnto your maiestie, to whom God gaue great fame and glorie: Since whose death also I haue lykewyse serued, and
<pb n="186" facs="196"/>
trust whyle the rest of my lyfe yet remayneth, to serue your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, as shall please you to commaunde. As touchyng whiche thinges, and suche other lyke, I haue more largely written in an hystorie begun assoone as my age was rype to take such matters in hande: Wherein furthermore I haue made mention of suche thinges as haue chaunced in Spayne, from the yeere .1494. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this tyme: addyng also therevnto suche thinges woorthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, as I haue obserued in other realmes and prouinces where I haue trauayled, and haue lykewyse particulerly wrytten the lyues and worthy actes of the catholyke Princes of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie <hi>Don Ferdinando,</hi> and Lady Elizabeth his wyfe, to theyr last dayes. After whose fruition of heauenly Paradyse, I haue noted such thinges as haue chaunced in your most fortunate suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession: not omittyng particulerly to wryte a large booke of suche thinges as haue seemed most woorthy to bee noted, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng your maiesties Indies. But forasmuch as that volume remayneth in the citie of <hi>San. Dominico,</hi> in the Ilande of <hi>His<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paniola,</hi> where I dwell, and am placed in housholde, with wyfe, chyldren, and famylie, I haue brought no more with me of that my writyng, then I beare in memorie, determynyng (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng) for your maiesties recreation, to make a breefe rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall of certayne notable thinges, wherof I haue more largely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated in my sayd generall historie, and such as may seeme most woorthy to be redde of your maiestie: Of the which, although a great parte haue been written by other, who haue also seene the same, yet perhappes they are not so exactly and particulerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed as of mee, forasmuche as in maner all that trauayle into these Indies haue greater respect to luker and gaynes, then dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to search the workes of nature, whervnto I haue ben euer naturally inclined, &amp; haue therfore with all possible endeuour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed myne eyes &amp; intelligence to fynde the same. And this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Summarie shall not be contrary or dyuers from my larger historie, wherein (as I haue sayde) I haue more amply declared these thinges: but shal onely more breefely expresse theffect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vntyl such tyme as God shall restore me to myne owne house, where I may accomplyshe and fynyshe my sayde generall hysto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Whervnto to gyue the fyrst principle, I say, that <hi>Don Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Colonus</hi> (as it is well knowen) beyng the fyrst Admirall of
<pb facs="197"/>
this <hi>India,</hi> discouered the same in the dayes of the Catholyke kyng <hi>Don Ferdinando,</hi> and the lady Elizabeth his wyfe, graund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father and graundmother vnto your maiestie, in the yeere .1491. and came to <hi>Barzalona</hi> in the yeere .1492. with the fyrst <hi>Indians,</hi> and other shewes and proofes of the great ryches and notice of this west Empire: The which gyft and benefite was suche, that it is vnto this day one of the greatest that euer any subiecte or seruaunt hath done for his prince or countrey, as is manifest to the whole worlde. And to say the trueth, this shall doubtlesse bee so commodious and profytable vnto the whole realme of Spayne, that I repute him no good Castilian or Spanyarde that doeth not recognise the same. And (as I haue sayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) forasmuche as in my sayde generall historie I haue more largely intreated of these thinges, I intende at this present on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly briefely to rehearse certayne especiall thinges, the whiche surely are very fewe in respecte of the thousandes that myght be sayde in this behalfe. Fyrst therefore I will speake somewhat of the nauigation into these parties, then of the generation of the nations which are founde in the same, with theyr rytes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes▪ and ceremonies: also of beastes, foules, byrdes, woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, fyshes, seas, ryuers, sprynges, trees, plantes, hearbes, and dyuers other thinges, whiche are engendered both on the lande and in the water. And forasmuche as I am one of thorder and company of them that are appoynted to returne into these regions to serue your maiestie, if therefore the thinges contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this booke shall not be distincte in suche order as I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to perfourme in my greater woorke, I desyre your maiestie to haue no respect herevnto, but rather to consider the noueltie of such straunge thinges as I haue herein declared, whiche is the chiefe ende that moued mee to wryte: Protestyng, that in this Summarie I haue written the trueth of suche thinges as came to my remembraunce, whereof not onely I my selfe can testifie, but also dyuers other worthy and credible men, which haue been in those regions, and are now present in your maiesties courte. And thus it shall suffyse to haue sayde thus much vnto your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, in maner of a proheme vnto this present worke, whiche I most humbly desyre your maiestie as thankefully to accept, as I haue written it faythfully.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>