<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122200_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11197</idno>
           <idno type="STC">679</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122200</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A soveraigne antidote against sabbatarian errours. Or, A decision of the chiefe doubts and difficulties touching the Sabbath : Wherein these three questions (beside others coincident) are clearly and succinctly determined, viz. I. Which is the fittest name whereby to call the day of Christian weekly rest, whether Sabbath day, Lords-day, or Sunday? II. What is the meaning of that prayer, appointed to be used by our Church: Lord have mercy upon us, and encline, &amp;c. as it is repeated and applyed to the words of the fourth Commandment. III. Whether it be lawfull to use any bodily recreation on the Lords-day? and if so, what kinde of recreation? By a reverend, religious, and judicious divine</title>
                 <author>Reverend, religious, and judicious divine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 27, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a matter of great use and necessity to have now in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apostle, and teacher of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <hi>Remember them, which have the rule over you, obey them, and submit your selves.</hi> Hebr. 13.7.17. <hi>and esteeme them very highly in love, for their works sake,</hi> 1. Thes. 5.13. And it is not without reason; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in the house of God, which is the Church of the living God, they worke the worke of the Lord, and they watch for our sake, as they that must give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. 1. Tim. 3.15. 1. Cor. 16.10. Heb.
<pb facs="3"/>13.17. whose office is so honourable, that God himselfe not onely hath given a charge, that <hi>every man that will do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuously, and will not bearken unto the Priest,</hi> the man shall be put away from Israel, but hath also severally this inobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diency punished: <hi>The wrath of the Lord arose against his people,</hi> and gave them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the king of Chaldees, <hi>because they mocked the messenger of God, and despised his words,</hi> and misused his Prophets. Deut 17.12. 2. Chron. 36.16.</p>
   <p>Yet this is the contumacy and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of some boasters, and some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull men, which no otherwise, but as <hi>Jannes and Iambres</hi> withstood <hi>Moses,</hi> 2. Tim. 2.3. so they them, whom Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracle hath adjudged <hi>to be worthy of double honour:</hi> 1. Tim. 5.17. saying in effect to them as <hi>Korah</hi> did (with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the children of Israel, two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Princes) to <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron; Ye take too much upon you,</hi> seeing all
<pb facs="3"/>the congregation are holy every one of them: <hi>Wherefore then lift you up your selues above the congregation of the Lord?</hi> Num. 16.3.</p>
   <p>The experiment of these things gives every day our <hi>England,</hi> in the businesse of the Sabbatarians, who measuring themselves by themselves, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themselves amongst themselves, even as in times past, the Scribes and Pharisees for a pretence make long pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, devoure widows houses, Mat. 23.14. so they creep into houses, and in a shape of sanctimony (is it through the envy, or strife, or ignorance, I cannot tell) they cast a snare upon the silly consciences of men, making concision in the Church of the Lord, and so <hi>the middle wall of partition</hi> which Christ hath broken downe, Ephes. 2.14. they do renew, and this doing, shew themselves to be the deceitfull workers.</p>
   <p>Therefore to avoyd this confusion,
<pb facs="4"/>we bring forth in the light this discourse penned for private satisfaction, and now approved to be printed for the publicke edification of the Church. Wherein the excellent Author seemes to have imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them which have the Art to make Roses grow <hi>sine spinis,</hi> without a thorne, and yet be as faire and fragrant as any other: so that his Pedalean penne deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us a Theologicall decision of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths difficulties, <hi>sine spinosis &amp; paedagogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis argutiis;</hi> yet punctually to the minde of Christ, and the Church. Worthily therefore may it be presented to the Church of England, and to be accepted of thy favour.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>