<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122315_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00473</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10608.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122315</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An example of Gods iudgement shew [n] vpon two children borne in high Dutch la [nd] in the citie of Lutssolof, the first day of Iulie. and translated out of Dutche into English the 6 [of] Nouember last by Cornelius Pet</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ballard, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eerly beloued Bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren like as daily wee see the wunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woorks of GOD, to aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise vs to the amendment of our sinful wicked &amp; detestable liues, be fore hee dooth plague vs, like as alwaise hee is good and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and doth not punish vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto our desarts, but sendeth vs first Signes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to admōish vs of his ire whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch wee so rightly deferne for our so little regarding &amp; esteeming of his most holy woord and gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. But wee dayly neglecting and not regarding the same.</p>
   <p>Hee therfore hath not only sent hydeous Monsters and fearfull Signes, vnto those where they were borne and seen: but aswel vnto vs, yea and rather vnto vs because wee hauing the sincere
<pb facs="3"/>
      Doctrine and Gospel of Christe so vnfeinedly preached yea so er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nestly set foorth and so diligētly vtterd, and yet wee nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. But like stubburn and obstinate Children run hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into our damnation.</p>
   <p>Wherfore wee haue to giue the greater account of the time which wee haue spent (when we shall come and appeer before the Iudgement seat of GOD the moste rightful Iudge) wherfore deerly belouid let vs not be like those of <hi>Sodome, Gomorra, Ierusalem,</hi> and many other Cities which would not esteem of the tokens and signes which God sent thē.</p>
   <p>But let vs repent with those of <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and pray vnto GOD for mercy and humble our selves be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m then wil hee not extend his wrath vpon vs▪ but be mercifull vnto vs.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>