<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
           <author>I., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122555_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08025</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1839.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122555</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
                 <author>I., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iacob's ladder : consisting of fifteene degrees or ascents to the knowledge of God by the consideration of his creatures and attributes</title>
                 <author>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 419, 7 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the receivedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of all, that of all the <hi>creatures</hi> which <hi>GOD</hi> (the Soveraigne <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor)</hi> made from the beginning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>one was created by him more noble and excellent, (next to the <hi>Angels)</hi> then <hi>Man:</hi> and that for his sake all things were made; as <hi>Heaven, Earth, Sea,</hi> and all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re in them; yea, that the <hi>Angels</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hemselves, and <hi>Principalities</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ere ordayned to be subservient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o him.</p>
   <p>But <hi>Man,</hi> being so richly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owed, and tyed to his <hi>maker,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o greater bonds then benefits and
<pb facs="3"/>
blessings, became <hi>rebellious</hi> and unthankfull to his so liber all <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor;</hi> and not duely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing his <hi>dignity</hi> and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, nor satisfied with such extraordinary <hi>favours,</hi> out of those things from which he should have taken occasion to love <hi>GOD</hi> his <hi>Maker,</hi> extracted that matter which produced his <hi>treason:</hi> and affecting no lesse then a <hi>Deity,</hi> rebelled, and brake the commands of his <hi>Creator:</hi> for which he was justly expelled <hi>Paradise,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of that <hi>honour,</hi> which he formerly possessed, and is now <hi>compared to the Beasts that perish.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 49. 20.</note>
   </p>
   <p>This was a wofull <hi>Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis;</hi> an unhappy change: from the <hi>best,</hi> to become the <hi>worst</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Creatures,</hi> and that so sodainly Nor was this the <hi>worst</hi> of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>misery;</hi> for by his <hi>fall,</hi> the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>masse of Man-kinde</hi> (his <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sterity)</hi> became so corrupt, as tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (the Devill excepted) <hi>Man</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
the most miserable of all other <hi>creatures:</hi> by nature fraile and weake; headlong in affections; tormented with cares and anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; mad in desires; blind in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding; weake in will, corrupt in memory; obnoxious to all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, miseries, and troubles: and lastly, liable to infernall punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and not without just cause: for he, which became a <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with the Devill in <hi>sinne,</hi> was worthily made his associate in <hi>sufferings.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, <hi>Man</hi> being thus wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and miserable, by incurring <hi>GODS</hi> high displeasure; it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the same most good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>GOD,</hi> not perpetually to looke upon the <hi>injury</hi> done to his high <hi>Majestie,</hi> but to compassio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate his <hi>misery;</hi> and rather pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying his <hi>error,</hi> then desiring <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge;</hi> determined to repayre his <hi>wofull condition,</hi> and to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile him to <hi>himselfe.</hi> But what <hi>tongue</hi> or <hi>pen</hi> is sufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
<pb facs="4"/>
the <hi>manner</hi> of this attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Nay, who can <hi>conceive,</hi> what it was, that wrought this <hi>reconciliation?</hi> Surely nothing but his owne meore <hi>compassion;</hi> and that by such a way, as may breed <hi>astonishment</hi> in the most sencelesse heart.</p>
   <p>By His <hi>Sonne,</hi> His <hi>onely Sonne, CHRIST JESUS, GOD</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> brought he this great <hi>worke</hi> to passe; who made such a <hi>peace</hi> betweene th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> such an <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or pacification, as that he not onely pardoned the <hi>offence,</hi> but received the delinquent to <hi>grace,</hi> making him one and the same with himselfe, by the bond of <hi>love.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And as we are infinitely <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted</hi> for this high <hi>benefit</hi> in generall; so are we no lesse <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> to him for the <hi>manner</hi> of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> then for the <hi>Redemption it selfe.</hi> For there were many <hi>wayes,</hi> whereby he
<pb facs="4"/>
might have <hi>saved</hi> us, without labour, without <hi>price:</hi> yet so wonderfull was his <hi>bounty</hi> to us; so great his <hi>goodnesse</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> that he would have it <hi>wrought</hi> by the infinite <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,</hi> (even to the losse of the dearest <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>life)</hi> of His <hi>onely Sonne;</hi> and that, by the shamefull Death of the <hi>Crosse;</hi> and all this (I say) for the <hi>love</hi> of <hi>us,</hi> without <hi>benefit</hi> to <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</hi> For as it is in Job. <hi>What profiteth it thee, and what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayleth it me, if thou sinnest?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 35.</note>
      <hi>If thou sinnest, what canst thou doe unto him? If thou be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, what givest thou unto him? or what receiveth he at thy hands?</hi> that is, What <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice</hi> could <hi>GOD</hi> receive by our <hi>evill,</hi> or what <hi>benefit</hi> by our <hi>good?</hi> For he is nothing the <hi>worse</hi> if men <hi>blaspheme</hi> him; nor the better if they <hi>praise</hi> him. It was His <hi>love</hi> then to us, and nothing else, which repayred
<pb facs="5"/>
our miserable <hi>condition.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This <hi>love</hi> therefore requires <hi>love</hi> againe: the <hi>love</hi> of the <hi>Creator,</hi> the <hi>love</hi> of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Certainly, in diverse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects we are <hi>bound</hi> infinitely to him. For our <hi>Creation,</hi> for our <hi>Preservation,</hi> for our <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and indeed for so many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable <hi>blessings,</hi> as cannot be <hi>conceived,</hi> much lesse <hi>expressed.</hi> What great matter then is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us, when we are onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to require this <hi>love</hi> with <hi>love?</hi> We should and ought to imitate a fertile Field, or piece of ground, which renders much more seed then it receiveth: but <hi>GOD</hi> helpe us poore miserable <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> if this were exacted of us, we should come farre short of this <hi>retribution.</hi> Why yet, if (for the infirmity of our <hi>natures</hi> while we live in this <hi>pilgrimage)</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe that which we should; yet let u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> doe what we may With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out question <hi>love</hi> him we may;
<pb facs="5"/>
nay <hi>love</hi> him we must, if ever we intend to take the benefit of his <hi>Sonnes</hi> passion.</p>
   <p>But thou wiltsay, how shall I <hi>love</hi> him that I <hi>know</hi> not? if I <hi>knew</hi> him, I would <hi>love</hi> him with all my <hi>heart;</hi> with all the affections of my mind and <hi>soule:</hi> Surely this is no difficult worke. For <hi>GOD</hi> himselfe hath made us capable of the <hi>knowledge</hi> of him, and therfore he (knowing our capacity sufficient for that act) hath commanded our performance of it, and that by <hi>seeking</hi> him. No man can come to the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of anything, but by <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>labour;</hi> and the more sublime that is, of which we are ignorant, the more <hi>paines,</hi> the more <hi>labour</hi> it will cost, before the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of it be attained. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, <hi>GOD</hi> being the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>object,</hi> the worthiest of all other, our <hi>knowledge,</hi> let us not spare any <hi>paines,</hi> any <hi>travaile,</hi> to possesse our selves of it; that
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>knowing,</hi> we may <hi>love</hi> him; which is a <hi>duty</hi> chiefly expected from us, for all the unvaluable <hi>benefits</hi> we have, and continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe receive from him.</p>
   <p>Now, that in the <hi>search</hi> or seeking after this <hi>knowledge,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 5. 14. 12. 25.</note>
      <hi>We grope not as blind men,</hi> of whom holy <hi>Iob</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Esay</hi> speake: nor that <hi>we gaze not,</hi> (gazing being an Act <note place="margin">Es. 59. 10.</note> so contrary to seeking, as that it was not onely condemned by the Angels in the Acts of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 1. 11</note> but forbidden by <hi>GOD</hi> himselfe; <hi>gazers</hi> being for the <note place="margin">Ex. 19. 21</note> most part a sort of people, desirous onely of new fangles and novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and no setled searchers or seekers.) It will not be amisse, by prescribing some rules of <hi>seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to take away <hi>filmes</hi> from the <hi>eyes</hi> of the former, and to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the <hi>sight</hi> of the other, that so they may be the better ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to proceed in their <hi>search.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But before we come to the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
we will looke a little into the <hi>necessity</hi> of this <hi>duty;</hi> that we may understand that a <hi>seeking,</hi> and thereby a <hi>knowing;</hi> and consequently a <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> of him, is <hi>necessarily</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us.</p>
   <p>That it is <hi>commanded</hi> as a <note place="margin">1.</note> speciall <hi>duty,</hi> appeares by many places in holy writ, of which I will select a few. <hi>Seek the LORD</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Chro. 16. 11. 22. 19.</note>
      <hi>and his strength, seeke his face continually,</hi> and <hi>Set your hearts and your soules to seeke the LORD your GOD.</hi> And <hi>GOD</hi> himselfe by the Prophet <hi>Amos, Seeke ye me and live.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Am 5. 4. 6.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, it was ever the <hi>counsaile</hi> of <hi>GODS Prophets</hi>
      <note place="margin">2.</note> and <hi>servants:</hi> as of King <hi>David</hi> to his Sonne, <hi>Know thou the</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Chro. 28. 9.</note>
      <hi>GOD of thy Fathers, &amp;c. If thou seek him, he will be found of thee.</hi> He adviseth him to <hi>know</hi> him, by <hi>seeking</hi> him. The same King gives the same <hi>counsaile</hi> to his Princes; as also
<pb facs="7"/>
to his Quire and Church-men, in the two places before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; to shew, that neither <hi>Prince, Nobility,</hi> nor <hi>Clergy</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from this <hi>duty.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, it hath alwaies bin the <hi>practise</hi> of <hi>Godly Princes</hi>
      <note place="margin">3.</note> and others. King <hi>Iehosaphat set himselfe to seek the LORD.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Chro. 20. 3.</note> King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> prayed for <hi>those that prepared their whole heart</hi>
      <note place="margin">30. 18.</note>
      <hi>to seeke the LORD.</hi> King <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah when he was yet a child, began to seeke after the GOD of</hi> David <hi>his Father.</hi> It was also the fame King <hi>Davids pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise.</hi>
      <note place="margin">34. 3.</note> For when <hi>GOD</hi> said <hi>Seeke my race,</hi> he answers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently, <hi>Thy face LORD will</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 27. 9</note>
      <hi>I seeke.</hi> And in another place, <hi>I have set GOD alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
      <note place="margin">16. 9</note>
      <hi>me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And surely not without <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi>
      <note place="margin">4.</note> was this <hi>duty</hi> either <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, counsailed</hi> or <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,</hi> for there is a <hi>promise</hi> of <hi>reward</hi> annexed: we shall not lose
<pb facs="7"/>
our <hi>labour,</hi> but receive much good in <hi>seeking</hi> to <hi>know</hi> him. In the Booke of <hi>Deuteronomie, GOD promiseth</hi> not onely to be <hi>found</hi> of them that <hi>seeke</hi> him; but to <hi>deliver</hi> them from <hi>misery,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 29. &amp;c.</note> and <hi>heape blessings</hi> upon them. King <hi>David</hi> found by <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> that <hi>GOD never failed them that seeke him.</hi> And <note place="margin">Ps. 9 10. 69. 33.</note>
      <hi>seeke ye after GOD</hi> (saith he) <hi>and your soule shall live.</hi> And <hi>GOD</hi> himselfe by the Prophet <hi>Esay. I said not in vaine to the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay 45. 19.</note>
      <hi>seed of</hi> Jacob, <hi>Seeke ye me.</hi> And lastly, (not to trouble you with many) <hi>The LORD is good</hi>
      <note place="margin">La. 3. 25.</note>
      <hi>to the soule that seeketh him,</hi> saith the Prophet <hi>Ieremie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, it is the <hi>end</hi> for which <hi>Man</hi> was <hi>created.</hi> S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Paul,</hi> after <note place="margin">5.</note> he had beaten much upon the point, that a <hi>GOD</hi> was to be <hi>sought out,</hi> whom men should <hi>worship,</hi> and had made it plaine, by the <hi>creation</hi> of all things, who that <hi>GOD</hi> was; came to the <hi>end</hi>
      <note place="margin">Acts 17.</note>
      <pb facs="8"/>
of Mans <hi>creation,</hi> which was to <hi>seeke</hi> him; Man being <hi>created</hi> for that <hi>purpose</hi> and <hi>end;</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that it would be no great <hi>labour</hi> to <hi>find</hi> him, <hi>as being not farre from every one of us.</hi> He then which shalbe <hi>negligent</hi> in this <hi>duty,</hi> is not worthy of his <hi>creation,</hi> and deserves not to <hi>live;</hi> it being a most absurd and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent thing, for a Manto be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of his <hi>Creator;</hi> having recerved from him the guift of <hi>understanding,</hi> and made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>know</hi> him. We see, that Rivers naturally returne to the Sea whence they come, and all things elso to their <hi>first being:</hi> Wherefore then should not <hi>Man</hi> returne in his <hi>thoughts</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires to <hi>GOD,</hi> who-gave him his <hi>being?</hi> and why should his <hi>heart</hi> be as rest; till be <hi>returne</hi> to him? considering (as I said) that he made the <hi>understanding,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might <hi>know</hi> him; the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> that he might ever be
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>mindfull</hi> of him; and the <hi>will,</hi> ever to <hi>love</hi> him?</p>
   <p>And now, since we have in some sort <hi>seene,</hi> that it is a <hi>duty</hi> enjoyned by <hi>GOD</hi> to <hi>seeke</hi> him; that it hath beene the <hi>counsaile</hi> and <hi>practise</hi> of many holy <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prophets;</hi> that we shall not <hi>lose our labour,</hi> but <hi>receive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit</hi> by our <hi>seeking:</hi> and lastly, that it is the onely <hi>end</hi> for which we were <hi>created;</hi> let us take a further view, how we may so <hi>seeke,</hi> that we may <hi>find</hi> and know him. To the due perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which act, we must ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve these cautions:
<list>
         <item>
            <hi>1</hi> That we <hi>prepare</hi> our hearts carefully and diligently to <hi>seeke.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>2</hi> That we <hi>seeke</hi> him in <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> and <hi>simplicity</hi> without <hi>hypocrisie.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>3</hi> That we be <hi>humble,</hi> and not <hi>curious seekers.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>4</hi> That we <hi>seek</hi> him in <hi>Faith, without</hi> wavering.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>5</hi> That wee be earnest and
<pb facs="9"/>
            <hi>zealous,</hi> and not <hi>cold or luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme seekers.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <p>This carefull <hi>preparation</hi> of the <hi>heart</hi> hath ever been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, <note place="margin">1.</note> as most necessary, before the undertaking of any pious act; and indeed is the <hi>foundation,</hi> and first degree to this <hi>seeking. Iehosaphat prepared his heart</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Chro. 19. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 27, 6.</note>
      <hi>to seeke the LORD,</hi> as you have seene. <hi>Iothan became mighty, because he prepared his waies.</hi> And S. <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ome</hi> saith, that <hi>purgandus est animus, ut perspicere illam lucem va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat,</hi> a man shall never be able to <hi>see</hi> the clearenesse and beauty of that <hi>light,</hi> if he first <hi>prepare</hi> not, nor fit himselfe before-hand; if <hi>hee seeke him not in due</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Chro. 15. 13.</note>
      <hi>order.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It was the Wisemans advice, to <hi>seeke GOD in simplicity of</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sap. 1. 1. Mat. 5. 8.</note>
      <hi>heart,</hi> and it is the <hi>Pure in heart that shall see GOD.</hi> as our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>r</hi> speakes The <hi>Sun</hi> beames sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne brightest upon a <hi>cleare</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>glasse;</hi> and in a <hi>cleane heart</hi> the <hi>beames</hi> of Divine <hi>grace</hi> shine most. <hi>The uncleane shall not see</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. 5. 5.</note>
      <hi>GOD,</hi> saith the Apostle.</p>
   <p>Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> calls the <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Man <hi>DEI Templum,</hi> the <note place="margin">3.</note>
      <hi>Temple</hi> or habitation of <hi>GOD.</hi> He shall not onely <hi>see GOD,</hi> but <hi>GOD</hi> will <hi>abide</hi> with him. <hi>GOD giveth grace to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
      <note place="margin">I am. 4. 6.</note> And <hi>CHRIST</hi> himselfe, while he was conversant upon Earth, delighted not in great or <hi>proud</hi> company, but chose <hi>fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to converse with: and the Centurions <hi>non sum dignus,</hi> with the Publicans <hi>humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession,</hi> pleased him more, then all the <hi>proud</hi> vaunts of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharises.</hi> He desires not, but abhorres to be looked on with <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> and <hi>prying</hi> eyes: and therefore <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Augustine</hi> writing against the Manichees saith, and his counsaile is, <hi>Compescat se humana temeritas, &amp; id quod non est non quaerat, ne illud</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>quod est inveniat▪</hi> after the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full example of <hi>Vzza.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Chro. 13. 9. 4. Eccle. 25. 11.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Faith</hi> is the beginning of <hi>clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> to <hi>GOD,</hi> saith the Sonne of <hi>Syrach.</hi> And <hi>Fides humanae sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis initium,</hi> saith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Augustine:</hi> For by it we <hi>understand</hi> what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is necessary for us to <hi>know</hi> concerning <hi>GOD.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, that there is a <hi>GOD,</hi> some <hi>Deity,</hi> all people, even the <hi>Heathen,</hi> that had their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectualls, held as a <hi>maxime.</hi> Hee in the Psalme that <hi>said</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 14. 1.</note>
      <hi>there was no GOD,</hi> said it but in <hi>his heart;</hi> was not so impudent, as to <hi>speake</hi> it out and yet for his <hi>thought</hi> onely, had the brand of a <hi>foole.</hi> This <hi>Faith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Augustine</hi> saith, <hi>Valet ad cognitionem DEI, non tanquam omnino incogniti, sed quò cognoscatur manifestius:</hi> And, <hi>Si quis hic non ambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit per Fidem, non perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet ad speciem beatae visionis.</hi> By it, the children of <hi>light</hi> are
<pb facs="10"/>
distinguished from those of <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;</hi> and <hi>per ipsam discitur ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis scientia, et percipitur cognitio Divinitatis.</hi> By it, the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>truth</hi> is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and of the <hi>Divinity per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, <hi>zeale, love,</hi> and <hi>hearty</hi>
      <note place="margin">5.</note>
      <hi>affection</hi> is of all vertues the clearest <hi>sighted,</hi> and will <hi>see GOD</hi> soonest. For it is the <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to a thing, that <hi>drawes</hi> a mans desire to <hi>see</hi> it. And yet, this vertue naturally depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former, of <hi>Faith.</hi> For if <hi>Faith</hi> be <hi>wavering, love</hi> and <hi>affection</hi> is soone <hi>cool'd:</hi> Fall from the one, and fall from the other quickly. For no Man can <hi>affect</hi> or <hi>love</hi> that, which he <hi>beleeves</hi> not to be. But yet, this vertue is so necessary, as that without it, none can ever attaine to the <hi>sight</hi> of <hi>GOD. S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> saith, <hi>Quantò flagrantius DEUM diligimus, tantó cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius serenius{que} videamus.</hi> We
<pb facs="11"/>
shall see <hi>GOD</hi> the surer, and more perspicuously, by how much the greater our <hi>zeale, aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ction,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> is to him.</p>
   <p>And being thus <hi>prepared,</hi> and <hi>fitted</hi> with these <hi>qualities,</hi> we must <hi>seeke</hi> him (as the Prophet <note place="margin">Esay 55. 6.</note> counsaileth) <hi>while he may be found.</hi> Wee must doe it in due time; that is, while we are in this <hi>vale of misery:</hi> we must <hi>seeke</hi> and apply our selves to <hi>see</hi> and <hi>know</hi> him, as much and as soon as we may here, that <hi>we may see him face to face</hi> to our comfort, <hi>as he is</hi> hereafter. <hi>Time</hi> is first either <hi>past,</hi> and that is not; we cannot make use of that. Secondly, or <hi>to come;</hi> and that we know not whether we shall have it to use or no, it is onely in <hi>GODS</hi> power. Thirdly, or it is <hi>present,</hi> and that we must lay hold of, and make use of it. Therefore, in what <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> of what <hi>age</hi> soever thou art, <hi>seek the LORD,</hi> and <hi>that instantly.</hi> And if thou shalt take
<pb facs="11"/>
hold of this <hi>time,</hi> with this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration;</hi> no doubt but <hi>GOD</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 33. 26.</note>
      <hi>will be favourable to thee, and thou shalt see his face with joy. Thou shalt finde him if thou seeke him:</hi> (and the rather, if <note place="margin">Ps. 63. 1.</note> thou doe it <hi>early</hi> with <hi>David;</hi> or with King <hi>Iosias, while thou art yet a child;)</hi> and <hi>finding</hi> him, thou shalt <hi>know</hi> him: and being come to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of greatnesse and goodnesse, thou shalt certainly <hi>love</hi> him; which is the chiefe <hi>duty</hi> he requires of thee.</p>
   <p>And now give me leave to offer to your view, a <hi>generation,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psa. 78. 9.</note> that have neither <hi>eyes,</hi> nor <hi>hearts</hi> aright; and with <hi>Esay,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay 43. 8.</note>
      <hi>Let me bring forth the blind that have eyes;</hi> that is to say, such <hi>as</hi> have their <hi>sight,</hi> yet <hi>wander like</hi> Jeremies <hi>blind</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lam. 4. 14. Deut. 28. 29. Psal. 135. 15.</note>
      <hi>men, and grope at noone day,</hi> with those in <hi>Deuteronomie, That have eyes and see not,</hi> have understanding, but make
<pb facs="12"/>
not true use of it, for which <hi>GOD</hi> gave it: but <hi>it is darkned</hi> (as S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Paul</hi> saith) <hi>because of the hardnesse of their heart.</hi> Among which I will set before you the chiefe: <hi>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ldlings, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, Selfe-lovers, Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Covetous</hi> and <hi>Idle:</hi> All which sorts of people, (as I said before) have <hi>filmes</hi> before their <hi>eyes,</hi> that hinder their <hi>sight</hi> and <hi>seeking.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>love</hi> of this <hi>World</hi> in generall, doth so <hi>blind</hi> the <hi>eyes</hi>
      <note place="margin">1.</note> of men, that <hi>worldlings</hi> cannot distinguish betweene <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill:</hi> they are not able, have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power, nor time to <hi>see</hi> the true <hi>GOD.</hi> For the <hi>World</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once fixed in their <hi>hearts, they cannot find out the things</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 3. 11. 2 Cor. 4. 4. Ephes. 6. 12.</note>
      <hi>which GOD made from the beginning:</hi> that is, they cannot think of their <hi>Creator.</hi> And (as S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh) <hi>The God of the World hath blinded their eyes, least the light of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>Gospell should shine to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hem:</hi> and therefore in another place he calls it <hi>the darknesse of the World.</hi> It was this <hi>love</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 10.</note>
      <hi>of the World,</hi> that caused <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> to for sake S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Paul.</hi> And S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Iohn</hi> affirmes plainely, that he <hi>which loveth the World,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2. 15.</note>
      <hi>hath not the love of GOD in him:</hi> and therefore neither can, nor desires to <hi>see</hi> him.</p>
   <p>Againe, the <hi>World</hi> (as a false glasse) deceives the <hi>sight:</hi> it's a very <hi>hypocrite,</hi> promiseth faire; but beleeve it not; rather feare the reward of its service: for <hi>breve est quod delectat, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum quod cruciat.</hi> It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to <hi>looke</hi> to <hi>Heaven</hi> with one eye, and to the <hi>Earth</hi> with the other. It was the <hi>dung</hi> of a <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> or <hi>Swallow,</hi> that deprived <note place="margin">Tob. 2. 10. Phil. 3. 8.</note>
      <hi>Tobias</hi> of his <hi>sight,</hi> and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle calls the things of the <hi>world, Terrena stercora:</hi> and therefore, while we dote on this <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>dung</hi> there of falls
<pb facs="13"/>
upon our <hi>sight,</hi> we may be justly reputed <hi>blind, we grope for the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay 59. 10.</note>
      <hi>wall like the blind; and grope as if we had no eyes:</hi> we may apply that to our selves which <hi>David</hi> did unto himselfe. <hi>The</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 38. 10</note>
      <hi>light of our eyes is gone from us:</hi> while we are in this estate, we shall never see <hi>God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>filme</hi> of <hi>preferment</hi> much darkens the <hi>sight,</hi> and the <note place="margin">2.</note>
      <hi>smoke</hi> of <hi>honour</hi> is so prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>eyes,</hi> that it hinders men from the <hi>sight</hi> of their <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator:</hi> For though they carrie their <hi>eyes</hi> loftily, yet <hi>look</hi> they <note place="margin">Esay 5.</note> not so <hi>high</hi> as they should; the <hi>myst</hi> of <hi>ambition</hi> is so <hi>thick</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>eyes;</hi> and the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beames of <hi>honour</hi> so <hi>dazles</hi> them, that in comparison of a true and cleare <hi>sight,</hi> these may also bee justly reckoned among the <hi>blinde.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Not much unlike to the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious.</hi>
      <note place="margin">3.</note> is the <hi>Selfe-lover, proud</hi> and <hi>vaine-glorious:</hi> he
<pb facs="13"/>
is also <hi>blind;</hi> for his <hi>eves,</hi> his <hi>sight</hi> is wholly reversed, and turned inward. The <hi>Pharisee</hi> lost his <hi>sight</hi> by this <hi>vanity:</hi> and so did <hi>Nabuchadonozor,</hi> and the Angels their <hi>blessed vision.</hi> The <hi>proud</hi> have not so much as a thought of <hi>GOD,</hi> much lesse a desire to <hi>see</hi> him: but all their desire is to <hi>see</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and that so long, in the <hi>burning glasse</hi> of <hi>selfe conceit,</hi> that in the end they lose their <hi>sight.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And this disease of the <hi>eyes</hi>
      <note place="margin">4.</note> begets another worse then the former, namely <hi>Rebellion.</hi> For the <hi>proud</hi> (thinks none better then himselfe,) presently with <hi>pharaoh</hi> saies, <hi>Who is the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 23.</note>
      <hi>LORD?</hi> The vice of <hi>pride</hi> makes the heart <hi>rebellious,</hi> as <hi>Ieremy</hi> speakes: and while a man is in <hi>rebellion,</hi> he never desires to <hi>see</hi> his <hi>Prince.</hi> It so hardens the <hi>heart,</hi> that it can receive no impression of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;
<pb facs="14"/>
but their <hi>eyes</hi> are as it were <hi>set in their heads,</hi> as it <note place="margin">1 Kings 14. 4.</note> is said of <hi>Ahia,</hi> in another case. <hi>They have eyes, but see not,</hi> as <hi>Ieremy</hi> saith, in the same <note place="margin">verse 21.</note> Chapter: and as our <hi>Saviour, seeing they shall see, and not</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 14, 15.</note>
      <hi>perceive; because they have closed their eyes.</hi> And this is that <hi>blindnesse of heart</hi> which the Apostle <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Paul</hi> meanes. For <note place="margin">Ephes. 4. 18.</note> indeed, the cause of this <hi>blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> is (as of all other evills) the <hi>heart;</hi> it being to the <hi>soule,</hi> as the <hi>eye</hi> to the <hi>body.</hi> For the <hi>eye</hi> is but as a <hi>conduit</hi> or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, through whose <hi>optiques,</hi> all good or bad desires passe to the <hi>heart.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Riches</hi> are as great an <hi>eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sore,</hi> as any of the former, for <note place="margin">5.</note> the <hi>eye</hi> of the <hi>covetous</hi> is ever fixed upon a wrong <hi>object: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varus est caecus,</hi> The <hi>covetous</hi> Man is <hi>blind,</hi> saith <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine;</hi> and therefore not without cause did our <hi>Saviour</hi> bid men
<pb facs="14"/>
      <hi>to be ware of covetousnesse:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luke 12. 15.</note> For these <hi>terrena stercora,</hi> of <hi>riches,</hi> the mucke of the World, <hi>blind the eyes</hi> even <hi>of the wise;</hi> they divert the <hi>eyes</hi> of the <hi>mind</hi> from <hi>seeing GOD.</hi> The <hi>Prodigall</hi> having his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion, went from his Father. Place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> looking-glasse upward, and you shall <hi>see</hi> Heaven: but downward, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd the Earth is in your <hi>sight.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t is not <hi>wealth,</hi> but <hi>poverty</hi> which <hi>enlightens</hi> the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. <hi>David</hi> in his <hi>prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ity said he should never be</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 30. 6.</note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>emoved: GOD</hi> did but <hi>turn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>way his face,</hi> and his <hi>sight</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>egan to be <hi>cleared.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, the <hi>Idle</hi> person can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot, shall not <hi>see GOD,</hi> because <note place="margin">6.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e takes no <hi>paines, labours</hi> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or this <hi>sight,</hi> he is as a <hi>dead</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>an. <hi>David</hi> in his <hi>idlenesse,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>st the <hi>sight</hi> of <hi>GOD.</hi> For the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yes</hi> of the <hi>slothfull</hi> are also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>losed, they cannot <hi>see</hi> him. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f thou hast a desire to <hi>see GOD,</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>
thou <hi>shalt finde him, if thou seek him with all thine heart,</hi> and <hi>with all thy soule:</hi> that is, fervently and diligently.</p>
   <p>Thus have we a short survey of the <hi>blind:</hi> for all which I will pray with <hi>Elisha, LORD open</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Kings 6. 20. Eph. 1. 18</note>
      <hi>their eyes,</hi> and <hi>that the eyes of their understanding may be enlightned,</hi> and advise them with the Prophet, <hi>Looke ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> blind, that ye may see;</hi> that <note place="margin">Es. 42. 18 Num. 24 4.</note> when with <hi>Balaam, their eyes be opened, they may see the vision of the Almighty.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And now that you have seen that to <hi>seeke</hi> and <hi>know GOD</hi> the <hi>Creator,</hi> is every mans <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty;</hi> as being <hi>commanded, per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swaded</hi> and <hi>patterned;</hi> and the it is the <hi>end,</hi> for which man w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>created:</hi> as also having a sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>direction</hi> set before you, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>preparation</hi> to this <hi>sight</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>search,</hi> together with some <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions,</hi> to avoyd the <hi>hinderance</hi> and <hi>lets</hi> to it; let us consider
<pb facs="15"/>
little, how farre we may enter into this <hi>search,</hi> by sufficient warrant, that we <hi>stare</hi> not upon the <hi>Sun,</hi> while we become <hi>blind.</hi> For <hi>Noli altum saper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, sed ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,</hi> was a good rule.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>No man hath seene GOD at any time (saith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Iohn,</hi> and <note place="margin">10. 1. 18. Exod. 33 20.</note>
      <hi>No man shall see GOD and live,</hi> saith <hi>GOD himselfe:</hi> For you must know saith <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine;</hi> that <hi>GOD</hi> cannot be <hi>expressed</hi> in <hi>words,</hi> nor <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended</hi> in any mans <hi>thought</hi> or <hi>knowledge:</hi> and his reason fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>how saith he, could we pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claim him immense and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible, if he could be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the speech or thought of any man? and it appeares how admirable he is, by that, that he is unutterable by all tongues, and incomprehensible within any thoughts.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Because GOD is above all, it followes, that he must needs exceed the capacity of</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
      <hi>men.</hi> Men, by the acutenesse of the <hi>mind</hi> may reach high; but they <hi>behold</hi> what <hi>GOD</hi> is, rather in <hi>opinion</hi> then <hi>defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> His <hi>fullnesse,</hi> none, either with corporeall <hi>eyes,</hi> or with the <hi>mind</hi> it selfe, have at any time apprehended.</p>
   <p>If then we can neither <hi>see,</hi> nor <hi>know,</hi> nor <hi>apprehend him;</hi> to what purpose is it, that we are so often commanded and advised to <hi>seeke him?</hi> We must <hi>seeke, see,</hi> and <hi>know</hi> him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this parallel. As the Sun is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be <hi>looked</hi> on, so that it may be <hi>seene</hi> and no more; lest by <hi>beholding</hi> it too stedfastly, we <hi>see</hi> lesse then we might: so <hi>GOD</hi> is to be <hi>knowne,</hi> so much as he permits thee to <hi>know</hi> and understand of him, and no more. And how farre, or short are we limited? how farre may we goe in the lawfull <hi>sight</hi> and <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of him? for though we take never so much warrantable
<pb facs="16"/>
paines to <hi>know</hi> and <hi>see</hi> him, yet wee <hi>shall but see him in this</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13 12.</note>
      <hi>pilgrimage, through a glasse darkly,</hi> as the Apostle speakes. It is true, yet paines we must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ake, and wayes we must and may use to <hi>see</hi> him. For <hi>GOD</hi> hath given man <hi>understanding</hi> above all creatures, to the end, that he should both <hi>see</hi> and <hi>know</hi> him in this <hi>vale of misery.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o hold you no longer in suspence, I conceive, that the best and safest way to come to the <hi>sight</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> of him, is by the <hi>consideration</hi> of his <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and <hi>Attributes.</hi> For in the first place, it was <hi>Davids practice, to muse upon all his</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 77. 5</note>
      <hi>workes and the dayes of old,</hi> that is (as some <hi>Commentators</hi> have it) the sixe dayes of the <hi>creation.</hi> And therefore they are justly taxed with the name of <hi>vaine, that are ignorant of GOD, and that could not out</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sap. 13. 1.</note>
      <hi>of the good things that are</hi>
      <pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>seene, know him that is; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther considering the workes, did they acknowledge the worke-master. For by the greatnesse and beauty of the Creature, proportionably the maker of them is seen.</hi> And <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Paul</hi> affirmes, that <hi>GODS</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 20.</note>
      <hi>eternall power and Godhead is understood by the things that are made:</hi> and <hi>St. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> goes a little further, when he saies, <hi>That to see the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator by the Creature; the Maker by his worke; and the Architector of the world by the World, is asmuch as Man can see concerning GOD.</hi> And as he may be <hi>seene</hi> in his <hi>Creatures,</hi> so in his <hi>Attributes</hi> he is no lesse <hi>visible,</hi> no lesse <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable:</hi> for if we well consider him (besides his infinite <hi>Essence)</hi> in his <hi>Power, Wisedome, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> (his principall <hi>Attributes)</hi> we may <hi>see</hi> and <hi>understand</hi> so much of him, as
<pb facs="17"/>
may conduce to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of him in this life. And yet I must confesse, that what <hi>sight</hi> we have of him here, is but (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh in the place formerly quoted) <hi>per speculum</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13</note>
      <hi>in aenigmate, through a glasse darkely,</hi> to that, which in the beatificall <hi>vision</hi> we shall <hi>see</hi> of him, to our comfort most <hi>clearly;</hi> if by our lives here, he shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after thinke us worthy of that most blessed <hi>sight.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And thus having briefly shewed the <hi>necessity</hi> of this <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>how farre;</hi> and <hi>by what meanes</hi> we may wade to the attayning of the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Creator:</hi> give me leave to tender to your view, a more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, devout and pious Treatise, tending to that purpose, which I have turned into true Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe English, though in a plaine Dialect, which at the first I s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lely intended for my owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate use: but now (not doubting
<pb facs="18"/>
of your favourable acceptance for the <hi>publique good,</hi> as I hope. Commending it and you therefore to the blessing of that <hi>Creator,</hi> (who so instruct us all in his <hi>knowledge</hi> here, that hereafter we may (with comfort) <hi>see him face to face, and know him, as we are knowne.)</hi> I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in CHRIST IESUS,
H. I.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>