<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR FRANCIS BACON KNIGHT, BARON OF VE∣RVLAM, LORD HIGH Chancellour of England.</title>
           <author>Wisemart, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122637_Bo1_4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72064</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10926</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122637</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR FRANCIS BACON KNIGHT, BARON OF VE∣RVLAM, LORD HIGH Chancellour of England.</title>
                 <author>Wisemart, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian knight compiled : by Sir VVilliam VViseman Knight, for the pvblike weale and happinesse of England, Scotland, and Ireland</title>
                 <author>Wiseman, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 7, 1, 39, 1, 41, 3, 75, 3, 83, 15 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="86"/>
   <pb facs="86"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR <hi>FRANCIS BACON</hi> KNIGHT, BARON OF VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RVLAM, LORD HIGH Chancellour of England.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, you are the highest Iusticer in this land, or next the highest. And therefore this peece of my labour if it be worth so much, I thinke fit to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to your Honor. In this garden of English iustice you are a principall gardiner, where euery subiect should be a weeder; to pull vp that by the roote, which makes you endlesse worke. This roote of</hi> Auarice <hi>is not so great but the compasse of a heart containes it. The biggest man hath no bigger plat to weed in: and yet your Lordsh. findes to your paines, that it is not done, and perhaps neuer lesse done. You can doe no more but cut it downe as it growes hurtfull: yet vp it comes againe like</hi> Hydraes <hi>heads. If I can weede it in my selfe, which J cannot well say; and can shew an other how, which J dare say: let no man despise an admonishing brother, that speakes in Gods name, and his countries, &amp; vnder your Lordships correction. My proiect J doubt not will be well pleasing, if it want not well hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. So, wishing you all the blessings of the Patriarke</hi> Ioseph, <hi>I humbly take leaue of Your Lordship.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>All your good Lordships to command <hi>W. Wisemart.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>