<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122394_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">718</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The. xi. bookes of the Golden asse : conteininge the Metamorphosie of Lucius Apuleius, enterlaced with sondrie pleasaunt and delectable tales, with an excellent narration of the mariage of Cupide and Psiches, set out in the. iiii. v. and vj. bookes. Translated out of Latine into Englishe by VVilliam Adlington</title>
                 <author>Apuleius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 126, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen that I had (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
Reader) slightly here &amp;
there runne ouer the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt
and delectable iestes
of Lucius Apuleius (a man
of auncient discent, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed
with singuler lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge)
written in suche a
franke &amp; flourishing stile,
as he séemed to haue the
Muses alwaies at will, to
féede and maineteine his penne: And when againe I
perceiued the matter to minister such excéedinge plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of myrth, as neuer (in my iudgement) the like hath
bene showed by any other, I purposed accordinge to
my sclender knowledge (though it were rudely, and
farre disagréeyng from the fine and excellent dooinges
now a dayes) to translate the same into our vulgar
tongue, to the ende, that amongest so many sage and
serious woorkes (as euery man welny, endeuor dayly
to encrease) there might be some freshe and pleasante
matter, to recreate the mindes of the Readers withal.
Howbeit I was eftesoones driuen from my purpose by
two causes: First, perceiuinge that the Authour had
written his woorke in so darke and highe a stile, in so
strange and absurde woordes, and in such newe inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
phrases, as he séemed rather to set it foorth, to show
his magnifency of prose, then to participate his doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges
to other: Secondly, fearinge lest the translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of this present booke (which séemeth a méere iest and
fable, and a woorke woorthy to be laughed at, by reason
<pb facs="5"/>
of the vanitie of the Authour, mighte be contemned &amp;
despised of all men, and so consequently, I to be had
in derisiō, to occupy my selfe in such friuolous and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling
toyes: but on the other side, when I had through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
learned the intent of the Author, and the purpose
why he inuented so sportfull a iest: I was verely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded,
that my small trauell, should not onely be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
of many, but the matter it selfe allowed, &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
of all. Wherfore I intend (God willinge) as nighe
as I can, to vtter and open the meaning thereof to the
simple and ignorant, whereby they may not take the
same, as a thing onely to iest and laugh at (for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
of Esope, &amp; the feigninge of Poetes, weare neuer
writen for that purpose) but by the pleasauntnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
be rather induced to the knowledge of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
estate, and therby trāsforme them selues into the
right and perfect shape of men. The argument of the
booke is: How Lucius Apuleius the Author him selfe,
traueled into Thessaly (being a region in Grece, where
all the women for the most parte, be such wonderfull
witches, that thei can transfourme men into the figure
of beastes) wheare after he had cōtinued a fewe daies,
by the mighty force of a violent confection, he was
chaunged into a miserable Asse, and nothinge might
reduce him to his wonted shape, but the eatinge of a
Rose, whiche after endurāce of infinite sorow, at lēgth
he obteined by praier. Verely vnder the wrappe of this
transformation, is taxed the life of mortall men, when
as we suffer our mindes so to be drowned in the sensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
lustes of the fleshe, and the beastly pleasure therof:
(whiche aptly may be called, the violent confection of
witches) that we léese wholy the vse of reason and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
(which proprely should be in man) &amp; play the partes
<pb facs="5"/>
of bruite and sauage beastes. By like occasion we reade
how diuers of the compaignions of Vlisses, weare tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by the meruelous power of Circe, into Swine.
And finde we not in the Scripture, that Nabuchodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noser
the ninth King of Babylō, by reason of his great
dominiōs and roialmes, fell into such excéedyng pride,
that he was sodenly transformed of almighty God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
an horrible monster, hauyng the head of an Oxe, the
féete of a Beare, and the taile of a Lion, and did eate
heye as a beast? But as Lucius Apuleius was chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
into his humaine shape by a Rose, the compaigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of Vlisses by great intercession, and Nabuchodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noser
by the continuall prayers of Daniell, whereby
they knewe them selues, and liued after a good &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
life: So can we neuer be restored to the right fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
of our selues, except we taste and eate the swéete
Rose of reason and vertue, which the rather by media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of prayer, we may assuredly attaine. Againe, may
not the meaning of this woorke, be altered &amp; turned in
this sorte. A man desirous to apply his minde to some
excellent art, or giuen to the studie of any of the scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
at the first appeareth to him selfe an Asse without
witte, without knowledge, &amp; not much vnlike a bruite
beast, till such time as by muche paine and trauell, he
hath atchieued to the perfectnes of the same, &amp; tastinge
the swéete floure and fruicte of his studies, doth thinke
him selfe well brought to the right and very shape of a
man. Finally, the Metamorphosie of L. Apuleius, may
be resembled to youth without discretion, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,
to age possessed with wisedome and vertue.
Now since this booke of Lucius, is a figure of mās life,
and toucheth the nature and manners of mortall men,
egginge them forward from their Asinall fourme, to
<pb facs="6"/>
their humaine and perfect shape, beside the pleasaunt &amp;
delectable iestes therein conteined, I trust if my simple
translatiō be nothing accepted, yet the matter it selfe,
shalbe estéemed by such, as not onely delight to please
their fancie in readinge the same, but also take a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern
thereby, to regenerate their mindes from brutish
and beastly custome. How be it, I haue not so exactly
passed thorough the Author, as to pointe euery sentēce
accordinge as it is in Latine, or so absolutely transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
euery woorde, as it lieth in the prose, (for so the
French and Spanish translators haue not done) consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
the same in our vulgar tongue would haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
very obscure and darke, &amp; thereby cōsequently,
lothsome to the Reader, but nothing erringe as I trust
from the giuen and naturall meaninge of the author,
haue vsed more commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and familiar woordes (yet not
so muche as I might doo) for the plainer settinge foorth
of the same. But how so euer it be (gentle Reader) I
pray thée take it in good part, considering that for thée
I haue taken this paine, to the intent, that thou maist,
Reade the same with pleasure.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>