<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, sound judgement, the
spirit of wisdome, uprightnesse of heart, and sweet
communion with GOD.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122227_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02990</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1313</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122227</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, sound judgement, the
spirit of wisdome, uprightnesse of heart, and sweet
communion with GOD.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A friendly triall of the grounds tending to separation : in a plain and modest dispute touching the lawfulnesse of a stinted liturgie and set form of prayer, Communion in mixed assemblies, and the primitive subject and first receptacle of the power of the Keyes: tending t satisfie the doubtfull, recall the wandring, and to strengthen the weak: by John Ball</title>
                 <author>Ball, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                    <distributor>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 314, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, sound judgement, the
spirit of wisdome, uprightnesse of heart, and sweet
communion with GOD.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is commonly professed, though
not so well known and observed
as it ought, that Satan is alwayes
busie to solicite, and our own
deceitfull hearts ready to turn aside from the
wayes of peace and comfort, either to the
right hand or to the left. To say nothing of
the lamentable state of heathen Infidels,
Turks, and Jews, who know not God, nor
believe the Gospel of JESUS CHRIST;
Amongst them that professe Christianity,
some are so deeply plunged into superstition,
that the truth of God and the ordinances of
grace are not prized in comparison of their
own vain and fruitlesse traditions. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
on the contrary, do so farre distast all
<pb facs="3"/>
inventions whatsoever (as they speak) in Gods
worship, as they reject that which beareth the
stamp and image of God, and might be greatly
profitable to their souls. Many come profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to the Lords table, and pollute the holy
things of God to their own destruction: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
through groundlesse fears of defilement,
do withdraw themselves from ordinances Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,
and the society of the godly, because
some unworthy are not debarred. To satisfie
this latter sort, who offend out of weaknesse &amp;
misguided judgement not of stubbornesse and
contempt, and to settle them that are stagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
I have penned this poore &amp; rude treatise,
nothing doubting but the truth will be able to
maintein it self, and that the beauty thereof
will procure favour and acceptance, though
it come arayed in a very homely garment.</p>
   <p>A stinted form of prayer hath been chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged
as an image forbidden in the second
commandment, a forged and devised wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
unlawfull both in them that use it, and
<pb facs="3"/>
those that joyn therein. To remove this
scruple, I have shewed the use of a stinted Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,
lawfull and allowable by the word of
God, of ancient use in the churches of Christ,
approved by all reformed churches at this
day: Upon which occasion many things are
disputed touching the meaning of the second
commandment, the nature of true and false
worship; and what it is to pray by the Spirit.</p>
   <p>Many are the objections which are made
against set forms of prayer, and particularly
against our book of common prayer: all
which I have endeavoured to answer seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally;
and not because they are of so great
weight, but because I desired fully to satisfie
every doubt, and roll away every stone I met
withall. If one and the same thing be oft
repeated, I desire it may be considered that
one and the same objection for substance is
often brought forth, though perhaps in
new aray, and every plain-hearted Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
(for whose use I principally intend
<pb facs="4"/>
this labour) is not able to apply an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
once given to sundry objections in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
diverse though for substance the same.
And I suppose the prudent will think it
more reasonable that the wise in heart be
burdened with over-much, then that the
weak should remain unsatisfied through
some defect. Some stagger at this, that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,
profane, notorious offenders are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to the Lords table, and conceive that
communicating with such in the ordinances
of religion they are partakers of their sinne.
And sure it is a thing to be lamented with
tears of bloud, that the body and bloud of
our Saviour CHRIST should be profaned,
the house and church of God defiled, the
name of the Lord dishonoured, religion
blasphemed, and the blind, notorious, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane
permitted to rush upon their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
But it is not for private persons to
take that upon them which belongeth not
unto their place; nor, being invited by
<pb facs="4"/>
CHRIST, to excommunicate themselves,
because such as are notoriously wicked be not
admonished, kept back, or censured.</p>
   <p>The main ground of the former doubt and
all others tending to Separation seemeth to be
this; That the power of the keyes is primitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
given to the community of the faithfull, as
the first receptacle. For then they conceive
that it perteineth to them to censure offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
or else to separate from them. Then
likewise it will more probably be concluded,
as they think, That that society which hath
not the power of CHRISTS keyes is not the
true church of CHRIST. Therefore to
raze the foundation of Separation, and at
once to overthrow their main objections, this
question is more largely disputed: wherein is
shewed by evidence of Scripture, That the
power of the keyes is given by Jesus Christ,
the Lord and King of his church, and great
Shepherd of his sheep, to the church-gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
whom he hath appointed to rule and
<pb facs="5"/>
feed his flock in his name, and to whom they
must give account.</p>
   <p>If any man shall think these things are small
and not to be insisted upon, he may please
to consider; How small soever the things in
themselves seem to be, the evil consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
that follow thereupon be both many and
great: It is no small matter to bury that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the condemnation of false worship,
which the Lord the authour of all truth, the
determiner of his true, pleasing and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
worship, doth allow in his service. It is
no small offense to forsake the prayers of the
congregation, to depart from the table of
the Lord when he calleth to feast with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
and to break off society and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
with the churches of Christ, where
he doth cause his flock to rest at noon; to fill
the hearts of weak Christians with doubts
and distractions, as not knowing what to
do, or which way to take; to spend time in
reasonings and disputations of this kind,
<pb facs="5"/>
which might much more profitably be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
in the practice of repentance and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
obedience: to expose religion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,
and the truth of God to reproch, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
them that delight to speak evil: These
are sad effects of this Separation which is here
opposed. Is it not lamentable to see poore
Christians, who sincerely thirst after the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of life, and long to meet the Lord in his
holy ordinances, cast into doubts and fears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
the things which so nearly concern
their comfortable walking with God and sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
of their souls? May not this tend to
the discouragement of divers that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
on, and turn them who are halting clean
out of the way? The rents and divisions
which have been in the church have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more
been one advantage which the enemies
of the truth have taken to speak reprochful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
And if the credit of religion, the glory
of God, and the souls of our brethren be dear
unto us, what can we do lesse then by a just
<pb facs="6"/>
and mild defense of the truth seek the reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of such as are gone astray, the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of them that be weak in judgement but
zealously affected to the wayes of God; stop
the stream of seducing, free the godly from
unjust imputations, and settle peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
in the truth amongst brethren? I heartily
wish we had not so much experience to lesson
us, that when men have once begun to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
the publick exercises of religion, and to
separate from the churches of Christ, they
have run from one errour into another after
the fond imaginations of their own seduced
hearts untill they have dashed themselves
upon the rocks.</p>
   <p>They that break off communion in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars
mentioned, have not proceeded to a
totall Separation from our congregations and
assemblies, as no churches of Jesus Christ:
This rigid Separation they condemn, as that
which was never approved or blessed of
God. But they have gone further then the
<pb facs="6"/>
word of truth doth warrant them, or they
have the Lord Jesus for their guide: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
it is the duty and safety of Christians to
follow after but not to go before their Lord
and Captain. The first entrance into an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous
way is dangerous: for in the track
thereof there is no stop, unlesse God of his
infinite mercy do prevent. Errours are lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
up together in a bundle, and many times
the least onely appear, which yet serve to
bring on and usher in the greater. At once
men fall not into strange and monstrous
opinions, no more then into outragious evils:
but by degrees they insensibly are drawn
from bad to worse, untill they come to a
great height. At the first sight many a mans
conscience would have been affrighted with
that errour which after some tampering he
highly admireth and is bewitched withall.
How many of great hopes and excellent
parts have been overthrown hereby, is too
evident by lamentable observation in all
<pb facs="7"/>
ages. Rents and divisions are the disease,
Separation the wound of the church, unto
which of long time she hath been obnoxious;
but it is the sinne of them who either lay stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks
of offense before their brethren,
or separate rashly or unjustly, being carried
away rather with prejudice then strength of
argument, and commanded more by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
of others then by the authority of the
rule of righteousnesse. There is but one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
the Church; and but one Lord, or head
of the body, Christ: And whosoever sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth
from the body the Church, separateth
from Christ in that respect. And if we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
our selves from Christ where he gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously
inviteth us to feast with him, may we
not justly fear that he will withdraw himself
from us, and make us seek, when we shall not
find him? Voluntary Separation from the
Lords table and prayers of the congregation,
what is it but a willing excommunication of
our selves from the visible tokens of the Lords
<pb facs="7"/>
presence and love? And if it be a grievous
sinne in church-governours, to deprive any
member of the church of all communion
with the visible church upon light and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary
occasions; is it not a greater sinne in
the members, to deprive themselves of the
same communion upon the like or lesse occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions?
Zeal and tendernesse of conscience
must be nourished by all good means; but
they are not to move alone without their
guide, that is, the word of God.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this kind of writing may occasion
more disputes. If so, it is contrary to my hearts
desire, who intend onely the satisfaction of
them that stagger, the reclaiming of them that
are gone too farre, and the maintenance of
peace, truth, and communion in the worship
of God, as it furthereth communion with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
Christ. If I may obtein this end, I have
that which I beg of the Lord. Willingly I
would not offend any that fear God,
but endeavour onely to remove the
<pb facs="8"/>
blocks at which I see some stumble, and to
further the more comfortable walking of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
who desire to please God in all things,
but are kept under in the means of comfort
with vain scruples. And happy were it, if,
doubtfull disputations laid aside, we might
joyn together with one heart and soul to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
religion, worship the Lord purely, edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
one another in our most holy faith, and
walk unblameably in the fear of God and
comfort of the holy Ghost. I take no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
in controversies of this kind, and could
heartily wish that, these matters rightly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed,
we might give heed to that one thing
which is necessary: But if it seem good to
any man to reply, I earnestly beg that he
would take the word of God truly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood
for his warrant, make proof of what he
saith, keep himself to the points in hand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
impertinent digressions, and proceed on
in love and meeknesse, as becometh them
that professe the truth, and desire to preserve
<pb facs="8"/>
the peace of a good conscience. A good
cause is no way advantaged by heat and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.
We must so write and speak in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies
of religion, as that we remember
we must give account to God of that which
we say. And if passionate and distempered
speeches in common talk be no light offense;
in matters of religion, which are soberly to
be debated as in the presence of God, to give
way to humane rashnesse and distemper is
much more disgracefull. God will not hold
him guiltlesse that telleth a lie for the glory of
his name. To bear false witnesse in civill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
betwixt man and man, is odious and
abominable: Therefore it behooveth us to
fear and stand in aw, lest being transported
with misguided zeal we call evil good and
good evil, and misapply the scriptures, when
we speak of our selves. Let us weigh all
things, and hold that which is good. The
Lord in mercy look down from heaven upon
his poore church and people, bring his truth
<pb facs="9"/>
to light more and more, dispell the mists of
ignorance, remove all occasions of offense,
settle peace and truth, prosper the means of
grace, build us forward in faith and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
and unite the hearts of his people in
love, that they may direct their course by
one rule (if they cannot be all of one mind
in every thing) and as one man may walk
together in heaven-way, untill they receive
the end of their faith, the salvation of their
souls.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>