<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, Sir IOHN SVVINER∣TON, Knight, Lord Maior of the Ci∣tie of London, All grace and happinesse.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122954_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02547</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12673</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122954</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, Sir IOHN SVVINER∣TON, Knight, Lord Maior of the Ci∣tie of London, All grace and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An holy panegyrick : A sermon preached at Paules Crosse vpon the anniuersarie solemnitie of the happie inauguration of our dread soueraigne lord King James, Mar. 24. 1613. By I.H. D.D</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pindley, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 109, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, Sir IOHN SVVINER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON,</hi> Knight, Lord Maior of the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of London, All grace and happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, Mine owne forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse (whereof it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth me not) hath sent forth other of my labours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden; but this, your effectual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie hath drawne forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the common light. Jt is an holy desire that the eye may second the eare in any thing that may helpe
<pb facs="3"/>
the soule: and we, that are fishers of men, should be-wanting to our selues, if we had not baits for both those sences. I plead not the disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of a dead letter, in respect of that life which elocution puts into any discourse Such as it is, I make it both publike and yours. I haue caused my thoughts, so neere as I could to goe back to the verie tearmes wherein I expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them, as thinking it better to fetch those words I haue let fall, then to follow those I must take vp. That therefore which it pleased your Lo to heare with such pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent attention, and with so good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to desire, I not vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suffer abroad; that these papers
<pb facs="3"/>
may speake that permanently to the eyes of all our countrimen, which in the passage found such fauor in the eares of your citizens, and such roome in so many heart's. Besides your first and vehement motion for the presse, your knowne loue to learning deserues a better acknowledgement, and no doubt finds it from more worthie hands. And if my gratulation would add any thing, those should enuie you which wil not imitate you. For the rest, God giue your Lo. a wise, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, &amp; courageous heart, that you may prudently &amp; strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly menage these wild times, vpon which you are fallen: and by your holy example and powerfull ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors,
<pb facs="4"/>
helpe to shorten these raines of licentiousnesse: That so this ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is better taught then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vnder heauen, may teach all other places how to liue; &amp; may honor that profession which hath made it renowmed, and all Gods Church ioyfull: The welfare and happinesse whereof, and your Lo. in it, is vnfainedly wished, by</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships humbly deuoted, Ios. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>