<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND SIR Robert Filmer, Knight.</title>
           <author>Grant, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122214_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00759</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10885</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122214</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND SIR Robert Filmer, Knight.</title>
                 <author>Grant, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the liturgie of the Church of England, or, Booke of common prayer : In a dialogue betweene Nouatus and Irenæus. By Ambrose Fisher, sometimes of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Fisher, Ambrose</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 309, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND SIR <hi>Robert Filmer,</hi> Knight.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was <hi>your care</hi> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued this <hi>Treatise;</hi> and it will bee <hi>your honour</hi> that you haue preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it. From you I had it in <hi>writing;</hi> to you I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne it <hi>printed.</hi> Pitie that <hi>hee,</hi> who was depriued of <hi>sight</hi> in his life, should be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the <hi>light</hi> of his <hi>true-worth</hi> after his death: Pitie that <hi>he,</hi> who (though his <hi>eminent abilities</hi> could not altogether bee
<pb facs="3"/> hid) liued in some obscuritie, if not <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded,</hi> yet <hi>vnrewarded;</hi> should (hauing left this <hi>Monument</hi> of his <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Loue</hi> to <hi>his</hi> and <hi>our</hi> Deare Mother, the English Church) be vtterly forgotten as if shee neuer had brought forth such a sonne. I confesse, many of <hi>Our Worthies</hi> (and be they euer acknowledged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred with honour) haue, <hi>by parts, vpon occasions,</hi> vindicated and iustified <hi>Our Common Prayer Booke</hi> against oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, but a <hi>through defence</hi> thereof neuer met I withall before this.</p>
   <p>It was conceiued in the <hi>braine</hi> and <hi>brest</hi> of this <hi>learned Authour</hi> in your Vncle <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall's</hi> house at <hi>Colchester,</hi> and the first draught thereof was there made. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Laconicall breuitie thereof; the Socraticall disputing, on <hi>Irenaeus</hi> part; and the Ramisticall <hi>Dichotomies,</hi> on the part of <hi>Nouatus,</hi> may perplexe some Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but questionlesse to the <hi>Learned,</hi> as familiarly therewithall acquainted, they will be acceptable. To gather, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue <hi>much</hi> into a <hi>little</hi> was his <hi>ordinarie</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>course,</hi> and he was happie in it. It was his labour in like manner rather to speake to the <hi>vnderstanding,</hi> then to the <hi>affections,</hi> yet closely withall (in a <hi>Crypticke Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke)</hi> he moues them.</p>
   <p>Brought vp hee was in his tender yeares among those, whom he here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes, &amp; by them was designed to vphold <hi>the faction.</hi> His conuersing with them (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides their Books printed) made himselfe acquainted with their <hi>plots,</hi> &amp; <hi>arguments,</hi> and had wel-nigh framed him for <hi>their purpose:</hi> But the <hi>Great-Ouer-Ruler</hi> of all <hi>plots</hi> and <hi>purposes,</hi> gaue this <hi>Blind-Man,</hi> when he came to maturitie, <hi>Inward-Light,</hi> and drew him out of that <hi>Schisme,</hi> which euen with the <hi>milke</hi> was instilled into him, and vnder the <hi>ferule</hi> was pressed vpon him. It was his happinesse to come to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and, in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to that <hi>Renowned Colledge</hi> sacred to the <hi>Sacred Trinitie.</hi> There (as your selfe remembers) we were <hi>coequalls</hi> in time, and <hi>companions</hi> in <hi>studies.</hi> There attained he to the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> both of the <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Arts;</hi> and improued them (by his <hi>vndefatigable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie)</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> euen almost to a <hi>Miracle.</hi> This <hi>deepe-learned-man</hi> was readie, euer-readie, to impart his knowledge, whether in Philosophie, or Diuinitie, freely, vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strainedly, cheerefully. To many young Schollers <hi>there,</hi> and at <hi>Westminster</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (where hee liued in my brother Doctor <hi>Grant's</hi> house) was hee a <hi>lightsome Guide,</hi> though his owne <hi>eyes</hi> were <hi>darke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Charitie</hi> stroue in him which should exceed the other; so that his departure hence so soone, was a great losse to many, if I said to this <hi>Whole Church</hi> of <hi>Ours,</hi> I said but the truth.</p>
   <p>It was his <hi>Charitie</hi> (grounded vpon <hi>Knowledge)</hi> that compiled this Dialogue. And the like <hi>Charitie</hi> excites me to draw it out of <hi>obscuritie</hi> into the <hi>publique light</hi> and view of the <hi>Church.</hi> And I am encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the rather hereunto by <hi>His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</hi> late <hi>Blessed-Instructions</hi> for the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing of the <hi>to-much-neglected-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and <hi>despised Rits</hi> of <hi>Our Church.</hi> This <hi>occasion</hi> iustly, mee thought, called for it; and would haue laid sacriledge to my
<pb facs="4"/> charge had I with-held it. It attends on the <hi>Scepter;</hi> and <hi>good successe God</hi> send it, that the <hi>Publique Liturgie</hi> of <hi>Our Church</hi> may hence-forth <hi>iustly</hi> bee <hi>valued,</hi> and <hi>duely obserued.</hi> I confesse ingenuously, that it is <hi>Catechizing</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> which enable vs to the <hi>required performance</hi> of <hi>God's Worship;</hi> but <hi>Prayer</hi> it is (especially <hi>Publique Prayer</hi> in the <hi>House-Of-Prayer)</hi> which is <hi>God's-Immediate-Worship.</hi> The more <hi>Publique</hi> this is, and the more <hi>frequent,</hi> the-more-likely (yea more then likely) is it to diuert iudgements, and draw downe blessings. And my <hi>priuate Prayer</hi> shall euer be, that <hi>Publique Prayer</hi> in <hi>Our Church,</hi> as it is <hi>reuiued,</hi> so it may be <hi>continued</hi> while the World continues, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen till <hi>Our Iesus</hi> returnes in <hi>glorie.</hi> So prayes</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Saint Barthol. Exchange, London,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>April</hi> 5. 1630.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in the <hi>same Iesus, who is euer</hi> the same § IOHN GRANT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>