<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A short Preface to be used before the Exhortation fol∣lowing, by the Minister who is not a Preacher.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122852_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72754</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16553</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A short Preface to be used before the Exhortation fol∣lowing, by the Minister who is not a Preacher.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A forme of common prayer, together with an order of fasting: for the auerting of Gods heauie visitation vpon many places of this kingdome, and for the obtaining of his blessings vpon vs : The prayers are to be read euery Wednesday during this visitation. Set forth by his Maiesties authority</title>
                 <author>Church of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bill, John 1, Assignees of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="41"/>
   <head>¶ A short Preface to be used before the Exhortation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, by the Minister who is not a Preacher.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Apostles wrote their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Epistles to divers Churches, they were to be read (by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters especially) in the Publike Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations. As it may appeare, in that S. Paul having written at large of many points of Religion to the Thessalonians, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth in this sort: <hi>I charge you in the Lord, that this Epistle be read unto all the brethren, the Saints.</hi> And in the end of his Epistle to the Colossians: <hi>When this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle,</hi> saith he, <hi>is read of you: cause that it be read in the Church of the Laodiceans also: and that ye also reade the Epistle written from Laodicea.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The name of Homilies by a misunderstanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, is not acceptable with many: and yet they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else in effect, but Epistles or Declarations groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Word of God, to teach Christian men &amp; women their duties to his Divine Majesty, how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and what to practice: carefully &amp; soundly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten unto us by Apostolicall men, with the approbatiō of the Church. There is here set downe, agreeable to the time, a godly Exhortation or Epistle (as it may wel be termed) written unto you all here present, by such as are in authority, and doe love you with an unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="42"/> love in Christ Jesu, who intreat you by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, that you will be content and willing to heare, what for your good, upon mature deliberation they doe write unto you: not as of themselves, but in the blessed Name of the most glorious Trinity: to whom they cease not to commend you all in their daily prayers.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>