<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122344_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19485</idno>
           <idno type="STC">591</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122344</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The brazen serpent: or, the copie of a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Decemb. 31. 1620. By Iohn Andrevves, priest and preacher of the VVord of God at Saint Iames Clerkenwell in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Andrews, John, vicar of Clerkenwell</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 51, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader (whether courteous or vncour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,
I <hi>know not;</hi> I am sure, I care
not: For, in this matter, I am <hi>Iohn</hi>
indifferent.) As I came, of late to the
Crosse, as a <hi>Beare to the Stake;</hi> so,
now I come to the Presse, (as a <hi>Theefe to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes)</hi>
sore against my mind. Which I write to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish</hi>
thee, lest thou shouldest <hi>mistake</hi> one for <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
For <hi>another</hi> there is, who writes <hi>both his
Names</hi> as I doe; and hath published <hi>diuers Bookes,</hi>
as <hi>Petitions, Subpoena's,</hi> Christ-<hi>Crosses, &amp;c.</hi> Now
because I would be loth to <hi>defraud</hi> him of any <hi>Right</hi>
or <hi>Honour,</hi> which may <hi>duly</hi> belong vnto him; or
that <hi>He</hi> should share <hi>with me</hi> in my shame; I doe
<hi>heereby</hi> certifie thee, that <hi>I</hi> am not the <hi>Man:</hi> For I
neuer saw the <hi>Kingdome of Ireland</hi> in all my life,
but in Bookes; nor the <hi>County of Wilts,</hi> but in the
worthy Worke of the learned, iudicious and famous
Antiquary, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Clarencieux.</hi> And for my part,
howsoeuer I be the <hi>meanest</hi> among the many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands
that are called to the <hi>Sacred Priesthood;</hi> yet
I may <hi>truly protest,</hi> that I neuer played the <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foranean
Theologaster: Istos enim Circulato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
<pb facs="6"/>
qui Sacram Philosophiam</hi> honestiùs <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexissent,
quàm vendunt, semper exosos habui.</hi>
And for mine Owne part, <hi>I was neuer in Print be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:</hi>
Neither was it either <hi>in my purpose,</hi> or <hi>in my
desire</hi> to come abroad to the World in Print <hi>at this
time.</hi> The importunate request of my friends could
neuer haue pressed me <hi>to the Presse,</hi> if I had knowne
which way to <hi>suppresse</hi> certaine bastard and <hi>illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
Copies</hi> of this silly Sermon, which <hi>wandred</hi>
vp &amp; down the Town, like <hi>vagrants;</hi> and were <hi>taken
Begging, here,</hi> for a Crown; and <hi>there</hi> for an Angel,
&amp;c. It was my desire, that <hi>they</hi> should haue been <hi>had</hi>
to the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Correction;</hi> and (after due <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)</hi>
sent <hi>back</hi> to the <hi>place</hi> where they were <hi>born,</hi>
or, rather, <hi>misbegotten.</hi> But the <hi>multitude</hi> of them
was so numerous, that <hi>Iustice (without inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence)</hi>
could <hi>not</hi> be <hi>done</hi> vpon them. Therefore, to
vindicate my selfe from the <hi>imputation</hi> of <hi>glorious
Barbarisme,</hi> and most lame and vnioynted <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence;</hi>
I knew no better course, then by making <hi>the
Genüine Copy</hi> of that, which I <hi>then deliuered,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
to the World. <hi>Such as it is,</hi> thou hast it; accept
it, euen as thou canst finde in thine Heart. I grant, I
haue not <hi>interlarded</hi> it with any exotique Elegancies,
nor <hi>conclouted</hi> the <hi>Margent</hi> with many <hi>Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi>
because I found it somewhat <hi>cumbersome</hi> to
the <hi>Compositors.</hi> For the Style, I confesse, it is plain
and incurious (euen <hi>like my Speach &amp; Garments.)</hi>
For it was my study, euer, to be rather <hi>inter Zeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, quàm <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And to say the
Truth, as I neuer had any <hi>facilitie</hi> in teaching Periods
<pb facs="6"/>
to <hi>daunce Friskin,</hi> and such-like curiosities; So did
I neuer take any <hi>felicitie</hi> in it: For I was perswaded,
that such <hi>laboriosae nugae</hi> were better <hi>neglected</hi>
then ambitiously <hi>affected;</hi> If for no other regard, yet
for this: That they do <hi>Emasculate the Sense.</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>it</hi> therefore to be such <hi>an homely</hi> piece, and so far
<hi>out</hi> of the <hi>Fashion,</hi> I could not expect any applause by
it: nay, I defie him that can thinke <hi>more contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly</hi>
of it, then <hi>I doe:</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <l>Falsus honor juvat,<note place="margin">Horat.</note> &amp; mendax infamia Terret,</l>
      <l>Quem? nisi Mendosum &amp; Mendacem.</l>
   </q>
   <p>For as there be many <hi>great Names,</hi> to whom I doe,
with all reuerence, <hi>rise vp;</hi> acknowledging that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
which can fall <hi>from me,</hi> can be worthy <hi>their
eye:</hi> So for <hi>vulgar and halfe-coddled Iudgements</hi>
(whether of <hi>Patricians</hi> or <hi>Plebeians)</hi> The <hi>VVorld</hi>
knowes, that
<q>Pro Captu Lectoris habent sua Fata Libelli.<note place="margin">Martial.</note>
      </q>
As it is, If it doe <hi>any good</hi> to any <hi>one;</hi> it is <hi>that</hi>
which I heartily <hi>wish,</hi> but <hi>dare not Hope</hi> for. For
(as the <hi>Times</hi> are) <hi>How</hi> may I hope for any <hi>Good</hi>
from a <hi>Sermon,</hi> when <hi>euen Ballads</hi> (which are in
<hi>farre more respect</hi> amongst the <hi>Many)</hi> can doe <hi>no
good</hi> vpon them? If it doe Good <hi>to none,</hi> it doth but
<hi>share</hi> with <hi>others</hi> of farre better worth; in the <hi>same
Fortunes.</hi> Yet, <hi>Come the worst that can;</hi> I am
sure, That after <hi>it</hi> hath burdened the <hi>Stationers Stall</hi>
the 12. part of the date of an <hi>Almanack,</hi> it may serue
well enough for <hi>waste Paper;</hi> which is the <hi>common
Destinie</hi> that hangs ouer the <hi>Most writings of this
Kind.</hi> So I take my leaue, <hi>May 25. 1621.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Io: ANDREVVES, <hi>Presbyter.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>