<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
           <author>Gheyn, Iacob de</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122015_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01673</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11810</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122015</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
                 <author>Gheyn, Iacob de</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exercise of armes for caliures, muskettes, and pikes : after the ordre of his Excellence. Maurits Prince of Orange Counte of Nassau etc. Gouernour and Captaine generall. ouer Geldreland. Holland, Zeeland, Vtrecht. Overyssel. etc. Sett forthe in figures. by Iacob de Gheyn. With written instructions. for the service of all captaines and comaundours. For to shewe hereout the better vnto their jong or vntrayned souldiers the playne and perfett maner to handle these armes</title>
                 <author>Gheyn, Jacob de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Baudous, Robert de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--The Hague</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 42, 43, 32 plates, 1°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Or your highnes, nor any man to vvhose vevv this present booke shall come, shall need to finde it strange, either, vvhy it hath borrovved an English habitt, or shrovvded it selfe vnder so great a protection: since on the one side it represents vnto You that manner of exercise of Armes, vvhich hath for many yeares bene practised in this schoole of vvarre, the Vnited Provinces, and that, by a Captayne vvhose vvorth (I thinke) not any part of the vvorld is ignorant of: in vvhich vvarre the valure of the English and Schottish nations (novv Brittaynes) hath bene of that speciall marke and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, that, for readye vse of theyr Armes, prouident care of the Commaunders and commendable obedience of the Souldier tovvards his chiefe, it can not be denyed but that the Provinces haue received verye acceptable services at theyr handes. On the other side: to vvhom could I (in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement) more fitly and (as I may saye) iustly, addresse the proprietye of a vvorke of this vvorthe and nature? then to a <hi>Prince</hi> descended from so many povverfull and victorious Kinges, vvho euen by destyny and iudgement of all the vvorld, is not onely the heyre of theyr Fortunes, but an inheritour of theyr vertues also: then to a <hi>Prince</hi> the sonne of the most puissant Kinge of all his predecessours: vvho, though he blesseth his Realmes vvith the svveetenesse of peace, yet (doubtelesse) he placeth the securitie of that content, in the due and lavvfull exercise of Armes. Lastely, to vvhom rather (I saye) should I dedicate this vvorke? then to a <hi>Prince,</hi> that through the light of his ovvne proper example, doth so much beautifye and ennoble the practise of Armes, vvho euen in the fore-springe of his yeares and amidst so many other princely entertaynements fitt for his youth and state, doth yet give such a lustre to this of Armes, by the continuall fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritye he hath vvith them in his often practise, that I thinke I may saye, and saye truely, that the most true and perfect knovvledge of them is rather to be found vvith your Highnes, then brought to You. Therefore, as all those excellent professours of excellent sciences (vvhere in yet your Highnes excells them all) are every one in speciall duety bound, to giue the best testy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye they can of theyr thankefulnesse, both in regard of the fauour vvhich some receive in being nere You, and also of the honour vvhich You doe to all theyr professions, in not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayninge to participate vvith theyr industries: So haue I in all humble and due respect, thought it fitt, to tender You this acknovvledgement of myne, hopinge that your Highnes shall receive no small contentement, by addinge the longe experience of the Nether-lands practise to Your ovvne knovvledge of ancient Histories, and those vvise and deep-grounded instructions of that great Monarche the Kinge Your Father.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnes his.</hi> Most humble servant in all duetye at command. Iacob de Gheyn.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>