<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to diuers learned Gentlemen, and other my louing friendes.</title>
           <author>Y., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122233_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07650</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18044</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122233</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to diuers learned Gentlemen, and other my louing friendes.</title>
                 <author>Y., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diana of George of Montemayor: translated out of Spanish into English by Bartholomew Yong of the Middle Temple Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Montemayor, Jorge de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 496 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to diuers learned Gentlemen, and other my louing friendes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout nineteene yeeres past (curteous Gentlemen) comming out of Spaine into my natiue countrey, and hauing spent welny three yeeres in some serious studies and certaine affaires, with no meanes or occasion to exercise the Spanish toong (by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance whereof it had almost shaken hands with me) it was my good hap to fall into the companie and acquaintance of my especiall good friend <hi>Edward Banister</hi> of Idesworth in the Countie of Southampton Esquier; who perceiuing my remissenes in the saide language, perswaded &amp; encouraged me earnestly, by some good translation to recal it to her former place: And to that intent he gaue me the first and second Part of <hi>Diana</hi> of
<hi>Montemayor</hi> in Spanish, which Booke (although I had beene two yeeres in Spaine) till then I neuer saw nor heard of; whose friendly care and desire to preuent so great a losse, and to preserue such an ornament in me, I confesse was the chiefe and principall cause (and therefore the onely credit) of this translation, whereby I recouered that toong againe that lay (as it were) smothered in the cinders of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion. The second cause of this my labour, was the delight I passed in discurring most of those townes and places in it with a pleasant recordation of my pen, which mine eies so often with ioy and sorrow had beheld. The third, the resolued then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent I had neuer (howsoeuer now it hath escaped my hands) to put it in Print, in proofe whereof it hath lyen by me finished <hi>Horaces</hi> ten and sixe yeeres more. For till then I neuer tried my vnproper vaine in making an English verse: how well or ill then the hard and strange kinde of Spanish is turned, I leaue to your fauourable censure and pardon: The low and pastorall stile hereof,
<hi>Montemayor</hi> in his Epistle to the L. of Villanoua excuseth, entreating of Shepherds, though indeed they were but shadowes of great and honorable personages, and of their marriages, that not many yeeres agoe liued in the Court of Spaine, whose posteritie to this day liue in noble estate. But touching the Bookes following, you must vnderstand that
<hi>George</hi> of <hi>Montemayor</hi> a Gentleman sprung out of the noble house of <hi>Montemayor</hi> in Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, after he had ended his first Part of <hi>Diana,</hi> which he distributed into seuen Bookes, intending to set forth the second Part, and before his departure into Italie (where I heard he died) imparted his purpose, and the subiect of his intended second Part, to <hi>Alonso Perez,</hi> who answering his intent, wrote the second Part of <hi>Diana,</hi> contayning eight Bookes, promising in the end thereof to continue it with a third Part, which yet he hath not done, although I heare he hath a purpose to do it. But <hi>Gaspar Gil Polo</hi> a Valentian Gentleman, who in my opinion excelleth for fine conceit (whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after that <hi>Alonso Perez</hi> second Part came forth) made another Part of <hi>Diana,</hi> naming it the first Part of Enamoured
<hi>Diana;</hi> the which being diuided into fiue Bookes, he intituleth to follow in due sequence the first seuen Bookes of <hi>Diana</hi> of
<hi>George</hi> of <hi>Montemayor.</hi> And in the ende of that first Part of Enamoured <hi>Diana,</hi> he likewise maketh a reference to another Part which he promised to set foorth; the which and that of <hi>Alonso Perez,</hi> if euer they come to light, I leaue to some finer wit and better iudgement to English, my selfe hauing done too much by launching so far into the maine, vnlesse (happily) in your fauourable iudgements it may finde a <pb facs="4"/>friendly and temperate construction. Hauing compared the French copies with the Spanish originall, I iudge the first Part to be exquisite; the other two corruptly done with a confusion of verse into Prose, and leauing out in many places diuers hard sentences, and some leaues in the end of the third Part, wherefore they are but blind guides by any to be imitated. Well might I haue excused these paines, if onely <hi>Edward Paston</hi> Esquier (who heere and there for his owne pleasure (as I vnderstand) hath aptly turned out of Spanish into English some leaues that liked him best) had also made an absolute and complete translation of all the Parts of <hi>Diana;</hi> the which, for his trauell in that Countrey, and great knowledge in that language, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with other learned and good parts in him, had of all others, that euer yet I heard translate these Bookes, prooued the rarest and worthiest to be embraced. The faults escaped in the Printing, the copie being verie darke and enterlined, and I loth to write it out againe, I pray you Gentlemen pardon, since all the last Terme that it was in the Presse (hauing matters of greater consequence in charge) I could not intende the correction: aduertising you by the way that the greatest faults are at the ende of the Booke set downe, the lesse being of no moment purposely omitted. Fare ye well and continue me in your woonted loue and fauours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all friendly offices, B. Y.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>