<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONble. IAMES CAMBELL, LORD Major; and the whole Court of ALDERMEN, of this Honble Citie: true Happines in this Life, and that which is to come, with a gracious Preservation from all their Enemies; especially, from the damnable and dangerous projects of the Jesuites, and their faction.</title>
           <author>Freake, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122937_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72111</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11346</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122937</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONble. IAMES CAMBELL, LORD Major; and the whole Court of ALDERMEN, of this Honble Citie: true Happines in this Life, and that which is to come, with a gracious Preservation from all their Enemies; especially, from the damnable and dangerous projects of the Jesuites, and their faction.</title>
                 <author>Freake, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrines and practises of the Societie of Iesuites : In two bookes. The first, containing their grounds and intentions, discovered by two of their owne societie, the Reverend Paulus Florenius, Doctor and professor of Divinitie, and Christianus Francken, professor of philosophy, both in the Imperiall Schoole of Iesuites at Vienna. The second, containing a detection of the secret designes and bloody proiects of that societie of later yeares; especially, since their first designes for disturbing the sate [sic] of Germanie. And may serue as a warning for vs of this iland, and these times whereinto wee are fallen. By W.F. an vnworthy minister of the Gospell of Iesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Francke, Christian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gibbs, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36, 4, 39-62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Book industry, catalogues and inventories</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HON<seg rend="sup">ble</seg>. IAMES CAMBELL, <hi>LORD Major; and the whole Court of</hi> ALDERMEN, of this Hon<seg rend="sup">ble</seg> Citie: true Happines in this Life, and that which is <hi>to come, with a gracious Preservation from</hi> all their Enemies; especially, from the damnable and dangerous projects of the <hi>Jesuites,</hi> and their faction.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O tell you these <hi>Times</hi> are times of Danger in the matter of Religion especially, and that they are indeed those later Dayes, which our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Lord and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles foretold long agoe, wherein Faith should scarcely bee found on Earth, because the Iniquitie of many shall abound, were nothing else but to take vp the vsuall Theame of
<pb facs="4"/>the times, which euery Pulpit ringeth of, and all men doe or may heare of day by day, as many as liue vnder a conscionable Ministrie. But to make demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of some particulars wherein that danger stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and to discouer some of those closer Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are practised in that <hi>Mysterie of Iniquitie,</hi> cannot chuse but be a worke acceptable to all knowing men; the rather because the <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of later times (as one well obserueth of them) like to Watermen vpon the Thames, set their faces one way, and row another. Amongst whom the <hi>Positions</hi> and <hi>Tenents</hi> of that Society of <hi>Iesuites,</hi> challenge all priority: For these men, aboue all others whom this last Century of yeares hath produced, haue the right tricke of it (as a Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> spoke wittily of them) with the one hand, to point vs the way towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and with the other hand to cheate vs of our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall possessions, vnder a colour of Religion, and cloke of Holinesse, trading for <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>Empires,</hi> and Soules of Men, <hi>Revel. 18.13.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It now draweth neare vpon an hundred yeares com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, since this Sect was first brought vpon the <hi>Stage</hi> of the <hi>Christian</hi> world, by a superstitious <hi>Spanish</hi> Souldier, named; <hi>INIGO LOIOLA,</hi> a man not more lame in his limbes, then in his Religion: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit his <hi>Disciples</hi> since his death, haue Christened him a new, for his and their owne further credit, into the name of <hi>IGNATIVS DE LOIOLA:</hi> Since which time; what wonders haue beene wrought by that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie,</hi> not in Christendome onely, but also in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motest Nations, their owne Annals doe relate; I will not say how truely, and our eyes haue seene, and our
<pb facs="4"/>eares haue heard not without astonishment, for they are the <hi>Spirits</hi> of <hi>Divels</hi> working Myracles, to goe therewith to the Kings of the Earth, and to the whole World, to gather them to the battle of that great day of God Almighty. <hi>Revel. 16.14.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And yet howbeit they haue power giuen them from God, as a iust plague <hi>to to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ment and hurt</hi> tht vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and disobedient world, their power and times are limited, their power is <hi>to torment and hurt</hi> onely, their time but for <hi>Fiue Moneths. Revel. 9.10.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>How neare they are now growne to such a Bulke, as they can hardly haue either meanes, or hope to inlarge, all wise and vnderstanding men discerne: and howeuer they flatter their great Catholicke Maister with hopes of a fifth Monarchy (for they haue a King ouer them, whose name is <hi>APOLLYON,</hi> the Destroyer, as <hi>Revel. 9.11.</hi> that Vniuersall Disturber of the peace of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome): yet we are not ignorant, nor could them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues be so, (if ambition of Temporall Glory, had not blinded them quite) that a fifth Monarchie in this case, is more by one, then <hi>DANIEL</hi> ever Prophecied.</p>
   <p>I am halfe perswaded, that the conclusion of this hundred of yeares which is now expired within ten, since these <hi>Iesuites</hi> first appeared in the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world, shall shew to Christendome, and to the whole world, an vnexpected and incredible alteration, in the Body of this Monster.</p>
   <p>And I am the rather induced to thinke so; because, I haue here vnderstood as much in effect, from a couple of their owne, men for learning and ingenuity second to none (for any thing I can perceiue) that euer that Societie bred. Who hauing beene educated many
<pb facs="5"/>yeares together, euen from their youth vpward in that Sect, and being (euen when they began to grow into yeares) illuminated by the beames of Gods more fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and blessed spirit, forsooke that Society, vpon mature deliberation, not for want of meanes or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any such <hi>Temporall</hi> discontentment, but meerely and onely, <hi>Motu Divino,</hi> as may sufficiently appeare by their ensuing discourse: and that no lesse then <hi>50.</hi> yeares agoe, as the date thereof testifieth: when the greatest part of those Mischiefes, which now ouerspread the face of the whole Christian world, were but in the shell: and those spirituall wickednesses, which at this day rule in high places, were onely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, and a meere <hi>Embryo.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now the same reasons, which caused these two most learned and graue Fathers, to renounce that double fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Societie in those times, may now (doubtlesse) much more preuaile with vnderstanding men, to whom I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to Minister this Discouery, as an <hi>Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Iesuitisme:</hi> forasmuch, as our eyes haue now seene those things, or the greatest part thereof, punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fulfilled, which these men, by obseruation of the <hi>Designes</hi> of that Society, haue so long since foreseene, and so truely foretold: Witnesse <hi>Bonemia, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> part of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and part of <hi>France,</hi> with their late atchieuement at <hi>Rochel,</hi> the Towne wherein that Copie was printed, out of which I haue extracted some part of this Discouerie.</p>
   <p>But I will not forestall the insuing Relation, with a tedious <hi>Epistle:</hi> For I dare say that your Honours and Worships are not ignorant, that as to particularize the Impostures of these times, in <hi>Divine things,</hi> is a
<pb facs="5"/>labour not fit for mortalitie to vndertake, seeing the Pen of such an one as might be accounted a Saint for his labour, would hazard to be blunted in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof: So, to anatomize the Multifarious and intricate subtilties of that pragmaticall Societie of <hi>Iesuites,</hi> were a worke almost of equall difficulty, and might beget no lesse wonder.</p>
   <p>What I haue beene enabled to doe herein, I doe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly praise God for, and doe as gladly and freely dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to your Honors acceptation, hoping that where the language shall seeme to sound harshly, you will fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably pardon it and consider me, as little better then a Translator, bound to tread in the steps of another.</p>
   <p>And if hereby, you shall be any way better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then formerly, touching those <hi>strong Delusions,</hi> wherewith Sathan, by meanes of this <hi>Societie,</hi> labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to deceiue the very Elect, giue God the praise, and let my weake, but well-meant indeavours, receiue a fauourable construction, as being intended for the good of my Country in generall; but especially, as a testimoniall of my due respect and seruice, who rest for the welfare of the Honourable and Graue Senate of this Citie,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A dayly Orator at the Throne of Grace WILLIAM FREAKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>