<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right worshipfull Sir Henry Lee Knight, Maister of the Leasshe.</title>
           <author>Hellowes, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122612_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72222</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12433</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right worshipfull Sir Henry Lee Knight, Maister of the Leasshe.</title>
                 <author>Hellowes, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The familiar epistles of Sir Anthony of Gueuara, preacher, chronicler, and counceller to the Emperour Charles the fifth. Translated out of the Spanish toung, by Edward Hellowes, Groome of the Leashe, and now newly imprinted, corrected, [and] enlarged with other epistles of the same author. VVherein are contained very notable letters</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 402, 401-412, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right worshipfull Sir Henry Lee Knight, Maister of the Leasshe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGht vvorshipfull, being combred vvith doubt too be noted of rash presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and no lesse afflicted vvith that vncouth &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable vice of dull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire: I vvas constrained vvith tvvo much oddes, to endure combat with both these furious sprites: and after long conflicte, as it vvere by the vvaye of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king breath, they began to argue: and first despaire (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more fierce, vvith thinne face and holovve eyes) grimmely began to saye, Oh beastly Svvine vvithoute prouidence, and enraged Beare, to performe thy ovvne disposition, vvithout all grace or learning, and voyd of all consideration of the issue of iudgemente of others, vvhich greedily despise, hate and beare enuie, and at all times ceasse not to persecute the feeble attemptes vvhich thou and others takest in hande, euery of vvhiche euills vvith many others might be auoyded, if by the nature and manner of my disposition thou couldst keepe thy selfe coy and mute. But vvith great impatiēce presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did breath foorth these or such like vvords: ah mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable Cockatrice, and caytife most cruel to mankind, vvhich by thy ougly shape declarest the lothsome frute of thy vvretched nature, vvhiche in all times and places
<pb facs="3"/>
dost practise the ouerthrovv of al honest, lavvdable and noble enterprises, vvherin they vvould haue vsed many tedious argumēts, if I had not cut off by sute for diuine assistance. Presently obtayning tvvo such auncient and famous Champions, of no common singularitie, by vvhose presidents, directions, and conductions, I vvas foorth vvith deliuered of all perplexities, namely Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and Iudas: but therevvithall not omitting to succour my selfe vvith the vvisedome and policie of the Bee, vvhi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h gathereth honey out of nettles, vvhich both and ioyntly made such discourses of the horrible euills, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate mischiefes, and cruell mishaps, that hath ensued the hatefull company of both these companions afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd, in such sensible maner, as suche feeling vvitnesses possibly might report. Leauing all their particular rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons vvhich vvoulde grovv ouerlong, they concluded, that euery extremitie engendreth vice, and only vertue is that which is equal in ballance: &amp; so departed. Therby giuing to vnderstand, that the vertue of a noble mind, is neither daūted vvith frovvard fortune, either exalted or puffed vp vvith gifts or prosperitie. And presently being brought to a certaine examination, I vvas driuen flatly to confesse that al strength is vveaknesse, al knovvledge ignorance, actiuitie impotencie, vvisdome foolishnesse, iustice vvrong, temperāce rashnesse, fortitude covvard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and all perfection but corruption: of all vvhich, &amp; no other notable deedes, man vvhatsoeuer, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume and boast himselfe, but vvhen God alone vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence doth adde his grace. And thus presumption vvith his sequele being remoued, and despaire vvith his drovvsie troupe being vanished, depending only of
<pb facs="3"/>
diuine prouidence, I began to cal to mind my God, my Prince, my countrey, &amp; also your vvorship, of vvhom I had receyued many good things, being very loth to shevv my selfe vtterly idle, either ingrate, receyuing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisemēt of Gueuara vvhich giueth vs to vnderstand, that since the beginning of the vvorld, there hathe not bin any Prince that hathe excelled, or to vvhom Iulius Caesar, either Alexander the great ought to giue place: obtayning soueraintie in their seuerall vertues, namely the one in pardonīg of iniuries the other in giuing large and bountiful revvards: affirming therevvithall, that to the ingrate or vnthankfull man, neither vvould Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander giue any revvard, either Iulius Caesar pardon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie: giuing vs therby to vnderstand, that they helde it much better to darken their ovvne singular and renovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vertues, thā to yeld benefit vnto so detestable vice. Forthvvith being vrged therby to confesse my debt, &amp; constrayned to shake off all drovvsie forgetfulnesse, &amp; avvake my dull spirits to yeld my selfe as abandoned to do your worship either seruice or pleasure: but my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and storehouse being searched and ransackt, I find it furnished vvith no other implements, but emptie abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and barren facultie to performe the same: forced in the place of vvorkes to furnish the satisfaction vvith vvords. Yet frankly confessing that although oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie shall deny to yeeld hir selfe to stretch to the merit of your great goodnesse vsed vvith me: notvvithstanding at all times and places, vvords of confession and disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to performe, shall neuer ceasse to do their indeuor to escape the vnkind disgrace of ingratitude. Adding therby hardines vnto my self once more to attēpt your patiēce vvith this present of Gueuara being finished,
<pb facs="4"/>
and also out of the French Booke somevvhat augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vvith matter both horoicall and deuine: the prayse and commendation vvhereof, I rather remitte vnto the glorious fame of the Auctor himselfe, than tediously vvithout skill to paint or polish the same vvith colours of imperfect hevv. Right humbly beseeching youre VVorship to accepte the same vvith the mildnesse of your vvonted fauoure: &amp; (as it apperteyneth) I shall not ceasse to pray that the protection of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God may conduct and follovve you vvith perfect felicitie in all noblenesse both of body &amp; mind, as may yeld your worship before god &amp; man immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal renowne.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worshippes most humble to command Edwarde Hellowes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>