<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122577_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03030</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13171</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122577</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations miscellaneous, holy and humane</title>
                 <author>Henshaw, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Andrewes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72, 71-136, 6 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader,</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not out of desire of being knowne, nor out of a desire to bee thought to know, that I doe commend this small tract to the world; but to take up the roome of worse thoughts in thy head, and of worse bookes in thy hands; it is the worke of younger yeeres, and the fruit of idle times, not of a serious study, and no otherwise doe I publish it to view; though I am perswaded it would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce much to the peace of the
<pb facs="5"/>
Church, if bookes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were more in use; it were to be wish'd that inferiours would imploy their time ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a holy meditation of those truths which are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy receiv'd in the Church, than in making themselves, or shewing themselves able to defend them; not that I would commend an ignorant devotion to any, or desire men to know lesse good, but more to practise that good which they know; not turne Religion into disputation, but turne their disputation into action, and obedience; they shall finde in the last day that it is holinesse, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="5"/>
(I doe not say holinesse without knowledge) that must bring them to Heaven; <hi>Supremo illi judici non scripta approbanda, sed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta</hi>; not the disputer, but the doer of Gods will shall be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified, men while they spend their time in disputing what they should doe, they too often neglect to doe even those things which are without dispute; in this book if there be little paines, yet there is no hurt, nay, it is thy owne fault if there rise not some good to thee from it, which if thou second with practise will bring thee to an eternall good which I wish thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>