<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOVR,
to his sonne Faustinus, and vnto the Readers
of this booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122394_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">718</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOVR,
to his sonne Faustinus, and vnto the Readers
of this booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The. xi. bookes of the Golden asse : conteininge the Metamorphosie of Lucius Apuleius, enterlaced with sondrie pleasaunt and delectable tales, with an excellent narration of the mariage of Cupide and Psiches, set out in the. iiii. v. and vj. bookes. Translated out of Latine into Englishe by VVilliam Adlington</title>
                 <author>Apuleius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 126, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOVR,
to his sonne Faustinus, and vnto the Readers
of this booke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THat I to thee some ioyous iestes, may show in gentle glose:</l>
      <l>And frākly feede thy bēded eares, with passing pleasāt prose.</l>
      <l>So that thou daine in seemely sorte, this wāton booke to view</l>
      <l>That is set out and garnisht fine, with writen Phrases newe.</l>
      <l>I will declare how one by happe, his humaine figure lost,</l>
      <l>And how in brutishe fourmed shape, his lothed life he tost:</l>
      <l>And how he was in course of time, from such estate vnfold.</l>
      <l>Who eftsoones turnd to pristine shape, his lot vnlucky told.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>WHat and who he was, attend a while and you
shall vnderstand, that it was euen I, the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of mine owne Metamorphosie, &amp; straunge
alteration of figure. Hymettus, Athens, Isthmia, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire,
Tenaros, and Sparta, beinge fat &amp; fertill soiles
(as I pray you giue credit to the bookes of more euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
fame) bée places where mine auncient progenie &amp;
lignage did sometime flourishe: there I say, in Athens
when I was yonge, I went first to schoole. Sone after
(as a stranger) I arriued at Rome, wheras by great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie
&amp; without instruction of any scholemaster I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued
to the full perfection of the Latine tongue: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde,
I first craue &amp; begge your pardon, least I should
happen to displease or offend any of you by the rude &amp;
rustike vtterance of this straunge &amp; forrein language.
And verely, this new alteration of speach doth corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spond
to the enterprised matter whereof I purpose to
entreate, I wil set foorth vnto you a pleasant Grecian
lest. Wherunto gentle Reader if thou wilt giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dāt
eare, it wil minister vnto thée such delectable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
as thou shalt be well contented withall.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>