<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL AND VVOR∣THILY EMINENT MERCHANTS:</title>
           <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122012_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10821</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21094</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL AND VVOR∣THILY EMINENT MERCHANTS:</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The merchants mappe of commerce : wherein, the universall manner and matter of trade, is compendiously handled. The standerd and currant coines of sundry princes, observed. The reall and imaginary coines of accompts and exchanges, expressed. The naturall and artificiall commodities of all countries for transportation declared. The weights and measures of all eminent cities and tovvnes of traffique, collected and reduced one into another; and all to the meridian of commerce practised in the famous citie of London. By Lewes Roberts, merchant. Necessary for all such as shall be imployed in the publique affaires of princes in forreigne parts; for all gentlemen and others that travell abroad for delight or pleasure, and for all merchants or their factors that exercise the art of merchandizing in any part of the habitable world</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Lewes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 12, 223, 3, 116, 119-202, 205-262, 2, 192, 22 pages, 2 plates (1 folded), portraits, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL AND VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THILY EMINENT <hi>MERCHANTS:</hi>
   </head>
   <p>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. MORRIS ABBOT, Knight, Alderman of the <hi>Citie</hi> of LONDON, <hi>and Governour of the Company of</hi> English MERCHANTS, trading <hi>into the</hi> East-INDIES▪</p>
   <p>And HENRY GARRAWAY, Esquire, Alderman of the said <hi>Citie</hi> of LONDON, <hi>and Governour of the Company of English</hi> MERCHANTS <hi>trading the</hi> Levant <hi>Seas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our excellent skill, <hi>(much honour'd</hi> SIRS) in all the particular parts of <hi>Merchandizing,</hi> and your skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full excellencie in the <hi>Universall Commerce</hi> of the World, not only demonstrated by continuall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but also practised by sundry demonstrations, (especially under your Government, in those so <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>honourable societies,</hi> of which you are at this present the happy <hi>Governours)</hi> promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, that you were not only the fittest PATRONS of this <hi>Modell,</hi> but the best <hi>Iudges</hi> of the WORKE <hi>it selfe;</hi> and therefore if I were not induced by any other
<pb facs="3"/>
motive, nor yet moved by any other inducement; yet this alone might both move and induce me, not onely to present you with this <hi>Dedication,</hi> but also crave from your <hi>Worths</hi> a friendly and favourable <hi>Protection.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But the further consideration of my particular <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligement,</hi> and the dayly experience of both your <hi>loves,</hi> challenged this justly from me, as the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my <hi>respect</hi> and <hi>service:</hi> for before I had the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of your acquaintance, I was made acquainted with your favours; and in <hi>Constantinople</hi> before you knew mee, I had the honour of your <hi>imployments;</hi> and after my returne thence, I found the approbation of my former indeavours extended <hi>it selfe</hi> not only to my admittance (as a Member) into those <hi>Societies</hi> you governe; but since into places of <hi>trust</hi> and <hi>repute</hi> in both of them.</p>
   <p>Your <hi>experience</hi> and <hi>judgement</hi> then in the contents of this <hi>Tract</hi> considered, and my never-dying <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> for these your noble <hi>courtesies</hi> remembred: please to <hi>Patronise</hi> these my <hi>Labours,</hi> and in a faire constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction accept of this my <hi>New-yeares acknowledgement:</hi> So shall both of you reap the <hi>Honour</hi> due to your owne <hi>Worths,</hi> and I the <hi>respect</hi> due to a gratefull FACTOR, which with all <hi>faithfull expressions</hi> I shall ever co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet to <hi>preserve;</hi> that I may as well <hi>futurely</hi> as <hi>formerly</hi> be honoured by your good <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> and intitle my selfe still your <hi>thankfull</hi> and <hi>affectionate friend,</hi> to serve you.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Ianuary 6. 1688.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>LEWES ROBERTS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>