<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the well affected Reader and peruser of this Booke, St. Bredwell Physition, greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122165_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01622</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11751</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the well affected Reader and peruser of this Booke, St. Bredwell Physition, greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The herball or Generall historie of plantes. Gathered by Iohn Gerarde of London Master in Chirurgerie very much enlarged and amended by Thomas Iohnson citizen and apothecarye of London</title>
                 <author>Gerard, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Joyce (Jocosa).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitaker, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 1630, 50 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the well affected Reader and peruser of this <hi>Booke, St. Bredwell Physition,</hi> greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Pen is the campe of glorie and honour for all men, saith the younger <hi>Pliny:</hi> not

<note place="margin">Plin. Iun. in pan.</note>

 onely men of great birth and dignitie, or men of office endued witb publique charge and titles, are seene therein, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the garland of praise and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment waiting to crowne their merits, but euen the common souldier likewise: so as he, whose name and note was crst all obscure, may by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> acts of valour obtaine a place among the noble. The schoole of science keepeth sembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proportion: whose amplitude, as not alwaies, nor onely, men of great titles and degrees, labour to illustrate; so whosoeucr doth, may confidently account of, at the least, his name to be immortall. What is he then that will denie his voice of gracious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to the Authors of this Booke: to euery one, no doubt, there is due a condigne measure.

<note place="margin">Turnerus. Dodonaeus. Pena. L <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Tabernamon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus.</note>

 The first gatherers out of the Antients, and augmentors by their owne paines, haue <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> spread the odour of their good names, through all the Lands of learned habitations. D. <hi>Priest,</hi> for his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation of so much as <hi>Dodonaeus,</hi> hath thereby left a tombe for his honorable sepulture. M. <hi>Gerard</hi> comming last, but not the least, hath many waies accommodated the whole worke vnto our English Nation: for this Historic of Plants, as it is richly replenished by those fiue mens labours laied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, so yet could it full ill haue wanted that new accession he hath made vnto it. Many things hath he nourished in his garden, and obserued in our English fields, that neuer came into their pennes to write of. Againe, the greatest number of these plants, hauing neuer been written of in the English tongue, would haue wanted names for the vulgar sort to call them by: in which defect he hath bin curiously carefull, touching both old and new names to make supply. And lest the Reader should too often languish with frustrate desire, to finde some plant he readeth, of rare vertue, he spareth not to tell (if himselfe haue seene it in England) in what wood, pasture or ditch the same may be seene and gathered. Which when I thinke of, and therewithall remember, with what cheerefull alacritie, and resolute attendance he hath many-yeares tilled this ground, and now brought forth the fruit of it, whether I should more commend his great diligence to attaine this skill, or his large bencuolence in bestowing it on his countrie, I cannot easily determine. This booke-birth thus brought forth by <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> as it is informe and disposition faire and comely, euery <hi>species</hi> being referred to his likeliest <hi>genus,</hi> of whose stocke it came: so is it accomplished with surpassing varietie, vnto such spreading growth and strength of euery lim, as that it may seeme some heroicall Impe of illustrious race, able to draw the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and expectation of euery man vnto it. Somewhat rare it will be here for a man to moue a question of this nature, and depart againe without some good satisfaction. Mamfold will be the vse both to the Physition and others: for euery man delighteth in knowledge naturally, which (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> said) is in prosperitie an ornament, in aduersitie arefuge. But this booke aboue many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers

<note place="margin">Laert. l. 5. cap. 1.</note>

 will sute with the most, because it both plenteously ministreth knowledge, which is the food of the minde, and doth it also with a familiar and pleasing taste to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> capacitie. Now as this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie is communicated to all, and many shall-receiue much fruit thereof, so I wish some may haue the minde to returne a benefit againe; that it might not be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in all that <hi>Iuvenall</hi> saith, <hi>Scirevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt

<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>

 omnes, mercedem soluere nemo: (i.) All desire to know, none to yeeld reward.</hi> Let men think, that the perfection of this knowledge is the high aduancement of the health of man that perfection is not to be attained, but by strong indeuor: neither can strong indeuor be accomplished without free maintenance. This hath not he, who is forced to labour for his daily bread: but if hee, who from the short houres of his daily and necessarie trauell, stealing as it were some, for the publike behoofe, and setting at length those pecces together, can bring forth so comely a garment as this, meet to couer or put away the ignorance of many: what may be thought he would do, if publicke mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance did free him from that priuate care, and vnite his thoughts to be wholly intent to the generall good. O Reader, if such men as this sticke not to rob themselues of such wealth as thou haste to inrich thee, with that substance thou wantest, detract not to share out of thine aboundance to merit and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage their paines: that so fluxible riches, and permanent sciences, may the one become a prop vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other. Although praise and reward ioined as companions to fruitfull endeuors, are (in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>)

<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>

 desired of all men, that vndertake losses, labours, or dangers for the publique behoofe: because they adde sinewes (as it were) vnto reason, and able her more and more to resine her selfe: yet doe they

<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>

 not imbrace that honour in respect of it selfe, nor in respect of those that conferredit vpon them, but <pb facs="7"/> as hauing thereby an argument in themselues, that there is something in them worthy estimation among men: which then doubleth their diligence to deserue it more abundantly. Admirable and for the imitation of Princes, was that act of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who setting <hi>Aristotle</hi> to compile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries

<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 8. cap. 16.</note>

 of the bruit creatures, allowed him for the better performance thereof, certaine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of men, in all Asia and Greece, most skilfull obseruers of such things, to giue him informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touching all beasts, fishes, foules, serpents, and flies. What came of it? A booke written, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all learned men in all ages since do exercise themselues principally, for the knowledge of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Great is the number of those that of their owne priuate haue laboured in the same matter, from his age downe to our present time, which all do not in comparison satisfie vs. Whereas if in those ensuing ages there had risen still new <hi>Alexanders,</hi> there (certainely) would not haue wanted <hi>Aristotles</hi> to haue made the euidence of those things an hundred fold more cleered vnto vs, than now they be. Whereby you may perceiue the vnequall effects that follow those vnsutable causes of publike and priuate maintenances vnto labours and studies. Now that I might not dispaire in this my exhortation, I see examples of this munisicence in our age to giue me comfort: <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror

<note place="margin">Gryllus in orat. de pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr. studij me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic.</note>

 and <hi>Cosmus Medices</hi> Prince of Tuscane are herein registred for furthering this science of plants, in following of it themselues and becomming skilfull therein: which course of theirs could not be holden without the supporting and aduancing of such as were studious to excell in this kinde. <hi>Bellonius</hi> likewise (whom for honours cause I name) a man of high attempts in naturall science,

<note place="margin">Bellon. de negl. stirp. cul. prob. 9.</note>

 greatly extolleth his Kings liberalitie, which endued him with free leisure to follow the studie of plants, seconded also herein by <hi>Montmorencie</hi> the Constable, the Cardinals <hi>Castilion</hi> and <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> with <hi>Oliuerius</hi> the Chancellor; by whose meanes he was enabled to performe those his notable <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in Italy, Africa and Asia: the sweet fruit whereof, as we haue receiued some taste by his obseruations, so we should plenteously haue been filled with them, if violent death by most accursed robbers had not cut him off. And as I finde these examples of comfort in forreine nations, so we are (I confesse) much to be thankfull to God, for the experience we haue of the like things at home. If (neuerthelesse) vnto that Physicke lecture lately so well erected, men who haue this worlds goods shall haue hearts also of that spirit, to adde some ingenious labourer in the skill of simples, they shall mightily augment and adorne the whole science of Physicke. But if to that likewise they ioine a third, namely the art of Chimicall preparation; that out of those good creatures which God hath giuen man for his health, pure substances may be procured for those that be sicke, (I feare not to say it, though I see how <hi>Momus</hi> scorneth) this present generation would purchasemore to the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Physicke, than all the generations past since <hi>Galens</hi> time haue done: that I say, nothing of this one fruit that would grow thereof, to wit, the discouering and abolishing of these pernitious impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures and sophistications which mount promising Paracelsians euery where obtrude, through want of a true and constant light among vs to discerne them by. In which behalfe, remembring the mournfull speech of graue <hi>Hippocrates; The art of Physicke truly excelleth all arts, how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it,

<note place="margin">Hipp. de Lege.</note>

 through the ignorance partly of those that exercise it, and partly of those that iudge rashly of Physitions, it is accounted of all arts the most inferiour:</hi> I say in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the art of Chimistrie is in it selfe the most noble instrument of naturall knowledges; but through the ignorance &amp; impiety, partly of those that most audaciously professe it without skill, and partly of them that impudently condemne that they know not, it is of all others most basely despised and scorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rejected. A principall remedy to remoue such contumelious disgrace from these two pure vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins of one stocke and linage, is this that I haue now insinuated, euen by erecting the laboratory of an industrious Chimist, by the sweet garden of flourishing simples. The Physicke reader by their meanes shall not onely come furnished with authorities of the Ancients, and sensible probabilities for that he teacheth, but with reall demonstrations also in many things, which the reason of man without the light of the fornace would neuer haue reached vnto. I haue vttered my hearts desire, for promoting first the perfection of my profession, and next by necessary consequence, the healthie liues of men. If God open mens hearts to prouide for the former, it cannot be but that the happy fruits shall be seene in the later. Let the ingenious learned iudge whether I haue reason on my side: the partiall addicted sect I <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, as <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that neuer meane good to posteritie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>