<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A NOTE OF CERTEIN WONDERFVL and most dangerous places in the Sea, which Wagenar hath set downe in his Epistle to the Prince of Orenge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122236_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14624</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24931</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122236</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A NOTE OF CERTEIN WONDERFVL and most dangerous places in the Sea, which Wagenar hath set downe in his Epistle to the Prince of Orenge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mariners mirrour : wherin may playnly be seen the courses, heights, distances, depths, soundings, flouds and ebs, risings of lands, rocks, sands and shoalds, with the marks for th'entrings of the harbouroughs, havens and ports of the greatest part of Europe: their seueral traficks and commodities: together wth. the rules and instrume [n] ts of nauigation. First made &amp; set fourth in diuers exact sea-charts, by that famous nauigator Luke Wagenar of Enchuisen and now fitted with necessarie additions for the use of Englishmen by Anthony Ashley. Heerin also may be understood the exploits lately atchiued by the right Honorable the L. Admiral of Engla [n] d with her Maties. nauie: and some former seruices don by that worthy knight Sr. Fra: Drake</title>
                 <author>Waghenaer, Lucas Janszoon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haslop (Hassellup), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>230 pages, maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>A NOTE OF CERTEIN WONDERFVL and most dangerous places in the Sea, which <hi>Wagenar</hi> hath set downe in his Epistle to the Prince of Orenge.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the merueilous workes, that the Almighty God hath</hi> created both vppon and in the Sea, by, and alongst all coastes: besides all other dangers whervnto the sea-faryng men are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as tempests, stormes, windes, sandes, rockes, &amp;c: there are certeine places, where the waues and flouds, do so encounter each other, and engoulph them-selues with such violence and swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that many shippes, men and goods haue been cast away er they were ware of them. The principall &amp; most perillous of all, is the <hi>Maelstreame,</hi> well or <hi>Slorp,</hi> called the <hi>Mouskstream,</hi> which lieth on the back side of <hi>Norvvay,</hi> in 68. degrees on the North-side of an Island or Rock called <hi>VVeeray.</hi> This well dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the water vnto it selfe duryng the whole floud (which is the space of sixe howers and .xij. minuts) with such an indraught and force, and with such a noyse, thorow the tombling &amp; falling of the waues and streames the one vppon the other that it is rather to wonder at then to write of. So that during that time, with in the space of more then two leagues rounde about that Rock of <hi>Mousk</hi> (vnder which that water floweth) no ship or other vessell may come neare, for they should to their vtter destruction be drawen into it &amp; swallowed vp. But all the time of the Ebbe, the water is so strongly cast vp agayne, that no kinde of substance or met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, how heauy so euer it bee, can there sincke. So that the Northren Fishers at that time do with their Iollen or fishing boates, take many and strange formed fishes, which they draw vnto their boates with hookes &amp; lines, which they haue ready layde for that purpose: for that, during the ebbe, they cannot returne into the goulphe, nor get vnder the water by any meanes.</p>
   <p>The Northren people that inhabite about those Rockes, do thinke, that that streame passeth away vnderneath a parte of <hi>Norvvay</hi> vnto the North bottom in <hi>East Finland:</hi> because in that place there is likewise such a <hi>Maelstream,</hi> though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether so strong nor daungerous: where the like fishes are taken and the water is in like sorte troublesom, as it is vnderneath and aboute the Rock of <hi>Mousk.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>VVheruppon many experimented Pilots, do call the sayd <hi>Slorp</hi> the Nauell of the sea: which causeth the course of the Ebbes and Flouds about al the lands that are on this Northside of the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> as the most conuement place for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to spreade the waters South, North, East and west, that is to say, Norther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towardes the <hi>Pole Artick:</hi> South easterly on the backside of <hi>Russia</hi> and <hi>Tartarie,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the streict of the great South-sea called <hi>Mar del Sur:</hi> wherin the Spicerie Islands called the <hi>Moluccas,</hi> neare the <hi>Equinoctiall</hi> are liyng: Southwards, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North-sea of these Lowe countries: as also on the backside of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> towards the <hi>Spanish and Atlantick seas:</hi> And towards the Northwest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde <hi>Izland</hi> towardes <hi>Furbushers streicts,</hi> where it is thought the way vnto <hi>Catay</hi> may be found.</p>
   <p>There are more ouer to be feared vpon the western seas very dangerous strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and goulphs, as is the <hi>Ras</hi> of <hi>Portland,</hi> where oft times happeneth such a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng and tombling of waues and streames, that the Ships which passe that way are many times in great perill.</p>
   <p>Moreouer the <hi>Ras</hi> of <hi>Blancquert</hi> between <hi>Normandie</hi> and the Isle of <hi>Alderney,</hi> roreth and rageth so dangerously, that many ships fal therin hedlong so deep, that sod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly they are swalowed vp and sunck vnto the very bottom.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Ras</hi> of <hi>Founteney</hi> is more daungerous then all these, wherin many smale ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels &amp; barks of <hi>Britteny</hi> &amp; of other countries are suddenly deuoured and cast away. And the entrance of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Garronne,</hi> called the Riuer of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> between the to w rs of <hi>Cordam</hi> and the Southern &amp; Northern <hi>Asses,</hi> is likewise very perilous and many ships do often perish there, if the Pilots be not skilfull &amp; well acqueinted with the place. And these be the most daungerous goulphs and streames in the northern and western seas, wherof it behoueth the seafaryng man to take speciall heede.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>