<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122050_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14292</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14783</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122050</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ben: Ionson his Volpone or The foxe</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Euer (<hi>most aequall</hi> SISTERS) had any man a wit so presently excellent, as that it could raise it selfe; but there must come both Matter, Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, Commenders, and Fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to it. If this be true, and that the Fortune of all <hi>Writers</hi> doth daily proue it, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houes the carefull to prouide, well, toward these ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents; and, hauing acquir'd them, to preserue that part of reputation most tenderly, wherein the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of a Friend is also defended. Hence is it, that I now render my selfe gratefull, and am studious to iustifie the bounty of your act: To which, though your mere authority were satisfying, yet, it being an age, wherein <hi>Poëtry</hi> and the Professors of it heare so ill, on all sides, there will a reason bee look'd for in the subiect. It is certaine, nor can it with any fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head be oppos'd) that the too-much licence of <hi>Poë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasters,</hi> in this time, hath much deform'd their <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse;</hi> that, euery day their manifold, and manifest ignorance doth stick vnnaturall reproches vpon her: But for their petulancy, it were an act of the greatest iniustice, either to let the learned suffer; or so diuine a <hi>skill</hi> (which indeed should not be attempted with vncleane hands) to fall, vnder the least contempt. For if men will impartially, and not à-squint, looke toward the offices, and function of a <hi>Poët,</hi> they will easily conclude to themselues, the impossibility of any mans being the good <hi>Poët,</hi> without first being a
<pb facs="3"/> good <hi>Man.</hi> He that is sayd to be able to informe <hi>yong-men</hi> to all good disciplines, inflame <hi>growne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to all great vertues, keepe <hi>old men</hi> in their best and supreme state, or as they decline to child-hood, recouer them to their first strength; that comes forth the Interpreter, and Arbiter of <hi>Nature,</hi> a Teacher of things diuine, no lesse then humane, a Master in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and can alóne (or with a few) effect the busines of Man-kind. This, I take him, is no subiect for <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> to exercise their railing <hi>rhetorique</hi> vpon. But, it will here be hastily answer'd, that the <hi>Writers</hi> of these dayes are other things; that, not onely their manners, but their natures are inuerted; and nothing remaining with them of the dignity of <hi>Poët,</hi> but the abused name, which euery Scribe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpes: that now, especially in <hi>Dramatick,</hi> or (as they terme it) Stage-<hi>Poëtry,</hi> nothing but Ribaldry, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation, Blasphemy, al Licence of offence to God, and Man, is practisd. I dare not deny a great part of this (and am sory, I dare not) because in some mens abortiue <hi>Features</hi> (and would they had neuer boasted the light) it is ouer-true: But, that all are embarqu'd in this bold aduenture for Hell, is a most vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thought, and, vtterd, a more malicious slander. For my particular, I can (and from a most cleare conscience) affirme that I haue euer trembled to thinke toward the least Prophanenesse; haue loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed the vse of such foule, and vn-washd Baudr'y, as is now made the foode of the <hi>Scene:</hi> And, howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I cannot escape, from some, the imputation of
<pb facs="4"/> sharpnesse, but that they wil say, I haue taken a pride, or lust to be bitter, and not my yongest Infant but hath come into the world with all his teeth; I would aske of these supercilious <hi>Politiques,</hi> what Nation, Society, or generall Order, or State I haue prouokd? what publique Person? whether I haue not (in all these) preseru'd their dignity, as mine owne person, safe? My WORKES are read, allow'd, (I speake of those that are intirely mine) looke into them, what broad reproofes haue I vsd: Where haue I bin particular? Where personall, except to a Mimick, Cheater, Baud, or Buffon, creatures (for their insolencies) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be tax'd? or to which of these so pointingly, as he might not, either ingeniously haue cōfest, or wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dissembled his disease? But it is not Rumour can make mē guilty, much lesse entitle me, to other mens crimes. I know, that nothing cā be so innocently writ, or carried, but maybe made obnoxious to cōstructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; mary, whilst I beare mine innocence about me, I feare it not. Application, is now, growne a Trade with many; and there are, that professe to haue a <hi>Key</hi> for the deciphering of euery thing, but let wise and noble Persons take heed how they bee too cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous, or giue leaue to these inuading Interpreters to be ouer-familiar with their fames, who cunningly, &amp; often, vtter their owne virulent malice, vnder o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mēs simplest meanings. As for those, that wil (by faults which charity hath rak'd vp, or cōmō honesty cōceald) make thēselues a name with the Multitude, or (to drawe their rude, and beastly clappes) care
<pb facs="4"/> not whose liuing faces they intrench with their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulant stiles; may they doe it, without a riuall, for mee: I chuse rather to liue grau'd in obscuritie, then share with them, in so preposterous a fame. Nor can I blame the wishes of those graue, and wiser <hi>Patriotes,</hi> who prouiding the hurts these licentious spirits may do in a State, desire rather to see Fooles, and Diuells, and those antique reliques of Barbaris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me retriu'd, with all other ridiculous, and exploded follies: then behold the wounds of Priuate men, of Princes, and Nations. For as HORACE, makes <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batius</hi> speake, in these
<q>—Sibi quisque timet, quanquam est intactus, &amp; odit.</q>
   </p>
   <p>And men may iustly impute such rages, if continu'd, to the <hi>Writer,</hi> as his sports. The encrease of which lust in liberty, together with the present trade of the Stage, in all their misc'line <hi>Enterludes,</hi> what lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or liberall soule doth not already abhor? where nothing but the garbage of the time is vtter'd, &amp; that with such impropriety of <hi>phrase,</hi> such plenty of <hi>soloe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cismes,</hi> such dearth of <hi>sense,</hi> so bold <hi>prolepse's,</hi> so rackt <hi>metaphor's,</hi> with brothelry able to violate the eare of a <hi>Pagan,</hi> and blasphemy, to turne the bloud of a <hi>Christian</hi> to water. I cannot but be serious in a cause of this nature, wherein my fame, &amp; the reputations of diuerse honest, &amp; learned are the question; when a NAME, so full of authority, antiquity, and all great marke, is (through their insolence) become the lowest scorne of the <hi>Age:</hi> and those MEN subiect to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulancie
<pb facs="5"/> of euery vernaculous <hi>Orator,</hi> that were wont to be the care of <hi>Kings,</hi> and happiest <hi>Monarchs.</hi> This it is that hath not onely rap't mee to present in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, but made mee studious, heretofore, and, by all my actions, to stand of, from them; which may most appeare in this my latest WORKE: (which you, <hi>most learned</hi> ARBITRESSES, haue seene, iudg'd, &amp; to my crowne, approu'd) wherein I haue labourd, for their instruction, and amendment, to reduce, not onely the ancient formes, but manners of the <hi>Scene,</hi> the easinesse, the propriety, the innocence, and last the doctrine, which is the principall end of POESY to informe men, in the best reason of liuing. And though my <hi>Catastrophe</hi> may, in the strict rigour of <hi>Comick</hi> Law, meete with censure, as turning back to my promise; I desire the learned, and charitable <hi>Critick</hi> to haue so much faith in me, to thinke it was done off industrye: For with what ease I could haue varied it, nearer his <hi>scale</hi> (but that I feare to boast my owne faculty) I could here insert. But my special aime being to put the snafle in their mouths, that crie out, we neuer punish vice in our <hi>Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes</hi> &amp;c. I tooke the more liberty; though not with out some lines of example drawne euen in the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> themselues, the goings out of whose <hi>Comoedies</hi> are not alwayes ioyfull, but oftimes, the Baudes, the Seruants, the Riualls, yea and the maisters are mulcted: and fitly, it beeing the offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick</hi>-POET to imitate iustice, and instruct to life, as well as puritie of language, or stirre vp gentle
<pb facs="5"/> affections. To which, vpon my next opportunity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the examining &amp; digesting of my <hi>notes,</hi> I shall speake more wealthily, and pay the World a debt.</p>
   <p>In the meane time (<hi>most reuerenced</hi> SISTERS) as I haue car'd to be thankefull for your affections past, and here made the vnderstanding acquainted with some groūd of your fauors; let me not dispayre their cōtinuance, to the maturing of some worthier fruits: wherein, if my MVSES bee true to me, I shall raise the dispis'd head of POETRY againe, &amp; stripping her out of those rotten and base ragges, wherewith the <hi>Times</hi> haue adulterated her forme, restore her to her primitiue habite, feature, and maiesty, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her worthy to be imbraced, and kist, of all the great and Maister <hi>Spirits</hi> of our World. As for the vile, and slothfull, who neuer affected an act, worthy of celebration, or are so inward with their owne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious natures, as they worthely feare her; and thinke it a high point of policie, to keepe her in contempt with their declamatory, and windy inuectiues: shee shall out of iust rage incite her Seruants (who are <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus iritabile</hi>) to spout inke in their faces, that shall eate, farder then their marrow, into their fames; and not CINNAMVS the Barber, with his art, shall be able to take out the brands, but they shall liue, and be read, till the Wretches die, as Things worst deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of themselues in chiefe, and then of all mankind.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my house in the Black-Friars</hi>
         <date>this 11. <hi>of February.</hi> 1607.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>