<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>SYLVESTER GIRAL∣dus Cambrensis, his second booke of the vaticinall historie of the Conquest of Ireland.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122178_Bo1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68198</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13569</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122178</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>SYLVESTER GIRAL∣dus Cambrensis, his second booke of the vaticinall historie of the Conquest of Ireland.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first and second volumes of Chronicles : comprising 1 The description and historie of England, 2 The description and historie of Ireland, 3 The description and historie of Scotland: first collected and published by Raphaell Holinshed, William Harrison, and others: now newlie augmented and continued (with manifold matters of singular note and worthie memorie) to the yeare 1586. by Iohn Hooker aliàs Vowell Gent. and others. With conuenient tables at the end of these volumes</title>
                 <author>Holinshed, Raphael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison (Harison), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, Luke (Lucas).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3 volumes (volumes 1, 10, 250, 4, 202, 2 pages, volumes 2, 61, 13, 183, 1, 421, 424-430, 436-438, 431-433, 439-445, 450-464, 56 pages, volumes 3, 8, 1080, 1080-1327, 2, 1332-1371, 1371-1421, 1490-1491, 1536-1555, 1574-1592, 62 pages), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="32" facs="101"/>
   <head>SYLVESTER GIRAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Cambrensis, his second booke of the vaticinall historie of <hi>the Conquest of Ireland.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">The Proheme of the author.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue thus farre continued our historie, in as perfect and full order as we could, hauing omitted nothing worthie the memorie, as farre as the matter seemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: but being occupied and busied with the generall and necessarie causes in religion, although we had not sufficient leasure and time to follow and prosecute this our enterprise and matter begun, yet did not we thinke it meet to giue the same ouer, and to leaue it helfe! vndoone. We haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and yet doo continue the historie but breefelie, not in anie high or eloquent stile; but in a common phrase and plaine speeches, giuing rather thereby an occasion to our posteritie for them to set foorth this historie, than to doo it our selues. For indeed our leasure is verie small, and such as it is, it is turned to troubles and vnquietnesse, our loue and zeale into hatred, our ioy into sorrow, and our rest to molestations.</p>
   <p>For now flourish not the honest exercises of studies, but the busie policies of warres: now the good studies of the mind are contemned, and the lusts of the bodie imbraced: now we haue no leasure to serue the Muses, but to be hammering with weapons: quiet minds are not now at leasure, but glistering weapons and armors are in euerie mans hands. Wherefore let not the reader looke now at our hands for anie good order, elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, or pleasantnesse in this our writing: for place must be giuen of necessitie vnto time. And as the same is now verie troublesome, so can the same bring foorth but trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some matters. In these troubled times, and wanting conuenient leasure and quietnesse, I haue trauelled with the more paines to absolue and end this my worke: not after the maner of a student, but as a traueller; whose nature and condition is, that when he dooth set foorth on his iournie verie slacklie and slowlie, then dooth he make the more hast, and trauell the more speedilie. How soeuer it shall please God to deale with vs in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices now in hand, I haue as diligentlie as I can compiled this my historie as also my topographie, leauing the same as a monument of our will, to remaine to our countrie and posteritie for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>