<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122230_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01336</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11459</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122230</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver of a trve Christian to the provde challenge of a counterfet Catholike : By VVilliam Fulke Doctor in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Fulke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 110 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS short trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) hath lyen by me neare hand or altogether tenne yeres space, vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at the request of a godly &amp; learned friend of myne, in aunsvver to a proud challenge of a Papist against the Protestant. VVhich though at the first and many yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I determined not to publish, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the same challēge to haue ben priuate, or in fevve mens handes: yet novv of late that I haue seene it in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse godly gentlemens handes, to
<pb facs="3"/>vvhom it hath bene deliuered by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes, belike to peruert them, and of vvhom also I haue bene desired to aū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svver it, and am further credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the same is in print, &amp; estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of many ignorant Papistes, to be so vnansvverable, that although it hath bin protested, by gentlemen of great vvorship, and credit, that they haue seene the aūsvvere therof in vvriting, yet they vvil not beleue, that any man dare set his penne to the paper, once to attempte the matter: I haue novve thought good to put it in print, as it vvas vvrittē at the first. Nothing dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, by Gods help, but I shall be able to stand to the defence, if the Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vvill proceede to mainteyne his challenge any longer. And vvhereas the same of late hath bene ioyned vvith my confutation of the doctrine
<pb facs="3"/>of purgatory, and yet is desired of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be set forth in seuerall, because the argument is more generall, it is thought good to satisfie their desire, &amp; to spare their exspenses, that being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued in the matter of purgatory, doe yet stagger in the challenge of the Church. The breuity that I haue vsed (as I vnderstand) is misliked of some men, vvhich vvoulde haue vvished a larger discourse, but seeing the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenger requireth shortnes, if this that is vsed be sufficient to satisfie his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds or any of them, a longer trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise vvere but superfluous. If he thinke him selfe not throughly aunsvvered, (&amp; declare the same) in all or in part, that vvhich is novve omitted shall then God vvilling be supplied. In the meane time vse this (gentle Reader) and fare vvell in the Lorde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>