<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE LIFE OF LVCIVS
Apuleius, briefly expressed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122394_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">718</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE LIFE OF LVCIVS
Apuleius, briefly expressed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The. xi. bookes of the Golden asse : conteininge the Metamorphosie of Lucius Apuleius, enterlaced with sondrie pleasaunt and delectable tales, with an excellent narration of the mariage of Cupide and Psiches, set out in the. iiii. v. and vj. bookes. Translated out of Latine into Englishe by VVilliam Adlington</title>
                 <author>Apuleius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 126, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE LIFE OF LVCIVS
Apuleius, briefly expressed.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Vcius Apuleius African, an excellent
folower of Plato his sect, borne in
Maudara, a countrey sometime inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
by the Romaines, and vnder the
iurisdiction of Syphar, situate, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng
vpon the borders of Numidia &amp;
Getulia, whereby he calleth him selfe, halfe a Numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,
and halfe a Getulian: And Sidonius named him
the Platonian Madaurēce: his father called Theseus,
had passed all offices of dignitie in his countrey, with
much honour: his mother named Saluia, was of such
excellent vertue, that she passed all the dames of her
time, borne of an auncient house, &amp; descended from the
noble Philosopher Plutarche, &amp; Sextus his Nephew.
His wife called Pudētila was endowed with as much
vertue and richesse as any woman might be. He him
selfe was of high &amp; comely stature, gray eied, his heare
yellow, &amp; a beawtifull personage: he florished in Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage
in the time of Iolianus Auitus, and Claudius
Maximus procōsules, where he spent his youth in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the liberall sciences, and much profited vnder his
maisters there, whereby not without cause, he glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously
calleth him selfe, the nourice of Carthage, &amp; the
Clestial Muse and venerable mistres of Affrick, sone
after at Athenes (wheare in times past the well of all
doctrine flourished) he tasted many of the cuppes of the
Muses, he learned Poetry, Geometry, Musike, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke,
and the vniuersall knowledge of Philosophie,
and studied not in vaine the nine Muses, that is to say,
the nine noble &amp; roiall disciplines. Immediatly after
<pb facs="7"/>
he went to Rome, &amp; studied there the Latine tongue,
with such labour and continuall studie, that he atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
to great eloquēce, and was knowen and approued
to be excellently learned, whereby he might woorthily
be called <hi>Polyhistor,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> is to say, one that knoweth much
or many thinges. And beinge thus no lesse endewed
with eloquēce, than with singular learning, he wrote
many bookes for them that should come after: Wherof
parte by negligence of times be intercepted, and parte
now extant, doo sufficiently declare with how muche
wisedome and doctrine he florished, &amp; with how much
vertue he excelled emongst the rude and barbarous
people. The like was Anacharsis emōgst the most lus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kishe
Scythes: but emongst the bookes of Lucius Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius
which are perished &amp; preuented, howbeit greatly
desired of vs now a daies, was one entituled Banke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
questions, an other entreatinge of the nature of
Fishe, an other of the generation Beastes, an other
conteininge his Epigrāmes, and an other called Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magoras:
but suche as are now extant, are the fower
bookes named <hi>Floridorum,</hi> wherein is conteined a flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishinge
stile, and a sauery kinde of learninge, whiche
delighteth, holdeth, and reioyseth the Reader merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously,
wherein you shall finde a great varietie of
thinges, as leapinge one from an other: One excellent
and copious oration conteininge all the grace and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
of the art Oratorie, whereby he cléereth him selfe
of the crime of art Magicke, which was sclaunderously
obiected against him by his enuious aduersaries, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
is conteined such force of eloquence and doctrine, as
he séemeth to passe and excell him selfe. There is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
booke of the God or spirit of Socrates, whereof
S. Augustine maketh often mētion in his booke of the
<pb facs="7"/>
definition of Spirites and description of men, twoo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
bookes of the opinion of Plato, wherein is briefly
conteined that which before was largely expressed: one
booke of Cosmographie, comprisinge many thinges of
Aristoteles Meteors: the Dialogue of Trismegistus,
translated by him out of Gréeke into Latine, so fine,
that it rather séemeth with more eloquence turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Latine, then it was before writen in Greke: but
principaly, these eleuen bookes of the Golden Asse, are
enriched with such pleasaunt matter, with such excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie
and variety of florishinge Tales, that nothing
may be more swéete and delectable, whereby woorthely
they may be intituled: The bookes of the Golden
Asse, for the passinge stile &amp; matter therein. For what
can be more acceptable than this Asse of Gold in déede:
How be it there be many whiche would rather Intitle
it Metamorphosis, that is to say, a transfiguration or
transformation, by reason of the Argument and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
therein.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>