<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122025_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15127</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25427</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a certen libel intituled, An admonition to the Parliament, by Iohn VVhitgifte, D. of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Whitgift, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 246, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant to what dangers (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of vncharitable &amp; slanderous tongs) I haue made my selfe subiecte by taking vpon me this worke: notwithstanding my reaconing is made, and I have armed my selfe against the worst, being taught so to do by the opprobrious speach of diuers, who as busy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies intermedling in other mens matters more than it becommeth them, do therof iudge most vnchristianly, and reporte most vntruly: beleuing as partial Iudges, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is reported, howsoeuer falsely and vniustly. But as I with all my harte for my parte forgiue them, and wish vnto them more Christian hartes, indifferent eares, and charitable mouthes. So do I exhorte thée (Christian reader) to abstaine from all suche rancor, and other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and sinister affections in reading of this my booke: And thinke of me as of one that to speake the truth, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie his conscience, to mainteyne the peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Churche, to withstande erronious opinions, or contentious doctrine, will neither spare his laboure nor his fame: and yet not so stiffely addicted to his owne opinion, but that he can be contented to submitte hym selfe to better authoritie and reasons than he him selfe hath. And I besée thée receyue this admonition at my hande: Trie before thou trust: beleue not lightly euery reporte: as thou hast two eares, so vse them both: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne no mā before he be heard: abstaine from speaking euill of any whē he is not present to make thée answere, (for that is a great iniurie:) respect not the person, but the cause, and let not euery pretenced zeale carrie thée head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thou knowest not whether: and suspende thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this booke, vntill thou hast aduisedly and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently redde the same.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>