<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OF THE TRVTH OF Christian Religion.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122528_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02267</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12400</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122528</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OF THE TRVTH OF Christian Religion.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>True religion explained, and defended against the archenemies thereof in these times : In six bookes. Written in Latine by Hugo Grotius, and now done in English for the common good</title>
                 <author>Grotius, Hugo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 350, 2 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="10"/>
   <head>OF THE TRVTH OF Christian Religion.</head>
   <head>The Preface, shewing the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of this worke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have eftsoones <note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the worke.</note> beene deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a man, that hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent well of his Country, and of learning, and of me also, what the argument of those bookes was, which were written by mee in my Countrey language, in the behalfe of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="2" facs="11"/>
Religion:</hi> Neither doe I wonder that hee should make such a question: For hee that with so good judgement did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himselfe to the reading of all things worthy to bee read, was not ignorant with what skill that matter hath beene handled by <hi>Raymond Sebund,</hi> after a subtile Philosophicall manner; by <hi>Iudovicus Ʋives,</hi> in divers Dialogues; but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with most learning and eloquence, by their famous <hi>Mornay.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating</hi> of them into the vulgar tongue, was more for use, than for <hi>making</hi> any new worke: Whereof, what other men will judge, I know not, but this I am perswaded will satisfie him, if I tell him, how that reading, not onely those Authors above men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioned; but also the writings of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for their old <hi>Iewish,</hi> and also of <hi>Christians,</hi> for our
<pb n="3" facs="11"/>
      <hi>Christian Religion;</hi> I thought good withall to use my owne judgement, (such as it is) and give some f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eedome to my minde, which my body wanted when I writ that worke. For it seemed to mee most sitting to contend for the <hi>truth</hi> only with <hi>truth,</hi> and that also with such <hi>truth,</hi> as whereof I was perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fully in my owne minde. For I know it were but a vanity in mee to goe about to teach others to credit those things that I could not bee perswaded of my selfe: Therefore omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such arguments as in my judgement were of lesse impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as also the authority of those bookes which either I cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knew, or justly suspected to be forged and counterfeit, I have made choice of such rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons both out of ancient &amp; later writings, as may bee best ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of. And as for those
<pb n="4" facs="12"/>
which pleased me best, the same I did both methodically di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spose, and also expounded as plainly as I could, distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing them by certaine verses, whereby they might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter committed to memory.</p>
   <p>For my purpose was to bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit all my <hi>Countrey-men,</hi> but specially <hi>Sea-faring-men,</hi> that they might not (as too many doe) lose and mispend their time. Wherefore beginning with the commendation of our <hi>Countrey,</hi> which for skill and diligence in <hi>Navigation</hi> excels the iest, I exhorted them to use that art, not onely for their owne proper gaine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, but also for the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of true <hi>Christian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For neither is there wanting <hi>matter</hi> for such their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, since that they might try their fortunes abroad in farre distant-forren <hi>Countries,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="12"/>
make incursions either upon the <hi>Pagans,</hi> such as live in <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Guinea;</hi> or upon the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetans,</hi> as those under the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the <hi>Turke,</hi> the <hi>Persian,</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians;</hi> or lastly, upon the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and such as at this day are professed enemies of <hi>Christianity,</hi> which are disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thorow the most parts of the world. Neither are there wanting such <hi>wicked men,</hi> as doe (secretly for feare) harbour the poyson of errour, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish the same unto the weaker sort, when they see fit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. Against which <hi>evils</hi> my desire is we may be well fortified with <hi>truth;</hi> And that such as are furnished with learning, would endevour according to their ability to confute <hi>errours:</hi> and in the meane while let others beware that they be not surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by those that are enemies of the <hi>truth.</hi> For which end, that
<pb n="6" facs="13"/>
I may make it appeare how that <hi>Religion</hi> is no vaine frivolous thing; in my first booke I doe beginne at the ground or foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation thereof, which is, <hi>That there is a God:</hi> This <hi>truth</hi> I thus proceed to prove, as followeth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>