<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my Lord Vieillart, Councellor to the King, Treasurer of France, and Ge∣nerall of the Reuennues belon∣ging to Soissons.</title>
           <author>Gaultier, Iacques</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122512_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01565</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11691a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122512</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my Lord Vieillart, Councellor to the King, Treasurer of France, and Ge∣nerall of the Reuennues belon∣ging to Soissons.</title>
                 <author>Gaultier, Iacques</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rodomontados. Or, Brauadoes and bragardismes. Collected out of the commentaries of the most dreadfull, terrible, and inuincible capitaine; Mattamores, Crocodillo, Raiabroquelos</title>
                 <author>Gaultier, Jacques</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To my Lord</hi> Vieillart, <hi>Councellor to</hi> the King, Treasurer of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Reuennues belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> to Soissons.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Stood a long while in doubt, whether I should deliuer to publick view or no, this slender impression, and vnder your fauor: because the matter appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to me too small, in regarde of your great merit. But when I considered, that generous mindes doe alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue with gratefull acceptance, whatsoeuer is offered them in honest affection; I was excited to proceed on boldly. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I present vnto your honour (with such respect as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth mee) these pleasant <hi>Castillian Rodomontados,</hi> or brauing boastes of an humorous <hi>Spaniard:</hi> wherein you you shall finde nothing else, but some harmelesse iests &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, without iniury or wrong to any one offered. Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally not vnto <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whose name is no otherwise heere vsed or borrowed, then was that bragging Souldiour <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so</hi> by <hi>Terence:</hi> vnder which might be vnderstood, an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishman, Scottishman, Frenchman,</hi> or some man of any
<pb facs="3"/>
other Nation. And indeed I am verily perswaded, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men in reading this Book, and falling into laughter: may happen to laugh and smile at themselues, because they may chance to finde their owne follies recorded, vnder the fable alluded to another.</p>
   <p>Well do I know, my Lord, that you are no such censurer as <hi>Cato,</hi> nor yes so seuere as <hi>Aristarchus,</hi> but after you haue employed your spirites in great and graue affayres; you may finde some content in reading this trifle, as a pleasing relaxation from former perturbances, as my selfe haue often made the like vse of them.</p>
   <p>If the Bow stand alwaies bent, it wil at length become too slacke, and fit for no seruice when it is needed. After stormes and Tempests, the heauens do affoord vs faire weather; and such as are stockt in Prison, or chained to the Oare in a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, will sometimes consolate their afflictions, by the helpe of Songs, or pleasant discourses.</p>
   <p>These Iests and Braggadochio mirthes, may serue in the like Nature to such men, who, after they haue trauailed and spent their spirits in great and serious matters; desire some other honest and sportiue recreation. And if I may perceiue, that your wonted sweet and gentle inclination, shall receiue this my poor vnworthy guift (which I offer you with my most humble seruice) with good lookes, and kinde acceptance; It wil excite me to more painefull labour heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and to remaine for euer</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most humble Seruant,
<hi>Iacques Gaultier.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>