<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honorable, and
Mightie Lorde, Thomas, Earle
of Sussex, Viscont Fitz∣waltre,
Lorde of Egremont
and of Burnell, Knight of the
most noble Order of
the Garter,
Iustice of the Forestes and Chases,
from Trente sowthwarde, and Capi∣taine
of the Gentlemen Pen∣tioners,
of the house of
the Queene out So∣ueraigne
Lady.</title>
           <author>Adlington, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122394_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">718</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honorable, and
Mightie Lorde, Thomas, Earle
of Sussex, Viscont Fitz∣waltre,
Lorde of Egremont
and of Burnell, Knight of the
most noble Order of
the Garter,
Iustice of the Forestes and Chases,
from Trente sowthwarde, and Capi∣taine
of the Gentlemen Pen∣tioners,
of the house of
the Queene out So∣ueraigne
Lady.</title>
                 <author>Adlington, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The. xi. bookes of the Golden asse : conteininge the Metamorphosie of Lucius Apuleius, enterlaced with sondrie pleasaunt and delectable tales, with an excellent narration of the mariage of Cupide and Psiches, set out in the. iiii. v. and vj. bookes. Translated out of Latine into Englishe by VVilliam Adlington</title>
                 <author>Apuleius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 126, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honorable, and
Mightie Lorde, Thomas, Earle
of Sussex, Viscont Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waltre,
Lorde of Egremont
and of Burnell, Knight of the
most noble Order of
the Garter,
Iustice of the Forestes and Chases,
from Trente sowthwarde, and Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
of the Gentlemen Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners,
of the house of
the Queene out So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne
Lady.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
vpon me (right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)
in manner of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned
and foolish poet <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillus,</hi>
(who rashly, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduisedly,
wrote a bigge vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume
in verses of the gestes
and valiant prowesse of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander
the great) to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
this present booke, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyninge
the Metamorphosy of <hi>Lucius Apuleius:</hi> beynge
moued therunto by the right pleasant pastime, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable
matter therein: I eftsones consulted with my
selfe, to whome I might best offer so pleasant and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
a woorke, deuised by the Author, it beyng now bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barously
and simply framed in our Englishe tongue.
<pb facs="3"/>
And after longe deliberatiō had, your Honorable Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe
came to my remembrance, a man muche more
woorthy then to whome so homely and rude a transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
should be presented. But when I againe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
the iestinge and sportfull matter of the booke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte
to be offred to any man of grauitie and wisedome,
I was wholly determined to make no Epistle dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
at all: till as now of late, perswaded thereunto by
my fréendes, I haue boldly enterprised to offer the
same to your Lordshippe, who as I trust will with no
lesse good will accept the same, then if it did entreate of
some serious &amp; loftie matter, consideryng that although
the matter therein séeme very light, and mery, yet the
effect thereof tendeth to a good and vertuous morall, as
in the followynge Epistle to the Reader may be cléerly
perceaued. For so hath all wryters in times paste em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
their trauell and labours, that their posteritie
might receaue some fruictfull profite by the same. And
therefore the <hi>Poetes</hi> feigned not their fables in vaine,
consideringe that children in time of their first studies,
are muche allured thereby to procéede to more graue
and déepe disciplines, whereas otherwise their mindes
would quickly lothe the wise and prudent woorkes of
learned men, wherein in suche vnripe yéeres they take
no sparke of delectation at all. And not onely that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
arriseth to children by suche feigned fables, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
the vertues of men are couertly thereby commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
and their vices discommended and abhorred. For
by the fable of <hi>Actaeon,</hi> where it is feigned, that when he
sawe <hi>Diana</hi> washinge her selfe in a well, he was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly
<pb facs="3"/>
turned into a <hi>Hart</hi> and so was slayne of his owne
<hi>Dogges:</hi> may be ment that when a man casteth his eies,
on the vaine and soone vadynge beautie of the worlde,
consentinge thereto in his minde, he seemeth to be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
into a brute beast, and so to be slayne thorough the
inordinate desire of his owne affectes. By <hi>Tantalus</hi>
that standeth in the middest of the floode <hi>Eridan</hi> hauynge
before him a tree laden with pleasant apples, he beyng
neuerthelesse alwaies thursty and hungry, betokeneth
the insatiable desire of couetous persons. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
of <hi>Atreus, Thiestes, Tereus</hi> and <hi>Progne</hi> signifieth the
wicked and abhominable factes wrought and attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by mortall men. The fall of <hi>Icarus</hi> is an example to
proude and arrogant persons that weeneth to clymbe
vp to the Heauens. By <hi>Mydas,</hi> who obteined of <hi>Bacchus</hi>
that all thinges whiche he touched mought be Golde,
is carped the foule sinne of auarice. By <hi>Phaeton,</hi> that
vnskilfully toke in hande to rule the <hi>Charriot</hi> of the
Sunne, are represented those persons whiche attempt
thinges passinge their power and capacitie. By <hi>Castor</hi>
and <hi>Pollux,</hi> turned into a signe in Heauen called <hi>Gemini,</hi>
is signified, that vertuous and godly persons shalbe
rewarded after life with perpetuall blisse. And in this
fable or feigned ieste of <hi>Lucius Apuleius</hi> is comprehended
a figure of mans life, ministringe moste swéete and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable
matter, to such as shalbe desirous to Reade the
same. The whiche if your Honorable Lordshippe shal
accept and take in good parte, I shall not onely thinke
my small trauell and labour well employed, but also
receaue a farther comforte to attempt some more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="4"/>
matter whiche may be more acceptable to your
Lordshippe: desiring the same, to excuse my rashe and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olde enterprise, at this time, as I nothinge doubte in
your Lordshippes goodnesse. To whome I beséeche Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
God to imparte longe lyfe with increase of
much Honour.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Vniuersitie Colledge in Oxforde
<date>the .xviij. of September. 1566.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honors most bounden William Adlington.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>