<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Musicall Murmurers, This Greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122017_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04616</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14735</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Musicall Murmurers, This Greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A musicall dreame. Or The fourth booke of ayres : the first part is for the lute, two voyces, and the viole de gambo; the second part is for the lute, the viole and foure voices to sing: the third part is for one voyce alone, or to the lute, the basse viole, or to both if you please, vvhereof, two are Italian ayres. Composed by Robert Iones</title>
                 <author>Jones, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Waterson, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To all Musicall Murmurers, This Greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou, whose eare itches with the varietie of opinion, hearing thine owne sound, as the Ecchoe reuerberating others substance, and vnprofitable in it selfe, shewes to the World comfortable noyse, though to thy owne vse little pleasure, by reason of vncharitable censure. I speake to thee musicall <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> thou from whose nicetie, numbers as easily passe, as drops fall in the showre, but with lesse profite. I compare thee to the hie way dust that flies into mens eyes, and will not thence without much trouble, for thou in thy dispersed iudgement, not onely art of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensiue to seeing knowledge, but most faulty false to deseruing industry, picking moates out of the most pure Bisse, and smoothing the plainest veluet, when onely thine owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is more wrinckled and more vitious in it selfe, then grosser soyle, so that as a brush in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with filth, thou rather soylest then makest perfect any way. I haue stood at thine elbow, and heard thee prophane euen Musickes best Note, and with thy vntunde rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Sol Fade most ignobly. I am assured, and I care not greatly, that thou wilt lay to my charge, my whilome vow, Neuer againe, because I promised as much: but vnderstand me thou vns kilfull descanter, deriue from that Note of Plaine Song charitable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and thou shalt find harsh voices are often a Note aboue Ela reduced by truer iudgement, which I bereaue thee of, knowing thy Rules, are as our new come Lutes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many stringes, not easily vsed, vnlesse in aduenture, till practise put forward into deseruing Diuision. This my aduenture is no deed but a dreame, and what are dreames, but airie possessions, and seuerall ayres, breathing harmonious whisperings, though to thee discord, yet to others indifferent, I will not say excellent, because it is an others office not mine, but let them be as they are, others profites and my paines, set forth for pleasure, not for purposed poyson to infect imagination, no, but as a showre falling in a needfull season, so I flatter my selfe at least, and will say so euer by any other, whose labour shall vplift Musicall meditation, the onely wing of true courage, being the most pleasing voice of man, whose sweetenes reacheth vnto heauen it selfe. It is hard if al this paines reape not good commendations, and it is water wrung out of a Flint in thee, sith thou neuer thinkst well of any, and wert in thy selfe so vnskilfull euer, as thy Tutor from the first howre could neuer make thee sing in Tune; be as thou art a lumpe of deformity without fashion, bredde in the bowels of disdaine, and brought forth by bewitcht <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaera,</hi> the fatall Widwife to all true merite.</p>
   <p>Giue me leaue to depart, or if not, without it I am gone, carelesse of thy censuring, and fully perswaded thou canst not thinke well, and therefore art curst in thy Cradle, neuer to be but cruell, and being borne with teeth in thy head, bitst euery one harmeles in this or what else honest industry, makes thy earegossip too.</p>
   <closer>Farewell if thou wilt in kindnesse, or hold thy selfe from further carping.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>