<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>R., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122506_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10725</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21005</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122506</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves from Virginia : The lost flocke triumphant. With the happy arriuall of that famous and worthy knight Sr. Thomas Gates: and the well reputed &amp; valiant captaine Mr. Christopher Newporte, and others, into England. With the maner of their distresse in the Iland of Deuils (otherwise called Bermoothawes) where they remayned 42. weekes, &amp; builded two pynaces, in which they returned into Virginia. By R. Rich, Gent. one of the voyage</title>
                 <author>Rich, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>how to stile thee I knowe not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps Learned, perhaps vnlearned: happily cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, happily enuious: indeed what or how to tearme thee I know not, only as I began I will proceede.</p>
   <p>Reader, thou dost peraduenture imagine that I am mercenarie in this busines, and write for money (as your moderne Poets vse) hyred by some of those euer to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Aduenturers, to flatter rhe world: No, I disclaime it, I haue knowne the Voyage, past the danger, seene that honorable work of Virginia, &amp; I thanke God am arriud here to tell thee what I haue seene, don, &amp; past: if thou wilt be lieue me so, if not so to: for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not force thee but to thy owne liking: I am a Soldier, blunt and plaine, and so is the
<pb facs="4"/>
phrase of my newes: and I protest it is true. If thou aske why I put it in Verse? I prethee knowe, it was onely to feede mine owne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: I must confesse, that had I not debard my selfe of that large scope which to the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of prose is allowed, I should haue much easd my selfe, and giuen thee better content. But I intreat thee to take this as it is; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many daies expire, I will promise thee the same worke more at large.</p>
   <p>I did feare preuention by some of your writers, if they should haue gotten but some part of the newes by the tayle, and therefore though it be rude, let it passe with thy liking, and in so doing I shall like well of thee: but how euer, I haue not long to stay: if thou wilt be vnnaturall to thy country-man, thou maist, I must not loose my patrymonie; I am for <hi>Virginia</hi> againe, and so I will bid thee hartily farewell, with an honest verse:</p>
   <q>
      <l>As I came hether to see my natiue land,</l>
      <l>to waft me backe lend me thy gentle hand.</l>
   </q>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy louing Country-man. R R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>