<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian reader, mercie and peace in Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1222_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18162</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4800.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1222</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian reader, mercie and peace in Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Catechisme in meter : for the easier learnyng, and better remembryng of those prinples [sic] of our faithe, whiche wee ought moste familiarly to be acquainted withall / for the proofe of those thynges, which I have not quoted, I referre you to the vsuall catechisme ; onely in the margent I haue quoted those thynges which I haue added for plainnesse ; the verse will agree with moste of the tunes of the Psalmes of David, and it is deuided into partes, that eche parte maie be song by it self</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Griffith (Gryffyth), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Walley (Waley), Robert</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>23 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian reader, mercie and peace in Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E, that considereth the dulle vntowardnesse of our nature in learnyng of heauenly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the tediousnesse that easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creepeth vpon vs, the scorne that many haue to teache, and others to bee taught by their Pastors and Maisters, the difficultie and infinite trauaile in teachyng, and the small encrease of continuall labor with thē, besides the diligence of the aduersaries, in blastyng abroade their poison, and how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily therefore the people of God are to be foreseasoned and confirmed with the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoison of truthe against them, shall ease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue this to bee no idle or vaine Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, but a needefull and Christian pollicie. This is more then inough to the godly wise: He that giueth encrease to the Planter and Waterer, giue a blessyng here vnto, that it maie spread it self to his glory, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of his kingdome. This Newyeres daie. <hi>1583.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ. T.R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>