<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>P., John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122303_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09537</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19817</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122303</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>P., John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great cicle of Easter : containing a short rule. To knowe vppon what day of the month Easter day will fall, made for the vse of such as would without their booke readily find out, and declare as well Easter day, as the other moueable feastes in the yeere: the domincall [sic] letter, the epact the age of the moone, her shining and the course of the tide. With other necessarie tables to learne out the course of the yeere, by Io, P. 1583 [...] Set foorth according to the Queenes iniunctiones</title>
                 <author>Pett, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue beene reques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> (gentle Reader) long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe to put in Printe this short rule, for the ease of them, that would bee cunning to knowe the chaungeable course of the moueable feastes in the yeere. But being partly hindred by my affaires in the world, and partly discouraged as wel through the simplenes of the worke as also least I should seeme to take from other men y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prayse due to their worke, by intermedling their labour with my small skill. I haue hetherto slacked my hand, from that which willinglye I would haue performed, vntill now at the last beeing ouercome with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion and request of some, that thinke it a thing needefull as well for the ease of them, that alwaies in their affaires neede the vse of a kalender, as also for the quickning of the memorye of such young Schollers, as would readily, speake of the changeablenes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeeres
<pb facs="4"/>
by the altering of Easter day and other festiuall dayes frō one day of the month to an other, I haue put it foorth, not min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to preiudice the worke of any man, who haue heretofore published such ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as hereto are annexed, nor yet to offend their mindes.</p>
   <p>Therefore I would request thee (good Reader) to haue pacience and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to iudge of my trauell herein, taken in hand for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> benefit of such as shall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy some small time and labour to learne these fewe verses &amp; rules with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the booke, whom and whose labour I commend in my prayer to the blessing of God, who turne all our endeuours to his glory. <hi>Seuenock</hi> this.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, Io. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>