<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HER,
VVHOSE TRVE
LOVE TO VERTVE
HATH HIGHLY ENNOBLED
HERSELFE, RENOVVNED HER SEXE,
Honoured her House:
The Right Honourable, the Lady
ARBELLA WENTVVORTH;
The accomplishment of her
Divinest wishes.</title>
           <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122488_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3565</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HER,
VVHOSE TRVE
LOVE TO VERTVE
HATH HIGHLY ENNOBLED
HERSELFE, RENOVVNED HER SEXE,
Honoured her House:
The Right Honourable, the Lady
ARBELLA WENTVVORTH;
The accomplishment of her
Divinest wishes.</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English gentlevvoman, drawne out to the full body : expressing, what habilliments doe best attire her, what ornaments doe best adorne her, what complements doe best accomplish her. By Richard Brathvvait Esq</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 221, that is 229, 3 pages, folded leaf, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HER,
VVHOSE TRVE
LOVE TO VERTVE
HATH HIGHLY ENNOBLED
HERSELFE, RENOVVNED HER SEXE,
Honoured her House:
The Right Honourable, the Lady
ARBELLA WENTVVORTH;
The accomplishment of her
Divinest wishes.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome moneths are
past, since I made
bold to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
to my Right
Honorable LORD
your Husband, an
<hi>ENGLISH
GENTLEMAN;</hi>
whom hee was
pleased, forth of
his Noble disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
to receive into his Protection. Into whose
most Honourable service hee was no sooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained,
<pb facs="3"/>
and upon due observance of his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie
approved; then upon approvement of
his more piercive judgement, he became gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
received. Out of these respects, my most
Honourable Lady, I became so encouraged, as
I have presumed to preferre unto your service
an <hi>ENGLISH GENTLEWOMAN,</hi>
one of the same Countrey and Family, a deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
sister of so <hi>generous</hi> a brother: Or (if you
will) a pleasing Spouse to so <hi>gracious</hi> a Lover.
Whom, if your Honour shall be but pleased to
entertaine, (and your noble Candor is such, as
she can expect nothing lesse) you shall finde
excellently graced with sundry singular quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
beautified with many choice endowments▪
and so richly adorned with divers exquisite
ornaments, as her attendance shall be no dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
to your Honour, nor no touch <hi>to your</hi>
unblemish'd <hi>Selfe,</hi> to retaine her in your favour.
Sure I am, the sweetnesse of her temper, sorts
and sutes well with the quality or disposition
of your Honour: For shee Loves without any
painted pretences to bee really vertuous, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
popular applause to be affably gracious,
without any glorious glosse to bee sincerely
zealous. Her Education hath so enabled her,
as shee can converse with you of all places, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
her judgement conceivingly of most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
and discourse most delightfully of all
fashions. Shee hath beene so well Schooled in
the Discipline of this <hi>Age,</hi> as shee onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires
<pb facs="3"/>
to retaine in memory that <hi>forme</hi> which is
least affected but most comely; to consort with
such as may improve her <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>practise</hi>
of goodnesse by their company; to entertaine
those for reall and individuate friends, who
make actions of pietie expressivest characters
of theyr amity. Diligent you shall ever finde
her in her imployments, serious in her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
temporate in her Discourse, discreet in
her answers. Shee bestowes farre more time in
eying the glasse of her life to rectifie her errors,
if there bee any, then the glasse of her face in
wiping of such outward staines as might ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish
her beautie. Neyther in preserving that,
is shee altogether so remisse, as not to retaine
that seemely grace in her feature, as may put
her in remembrance of the unexpressive beauty
and bounty of her Maker. Neate she goes usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
in her attire, which she puts on with more
<hi>care</hi> then <hi>cost.</hi> And to these shee addes such a
well-seeming grace, as she bestowes more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
on them, then shee receives from them.
Phantasticke habits or forraine fashions are so
farre from taking her, as with a sleight but
sweet contempt they are disvalued by her. She
wonders how a wise state should employ so
much time in inventing varietie of disguises to
disfigure theyr <hi>Shape.</hi> This makes her desire
rather to bee out of request with time, then
with a civill and well-composed mind; whose
honour it is to bee prized more by her owne
<pb facs="4"/>
internall worth, then any outward weare.
Constant shee is in her <hi>behaviour;</hi> wherein she
<hi>affects</hi> little, but <hi>observes</hi> much. With a bash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
admiration she smiles at these civilized si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pring
Dames, whose onely glory it is to affect
a kind of reserved state; which, as they hold,
consists principally in a minc'd speech, set
looke, or ginger pace. Shee loves alwayes to
bee her selfe, nor to entertaine ought which
may estrange her from her selfe. So as, there is
nothing in the whole posture of her <hi>Behaviour,</hi>
but with a native gracefull propriety doth infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
become her. Take upon her to instruct
others, shee will not, such is her Humilitie; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit,
every moving posture which comes from
her, may be a line of direction unto others to
follow her. <hi>Complement</hi> shee affects not, as the
world takes it. The word in his owne native
and unborrowed signification is good, and in
that sence she admits it; but to be restrained to
an inforced formality, shee cannot relish it.
Whence it is, that she preferres the incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Liberty of her mind, before the mutable
formality of a Deluded age. Shee desires to be
<hi>Compleat</hi> in the exercise of goodnesse; to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
her Honour not by titles but a lovely
and lively proficience, graced with a continuate
practise in all vertues. She cannot indure this
later introduc'd kind of Complement, which
consists in Cringies, Congies, or supple salutes.
A cheerefull modesty is her best <hi>Complement,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
which shee ever weares about her as her chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
ornament. <hi>Decency,</hi> shee affects in her
<hi>Cloathes,</hi> affability in her Discourse; shee hath
made a covenant with her eyes never to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
nor intentively to bestow themselves on
any other object than the glory of her Maker.
A proper personage is no such attractive mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
to her eye, to make her loose her selfe.
Whatsoever shee undertakes beseemes her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
shee affects naught but what naturally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
her. Her beauty is her owne; and
whatsoever else may better accomplish her.
Her pathes are evenly vertuous; her desires
truely religious; Piety is her practise; which
shee expresseth so fully in every action; as the
whole course of her well-disposed life is not so
much as justly conscious of the least aspersion.
So highly shee values her <hi>Estimation,</hi> as she will
not engage it to suspition. Promises cannot
tempt her, nor hope of advancement taint her.
She wonders one should preferre a conceit of
being <hi>great</hi> before a desire of appearing <hi>good.</hi>
Protesting Lovers she holds for no better then
deceiving Lures. Bee their vowes of <hi>seruice</hi>
never so incessant, their assaults never so vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;
her resolves have vow'd her constant.
Hope of <hi>Profit</hi> cannot surprize her, nor
thought of <hi>Pleasure</hi> vainely delude her. <hi>Esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi>
she holds her highest grace; with which
untainted shee purposeth to goe to her Grave.
Shee knowes how to <hi>fancie;</hi> and in her shee
<pb facs="5"/>
retaines what shee <hi>fancies</hi> most: A <hi>chast soule;</hi>
this is that she <hi>loves,</hi> and with which she cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<hi>lives.</hi> Shee was neuer yet acquainted with
a passionate <hi>ah me;</hi> nor a carelesse folding of her
armes, as if the thought of a prevailing Lover
had wrought in her thoughts some violent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper.
So seriously doth she taske her selfe
to imployment, as she never reserues so much
time as to treate of so light a Subject. Yet shee
unfainedly vowes, that if it be ever her fortune
to make her <hi>choyce,</hi> her constant affection must
never admit any <hi>Change.</hi> To be <hi>Generous</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
action, hath beene ever the height of her
ambition. Howsoever she might boast of <hi>Des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi>
her desire is to raise it by <hi>Desert.</hi> Shee
holds, no family can bee truely <hi>Generous,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
it be nobly vertuous. Her <hi>life</hi> must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
the <hi>line</hi> from whence shee came. Shee
scornes to entertaine one thought below her
selfe. Or to detract from the glory of that
house from whence she came. As the blood
that streames through her veines was nobly
Derived, so must it not by any <hi>action</hi> or <hi>affection</hi>
drawne from the rule of her direction, become
corrupted. For <hi>Honour,</hi> she admits it, but sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
or never admires it; the <hi>Staires</hi> by which
she meanes to clime to it, must be faire &amp; firme,
or she will never mount them. She rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires
the Ages folly; while shee observes how
many hazard their high-priz'd liberty, for a
vading glimpse of popular glory. Her desires
<pb facs="5"/>
are higher seated, where they are onely to bee
sated. A secure State consists not in <hi>styles</hi> but
<hi>vertues,</hi> which are <hi>Honours</hi> surest stayes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
her highest <hi>Honour</hi> reflects on her Creator,
wherein she is so farre from fearing, as shee is
ever wishing more <hi>Corrivals.</hi> THIS is the
<hi>GENTLEWOMAN</hi> whom I have presumed
heere to present vnto your <hi>Ladiships</hi> seruice;<note place="margin">Such, to your <hi>Honour,</hi> is her zealous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as shee makes it the sole Apologie of her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption: which shee weaves vp in this Dimensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</note>
whose sweete converse will at retired houres
afford you choicest solace. Neyther, should
you ranke her amongst the lowest of your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
will it displease her, such is her Humility:
for she hath learned as well to <hi>obey</hi> as <hi>command.</hi>
Nor will she spare for any paines, so her dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
may please. Onely (<hi>Madam</hi>) be pleased to
shine upon her with the gracious raies of your
favour,<note place="margin">To serve some <hi>GREAT ONES</hi> l've bene oftimes wood.</note> to shrowd her bashfull endeavours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the wings of your Honour; and entertaine
her blushing approach with your benigne Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.<note place="margin">But <hi>HERS</hi> I'm vow'd, that is both <hi>GREAT</hi> and <hi>GOOD.</hi>
      </note>
So shall you finde a constant desire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall
in her; and engage <hi>Him,</hi> whose intimate
Zeale to your <hi>Honour</hi> recommended her,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships
devoted servant:
<hi>Richard Brathwait.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>