<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In commendation of Poetry.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S122590_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72345</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13627</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S122590</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In commendation of Poetry.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Batrachomyomachia: or: The wonderfull and bloudy battell betweene frogs and mice : The occasion of their falling out: their preparation, munition, and resolution for the warres: the severall combats of every person of worth, with many other memorable accidents. Interlaced with divers pithy and morall sentences, no lesse pleasant to be read, then profitable to be observed. Paraphrastically done into English heroycall verse, by William Fowldes, late one of the cursitors of his Majesties high Court of Chancery</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chapman, Laurence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>In commendation of Poetry.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the divers currents that do flow</l>
      <l>Frō th'euer springing fountain of al art,</l>
      <l>The perled Nectar most cōtent doth show</l>
      <l>Which Poetry full sweetly doth impart,</l>
      <l>Whose hony'd vapour comforteth the heart,</l>
      <l>And under vailed fancies that doth sing,</l>
      <l>Which doth much profit with great pleasure bring</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For certs the truth (though truth no colours need</l>
      <l>To men of understanding and ripe yeeres)</l>
      <l>When she is masked in a seemely weed,</l>
      <l>More faire, more sweet, and beautifull appeares,</l>
      <l>Her tale contents the mind, and glads the eares</l>
      <l>And makes men more attentive to her story,</l>
      <l>That truth may still prevaile with greater glory.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For as an Image drawne in white and blacke,</l>
      <l>Though it be well proportioned with care,</l>
      <l>If it doe other comely colours lacke,</l>
      <l>To beautifie the members, head, and haire,</l>
      <l>Vnto the eye appeares not halfe so faire;</l>
      <l>Nor with so much content doth fill the minde,</l>
      <l>As that portrayd with colours in his kinde:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>Ev'n so a naked story simply told,</l>
      <l>Though cause be true and worthy due regard,</l>
      <l>Doth not mens hearts with such affection hold,</l>
      <l>Nor hath the outward sences so in gard,</l>
      <l>As doth that matter which is well declard,</l>
      <l>Adorned pleasantly with tearmes and art,</l>
      <l>Which piercing th'row the eares, doth move the heart.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This knew the learned Poets all of yore,</l>
      <l>This knew th'immortall Sages long agone,</l>
      <l>Whose workes the wisest of our age adore,</l>
      <l>Such store of wisedome in their bookes is shone,</l>
      <l>Such pleasure unto all, offence to none,</l>
      <l>Such grave precepts hid under fine device,</l>
      <l>As eares and heart with wonderment surprise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No fable sweet <hi>Philosophy</hi> containes,</l>
      <l>Within the sacred volumes of her cell,</l>
      <l>Dipt in the fount, which from <note n="*">
            <hi>A hill consecrate to the Muses.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Pernassus</hi> strains,</l>
      <l>Whereas the thrice three <hi>Nymphs</hi> are said to dwel,</l>
      <l>That barbarisme and ignorance expell:</l>
      <l>But under vaile deepe secrets doth unfold,</l>
      <l>Though but a tale by wanton <hi>Ovid</hi> told.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>By wanton <hi>Ovid?</hi> heavenly Poesie,</l>
      <l>Parden the rashnesse of my infant Muse,</l>
      <l>That I, a client to thy mysterie,</l>
      <l>Should unadvisedly by that word abuse,</l>
      <l>And terme him wanton, did no folly use:</l>
      <l>For though his Muse was wanton, as he playned,</l>
      <l>Yet <hi>Ovids</hi> life was chaste, and never stayned.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor sung he alwayes in a wanton lay,</l>
      <l>And penned pleasing ditties of blinde fire:</l>
      <l>Of deeper matters much could <hi>Ovid</hi> say,</l>
      <l>As he whose soaring spirit mounted higher,</l>
      <l>Than ever Poet after could aspire.</l>
      <l>And save the famous <hi>Homer</hi> chiefe of all,</l>
      <l>
         <note n="*">
            <hi>Semper Virgilium excipio.</hi>
         </note> The Prince of Poets may we <hi>Ovid</hi> call.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But neither <hi>Homer, Ovid,</hi> nor the rest,</l>
      <l>That ever tasted <note n="*">
            <hi>A fountaine of the Muses.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Aganippes</hi> spring,</l>
      <l>Though but to write of fables they addrest,</l>
      <l>Which to th'unskilfull no contentment bring,</l>
      <l>But with such arte and knowledge did them sing,</l>
      <l>That in their volumes scarce appeares one line,</l>
      <l>Which to the learned doth not seeme divine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>No vice of youth, no villany of age,</l>
      <l>No lewd behaviour of each degree,</l>
      <l>But in the secret myst'ries of the sage</l>
      <l>And grave instructions of philosophy,</l>
      <l>Clad in the habit of sweet Poesie,</l>
      <l>Is aptly couched in some pretty fable,</l>
      <l>As well the learned to discusse are able.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And not alone are vices set to view,</l>
      <l>And horrid plagues attending wickednesse:</l>
      <l>But blessed vertue with the heavenly crew,</l>
      <l>Which ever wayt upon her worthinesse,</l>
      <l>By them are portrayed forth with comelinesse:</l>
      <l>The meanest fable Poet e're did make,</l>
      <l>May stand as mirrour for example sake.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For proofe whereof, read but this little booke</l>
      <l>With understanding, knowledge, care and skill,</l>
      <l>And thou shalt finde presented to thy looke,</l>
      <l>Such wit and learning from the Authors quill,</l>
      <l>Which under fine inventions meet thee still;</l>
      <l>So pleasant obiects that occurre thine <note n="*">
            <hi>The eyes of thy minde.</hi>
         </note> eyes,</l>
      <l>As will thy soule with wonderment surprise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>And not alone shall pleasure thee awayte,</l>
      <l>As thou perusest what I now present;</l>
      <l>Here thou shalt have fit matter for each state,</l>
      <l>If thou consider what hereby is ment.</l>
      <l>Then thinke thy time herein not idly spent.</l>
      <l>Ponder with iudgement what thou read'st at leysure,</l>
      <l>So may thy profit equalize thy pleasure.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>