<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST NOBLE PRINCE, MAVRICE Land-Grave of Hassia.</title>
           <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123739_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73571</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3875</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123739</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST NOBLE PRINCE, MAVRICE Land-Grave of Hassia.</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Our Lordes famile and many other poinctes depending upon it : opened against a Iew, Rabbi David Farar: who disputed many houres, with hope to overthrow the gospel, opened in Ebrew explication of Christianitie; that instructed, Rabbi Abraham Ruben. With a Greke epistle to th Geneveans. By H. Broughton</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>98 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO <hi>THE MOST NOBLE PRINCE,</hi> MAVRICE Land-Grave of Hassia.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>WHEN I came to Marpurg (Most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince) your Doctour promotor layd among positiones of al faculties, this one against me:</hi> quidam autumat Descendere ad inferos in sacro Symbolo, esse idem quod ascendere ad coelos, quod nos non credimus. <hi>And they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested me to dispute: vvher I shevved that, all dead, be inferi, all vvhose soules be in Heaven: &amp; euerie taking of a lourney is descendere by scripture speach. And yf an horse die: antiquitie held it enough to say, he vvas dead: but for men, they toke more in their mouth: as,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; <hi>is he dead &amp; gone to the dwellinges of Hades.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And all Heathen vvold expound our Symbolū of faith to meane as the Gospel▪ that our Lord vvēt from hēce to the most happy lodge of the happy. Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <hi>milliones in England think so: your tendered the truly learned D. Fortius thinketh so: &amp; since I ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the cause, the flour of Christendome thinketh so: though the Cyclopes of Aetna vvold haue svva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved me up in their Gehennean torment. The Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natours yelded, and svvare a great oth, that they vvold teach the teachers, to use strangers better. Novv a Ievv hath dealt openly against me: vvher in your Doctours take vvith him, against my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brevv bookes to your Highnes and to your Brother the Grave of Hanavv. You haue sene both transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I defend the Gospel: Yf Papist or Caluinistes doe cross, I vvil combat. Your Highnes may tell your Doctours of flight or fight. It is not vvell, that men teach, vvhat they haue not learned themselues.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnes most humble Hugh Broughton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>