<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOrable William Earle of Pembroke, Lord Herbert of Cardiffe, Lord Par and Rosse of Kendall, Lord Marmion and St Quintin, Lord War∣den of the Stanneries in the Counties of Deuon and Cornewall, Captaine of his Maiesties Towne and Castle of Portsmouth, and the Isle of Portsey, in the County of Southampton, Lord Lieutenant of the Counties of Wilts and Somerset, Chancellor of the Vniuersity of Oxford, Lord Chamberlaine of his Maiesties most Honourable Houshold, Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuic Councell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123303_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24099</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123303</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOrable William Earle of Pembroke, Lord Herbert of Cardiffe, Lord Par and Rosse of Kendall, Lord Marmion and St Quintin, Lord War∣den of the Stanneries in the Counties of Deuon and Cornewall, Captaine of his Maiesties Towne and Castle of Portsmouth, and the Isle of Portsey, in the County of Southampton, Lord Lieutenant of the Counties of Wilts and Somerset, Chancellor of the Vniuersity of Oxford, Lord Chamberlaine of his Maiesties most Honourable Houshold, Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuic Councell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts : By Thomas Tomkins: organist of his Maiesties Chappell Royall in ordinary</title>
                 <author>Tomkins, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>154 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="30"/>
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<seg rend="sup">rable</seg>
      <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Cardiffe,</hi> Lord <hi>Par</hi> and <hi>Rosse</hi> of <hi>Kendall,</hi> Lord <hi>Marmion</hi> and S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Quintin,</hi> Lord War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the <hi>Stanneries</hi> in the Counties of <hi>Deuon</hi> and <hi>Cornewall,</hi> Captaine of his Maiesties Towne and Castle of <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> and the Isle of <hi>Portsey,</hi> in the County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the Counties of <hi>Wilts</hi> and <hi>Somerset,</hi> Chancellor of the Vniuersity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine of his Maiesties most Honourable Houshold, Knight of the most Noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuic Councell.</head>
   <p>My very good Lord;</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it may seeme a presumptuous and improper thing for me to present your Honour with a Song, who are daily busied in the great and waighty Counsells and affaires of the King and Kingdome: Yet haue not my thoughts been wound vp to this height, without an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing reason to my selfe, of excuse, and pardon at the least, if not of fittingnesse, and hope of acceptation.</p>
   <p>For though your Lordships imployments be daily, yet hath the Day many houres, and if you should bestow all of them on sad and serious matters, you might shorten them, and depriue vs too soone of the benefit both of your Counsels and Actions. Besides, (if I may presume to giue your Lordship any account of my poore selfe) I first breathed, and beheld the Sunne, in that Country, to which your Lordship giues the greatest lustre, taking the Title of your Earledome from it, and euen therefore haue alwaies (I know not by what secret power of naturall affection) euer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and wished your Lordships prosperity. To which considerations may be added that goodnesse of nature, eminent in your Lordship, which was euer a friend to Musicke, and the knowne vertues of your minde, which seemes to be best in tune, in those who loue Musicke best, as being least distracted with low cogitations, and your often frequenting and fauourable attention to the Musicke in the Chappell, which vseth sometimes to raise the soule aboue her Companions, Flesh, and Bloud; as also the place you hold vnder his Maiesty, which consequently renders you, a Patron and Protector of Musicke.</p>
   <p>Concerning the Songs, if they shall be found answerable to the desire and affection of their indulgent Parent: I beseech your Honour to consider, that as there are few men absolutely perfect, saue onely in contemplation; so neither is more clearenesse to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in the Riuers, then in the Spring, nor more perfection, in imperfect mens contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, or workes of this kinde.</p>
   <p>For the lightnesse of some of the words, I can onely pleade an olde (but ill) custome, which I wish were abrogated: Although the Songs of these Bookes will be euen in that poynt, sutable to the people of the world, wherein the rich and poore, sound and lame, sad and fantasticall, dwell together.</p>
   <p>Lastly, I doe againe most humbly beseech your Lordship to pardon my presumption, and to accept of these my imperfect offers, who will offer my prayers to God for your Lordship, that you may enioy a happie and blessed Harmony in the whole course of your life, (betweene your selfe and your friends, your body and minde) to the end that you may haue content (which is the best kinde of Musicke) here, and the Musicke of Angels hereafter. This is, and shall be, the prayer of</p>
   <p>Your Honours most humbly deuoted in all obseruance and duty,</p>
   <p>THOMAS TOMKINS.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>