<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Leech, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123497_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72530</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15363.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123497</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Leech, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and profitable catechisme : with certaine prayers adioyned, meete for parents and housholders to teach their children and seruants</title>
                 <author>Leech, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56, 59-82 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can not but earnestly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (good christan Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) as I hope thou dost with me, these miserable times wherein we liue behoulding the great number, already growne and daily encreasing, of wicked atheists, superstitious papists, prophane wordlings, carnall gospellers, vaine and idle professors and great multitudes of ignorant people euen in the principles of religion in this land. Notwithstanding the gospel hath beene so long &amp; plentifully preached amongst vs, so many godly books published, both of the interpretation of scriptures and also of other learned and holy treatises by sundry worthy men, so many excellent and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble catechismes, set forth and fitted for teaching the grounds of religion to all sorts of people. So as we may iustly weepe ouer cities, townes, and villages as the Lord Iesus did ouer Ierusalem.<note place="margin">Luc. 19.42.</note> Oh that you had known euen in this your day those things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto your peace. But now are they hid from your eyes; for ah alas who seeth not,
<pb facs="3"/>
almost in all places, the mightie sinnes of the land, crying for vengance: That that may iustly be pronounced vnto vs which the prophet denounceth to Israel.<note place="margin">Hosea. 4.1.</note> Heare the word of the lord O people of England. The lord hath a controuersie with the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the land, because ther is no truth, no mercie, no knowledge of God in the land, by swearing and lying and stealing and killing and whoring they breake out, and blood toucheth blood. Wherefore it is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be feared that seeing wisedome hath cryed vnto vs so long,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.20.25.26. &amp;c.</note> and vttered her words so lowd abroad in the streets, in the assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, in citties and townes, and all sorts haue refused, none would regard her cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, least shee also laugh at our distruction, and mocke when our feare commeth like a sodaine desolation, and our destruction like a whirlewind and a tempest, to sweepe vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way headlong into the gulfe of all miseries and calamities. The Lord in mercie raise vs vp out of our deadly sleepe of sinnes and securitie that we may awake to liue righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and sinne no longer. Many of vs haue in our mouths, vainly boasting as the people of Israel,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.4.</note> the temple of the Lord, the temple
<pb facs="3"/>
of the Lord, we haue the temple of the lord, so wee the gospell of Christ, the gospel of Christ, we haue the gospel of Christ, but ah alas many thousands of vs knowe nothing what the gospell meaneth. A multitude of people throughout the land haue not yet learned the very beginnings of the doctrines of Christ, of repentance from dead works: of faith towards God, of baptisme, of laying on of hands, of the resurrection from the dead, and of eternall iudgement, nay not so much as what sinne is, or how they becam sinners, what the punishment of sinne is, or how they may scape it. Many thousands know nothing what sinnes are forbidden, what duties are required in any of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, they vnderstand not any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the faith aright, any petition of the Lords praier, the meaning of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or any thing that belongeth to a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian life. O that we would learne in time to repent and turne vnto the lord,<note place="margin">Ier. 4.4.</note> before his wrath breake forth vpon vs like fire, and burne that none can quench it, for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of our inuentions. Euen this were one good meanes if all parents and householders would set apart some howre euery day to
<pb facs="4"/>
pray with their children and seruants, &amp; vse some for catechisme to enforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and their familie in the grounds, and principles of religion,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.6.7.8. &amp; 11.18.19. Ephes. 6.4. Genes. 18.19. Iosu. 24.15. Act. 10.21</note> as they are bound in duty by the commandements of the Lord and taught by the example of Godly fathers and howseholders in the scriptures, namely <hi>Abraham, Iosua</hi> and noble <hi>Cornelius.</hi> So should themselues, their children &amp; their seruants bee better prepared and fitted to vnderstand the word of God &amp; the doctrines thereof deliuered vnto them by their godly pastors and ministers, which now they heare most vnprofitably, and after much and long teaching learne nothing at all. Amonge other catechismes I haue found by long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience this one to bee of very fit and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vse, for the instruction of a family, beeing plaine and easie and not longer then may euery seauen daies be repeated through, being fitly deuided. For the questions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fasting and gouerment may bee omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, except there bee speciall occasion, this may bee done and praier ioyned withall in litle more then halfe an hower at one time. I confesse some good part of this was published many yeares since, gathered out of another
<pb facs="4"/>
cathechisme by a godly and reuerent prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher M. Moore of Norwich, which I haue altered and enlarged in many places with such questions and answers as I thought meete for the instruction of the simple and vnlearned, vnto which I haue added cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine praiers for the helpe of such as are not yet able to conceiue a prayer of themselues. I wish thee (good Reader) whosoeuer wilt vse it, to examine with the doctrines the places of scripture quoted, some of them at the least though not all: otherwise thou shalt depriue thy selfe of a great benefit and comfort.</p>
   <p>This poore mite amid my ordinarie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at the request of some freinds, I haue cast into the Lords treasurie, If thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt by it remember me in thy praiers. And so I commend thee to god and to the word of his grace, who is able to build further, and to giue thee an inheritance among them which are sanctified.</p>
   <p>And the Lord giue thee vnderstanding to growe in grace &amp; in the sound knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, to whome with the father and the holy Ghost be ascribed all glory and praise power, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie
<pb facs="5"/>
and dominion now henceforth and for euermore.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy poore louing brother in Christ, Iames Leech.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>