<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123394_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00290</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16288a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of the common prayer : and adminystracion of the sacramentes, and other rytes, and ceremonies in the Churche of Englande</title>
                 <author>Church of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>440 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was neuer any thyng by the wyt of man so well deuysed, or so sure establysshed, (whyche in contynuaunce of tyme) hath not been corrupted: as (emong other thynges) it may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by the cōmon prayers in the Churche, cōmonly called deuine seruice. The first originall and grounde whereof, if a man would searche oute by the auncyente fathers, he shall fynde that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same was not ordained but of a good purpose, and for a greate aduauncement of godlynes. For they so ordred the matter, that all the whole Byble, (or the greatest part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) should be read ouer once in the yere: entēdyng therby, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Cleargie, and speciallye suche as were ministers of the congregacyon, shoulde (by often readyng and meditacyon of Goddes worde) be styrred vp to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes themselues, and be more hable also to exhorte other by wholesome doctryne, and to confute them that wer aduersaries to the truth. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the people (by dayly hearing of holy scrypture read in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church) should contynually profyt more and more in the knowledge of God, and be the more enflamed with the loue of hys true religyon. But these many yeres passed, this godly and decente ordre of the auncyente fathers, hath been so altered, broken, and neglected, by plantyng in vncertayne Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, Legendes, Respondes, Verses, vayne Repeticions, Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, &amp; Sinodalles, that commonly whē any boke of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Bible was begon, before three or foure Chapters were read out, al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rest were vnread. And in thys sorte the boke of Esai was begonne in Aduent, and the booke of Genesis in Septuagesima: but they were only begonne, and neuer read throughe. After a lyke sorte were other bokes of holy scripture vsed. And moreouer, wheras Sainct Paul would haue such language spoken to the people in the Churche, as they myghte vnderstande, and haue profyt by hearyng the same: The seruice in thys Churche of Englande (these many yeres) haue been read in Latine to the people, which they vnderstode not: so that they haue heard with their eares onely, and theyr heartes, spirite and mynde, haue not been edifyed thereby. And furthermore, notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng that the auncyente fathers haue deuyded the Psalmes into se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen porcyons, wherof euery one was called a Nocturne: now of late time a fewe of them haue been dayly sayd, and oft repeated, and the rest vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omytted. Moreouer, the noumbre and hardnes of the rules, called the Pye, and the manyfolde chaungeinges of the seruyce, was the cause, that to turne the booke onely, was so hard and intricate a matter, that manye tymes there was more busynes to fynde out what should be read, then to reade it when it was founde out.</p>
   <p>These inconueniences therefore consydered, here is set furth suche an ordre, whereby the same shalbee redressed. And for a readinesse in thys matter, here is drawen out a Kalender for that purpose, whych is playne
<pb facs="3"/> and easy to be vnderstanden, wherin (so muche as may be) the reading of holy scriptures is so set furth, that all thynges shalbe done in ordre, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breaking one piece therof from an other. For this cause be cut of, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themes, Respondes, Inuitatories, and suche lyke thynges, as did breake the continuall course of the reading of the scripture. Yet because there is no remedie, but that of necessitie there must be some rules: therefore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne rules are here set furthe, whiche as they be few in numbre, so they be playne and easy to bee vnderstanden. So that here you haue an ordre for prayer (as touching the reading of holye scripture) muche agreable to the mynde and purpose of tholde fathers, and a greate deale more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and commodious, then that which of late was vsed. It is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, because here are left out many thynges, whereof some be vntrue, some vncertayne, some vayne and supersticious, and is ordeined nothing to be read, but the very pure woorde of God, the holye scriptures, or that whiche is euidentlye grounded vpon the same: and that in suche a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and ordre, as is most easy and playne for the vnderstandyng, both of the readers and hearers. It is also more commodious, bothe for the shortnes thereof, and for the playnnes of the ordre, and for that the rules be few and easy. Furthermore, by this ordre, the Curates shall nede none other bookes for theyr publyque seruice, but thys booke and the Byble: By the meanes whereof, the people shall not bee at so greate charge for bookes, as in tymes past they haue been.</p>
   <p>And where heretofore there hath been greate diuersitie in saying and synging in churches within this realme, some folowyng Salisbury vse, some Herforde vse, some the vse of Bangor, some of Yorke, and some of Lincolne: Now from hence foorthe, all the whole Realme shall haue but one vse. And yf any would iudge thys waye more paynfull, because that all thinges must be read vpon the booke, whereas before by the reason of so often repeticion, they could saye many thynges by hearte: If those men will weigh their labour, with the profite and knowledge whiche daylye they shall obteyne by readyng vpon the booke, they wyll not refuse the payne, in consideracion of the great profite that shall ensue thereof.</p>
   <p>And forasmuche as nothyng can almost bee so playnely sette foorthe, but doubtes may ryse in the vse and practisyng of the same: To appease all suche diuersitie (if any aryse) and for the resolucion of al doubtes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the maner howe to vnderstande, dooe and execute the thynges conteyned in this booke: The parties that so doubte, or diuerslye take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye thyng, shall alwaye resorte to the Bysshoppe of the Dyocesse, who by hys dyscrecion shall take ordre for the quieting and appeasyng of the same, so that the same order bee not contrary to anye thyng conteyned in thys booke. And yf the Bysshoppe of the Dyocesse be in anye doubte, then may he sende for the resolucion thereof vnto the Archebishoppe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>