<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTVOVS Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123202_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05085</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15227</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123202</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTVOVS Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Salue Deus Rex Iudæorum : Containing, 1 The Passion of Christ. 2 Eues apologie in defence of women. 3 The teares of the daughters of Ierusalem. 4 The saluation and sorrow of the Virgine Marie. With diuers other things not vnfit to be read. Written by Mistris Æmilia Lanyer, wife to Captaine Alfonso Lanyer seruant to the Kings Majestie</title>
                 <author>Lanier, Emilia</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_virtuous_reader">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTVOVS Reader.</head>
   <p>OFten haue I heard, that it is the property of some wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, not only to emulate the virtues and perfections of the rest, but also by all their powers of ill speaking, to ecclipse the brightnes of their deserued fame: now contrary to this custome, which men I hope vniustly lay to their charge, I haue written this small volume, or little booke, for the generall vse of all virtuous Ladies and Gentlewomen of this kingdome; and in commendation of some particular persons of our owne sexe, such as for the most part, are so well knowne to my selfe, and others, that I dare vndertake Fame dares not to call any better. And this haue I done, to make knowne to the world, that all women deserue not to be blamed though some forgetting they are women themselues, and in danger to be condemned by the words of their owne mouthes, fall into so great an errour, as to speake vnaduisedly against the rest of their sexe; which if it be true, I am perswaded they can shew their owne imperfection in nothing more: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could wish (for their owne ease, modesties, and credit) they would referre such points of folly, to be practised by euill dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed men, who forgetting they were borne of women, nourished of women, and that if it were not by the means of women, they would be quite extinguished out of the world, and a finall ende of them all, doe like Vipers deface the wombes wherein they were bred, onely to giue way and vtterance to their want of discretion and goodnesse. Such as these, were they that disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Christ his Apostles and Prophets, putting them to shamefull deaths. Therefore we are not to regard any imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they vndeseruedly lay vpon vs, no otherwise than to make vse of them to our owne benefits, as spurres to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, making vs flie all occasions that may colour their vniust
<pb facs="23"/>speeches to passe currant. Especially considering that they haue tempted euen the patience of God himselfe, who gaue power to wise and virtuous women, to bring downe their pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie. As was cruell <hi>Cesarus</hi> by the discreet counsell of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Deborah,</hi> Iudge and Prophetesse of Israel: and resolution of <hi>Iael</hi> wife of <hi>Heber</hi> the Kenite: wicked <hi>Haman,</hi> by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine prayers and prudent proceedings of beautifull <hi>Hester:</hi> blasphemous <hi>Holofernes,</hi> by the inuincible courage, rare wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and confident carriage of <hi>Iudeth:</hi> &amp; the vniust Indges, by the innocency of chast <hi>Susanna:</hi> with infinite others, which for breuitie sake I will omit. As also in respect it pleased our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, without the assistance of man, beeing free from originall and all other sinnes, from the time of his conception, till the houre of his death, to be begotten of a woman, borne of a woman, nourished of a woman, obedient to a woman; and that he healed woman, pardoned women, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted women: yea, euen when he was in his greatest agonie and bloodie sweat, going to be crucified, and also in the last houre of his death, tooke care to dispose of a woman: after his resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, appeared first to a woman, sent a woman to declare his most glorious resurrection to the rest of his Disciples. Many other examples I could alleadge of diuers faithfull and virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous women, who haue in all ages, not onely beene Confessors, but also indured most cruel martyrdome for their faith in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ. All which is sufficient to inforce all good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and honourable minded men to speake reuerently of our sexe, and especially of all virtuous and good women. To the modest sensures of both which, I refer these my imperfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, knowing that according to their owne excellent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spositions, they will rather, cherish, nourish, and increase the least sparke of virtue where they find it, by their fauourable and best interpretations, than quench it by wrong constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To whom I wish all increase of virtue, and desire their best opinions.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>