<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Ladie Susan, Coun∣tesse Dowager of Kent, and daugh∣ter to the Duchesse of Suffolke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123202_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05085</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15227</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123202</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Ladie Susan, Coun∣tesse Dowager of Kent, and daugh∣ter to the Duchesse of Suffolke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Salue Deus Rex Iudæorum : Containing, 1 The Passion of Christ. 2 Eues apologie in defence of women. 3 The teares of the daughters of Ierusalem. 4 The saluation and sorrow of the Virgine Marie. With diuers other things not vnfit to be read. Written by Mistris Æmilia Lanyer, wife to Captaine Alfonso Lanyer seruant to the Kings Majestie</title>
                 <author>Lanier, Emilia</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>¶ To the Ladie <hi>Susan,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse Dowager of Kent, and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Duchesse of Suffolke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>COme you that were the Mistris of my youth,</l>
      <l>The noble guide of my vngouern'd dayes;</l>
      <l>Come you that haue delighted in Gods truth,</l>
      <l>Help now your handmaid to sound foorth his praise:</l>
      <l>You that are pleas'd in his pure excellencie,</l>
      <l>Vouchsafe to grace this holy feast, and me.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And as your rare Perfections shew'd the Glasse</l>
      <l>Wherein I saw each wrinckle of a fault;</l>
      <l>You the Sunnes virtue, I that faire greene grasse,</l>
      <l>That flourisht fresh by your cleere virtues taught:</l>
      <l>For you possest those gifts that grace the mind,</l>
      <l>Restraining youth whom Errour oft doth blind.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>In you these noble Virtues did I note,</l>
      <l>First, loue and feare of God, of Prince, of Lawes,</l>
      <l>Rare Patience with a mind so farre remote</l>
      <l>From worldly pleasures, free from giuing cause</l>
      <l>Of least suspect to the most enuious eie,</l>
      <l>That in faire Virtues Storehouse sought to prie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whose Faith did vndertake in Infancie,</l>
      <l>All dang'rous trauells by deuouring Seas</l>
      <l>To flie to Christ from vaine Idolatry,</l>
      <l>Not seeking there this worthlesse world to please,</l>
      <l>By your most famous Mother so directed,</l>
      <l>That noble Dutchesse, who liu'd vnsubiected.</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <lg>
      <l>From <hi>Romes</hi> ridiculous prier and tyranny,</l>
      <l>That mighty Monarchs kept in awfull feare;</l>
      <l>Leauing here her lands, her state, dignitie;</l>
      <l>Nay more, vouchsaft disgnised weedes to weare:</l>
      <l>When with Christ Iesus she did meane to goe,</l>
      <l>From sweet delights to taste part of his woe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Come you that euer since hath followed her,</l>
      <l>In these sweet paths of faire Humilitie;</l>
      <l>Contemning Pride pure Ʋirtue to preferre,</l>
      <l>Not yeelding to base Imbecillitie,</l>
      <l>Nor to those weake inticements of the world,</l>
      <l>That haue so many thousand Soules insnarld.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Receiue your Loue whom you haue sought so farre,</l>
      <l>Which heere presents himselfe within your view;</l>
      <l>Behold this bright and all directing Starre,</l>
      <l>Light of your Soule that doth all grace renew:</l>
      <l>And in his humble paths since you do tread,</l>
      <l>Take this faire Bridegroome in your soules pure bed,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And since no former gaine hath made me write,</l>
      <l>Nor my desertlesse seruice could haue wonne,</l>
      <l>Onely your noble Virtues do incite</l>
      <l>My Pen, they are the ground I write vpon;</l>
      <l>Nor any future profit is expected,</l>
      <l>Then how can these poore lines goe vnrespected?</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>