<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>S., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123178_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73149</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22391.6</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123178</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>S., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Soli gloria Deo. Certaine rare and nevv inventions for the manuring and improving of all sorts of ground : Published by the author, for the helpe and instruction of all those that having any barraine land or other, and that are desirous to use the same unto their best profi and the publique good</title>
                 <author>Shaw, John, inventor</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 29, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I have here layd open unto thy view certaine Instructions in points of <hi>Husbandry</hi> that as yet hath not beene Practised by any, such as are in use already I will not undertake to teach nor yet to treat of; Although I thinke it were not a labour superfluous, by reason that <hi>Husbandry</hi> is not a needlesse thing, but a principall suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and maine Piller both in Church and Common-wealth; yea it is that, that our GOD hath ordayned to be the susten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our naturall Lives.</p>
   <p>The prosperity of this Science presageth Plenty, it presa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Health, it presageth Wealth, it presageth Life, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth glad the Heart of man; but the contrary presageth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie, Famine, and woe: For, if this Science thriveth, the whole Land thriveth, but if it fayleth, who is it that feeleth not some smart thereof; and therefore, if all or the greatest part in some kind or other partake of the Calamities that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sueth through the unskilfulnesse of the <hi>Husband-man,</hi> I hope there is none eyther so foolish, or wicked, as to be offended at any that shall endeavour in a lawfull sort to discover any thing, that may bee helpfull to the <hi>Husband-man,</hi> and that may further his skill in <hi>Husbandry.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Husband-man</hi> perhaps may thinke, it onely belongs unto him to discourse of <hi>Husbandry;</hi> but I must tell him, and all others of the like minde, That it is the duty of every one (so farre as they are bound to procure the Publique good) to produce some thing or other, if they can possibly, that may further the good of <hi>Husbandry:</hi> Indeed, looke how much the Soule in excellency exceeds the Body, &amp; Celestiall things exceeds Terrestriall; so farre doth the science of <hi>Divinitie</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
exceed all other Sciences; but excepting the Science of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> no Science is of that antiquity, worth, and excellency (in my judgement) as is this Science of <hi>Husbandry.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many other sciences are of more esteem in the world then this, yet innumerable are there that have passed their whole lives, some others the greatest part of their lives with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of divers of them; yet never any passed through any one part of their lives without being beholding unto this Science; and therefore I cannot but marvaile to thinke how many great wits have beene imployed to illustrate, and set forth other Sciences, and how few have bent their minds to perfect this Science, when as there is both matter super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant, and reason sufficient to induce men thereunto.</p>
   <p>In <hi>Martiall</hi> affaires the skill and direction of some great man, as of the Generall oftentimes, doth profit more in the battaile, then the skill and courage of the Souldiers; And the prescription of the <hi>Physitian</hi> is a direction unto the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary:</hi> And the skill of the <hi>Pilate</hi> is of more worth for the preservation of the Ship, then the toyle and labour of the <hi>Mariner:</hi> And shall we thinke it would not profit <hi>Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,</hi> if such as are of a deepe judgment should but bend their mindes and frame their studies, for the discovery of such points of <hi>Husbandry,</hi> as may serve for use and direction unto the <hi>Husband-man,</hi> whom the continuall toyle and daily care they undergoe will never suffer them to become so truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious, as to discry in this Science any more then what they may discerne with their bodily eyes, nor yet all that. Some may thinke perhaps meanely of a subject of this nature; and yet I doubt not, but that moderate men may be exercised in such Points of <hi>Husbandry</hi> as I shall here discover, with as great delight and profit, as they shall desire:</p>
   <p>I shall not at this Impression, publish all the skill I have attain'd unto in this Science, neyther shall I describe all the severall <hi>Instruments</hi> and <hi>Inventions</hi> to be used in those points of <hi>Husbandry,</hi> as I shall here now treat of, because I shall want words that may expresse the particulars of the same, for new <hi>Inventions</hi> must have new nominations, both of the things
<pb facs="4"/>
themselves, and also of the particulars thereof; And when both the thing it selfe the Names, and the Particulars, are all unknowne unto the <hi>Reader,</hi> the description thereof would but puzzle him, and so tire his affection, before he would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto the true knowledge and use of the same; therefore at the end of this little <hi>Treatise,</hi> shall all such as are desirous to receive further instructions concerning the same, be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted where they may both see the severall <hi>Engines</hi> and <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> &amp; also receive further information therin if they please.</p>
   <p>I will not stand much to intreat for acceptation, for I know men will accept of it according as they find it, onely this I must say, I hope there is none of so evill a nature, as to take it in evill part; and if that I find it to be well taken, I shall with the greater alacrity discover other <hi>Points</hi> of the like nature more freely and fully hereafter, and unto all those that shall find or discerne any good by any thing herein declared, my desire is, that they would give the Lord the glory thereof, whom I take to bee the revealer of all true and lawfull <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries;</hi> and therefore, the glory of the same to bee due unto him onely, if any thing herein seeme imperfect, that attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to my insufficiencie.</p>
   <p>As for the Subject, it is of such a nature that it will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of an high stile, nor Rhetoricall phrases, neither is it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in such a subject, to speake above the capacity of <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-men,</hi> who most commonly are illiterate; therefore in this worke, I have rather endeavoured plainly and briefly to deliver the severall <hi>Directions</hi> and <hi>Instructions</hi> herein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then Amply or Elegantly to write of the same: And howsoever I may be censured by any; yet my comfort is, the Lord knoweth that in undertaking this taske, my ayme is, and ever shall be the glory of God, and the publique good of my native Countrey, in which minde, I hope ever to subsist and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Alwayes studying and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the same:</hi> I. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>