<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TOMY WELL DEVO∣ted Neighbours in the towne of Eckington; all grace and love of the truth be multiplyed in you.</title>
           <author>Kenrick, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123195_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72485</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14933</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123195</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TOMY WELL DEVO∣ted Neighbours in the towne of Eckington; all grace and love of the truth be multiplyed in you.</title>
                 <author>Kenrick, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tell-troth's reqvitall, or, Truth's recompence : as it was preached the 12th day of November, 1626, at Eckington: wherein are contained these three propositions, (vindicating Paul from the aspersion of enmity, and laying it on the Galatians,) viz. 1 No grace of God in man can secure him from the enmity of the unregenerate. 2 Sometimes a ministers owne hearers are set in variance against him. 3 The publication of the truth is the cause of this variance. By Samuel Kenrick student in divinity, and preacher of Gods word in the same place</title>
                 <author>Kenrick, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 27, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TOMY WELL DEVO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Neighbours in the towne of <hi>Eckington;</hi> all grace and love of the truth be multiplyed in you.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian friends,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Bring you here onely an <hi>Herbe</hi> of your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tasting, by presenting (now) unto your <hi>eyes,</hi> what heretofore I preached to your <hi>eares:</hi> and it is of your owne garden (too;) for you are Lords of my <hi>Ministeriall services:</hi> yea you may say unto mee as sometimes <hi>Paul</hi> did unto <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Epist. Pauli ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, vers. <hi>19.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Thou owest thy very selfe</hi> unto us. Well then; take my notes unto you: labour to make them usefull unto your soules; Buy this <hi>Truth</hi> with your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; Sell it not with your sleighty regard of it: If you have hated it, learne now to love it; if you love it, love it still; maintaine it; stand for it; make much of it; so shall you know that the <hi>Lord will doe you good</hi> (not so much, <hi>because you have</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Iudg. 17.13.</note>
      <hi>a Levite to your Priest,</hi> as) because you have the <hi>Truth</hi> dwelling in you. But why stand I here to move your affections, when (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily) your understandings are not altogether so rightly
<pb facs="5"/>informed in the Text as they ought? Now indeed tis fit that the<note n="a" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Talmud.</note>
      <hi>beginnings of things should bee diligently looked</hi> unto. And it is a good rule for a Scholler often<note n="b" place="margin">Pliny Sec. Epist. <hi>6.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>to looke backe upon the Title of his owne workes.</hi> You may (indeed) make a doubt, whether I haue rightly interpreted this Text, or not: whether the Apostle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>[Am I therefore become your enemy, &amp;c?]</hi> to free himselfe from the aspersion of <hi>Enmity,</hi> or to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid the <hi>Galatians</hi> with it; I say, to upbraid them with it: which position, I bind with these arguments.</p>
   <p>First,<note place="margin">
         <hi>1.</hi> Galatorum inobedientia.</note> the Apostle takes them up sharply for their<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience unto the truth; (which is the usuall companion of Emnity.) <hi>Chap. 3. vers. 1.</hi> as also <hi>chap 5. v. 7.</hi> which makes a probability that hee upbraids them here of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity against him.</p>
   <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Epanorthosis Apostolica.</note> I argue from the Apostles sudden <hi>correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of himselfe in this present text: Before he blazoned forth their <hi>Encomiasticke</hi> praises: now he sings a <hi>Pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node, Am I therefore become your enemy, &amp;c.?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>they would have plucked out their owne eyes</hi> for him, &amp;c. Now, they seeme to hate him. Therefore I conjecture hee upbraids them in these words, <hi>Am I therefore become your enemy, &amp;c.?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>3.</hi> Orthodoxorū Consensus.</note> I gurge the <hi>consent</hi> of orthodoxall Writers upon this place; as<note n="d" place="margin">Haet est con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio veritatis, ut semper inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie persequax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Hier. in hunc versime.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Hierome,</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Tàm expro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandicausá, quàm admonendi, &amp;c. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Calvin,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="bottom">Ju vers. <hi>17.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Beza,</hi> and<note n="g" place="bottom">Cum voserga me praesen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tm alacres ostenderitis, tanto{que} amore me complexi fueritis, non debebatis menunc pro inimice habere. <hi>Pisc. in hunc locum.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Piscator:</hi> and also <hi>Bezaes</hi> Glosse upon the <hi>17</hi> verse, <hi>They zelously affect you, &amp;c.</hi> that they might trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port all your love from me upon themselves. Therefore it seemes unto me that the Apostle (now finding them to
<pb facs="6"/>halt in their love to him-wards) upbraids them with an <hi>Am I therefore become your enemy, &amp;c?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But, if I have erred herein, pardon my haste: I little thought to print it, when I pend it: and (I know) you will witnesse with me, that I have not much mended the <hi>coat</hi> of the delivery. Blesse it then with your Christian approbation, and you shall incourage me hereafter (the rather) to plead for the <hi>Truth.</hi> Now, with my prayers to Almighty God for the increase of grace in your hearts, I leave you for this time, and will rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most assured friend and Pastor, <hi>Samuel Kenricke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>