<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the vertuous Louers of Musicke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123303_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24099</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123303</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the vertuous Louers of Musicke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Songs of 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts : By Thomas Tomkins: organist of his Maiesties Chappell Royall in ordinary</title>
                 <author>Tomkins, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>154 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="18"/>
   <head>To the vertuous Louers of <hi>Musicke.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Sonnets, composed first most exquisitely in Italian by</hi> S<seg rend="sup">ior.</seg> Francesco Bembo <hi>a Gentleman of Italie; were so admired of</hi> Giouan. Croce, <hi>one of the most excellent Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians of the world; as well for their Poesie, as Pietie (the Substance of them being drawen from those seauen nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Psalmes called Penetentials; indited by that Sweete Singer of Israel, inspired of the holie Spirit) as that hee thought it worthy of his skill in Musicke, to apply them to this Harmonie of Sixe parts; as well to honour their Author and his Compositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to giue a profitable Delight vnto the vertuous. And my selfe often obseruing the generall applause giuen these Songs when I haue heard them soong, (though somtimes without the words) thought it would be verie gratefull to many of our English louers of Musick, if they were translated, or imitated in our tongue: the rather, because through their want of vnderstanding the Italian, they are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of a Chief part of their delight. For albeit that the verie concent of the Note may sweetly strike the outward sence of the eare; yet it is the Dittie, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayed with the Musicke to the intellectual Soule, by the Organs of hearing, that doth touch the hart, and stir the affections eyther to Iocondnes, or Sadnes, Leuitie, or Grauitie, according to the nature of the Composition: in which respect (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) the articulate voice of man excelleth all other voices, and Instruments in the world. Besides I supposed, that the Scarcetie (not onely in our tongue, but in all other vulgars) of Musicke in this kinde, whereby men may be edified and God glorified, would make these the more acceptable; and peraduenture be a motiue to some of our excellent Musitians to dedicate their diuine skill to the Seruice of God, in Songs of this more Sanctified kinde In which respects; and for that I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged thereto by some, Skilfull in this Arte: I haue aduentured to publish these (otherwise destinate to priuacie) vnto the view of the world: Although I am not Ignorant that in this curious age, it is likely to run the ordinary fortune (euen of more exact labours) vpon the Shelues of ridged censure: But the Gentle, will winck at small faults where they spie them: As for the Supercilious Critick if (after he haue compared them with the Originall) he dislike them: he may please him selfe, and doe them all better: But doe Yee accept them with a Sèrene browe, and vse them to the glory of God, and your Laudable and Christian delight. Fare yee well.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Your well-willer</p>
   <p>R. H.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>