<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Ladie Margaret Coun∣tesse Dowager of Cumberland.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123202_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05085</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15227</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123202</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Ladie Margaret Coun∣tesse Dowager of Cumberland.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Salue Deus Rex Iudæorum : Containing, 1 The Passion of Christ. 2 Eues apologie in defence of women. 3 The teares of the daughters of Ierusalem. 4 The saluation and sorrow of the Virgine Marie. With diuers other things not vnfit to be read. Written by Mistris Æmilia Lanyer, wife to Captaine Alfonso Lanyer seruant to the Kings Majestie</title>
                 <author>Lanier, Emilia</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>To the Ladie <hi>Margaret</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse Dowager of Cumberland.</head>
   <p>{inverted ⁂}</p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honoutable and Excellent Lady, I may say with Saint <hi>Peter, Siluer nor gold haue I none, but such as I haue, that giue I you:</hi> for hauing neither rich pearles of India, nor fine gold of Arabia, nor diamonds of inestimable value; neither those rich treasures, Arramaticall Gums, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense, and sweet odours, which were presented by those Kingly Philosophers to the babe Iesus, I present vnto you euen our Lord Iesus himselfe, whose infinit value is not to be comprehended within the weake imagination or wit of man: and as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> gaue health to the body, so I deliuer you the health of the soule; which is this most pretious pearle of all perfection, this rich diamond of deuotion, this perfect gold growing in the veins of that excellent earth of the most blessed Paradice, wherein our second <hi>Adam</hi> had his restlesse habitation. The sweet incense, balsums, odours, and gummes that flowes from that beautifull tree of Life, sprung from the roote of <hi>Iessie,</hi> which is so super-excellent, that it giueth grace to the meanest &amp; most vnworthy hand that will vndertake to write thereof; neither can it receiue any blemish thereby: for as a right diamond can loose no whit of his beautie by the blacke foyle vnderneath it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by beeing placed in the darke, but retaines his naturall beauty and brightnesse shining in greater perfection than before; so this most pretious diamond, for beauty and riches exceeding all the most pretious diamonds and rich jewels of the world, can receiue no blemish, nor impeachment, by
<pb facs="17"/>my vnworthy hand writing; but wil with the Sunne retaine his owne brightnesse and most glorious lustre, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so many blind eyes looke vpon him. Therefore good Madame, to the most perfect eyes of your vnderstanding, I deliuer the inestinable treasure of all elected soules, to bee perused at conuenient times; as also, the mirrour of your most worthy minde, which may remaine in the world ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares longer than your Honour, or my selfe can liue, to be a light vnto those that come after, desiring to tread in the narrow path of virtue, that leads the way to heauen. In which way, I pray God send your Honour long to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, that your light may so shine before men, that they may glorifie your father which is in Heauen: and that I and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others may follow you in the same tracke. So wishing you in this world all increase of health and honour, and in the world to come life euerlasting, I rest.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>