<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR OLIVER SAINT IOHN Knight, Lord Deputy of IRELAND.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123522_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10706</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20989.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123522</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR OLIVER SAINT IOHN Knight, Lord Deputy of IRELAND.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Irish hubbub or, The English hue and crie : Breifely pursuing the base conditions, and most notorious offences of this vile, vaine, and wicked age. No lesse smarting then tickling. A merriment whereby to make the wise to laugh, and fooles to be angry. By Barnaby Rich gentleman, and seruant to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 61, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR OLIVER SAINT IOHN Knight, Lord Deputy of IRELAND.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or want of a better cloake, wherby to shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter these endeauours of my vntutored pen, I haue borrowed an Irish mantle.</p>
   <p>I might haue clad them in a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious garment, I confesse that would haue made them more acceptable to the world, which graceth men now adayes more for their outward shew, then for their inward vertue: but this habit wherein I haue now suted them, carrieth no shew of pride, and is fittest for them to trauell in, that hauing first in all reuerent and dutifull manner presented themselues to your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble view, and with like humblenesse againe besought your Lordships fauourable pasport, and then to wander through the world, where they shall meet with men of diuers disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who seeing them come out of <hi>Ireland</hi> in this disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed manner, hoping to heare some strange newes, may enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them for a time, and howsoeuer their expectation bee answered, may suffer them to passe, some in respect of policie
<pb facs="3"/>
some in respect of pittie, and some in respect of pietie.</p>
   <p>The lines I send, are like flowers that be of sundry smells pleasing and displeasing, according to the diuersity of mens complexions: if they offend any, I am sure they bee such as doe know themselues to bee faultie: perhaps they may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please some that are accounted to bee worldly wise, but not any one at all that is truly reputed to be godly wise: and in this cause I would not sticke with <hi>Marcus Cato,</hi> to stand to the censure of my most deprauer <hi>Titus Gracchus.</hi> I haue grasped at abuse, yet vnder generalities, and haue aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at many matters, whereof some not altogether vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary: Amongst some others that be more serious, I haue mixed measurable mirth. I haue beene somewhat curious with the Painter, to giue euery shape his perfect shadow: I haue presented all together to your honourable view, to the end that at your leisure they might serue you to laugh at; for others, if they finde themselues agreeued, let them lump and lowre. they shall but shew themselues to haue guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences.</p>
   <p>If my ability were answerable to my good will, my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to your Honour would streatch farre: In the meane time, pleaseth it your Lordship to accept of his good intent, that liueth to doe you what seruice hee may, and so will rest while he draweth breath.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Dublin the</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>24. of Iune 1618.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all humble and dutifull affection, BARNABY RICH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>