<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable Sir Edward Bromfield Knight, Lord Major of this honorable City; and to the rest of the right Worshipful Court of Aldermen, with the right Worshipful William Abell, and Iames Garrard, Esquires, Shriefes of this Honourable Citty for this yeare.</title>
           <author>Freake, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123109_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00055</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11347</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123109</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable Sir Edward Bromfield Knight, Lord Major of this honorable City; and to the rest of the right Worshipful Court of Aldermen, with the right Worshipful William Abell, and Iames Garrard, Esquires, Shriefes of this Honourable Citty for this yeare.</title>
                 <author>Freake, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Love and obedience or, Christs precept and promise : Being a sermon preached on Whitsunday last, 28. of May, 1637. in Guild-hall chappell, before the right Honorable the Lord Major of this City of London. By William Freake minister of the Word of God</title>
                 <author>Freake, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Sir Edward Bromfield</hi> Knight, Lord Major of this honorable City; and to the rest of the right Worshipful Court of Aldermen, with the right Worshipful <hi>William Abell,</hi> and <hi>Iames Garrard,</hi> Esquires, Shriefes of this Honourable Citty for this yeare.</head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>William Freake</hi> Minister of Gods Word, wisheth in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of this his service, all reall happinesse, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to this life and a better.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right honorable and right Worshipfull:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O shew reasons for my Dedication of this Sermon, and my service therein to <hi>your Honour,</hi> and to this <hi>City,</hi> may bee expected by some that have not knowne me and my course; but they are well known almost to all that know me, to be such, and of that <hi>Nature,</hi> that if I should neglect this duty, the World might well crie shame upon me. <hi>I</hi> have beene above <hi>thirty foure yeares</hi> imploied here wholy, and within the Verge of this City: I haue received the greatest good that I enjoy in my present course from the reverend Ministry of this City. <hi>I</hi> have had my first incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb facs="3"/>in this <hi>way,</hi> from a <hi>worshipfull Society</hi> of this City. What <hi>I</hi> hope to enjoy during life, hath beene the free gift of this <hi>honourable Court of Aldermen,</hi> and of this <hi>Citty.</hi> All which are iust incentives to a respective thankefulnesse from me.</p>
   <p>But <hi>I</hi> must adde one reason more, in respect of you my much honoured Lord, your Honours free goodnesse to mee at my first comming to <hi>Saint Georges</hi> in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> now five yeares since compleate. The free continuation of your love in some distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses falne upon me in the <hi>interim.</hi> And lately your Honors unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served favour in appointing me to this <hi>Service. All these</hi> have enioyned me to this Dedication; which <hi>I humbly beseech your Honor</hi> to accept of, as proceeding from him, whose daily praiers, and constant indeauours, in the way of all thankefulnesse and dutifull obseruance are, and shall be during life, ever <hi>yours,</hi> as obliged,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours, and the Cities Chaplaine, to be commanded,</hi> William Freake.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>