<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶An Admonition to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123131_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06346</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16812</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123131</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶An Admonition to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatie of the Churche : conteining a true discourse, to knowe the true Church by, and to discerne it from the Romish Church, and all other false assemblies, or counterfet congregations. Written by M. Bertrande de Loque of Dolphinee, and dedicated vnto my Lord the Viscount of Turenne. And faithfully translated out of French into English, by T.W</title>
                 <author>Loque, Bertrand de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Langton, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 384, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>¶An Admonition to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was loth gentle Reader, to publish this profitable and necessary treatise, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause it being meant wel, may bee taken ill, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a rule and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō to forraine Churches reformed, may perhaps fall into the hands of vndiscreete readers, &amp; trouble the happy &amp; quiet state of the Church of England. But to preuent this inconuenience, and to helpe the weakenesse of many whiche carried with a preposterous rash zeale, doe iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they conceaue, and like rather to feede their humor, then foster the peace of the Church. I thought it necessary to put the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in remembrance of those thinges, which being greedily snatched at, and read without iudgement, by curious and contentious heads may tende to the disturbance of the peace, and tranquilitie of the Church. Whereas therefore in the nienth Chapter intreating of the degrees of the Ministerie, the authour
<pb facs="14"/>
seemeth to detract frō Archbishops Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politanes, Deanes, Archdeacons, and other Ministers in this Church of England and els where, his meaning is not to condēne those ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles allowed &amp; attributed to faithfull Pastors in other reformed Churches, according to the auncient and laudable order of the primitiue Church, but to eleuate and impugne, the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, pompe, and ambition of the popishe prelacie: who leauing their function of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and teaching haue vsurped I knowe not what authoritie and power of comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and countercommanding what they list, in the church of God. Who in crueltie succeed not Peter, but Romulus, in pompe and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, not Peter, but Cōtantine as Bernard faith. They doe all for honor, and nothing for holines saith the same authour. Their courts are full of Symoniacks, their thresholds more troddē by ambitiō, then by deuotiō, and their Cannons Ecclesiasticall procurers of gain &amp; lucre. The Church is not gouerned by names but by offices, which they faithfully performe this day, to whom for reuerence wee willingly ascribe the names of honor and dignitie.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, no man will denie, though the same authoritie be committed to all Gods
<pb facs="14"/>
faithfull Ministers in binding, losing, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, or ministring the Sacraments: yet that this equalitie in ministration doth nothing hinder a diuersitie, distinction of degrees, and superioritie in gouernment, being very neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary for the auoiding of cōfusion and schisme. That this preheminence is not lately deuised or newe begunne, may soone appeare by these words of the Apostle. The spirites of the Prophetes are subiect to the Prophetes.</p>
   <p>Whereupon I gather, that if the spirites of all the Prophetes, being lightened by the vertue of the holy Ghoste, were not free from the checke of other Prophetes, vpon whom it had pleased God to bestowe his gifts of iudgement, knowledge, and learning: much more ought wee to allowe and preferre the graue and learned iudgement of the best, and graunt them a dignitie &amp; preheminence in matters of lesse importance. The reason by the Apostle is not to be neglected. <hi>Non est Deus author confusionis, sed pacis,</hi> as who shoulde say: if some were not appointed to decide such doubtes as arise either of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raūce or of mallice, all woulde goe to wracke in haste, and Christian education to mortall hatred. Thē would the frost of priuate quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, either sterue the buddes of the Gospel, or
<pb facs="15"/>
rage of spirituall ambition disturbe the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of euery congregation. Gregorie Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen in his Oration intituled, <hi>Apologeticus,</hi> saith: There must of necessitie be two sortes of mē, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> some that must rule and guide, others that must bee guided and gouerned. In man there are two thinges, the soule which gouerneth by reason, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which submitteth it selfe and obeyeth, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise if in an armie all were souldiers, or all Captaines, what hope were there of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and good successe? If in a ship all shoulde bee alike, all marriners, who shoulde stande at the Helme, who shoulde guide the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe? If in a Citie all were equall, who shoulde make decrees, prescribe lawes, and execute the same? If the whole bodie were a head, what disorder? Or if the members were without a head, what confusion? The learned therefore send vs to learne order to the heauens &amp; to the earth: to the angels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom there are degrees Angels, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changels, vertues, <hi>potestates, principatus, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationes, throni, Cherubin, Seraphin,</hi> to the Sun, to the moone, to the stars, which in glory &amp; brightnes excell one another. To the Bees which haue their graūd captaines at whose buzzing they go forth, they follow &amp; cluster
<pb facs="15"/>
together, to the trees, wher you see of a great stocke many braunches arise and spring. Our naturall appetite and affection acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, the gouernmēt of reason &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāds: And so in the Church of God ther hath been alwayes gouernours, and they gouerned chiefly and souerainly, as in the ciuill estate. Seth, Enos, Sem, ruled the Church in their time, &amp; the Church acknowledged &amp; obeyed their gouernment. The best writers affirme that the first borne had the rule of the whole familie. Noah alone ruled in making and ordering the Arke, in which there were cleane and vncleane beastes, tame and sauage of all kindes, to signifie the church gathered together of both Iewes &amp; Gentiles, and gouerned by Iesus Christ only, as by a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Noah. The Church vnder the lawe had diuersitie of orders as may appeare in sundry places. In the third of Numbers, where the Tribes are mustered, the three families of the Gersonites, Kohathites, Merarites, had their Prince or head which they called Nes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha. In the first of Kings, &amp; the 4. Azaria is called the Prince of the Leuites. Obadiah that worthie Counceller, meeting with olde Heli, disdaineth not to call him lord. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Nazianzen writeth to Gregory Nissien,
<pb facs="16"/>
which supposed him to be angry, because they had ordeined one without his consent saide. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. Let no mā bely vs, nor any of my lords the brethrē. Good Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie, an humble and simple man weighed not titles, nor cared for any worldly honour, but was carefull that order should bee prescribed in the Church, and that one should goe before an other in honour. S. Iames saith: Be not yee many masters. And Chrysostom saith, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie of dignitie and place bringeth forth schisme. Likewise Ierome writing to Euagri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us saith: that from Marke to Dionisius and Heraclas, there was one alwayes set in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place of dignitie aboue the rest, and this he saith was to auoid schismes, which seeing they lacke skill and be in the Church, and shalbe to the end, sith the disease remaineth still, what great folly is it to condemne or refuse the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie. In the Counsell called Gangrensse, the holie fathers assembled there, writing to the Bishops of Armenia, vse these wordes. <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratissimis dominis.</hi> To our most honourable Lordes. The late writers most of them allow and affirme a primacie of order, though not in degree of ministration. M. Caluin, writing vpon the 2. Cor. &amp; 10. <hi>Etsi omne commune sit, &amp;c.</hi> Although one and the same office be
<pb facs="16"/>
common to all, yet be there degrees of honor. And the same Authour writing vpon these wordes out of the 2. to the Philipp. <hi>Sicut patri filius ita mihi Timotheus seruiuit in Euāgelio.</hi> As a father his sonne, so hath Timothie ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mee in the Gospell. Wee learne saith hee in this place, that no such equalitie was amōg the Ministers, but one did rule and gouerne the rest by counsell and authoritie. Againe in his 4. booke, 8. Chapter sect. 54. He saith that euerie prouince had among their Bishops an Archb. and that the Councell of Nice did appointe 4. Patriarches which shoulde be in order and dignitie aboue Archb. it was for the preseruation of discipline. Wherefore it is apparant by testimonies of holie scripture, by light of reason, and by practise of the Church, by the necessitie of the thing that distinctiō of degrees &amp; superioritie is necessarie in the church, as without the which, law would soone grow to libertie, faith wold soone be deuided, &amp; the coat of christ Iesu, which is his church, rent and torne in sunder, so many fancies, so many faithes would follow.</p>
   <p>Nowe whereas many make much adoe, about the titles of Bishops, Metropolitans, &amp; Archb. and the scripture is still alledged, as an aduersarie in this quarell: &amp; containing
<pb facs="17"/>
expresly no such names. Thus may they make our Sauiour Christ inferiour to his father, concerning his diuinitie, because the title <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> is no where literally expressed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the same by sūdrie places may be well and iustly gathered. Therefore to conclude, to them that list to be contentious. <hi>Vbi de re constat, puerile est de verbolitigare.</hi> And to the discreete Reader, that hee peruse this booke, to profite his conscience, and not to please his affection. Seeke peace, and the God of peace shall blesse you, &amp; increase his grace amongst you, to the terrour of your enemies, and comfort of your soules, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>