<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, WHEREIN THE SCOPE, MANNER OF PROCEDING, AND PROFIT OF THIS BOOKE IS DECLARED, REQVISITE TO BE READ BEFORE THE BOOKE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123294_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00718</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22810</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123294</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, WHEREIN THE SCOPE, MANNER OF PROCEDING, AND PROFIT OF THIS BOOKE IS DECLARED, REQVISITE TO BE READ BEFORE THE BOOKE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A conference of the Catholike and Protestante doctrine with the expresse words of Holie Scripture : Which is the second parte of The prudentiall balance of religion. VVherein is clearely shewed, that in more then 260. points of controuersie, Catholiks agree with the holie Scripture, both in words and sense: and Protestants disagree in both, and depraue both the sayings, words, and sense of Scripture. Written first in Latin, but now augmented and translated into English</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 798, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, WHEREIN THE SCOPE, MANNER OF PROCEDING, AND PROFIT OF THIS BOOKE IS DECLARED, REQVISITE TO BE READ BEFORE THE BOOKE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are now diuers years (Gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) since I published the first parte of the <hi>Prudential Balance of Religion,</hi> in which, by the weights of Prudence and Right Reason I weighed together the Catholik and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant religion according to their first Founders in our English nation, to wit, <hi>S. Austin</hi> and <hi>Martin Luther:</hi> which booke hath neuer since bene answered by anie Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant albeit diuers ministers, and superintendents haue car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at it both in Pulpits and printed books, shewing thereby that they wanted no will to answere it, if they could haue performed it. In the preface thereof I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised a second parte, in which I would after the same manner weigh the forsaied religions according to their claimes to the holie Scripture, and the expresse words thereof, which here now I offer vnto thee. The causes why I haue so long differred the publishing of this second par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, are well enough knowne to them who know me, and not needfull to be known of them who know me not. And therfore I will not trouble thee with the rehearshall
<pb facs="4"/> of them, but here propose vnto thee the scope, manner of Proceding, and Profits of this second parte.</p>
   <p>2. As a man consisteth essentially of a Soule and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and can neither be, nor be imagined without them both: So the true Church of Christ essentially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth <note place="margin">Two things wholy neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarieto Christs Church.</note> of his true <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which is the forme, and (as it were) the soule of his Church, and of <hi>lawfull Pastors and People,</hi> who teach and embrace his Doctrine, which Pastors and People make (as it were) the bodie of Christes Church. And without both these partes, to wit, Christs true <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and true <hi>Pastors</hi> teaching, and <hi>People</hi> embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it, Christs true Church can no more be, or imagined to be, then a true man can either be, or imagined to be, without both the true bodie and true soule of a man. And albeit the manifest need of both these partes to the true Church of Christ, doth enforce Protestants to make some clame to them both, and to pretend that they haue alvaies had both true <hi>Pastors</hi> who taught, and <hi>People</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiued their Doctrine; yet their pretense to this parte of the Church is so weake and slender, as but seldome and vpon mere necessitie they insist thereon. But their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test pretense and claime is to the true <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Christ; and think thereby to proue, that they haue alwaies had true <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>People</hi> who taught and beleiued their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, as I haue shewed in a Booke of the <hi>Author of the Protestant Church and Religion;</hi> wherein also I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced by ten Demonstrations, (all taken out of the open Confessions of the best learned Protestants both of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and other Countries) that they neuer had anie one <hi>Pastor</hi> who taught, or man who beleived the very funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall and most substantiall points of their religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luther</hi> arose; but that he was first Author, Inuentor, and Father therof, as some of them in plaine termes do call him.</p>
   <p>3. And although this Booke haue bene now these ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie years published both in Latin and English, and doth by the open confessions of the best learned Protestants
<pb facs="4"/> ouerthrow the very foundation of their Church, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shew, that it hath no foundation at all besides their owne imagination; yet hitherto no Protestant hath made anie shew of a solid answere vnto it. I saie, no shew of a <note place="margin">why D. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux lecture is no answer to the Author of Protest. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> solid answere, because that florish which Doctor Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux the Kinges diuinitie Reader in Oxford hath made in a lecture, deserueth not the name of shew or shadow of an answer. First, because he nether mentioneth the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of answering my saied booke, which I set downe, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> proue by reason, testimonie of holie Fathers, and confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Protestants, ought to be kept in answering such a booke: And which lawes, I tell him before hand, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he ether keepe, or refute, I would accounte his answer no solid or lawfull answere, but the babling of one who could neither sufficiently answere, nor yet hould his peace. Secondly, because he maketh no other answere <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to the manifold and manifest depositions of the best learned Protestants, which I haue my self brought, and clearly confuted by the depositions or testimonies them selues, against which confutation of myne, he replieth nothing, but standeth mute. Thirdly, because he so mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> mangleth the answere which I make to their Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sme, wherewith they by pretense of true <hi>Doctrin,</hi> would proue that they haue alwaies had true <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>People</hi> who taught and beleiued it, and so pittifully replieth to the saied answere, as he plainly sheweth him self to be a true Heretike, that is, conuicted in his owne iudgement, as I think euerie one, that compareth his lecture with my Booke, will clearly perceiue.</p>
   <p>4. But sith the Protestants cheife and almost whole pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tense of the truth and euer being of their Church, is the pretense of the truth of their doctrin by the Scripture, I will euidently shew, euen by the light of Reason and Prudence, that they haue no reasonable or colourable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tense of Scripture: but that it maketh expresly, clearly, and directly against thē, and for Catholiks, almost in all points of cōtrouersie. For whereas there be twoe waies to shew, <note place="margin">Twoe waies to proue that. the Scripture is against Protest.</note>
      <pb facs="5"/> that the holie Scripture is plainely against Protestants; the one by conferring of diuers places together, by bringing the exposition of the holie Fathers, decrees of Councels, and tradition of the Church: the other, by onely compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the expresse words of Catholiks and Protestāts with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Protest. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin as clear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly contrarie to Scripture as</hi> yea <hi>is to</hi> no.</note> expresse words of holie Scripture touching the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; I take not the first way, which hithertoe Catholike writers haue followed, because it is not so fit to the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of commun people, for whome especially I compose this worke; but the second, which is as cleare, for euerie one that hath reason, to see, as it is cleare to see, that <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Yea,</hi> of the same matter agree, and that <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> do disagree.</p>
   <p>4. This perhaps may seeme strange, nay impossible to simple Protestants, whose eares haue bene still accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to heare their ministers vaunt, and brag of the word of God, of the Scripture, and Bible, and to auouch that Catholiks haue nothing to alleadge for thē selues but tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and word of men: But I beseech such to suspend a while their iudgment, and sith they wil haue the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants doctrin to be tried or iudged by nothing but by Scripture onely, let them grant me these two conditions <note place="margin">
         <hi>Two condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to proue the Scripture to be against Protest.</hi> 1. <hi>Touching the letter.</hi> 2. <hi>Touching the sense.</hi>
      </note> of trying their doctrin by the Scripture, which the very light of reason, the authoritie of holie Fathers, and the Confession of the best learned Protestants will enforce them to graunt. The first condition is touching the words or letter of the holie Scripture; The second, is touching the sense or meaning of the saied words or letter. For as the holie Scripture consisteth of two partes, whereof the one is the word or letter, the other, is the sense therof, so I require one condition for the word, and an other for the sense.</p>
   <p>5. The condition touching the word or letter is, that the words of holie Scripture be taken as they be in the <note place="margin">
         <hi>The</hi> 1. <hi>cōditiō to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ching the letter, proued.</hi>
      </note> Bible or booke of God, without anie addition, subtraction, or transposition: breefly without anie chopping or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging whatsoeuer. This condition is so iust and reasonable,
<pb facs="5"/> as I think no reasonable man will denie it; and neuertheles I wil proue it. First, because where God alone is Iugde, there <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it is reason, that all men be silent, and onely harken what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God saieth, nor interrupt or corrupt his words. <hi>Let vs heare</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>peccat. c.</hi> 20. <hi>De vnit. c.</hi> 13 <hi>Serm.</hi> 27. <hi>de verb. Apo.</hi>
      </note> (saieth S. Austin) <hi>our lord, and not ghesses or suspitions of men.</hi> Againe: <hi>I beleiue that which I read in holie Scripture, not that which vaine Heretiks say.</hi> And other where: <hi>There is a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie risen, let is goe to the Iudge, let the Prophet iudge: yea let God iudge by the Prophet, let vs both hold our peace.</hi> And yet againe: <hi>let vs not heare: This I say: This thou saiest, but let vs</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cont. Iul. c.</hi> 4. <hi>In Confutat. Latomito.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 234.</note>
      <hi>heare, This our lord saieth.</hi> Yea Luther writeth: <hi>That mans word added vnto Gods word is a couer, nay mans dung, wherwith pure truth is hidden.</hi> Moreouer, seing Protestants impose silence to the Church, Councells, Fathers, and all Catholiks in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> decision of matters of faith, and therin admit onely the written word of God, it were impudencie for them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest to speake. Agayne, if Protestants will mingle their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> owne words with the words of God, they admit not the onely word of God for iudge of controuersies, but parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly also their owne, and make one entire iudge of them both. Finally, Protestants are wonte to crie, <hi>that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
      <hi>is the onely, and profest rule of faith; that they will heare</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Beza cont. Heshus. Daneus Cont.</hi> 3. 6. 7. <hi>Hospin part.</hi> 2 <hi>Caluin cont. versipel. &amp; cont. Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>nothing besides Scripture; that nothing is to be taught but the pure written word; nothing to be beleiued but that which is expressely conteined in the Scripture.</hi> Let them heare therefore in these twoe hundred and sixte points, in which I will compare their doctrine with the Scripture, mere Scripture, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, and let them harken to nothing but Scripture; let all their owne words whatsoeuer be set aside: let the Scriptures pure and onely words shew and iudge, whether Catholik or Protestant doctrin in these 260. points here set downe, be agreable or disagreable vnto it.</p>
   <p>6. The second condition touching the sense is: That <note place="margin">
         <hi>The</hi> 2. <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching the sense, proued.</hi>
      </note> the pure written word of God may iudge betwixt vs according to the pure sense therof, which (when it is spoken clearly or of purpose to tell: vs what Gods mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is) of it self and according to the vsual acception of
<pb facs="6"/> men it doth afford, and this is euident also especiallie, if the Church must not be admitted to be the infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the true sense of Scripture. But neuertheles I proue it. First, because Protestants cannot set downe anie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> condition which is so reasonable or indifferent to both partes. Secondly, because ether the Scripture in matters of controuersie clearly declareth her meaning by her self without any help or exposition of man, or she doth not. If she clearly declare her meaning by her self, then needeth she no help of man at all. For what need she help of others to declare her meaning, who clearly declareth it her self? And vndoubtedly if in any place she clearly declareth her meaning, she doth it in those places, in which she speaketh both clearly, and of set purpose, for to expresse her mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But if by her self she doe not clearly declare her meaning in matters in controuersie without some help of man (especially without the help of one of the opposite parties who contend about her meaning) certainly she is <note place="margin">A iudge must be able by himself to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his mynd.</note> not fitt to be the onely iudge of controuersies, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants would haue her. For who will saye, that she alone is fitt to be iudge, who alone and by her self is not able to vtter clearly her mynd? Besids, if the pure word of God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> may not iudge according to the pure sense which of it self it clearly yeeldeth, but according to a different, nay quite opposite sense, which being conferred, expounded, wrested by man, it is forced to yeeld, who shall assure vs, that Gods sense, and not the sense of man, whose (and not Gods) that conference, inference, and wresting is, is made <note place="margin">
         <hi>Serm.</hi> 14. <hi>de verb. Apost. Tractat.</hi> 2. <hi>de Cant. c.</hi> 17. <hi>L.</hi> 6. <hi>cont. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. c.</hi> 5. <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismo c.</hi> 6.</note> iudge of controuersies? <hi>Let mens ghesses</hi> (saieth S. Austin) <hi>giue place for a time, let vs take in hand diuine weapons.</hi> Againe: <hi>This is humane inference, not dinine authoritie. The arguments which you bring are humane, these are diuine munitions.</hi> And otherwhere: <hi>let vs not bring false scales, with which we may weigh what we will and how we will, and saye as we please: This is heauie: This is leight; But let vs bring the diuine scale of the holie Scripture, and in that let vs weigh which is heauiest, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let not vs wheigh it, but let vs aknowledg it weighed of God.</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> Let vs set aside a while mens ghesses or imaginations of the conference or exposition of this or that place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, let vs not bring deceitfull scales of mans conference, inference or exposition of Scripture, with which we may weigh what we will, and how we will saying according as we please: This is the meaning, That is not the meaning; This followeth, That followeth not; This is true, that is false, againe all which we may oppose those words of S. Austin: <hi>This is mans inference, mans conference, mans exposition, mans ghesse, not diuine authoritie,</hi> and let vs bring the diuine and sure scale of the pure meaning of Gods pure word, and in that let vs weigh the doctrin of both partes, or rather let vs acknowledge that which is weighed and allowed by God him self in this his scale. Moreouer, if mans help be necessarie to Scripture for the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> conference and expositiō of the places therof, or inference of that which is to be inferred out of them, so that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mans help it can not sufficiently decide questions of faith, I aske of Protestants, what men these must be; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we or they, or some third, who nether are Catholiks nor Protestants? Sure I am, they will nether admit ours nor other mens expositions of Scripture for their iudge, and I think they wilbe ashamed to exact of vs that we should admit their interpretatiō, especially sith they refuse the conference, inference, and exposition of the holy Councells, and Fathers. Wherfore vnles they will stand to <note place="margin">Protestants must be tried by the natiue, and vsual sense of he words, or thy no sense.</note> that sense of Scripture which is no way partial, to wit, which the Scripture it self, by it self, without any conference or exposition of man, giueth, they can name no sense of Scripture which both parties may admit for their iudge: and to refuse all sense of Scripture whervpon both parties may reasonably agree, is plainly to refuse all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable triall by scripture. For seing the soule and kernel of the Scripture is the sense therof; and that the letter or words is but the shell or bark of it, as is euident and both holie Fathers and Protestants agree, manifest it is, that whosoeuer will not reasonably agree vpon any sense of
<pb facs="7"/> the Church, Councells, or Fathers) where it is spoken of set purpose to declare Gods meaning, of it self without any mans exposition, and according to the vsual vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of men, it doth afford, rather then the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie sense, which by the wresting of Protestants it is compelled to carrie. Let but this right reason and true prudence lift vp this Balance, wherein I weigh the <hi>Doctrin</hi> of Catholiks and Protestants according to holie Scripture in more then 260. points, and I nothing doubt, but it will clearly see and iudge the Catholik doctrin agreable to Scripture and the Protestant, quite opposite and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. And this is my purpose, Scope, and butte in this 1. <note place="margin">The Scope of the first booke And of the second.</note> booke, to which I adde a second, wherin I manifestly shewe that Protestants <hi>Doctrin</hi> is not onely quite oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site in more then 260. points both in words and meaning to the holie Scripture, but also, that they are forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect many and great partes of the Scripture; to alter that parte which they admit, to weaken all force of Scripture; to say that much of the Scripture was not spoken of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge, or not according to the meaning of the speaker; to teach, that most weightie sentences of the Scripture were spoken ironically, mimetically, and hyperbolically, to change the most vniuersall propositions of the Scripture into particulers, to limitate speeches not limited by the Scripture; to alter absolute speeches into conditionall; to make causall propositions not causall, to expound words in some sorte, which were spake simply; <note place="margin">The contents of the second booke.</note> which were spaken of one time, to interprete them of an other, to make one saying, of many; to vnderstand words that signifie the doing of a thing, of an endeauour to doe it; which signifie working a thing, of the way or meane therto; which signifie that a thing is, to expound that it ought to be: words which signifie a true thing, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound them of a shew or apparent thing: to expound the words of Scripture of different, yea wholy diuerse, &amp; contrarie matters; to deuise improprietes and all figures of speeches; to feigne friuolous and neuer before heard
<pb facs="7"/> of distinctions; to reiect the exposition of the Fathers, Councells, and Church: to confesse, that they teach <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin</hi> damned in ould time for heresie: to frustate the ends of the incarnation and passion of Christ: to take out of the world all vertue and giue free scope to all vice: and finally, to confesse, that much of the Protestant <hi>doctrin</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to holie Scripture. All which clearly shewe, that Protestant leaders doe not onely teach doctrin contrarie to the Scripture, but also do in very deed mock and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it.</p>
   <p>8. The manner of my proceeding is this. First I deuide <note place="margin">Manner of proceeding in this booke.</note> the matters which are in controuersie according to their order, and in euerie matter I distinguish manie articles which I propose in forme of question: After, I set downe the expresse words of Scripture: Next I bring the decrees of the Councell of Trent, or the Instructions of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techisme of that Councell: And where I find not their determinations, I alledge the doctrin of S. Thomas, or of D. Stapleton, or Cardinal Bellarmin. Against these, I produce the assertions of one or manie famous Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants directly opposite to the doctrin of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and of the Catholiks. Lastly, I gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a summe of the words of the holie Scripture, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a summe of the sayings of Protestants, that thereby the opposition betwene the doctrin of them both may the better appeare. As for the words of Scripture; <note place="margin">
         <hi>Plessie of the Church c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 145. Let them bring one text that is cleare and euident and we are readie to yeeld vnto them.</note> I bring not all which might be brought of euerie article, because nether is that necessarie to my purpose, sith God is as much to be beleeued in one word as in manie, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as the Councell of Arausica saieth truly) <hi>will manie te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of Scripture auaile any thing with him, to whome few are not sufficient,</hi> but I bring those onely testimonies which to me seemed most opposite to the words of Protestants, Nether do I proue, that the words of Scripture, which I cite, be cleare, and vttered of purpose to declare vnto vs Gods mynd of that matter wherof they treate, or do of themselues and according to their accustomed acception
<pb facs="8"/> amongst men, manifestly afford that sense in which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants gayne saye them; because al thefe points are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest by them selues, and the shifts which Protestants vse to delude them, do manifestly proue them. Nether also do I proue, that Protestants can not at least (touching the most of these Articles) produce any such testimonies of Scripture, which, in expresse words may seeme directly, and without any inference, conference, or exposition of theirs to speake for them, as in these 260. points the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies which I bring, do speake for vs. First, because this being a denial, it is of it self sufficiently proued, vnles the Protestants can demonstrate their contrarie affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, because this is euident to euerie one who <note place="margin">
         <hi>See Tertul. l. de Resur. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Luther de verb. Caenae, fol.</hi> 389.</note> considereth the testimonies brought by Protestāts, which in verie few and almost no matters at all in controuersie betwixt vs and them are such, as of them selues without the addition of some humane principle or illation, they may, so much as seeme, to be directly opposite vnto vs. Which if Protestāts would consider, they should easily see, almost in all controuersies, as much difference betwene our proofes out of Scripture and theirs, as there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the expresse word of God and humane discourse. Nether may they saye, that they are not bound to proue <note place="margin">Why Protest. are bound to prooue their negatiue points of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin.</note> those points wherin they contradict vs, because their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial needeth no proof; Both because in some contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies they are the affirmers, and we the deniers; as when they say, that God will and worketh sin, tempteth and predestinateth to sin; That Christ was truly a sinner feared <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> his dānation, suffered the paines of hel, the like: In which questions, seing Catholiks proue their denial by expresse words of Scripture, much more ought Protestants by the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> like expresse words to proue their affirmation. As also, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is one thing simply to deny or not to beleeue the Catholik affirmation (as euerie Iew, Turk, or infidel doth) an other thing, not onely to denie it or not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue it, but also to condemne it as an vntruth contrarie to <note place="margin">
         <hi>See Tertul. de Corona. c.</hi> 2.</note> Scripture, and to auouche the denial as a truth taught by
<pb facs="8"/> Scripture; For albeit a simple denial or not beleefe need no proofe, yet such a mixt denial, as denying the opposite affirmation, affirmeth it self to be auouched by Scripture, and the affirmation to be condemned thereby, hath as great need of proofe out of Scripture, as any other affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whatsoeuer. Moreouer, these denials are articles <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of faith with Protestants, and as such are put in their Confessions of faith, and therfore ether ought to be proued by Scripture, as other articles are; or they must confesse, that they can not proue out of Scripture the greatest parte of their faith: which principally consisteth of these negatiue articles or denials of our faith.</p>
   <p>9. As for Catholiks, for the most parte, I produce the <note place="margin">Why one Cath. saying is alledged.</note> words of one onely of the foresaied Authors; because the agreement of Catholiks in matters of faith is wel enough knowne; I might, if I would, haue my self set downe the Catholik doctrin in euerie article in the same words in which the Scripture deliuereth her doctrin of the same: or perhappes haue found the Catholike doctrine proposed by some Catholik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Author in the verie same words which the Scripture vseth: But that Protestants should not saye, that it was no maruel if the Catholik doctrin be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in the Scriptures words by any Author whatsoeuer; or when it is done of purpose, I would not set it downe but in the words of some famous Catholik writer, &amp; those spoaken not of purpose to accomodate their speech to the phrase of Scripture; but spoaken to declare and expresse the Catholik doctrin. And here by we may see that when the Catholik doctrin is to be sett downe most plainly and distinctly by thē who best know it, of it nature it requireth to be deliuered with the very same or the likewords which the Scripture vseth. Whence we may also gather (as I shal herafter) that the Catholik doctrin is in very deed one and the self same with the doctrin of the Scripture.</p>
   <p>10. For the like cause I haue alledged the words onely <note place="margin">Why manie Prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stants saying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> of famous Protestants, such as almost all were not onely writers but also Professors of Protestant diuinitie, lest
<pb facs="9"/> any should attribute their words to ignorance. And some <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> times I haue cited diuers sayinges of the same Author, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> partly lest any should think, that such words fell from him vnawares: partely also, because some times they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Scripture in so different manners of speech, as if they would that none should be ignorant therof: parte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly also, to the end, that the Catholik Reader may make choice amongst manie sayings of Protestants, which he iudgeth most opposite to the Scriptures words. Nether yet do I feare, that the multitude of Protestants sayings opposed against the Scripture, may scandalize any weake Catholik; for seing the Scripture most directly contrarie to them, and armed with this sheild, he wil no more regarde the Protestants words then so many barkings of of doggs against heauen, so many cries of Ieves against Christ, so many blasphemies of damned men against God. And if it be wearisome or irkesom to the Catholik Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to read all the blasphemous speeches of Protestants (as it was to me to write them out) let him runne ouer the Summe which <hi>I</hi> make of their words, or, by the notes in the margent, chuse which are fittest to his purpose. And thus much for the māner of my proceeding in this booke.</p>
   <p>11. The profit of this work is manifould. First, because by it a short and easie way may be taken to make an end <note place="margin">The profits of this worke.</note> of all controuersies, and that out of Scirpture alone, as Protestants desire: to wit, by mere rehearsall of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> words of Scripture, of Catholiks, and of famous Protestants touching 260. articles of controuersie: For if it appeare that catholikes in 260. articles agree both in word and sense with the expresse words of Scripture and these spoken of purpose to declare her meaning vnto vs: and that Protestants in those 260. articles directly contradict the said words and sense of the holie Scripture, no man will doubt, but that all Protestant doctrin (for as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the Catholik) is also contrarie to the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. An other commoditie is, that in this booke are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> those places of Scripture, and they ranked accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="9"/> to order of their matters, which in 260. articles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and in their proper and vsual sense do approue the Catholik doctrin, and condemne the Protestant. A third <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> commoditie is, that hereby are at hand in euerie kind of controuersie such sayings of famous Protestants, as not onely directely crosse the Scripture; but also many of them are so blasphemous against God, against Christ, against the Saints, the Church, Sacraments, Faith, Good works: so opposite to pietie, vertue and religion: so fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to vice, and all licenciousnes: so repugnant to reason, as some Protestants will deny, and others scarse beleeue, that euer any of theirs taught such doctrin. Whome I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest <note place="margin">The Authors fidelitie in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> to take the paines to looke vpon the bookes and places by me alledged, and then to beleeue their owne eyes. For I not onely gathered their sayings out of their owne bookes, but also, after I had my self gathered them and caused them to be faire copied out, I diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them with their books, and admitted none which he, that read their bookes, did non find to be truly cited out of them. Wherfore I say for my self as Caluin said for him self against Gentilis: <hi>There shalbe no colour for them to cōplaine that they are slandered, seing I request that iudgmēt be made of their impietie out of their owne mere words.</hi> And they, who haue had to deale with Protestants ether by word or writing, know well how important a thing it is, to be able to conuince them, that they teach that which in in very deed they teach; which may clearly be done by their sayinges here rehearsed.</p>
   <p>12. The fourth commoditie of this worke is, thar here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> shall appeare, that almost in all controuersies which betwene Catholiks and Protestants, Catholiks do stick fast to the very words of Scripture, and religiously keepe her letter and forme of speech; and Protestants goe fare from the words, at lest of Scripture and bring in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, yea quite opposit, forme of speech. Nether ought they to think this to be a small fault, both because they boasting of the pure and expresse word of God, ought
<pb facs="10"/> also to keep the very letter thereof, and not to reiect it and to vse the contrarie: as also because the Apostle comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>to auoide profane nouelties of words, and to keepe the</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>forme of holesome words which we haue learned of him:</hi> which commandment they do not follow, who forsake the Scriptures forme of speech, and embrace the contrarie: and finally, because not onely the sense, but also the words and forme of speech vsed by the Scripture, did proceed from the holie Ghoste, and therefore it is sacrilegious au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacitie to reiect Gods words and Gods forme of speaking, and to bring in mans words and fashion of speaking quite contrarie. As if these new Ghospelers should teach God how to deliuer his mind, or he ment to speake other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise by them, then he did by his Prophets, Apostles, and Euāgelists, wherefore their impietie is not to be borne withall who when the Scripture most often and most plainly calleth the beleefe of wicked men or reprobats, <hi>faith,</hi> and neuer denieth it to be faith, yet dare say, <hi>that it</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Caluin</hi> 3. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. c.</hi> 2. §. 10.</note>
      <hi>is vnworthie the name of faith:</hi> When the Scripture often times and most directly calleth the Eucharist <hi>the bodie of Christ,</hi> and not once directly denieth it to be his bodie, yet dare say, <hi>it is not his bodie.</hi> And the like they doe in many other matters, wherin if they controll not the meaning of the holie Ghoste; at least they correct his speech, and reforme it according to the square of their new doctrin. Far otherwise proceeded the holie Fathers, who would not suffer so much as a letter or syllable of the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be altered: And as S. Austin grauely aduertized. <hi>Philosophers may speake as they please, but we speake according</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>de Ciuit. c.</hi> 23.</note>
      <hi>to a certaine rule, lest licencie in words breed impious opinions of the thing which they signifie.</hi> Yea Protestants them selues some times will seeme to be very carefull of the words and phrases of Scripture. For thus speaketh Luther: <hi>If the</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In Confutat. Latomi. f.</hi> 227</note>
      <hi>Scripture terme any thing sin, beware thou beest not moued by any words of theirs, who (as if they could speake better) deny it to be sin.</hi> And Caluin: <hi>There is to be taken out of Scripture a</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Instit. c.</hi> 13. §. 3.</note>
      <hi>certaine forme of thinking &amp; speaking, by which all the thoughts</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>of our mynd and words of our mouth are to be examined.</hi> Beza <note place="margin">Ad defens. Castell.</note> also: <hi>I see that all godlie and learned Diuines haue euer taught, that the holie Ghost gouerned not onely the mynd, but also the tongue and pen: in so much as concerning the wonders of God, not onely nothing can be saied of any mā more truly or more habily, but also nether so grauely nor so properly.</hi> Likewise Bucer: <note place="margin">Prefat. in Math.</note>
      <hi>No wisdom of the flesh can reach to these misteries of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. Therefore, then we speake most plainly most perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuously and most surely of matters of faith, when we speake ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule and forme of Scripture.</hi> And otherwhere: <hi>we</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In Hospin. part.</hi> 2. <hi>Histor</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>must learne of the Scripture and the holie Ghoste, how to speake and think of euerie matter. Wherefore the holie Ghost his formes of speaking ought not to be corrected according to the iudgment of our reason.</hi> Thus they, which if they and theires had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, we should not haue had so much speech contrarie to the Scripture.</p>
   <p>13. The fift, and that no small, cōmoditie is, that by this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> worke wilbe taken from ministers all their false pretense of Scripture and of the worde of God, wherewith perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually they crie, that the Catholik faith is grounded onely vpon mens authoritie, and all their doctrin for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>south vpon the expresse Scripture and word of God, and <note place="margin">
         <hi>In c.</hi> 1. <hi>Galat. In Assert. art</hi> 2.</note> thereby draw the simple people to follow them. <hi>The Pope</hi> (faieth Luther) <hi>hauing no Scripture wherewith to defēd himself, vseth this onely and perpetuall argument against vs. The Church, the Church.</hi> Agayne: <hi>Our opinion is deliuered by these words of God, the contrarie, by the words of men.</hi> And otherwhere. <hi>All the Scripture standeth an our sides through all letters and tittles.</hi> Caluin: <hi>Papists find no weapons in Scripture, yea they</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In Actor.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>In Antid. sess.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>see it wholy against them.</hi> Agayne. <hi>I haue the whole Scripture on my side.</hi> And Sadeel: <hi>Our doctrin doth relie vpon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse worde of God?</hi> And in an other place: <hi>we professed in the fift article of our French Confession, that our faith is onely and wholie, and expressly grounded vpon the word of God as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>De vocat. Ministr. Ad art.</hi> 1. <hi>abiurat.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>in the Scripture.</hi> Fulk in Ioan. 5. note 2. <hi>Papists can not find a iote of Poperie allowed ether by expresse wordes of the Scripture, or by necessarie cōclusiō out of the same.</hi> And the like
<pb facs="11"/> most vaine pretence, this most impudent boast is most <note place="margin">
         <hi>Apol. Anglic p.</hi> 20. <hi>Pareus praefat lib. de Grat. Caluin epist.</hi> 193. <hi>Whitak. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monst.</hi>
      </note> manifestly refuted in this booke, wherein is clearly she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, that the Catholik doctrin, in more then 260. points denied by Protestants, is in expresse termes and most di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly taught and deliuered, by the Scripture, and in the same points the Protestants doctrin condemned: and that these in very deed do relie vpon their owne inferences out of Scripture, their owne conferences of places of Scripture and oppose their owne expositions, glosses, tropes, and figures, against the expresse words and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of almightie God.</p>
   <p>14. The sixt commoditie is, that though some obstinatly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> will not confesse, that in all these 260. points or in most of them, the Scripture or word of God doth expresly approue the Catholik doctrin and condemne the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, yet this he can not denie, but in all these points the holie Scripture both for word and for sense fauoureth more the Catholik doctrin then the Protestant: which if ignorant Protestants would mark, they would not be so easily misled. For as for words, in all these 260. points we <note place="margin">Catholiks ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage ouer Protestants. For words of Scripture.</note> vse the very same or equiualent words with the Scripture: what she calleth faith, we call faith: what she calleth the bodie of Christ, we call the bodie of Christ. And so in others: whereas Protestants do the quite contrarie, as hath beene touched before, and shall appeare in the whole booke. And as for the forme of speach, where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">For phrase of Scripture.</note> affirmeth, we affirme; where the Scripture denieth, we deny: And contrarie wise the Protestants affirme, where the Scripture denieth; and deny, where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture affirmeth: as shalbe most euident to him that will read this booke. Besids no parte or parcell of the Scripture for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <note place="margin">For partes of Scripture.</note> Catholiks to denie it, but they hould all that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants account for Scripture and some what more: whereas Protestāts are compelled to reiect manie bookes of those which Catholiks and the holie Church heretofore hath beleeued to be Gods word, and fouly also to mangle and corrupt these bookes which they admit. Moreouer Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks
<pb facs="11"/> refuse no authenticall edition or translation of the <note place="margin">For transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> Scripture: but Protestants will sland to no translation. And thus much touching the words of Scripture. As for <note place="margin">For the sense of Scripture.</note> the sense thereof: Catholiks in all these 260. points do admit that sense, which the expresse words of Scripture, and they spoaken of purpose to declare Gods mynd doe of them selues proporse: which sense Protestants reiect and force the quite contrarie. Agayne, scarce in any of these 260. articles Catholiks are driuen to any answere which hath any shew of a shift or euasion, because in them (as I saied) they embrace the natiue and proper sense of the words of Scripture: but Protestants in euerie one of them are driuen to sundrie and foule shifts, because they refuse the naturall and plaine sense of Gods word. Besids, Catholiks in all these 260. points dare stand to the iudgment of the expresse worde of God according to that sentence which of them selues with out all helpe, force or pressing of Catholiks they doe pronounce: Protestants dare not in these articles stand to the iudgment of Gods expresse worde, vnles they may wrest, wring, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete it as they thinke best. Finally, Catholiks in none of all these questions reiect that sense of Scripture, which is deliuered by vnanimous consent of the holie Fathers, Councells, or Church. Protestants refuse it in manie. Seing therefore Catholiks haue the aduantage ouer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, not onely for Fathers, Councells, Church, mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, the like, but also that they haue such and so great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantages ouer them in more then 260. points of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, both for the expresse worde, and plaine sense of the Scripture, it is plaine willfulnes and carelesnes of saluation to leaue Catholiks for to follow Protestants. I would to God, that Protestants would (as they pretend) follow the expresse word of God, and embrace that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <note place="margin">Note.</note> which the expresse word of God most fauoureth, reiect that which it most disliketh; and enquire diligently whether the Catholik or Protestant religion can in more points of controuersie proue her doctrin by the pure and
<pb facs="12"/> expresse written word of God without the mixture of any word of man, and by the pure sense therof, which of it self it affordeth without any help or exposition of man, when it is spoaken of purpose to declare Gods meaning vnto vs. Let that religion florish and be embraced, which in this conflict ouercomet: let that perish and be reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, which is ouercomen. And what more reasonable then to preferre Gods pure word before that which is not pure, mixt partely of Gods words, partely of mans. What more reafonable, then to preferre Gods direct speech, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mans inference or collection out of his speech? What more reasonable, then to follow rather Gods expresse words, then mans glosses, tropes, and figures? And finally, what more reasonable, then to follow that religion which in more then 260. points of controuersie is grounded vpon the pure word, the direct word, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse word of God, and hath against it nothing but mans mixt word, mans inference, mans glosses: rather then that which in all those points is condemned by the pure, direct, and expresse word of God, and supported onely by mans mixt word, mans inference, and mans glosses? For example: That the Eucharist is the bodie of Christ, we haue for vs in foure places of Scripture the pure, direct, and expresse word of God, saying: <hi>This is my bodie:</hi> and against vs there is not so much as once any pure word of God, saing directly and expresly: <hi>This is not my bodie.</hi> But onely mens inference out of a mixt word, to wit: <hi>Christs bodie is in heauen, and can not be in two places;</hi> which word is mixt, partely of Gods word, for the former parte, and of mens word, for the latter. And shall we thinke that in a matter of faith, which we can not know but by Gods teaching, his pure and expresse word is not to be preferred before mens inference out of a mixt word, which is in parte mens word? What els can we thinke vnles we will euen in Gods matters preferre men before God.</p>
   <p>15. The seauenth cōmoditie is that in this word are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered
<pb facs="12"/> all or the most vsuall shifts wherewith Protestāts vse to delude the testimonies of holie Scripture. Which surely is no lesse profitable, then to know the deceits of enemies with whom we are to fight. And as Tertullian saieth: <hi>VVoe be to him, who whiles he is in this life, knoweth not</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>De resur. c.</hi> 19.</note>
      <hi>the secrets of Heretiks.</hi> And these are the especiall profits and commodities which may be reaped by this work; Now let vs remoue certaine scruples or hinderances of the reaping of them.</p>
   <p>16. The first scruple may be about the vulgar Latin trās<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <note place="margin">Obiections or difficulties remoued.</note> which I follow in citing the words of Scripture. But to omit all which Catholiks produce for to proue that translation to be authenticall (because this is no place to treate of that matter) Protestants cōfessions here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may suffice, which may be seene in the Protestants Apologie for the Rom. Church Treat. 1. Sect. 10. subd. 4. to which I add, that Casoubon writeth. <hi>I acknowledg the Latin translation of the bible to be holie Scripture, and I account an vnperdonable fault to so much as doubt thereof:</hi> That Iuel. art. 17. sect. 4. saieth: <hi>It hath bene euer more generally receaued in the Church:</hi> That Beza in Luc. 1. confesseth: <hi>That the ancient interpreter did most religiously translate the Scripture.</hi> And in Luc. 8. v. 54. That him self had <hi>twoe ancient Greek copies which meruailously agreed with the vulgar Latin.</hi> And Prefat. in Testam. That the vulgar interpreter <hi>had a truer Greek copie then theirs now are.</hi> Whitaker also Cont. 1. q. 2. c. 7. graunteth, <hi>that the Latin Fathers commend it and iustly.</hi> Hounfrey l. 1. de Rat. interpret. affirmeth. <hi>That the old In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretor seemeth enough addicted to the proprietie of the word.</hi> Moreouer Luther and Protestants commonly confesse, that Catholiks haue the word of God that the Fathers vsed the Latin translation in their disputes for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Catholik faith and confutation of Heresies. Besids Fulk in his preface to the Testament, saieth, that <hi>none of them calleth the vulgar translation of the new testament, Papisticall, as though it were translated by Papists, or els made so greatly for Papists when it is rightly vnderstood.</hi> Finally the
<pb facs="13"/> vulgar Latin translation differeth not from the originall Hebrew or Greek text, but in very few of those places which here I cite; and therefore it wilbe but vayne to cauil here about this matter.</p>
   <p>17. The secōd scruple may be, that some times the very <note place="margin">why Protest. can not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse them selues by the Scripture.</note> Scripture contradicteth it self in shew of words, and neuertheles in sense and meaning is neuer repugnant to it self. And therefore it is not so great meruail if Protestāts some time contradict the words of Scripture, nether can it be thereof inferred that the contradict the sense. To this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I answer, that the Scripture nether so often, nor in so many and so weightie matters, nor so manifestly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contradicteth it self in words, as Protestants doe: Nether need we so many and so incredible shifts for to reconcile the words of Scripture, as Protestants need to reconcile their sayings with the Scripture. Besids, God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> may speak as he pleaseth, &amp; therefore may for to exercise our faith and studie mingle some shew of contradiction in his words: but Protestants are bound to speak as God speaketh, and not to gaine say so much as his words, as doubtles they would not, if their meaning were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to his. Agayne, we may not out of anie seeming <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> contradiction in Gods words, infer anie opposition in his meaning, because we know, that he can not be contrarie to him self: but we know that Protestants can not be contrarie to Gods meaning, as we see that they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his words: and therefore out of their so frequent, so manifest, so direct contradicting of his words, we iustly inferre, that they also contradict his meaning, as we would inferre the same of anie Heretiks whatsoeuer. Moreouer <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> this cauil will no more help Protestants, then it will help anie other Heretiks, sith there were euer scarce anie, who so often, so plainly, so directly contradicted the expres word of God, as Protestants haue done. And therefore ether we may inferre out of the Protestants contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the words of God, that they also contradict his true meaning, or we can not inferre that of anie Heretiks
<pb facs="13"/> whatsoeuer. But of this more in the second booke cap. 1.</p>
   <p>18. The third scruple may be, that perhaps also <note place="margin">VVhy they can not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse them selues by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks.</note> some Catholik writers haue in shew of words contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the Scripture. But to this I answere that this is to accuse others, not to cleare them selues: Let them first an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere for them selues, before they recriminate others. And if anie of them will goe about to lay the like fault vpon Catholiks, let him keep these most iust and equal conditions. First, let him not medle with other matters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> then such as are in controuersie betwixt vs and them, as I touch no other matters. Secondly, let him bring forth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in so manie controuersies, so manifest and so direct testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of holie Scripture agreeing with their doctrin both in wordes and sense, and opposite to our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, as I haue brought. <hi>Thou must proue</hi> (saieth Tertullian) <hi>as euidently as we proue. Giue me a proof which I demand like to</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cont. Prax. c.</hi> 11. <hi>De vnit. c.</hi> 6. 24.</note>
      <hi>mine.</hi> And S. Austin: <hi>Produce as cleare testimonies as these are which we produce to you. We demande some manifest place which needeth no interpreter.</hi> Thirdly, let him shew that the Councell of Trent contradicteth as directly so many and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> so expres places of Scripture, and that in so weightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as we haue shewed that theire confessions of faith, <hi>of which</hi> (as they say) <hi>they make almost as great account of, as</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vorstius prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. Antil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praefat. Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagm.</note>
      <hi>we doe of the Councell of Trent.</hi> Fourthly, let him shew, that so many and so famous Catholik writers haue in so many and so great controuersies contradicted the expres propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions or assertions of the holie Scripture, as we haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> shewed of the Protestant writers. I say <hi>Propositions,</hi> or <hi>Assertions,</hi> because it is a farre greater matter to contradict the proportions of Scripture, in which it pronounceth a thing to be, or not to be; to be such, or not to be such, then to varie onely from some of the words wherewith here or there it signifieth this or that thing. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, it is a farre greater matter to deny the Eucharist to be the bodie of Christ, which the Scripture often times &amp; plainly affirmeth, then not to call it bread as some times
<pb facs="14"/> the Scripture doth, but neuer directly saieth that it is bread: Wherevpon Spalatensis l. 5. de repub. c. 6. writeth thus: <hi>It is one thing, for a seeming thing to be called by the name of the true thing, which the appearence doth shew; An other, to be said, This is that. The first may and is borne withall in all equiuocall termes, but not the latter.</hi> Wherefore let him omit these kinds of matters. Fiftly, let him shew, that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> haue done thus, not by the way, treating of other matters, but of set purpose, as Protestants haue done, who most often then contradict the Scripture in plaine termes, euen then when they answere it or comment vpon it. Lastly, let him shew, that Catholiks haue beene <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> forced for the maintenance of their doctrin to denie so many bookes, to corrupt so many places of holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to deuise, so many and so incredible shifts, as we haue shewed the Protestants haue done, or let him be ashamed to say, that Catholiks are as faultie in this kind, as Protestants be. Moreouer, though they could proue, that some Catholiks haue bene as faultie herein, as they are (which they can neuer proue) yet that would nothing preiudice the Chatholik Church, because her faith is not the doctrin of one or of many Catholiks, but the common of them all: But the Protestant faith is in many points the doctrin of some or of manie of them, euerie one of them making that a point of faith, which him self gathereth out of Scripture, whether his fellows beleeue it, or no. Besids, the Catholik Church, if she find anie thing in the writinges of her children contrarie to holie Scripture, she nether alloweth nor dissembleth it, but commandeth it to be blotted out, as is euident by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatorie Indices; but the Protestant ether approueth or dissembleth the errors of her writers, and so maketh them her owne. <note place="margin">VVhy all Cōtradictiōs here related may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to the Prot. Church.</note>
   </p>
   <p>19. The fourth scruple may be, that all the Cōtradictions against holie Scripture, which are here rehearsed out of Protestant writers, were not made nor allowed of all Protestants, or of their Church, and therefore all of them
<pb facs="14"/> are not to be imputed to all Protestāts or to their Church. I answere. First, that very many of the Contradictions <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> against holie Scripture here set downe are found in their Confessions of faith, and in other writings set forth in their common name: which Contradictions are most iustly attributed to their Church, and these alone suffice to shew, that the very faith and common doctrin of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants is directly opposite both to the word and sense of holie Scripture. Secondly, almost all these Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> are taken out of the writings of the first, the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, and famousest teachers, guides, and leaders of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and therefore ether Protestants must acknowledge these Contradictions, or reiect the doctrin of their first and chefest Maisters as directly contrarie to Gods word. Thirdly, all the Contradictions or Antitheses here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> are taken out of famous writers and mainteiners of the Protestant faith, whose doctrin the Protestant Church hath not publikly condemned, nor compelled the Authors thereof to recall it, nor commanded it to be taken out of their writings, and therefore, if not by publike consent, yet by silence and dissembling approueth it, and so (as I saied before) maketh it her owne. Fourthly, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> obiect to the Catholik Church whatsoeuer any Cotholik writer, though neuer so obscure, hath written: why then may not we better obiect vnto their Church what many and the most famous of their writers haue published? Finally my intention in this workes not to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> shew the Contradictions of this or that Protestant man or Church against the holie Scripture; but of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants in generall, especially of the cheefest and most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</p>
   <p>But whether the Contradictions of Scripture made by <note place="margin">And though they could not yet that would suffice.</note> many and famous Protestant writers, and not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but dissembled by their Church, be to be obiected to their Church, or no, these points ensuing will suffice to my purpose. First, that the commun fairh of Protestants is in many and weightie articles directly contrarie to the
<pb facs="15"/> expresse word and cleare meaning of holie Scripture, as is euident by that which in diuers articles I recite out of their Confessions of faith and other their common wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. The second is, that touching many other matters, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that self same doctrin which I cite out of other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, is conteined in their Confessions of faith though it be not deliuered there in termes so expresly opposite to the words of holie Scripture, as it is by other Protestants. The third is, that much of that Protestant Doctrin which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> here if cite as opposite to holie Scripture, is in very deed the common beleef of Protestants, albeit it be not inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Confessions. The fourth point is, that those <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Protestants whose words I alledge, knew the common <note place="margin">
         <hi>Apol. Anglic Cont.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. c.</hi> 42.</note> doctrin of Protestants, as well as anie who now will denie or reiect that doctrin. The fift is, that Iuel, Whitaker, Feild, and diuers other Protestants auouch, that there is no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall difference in doctrin amongst the cheefe Protestāts, which ether they must confesse to befalse, or maintaine <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the doctrin which here I cite out of their cheefest writers. The sixt point is, that housoeuer the doctrin which I cite, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> is not in all points the Doctrin of this Protestant man or Church, yet it is as I saied Protestant doctrin, taught and maintained by famous Protestants, such as our English Protestants hould communion withall, and account them their brethrē in Christ, And therefore ether let thē defend their doctrin, or refuse their cōmunion. The seuenth point is, that whether all or most of the Protestant doctrin, which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> here I cite as opposite to holie Scripture, be the cōmon do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin or beleefe of Protestāts, or no, this alone would suffice to my purpose, that the doctrin of the first, chefest, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mousest Protestant preachers and leaders, is in more then <note place="margin">Note.</note> 260. points of controuersie quite opposite to the expresse words of holie Scripture. For thereby euerie one may see, that the first &amp; cheefest Protestāt preachers, did not teach the word of God, but the word of the Diuel quite contrarie there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o: were not ministers of the word of God, but mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Diuel: not Reformers, but Deformers: not
<pb facs="15"/> sent of God, but thrust on by the Diuel: not lightned from heaune, but blinded from hel: not Apostles, but Apostatas: not Pastores but wolues: who vnder a most false pretence of the word of God, did most directly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it, drew Cristians from Gods truth to the Diuels lies, from the lap of the Catholik Church to the den of theues, from the assured path of saluation to the open way of damnation.</p>
   <p>Finally I aduertise the Reader, that if at anie time I vse anie sharp words against Protestants, I intend them onely against their teachers and leaders, yet vse I the common name of Protestants, that the rest may know that the crimes which I obiect vnto them, proceed of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, and thereby flie and reiect it, lest they become par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the crimes. I shew them the gulfe of impietie, into which their guides doe lead them: let them not be offended with me, that I set before their eyes the impietie of the doctrin which they are tought, but let them be angrie with their teachers who vnder the most false pretense of Scripture and Gods word, haue thaught them such impious doctrin and so contrarie to Gods words. And I hartely pray God, and euer shal, that he open their eyes, that they may see the most imminent and greiuous danger wherein they stand, and auoide it, &amp; lighten with his true light that zeale which they haue to his word, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> lest they perish for euer with them who had zeale but not according to knowledge.</p>
   <pb facs="16"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>