<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND LADY ABBESSE Of the English Religious Dames, of the Order of S. Benet in Gant.</title>
           <author>W., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123265_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21148</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123265</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND LADY ABBESSE Of the English Religious Dames, of the Order of S. Benet in Gant.</title>
                 <author>W., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of mentall prayer : With another of the presence of God. Composed by the R. Fa. Alfonsus Rodriguez, of the Society of Iesus. And translated out of the Spanish, into English</title>
                 <author>Rodríguez, Alfonso</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 303, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND LADY ABBESSE</hi> Of the English Religious Dames, of the Order of S. Benet in Gant.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME, Since by the instinct of <hi>Nature,</hi> all things acknovvledge the <hi>Fountayne,</hi> vvhence originally they flovv: I
<pb facs="6"/>should haue vvronged this Excellent <hi>TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE,</hi> had I directed the same, into any other, then your <hi>LADIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HIPPS</hi> Hands, from vvhome I first receaued it; and to vvhome, by the <hi>TRANSLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOVRS Intention,</hi> and for many other respects, it is singularly due.</p>
   <p>And although, this be but a small <hi>Part,</hi> or one single <hi>Tracte</hi> only, of the admirable <hi>VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KES</hi> of the <hi>Authour;</hi> yet
<pb facs="6"/>hath it byn iudged fit, to be published alone; to the end the pious <hi>Reader</hi> may not be depriued of so <hi>Excellent</hi> a <hi>Treasure,</hi> vntill the <hi>ƲƲhole</hi> may come to light. And I doubt not, but that the printing of this, vvilbe no small <hi>Motiue</hi> to the <hi>ƲƲorthy TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATOVR,</hi> to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard vvith the rest; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his former Deuout <hi>Labours,</hi> in furthering of Spirituall <hi>Matters,</hi> are highly esteemed, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
<pb facs="7"/>by all pious, and vnpartiall Readers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
   <p>In this Treatise <hi>(MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAME)</hi> may the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout <hi>Contemplant,</hi> read vvithout <hi>ƲƲearinesse,</hi> &amp; repeat vvithout <hi>Tedious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;</hi> sucking euermore from hence, most svveet <hi>Delightes</hi> of Diuine <hi>Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort;</hi> the vvhich do so sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate, as they procure also nevv <hi>Appetite,</hi> in those, vvho addict themselues to the practice of <hi>MEN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TAL PRAYER.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>For, amongst all the <hi>Spirituall BOOKES,</hi> novv extant, I knovv not any one, more generally <hi>Applauded,</hi> or accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more <hi>Necessary,</hi> for such, as attend to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Exercise of <hi>Prayer,</hi> then this: The <hi>AƲ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOVR</hi> vvherof, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing byn not only tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp, all his life tyme, in the <hi>Schoole</hi> of <hi>ƲER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TƲE;</hi> but also, one of the most expert <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> of <hi>SPIRIT,</hi> that are knovvne, at this day,
<pb facs="8"/>in the Christian vvorld.</p>
   <p>Vnto this <hi>Tracte</hi> of <hi>MENTAL PRAY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER,</hi> haue I adioyned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other more briefe, <hi>Of the Presence of God,</hi> made by the same <hi>AVTHOVR.</hi> For, as these tvvo pious <hi>Exercises,</hi> haue such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance one of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they cannot be separated in <hi>Practice:</hi> So vvas it thought conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to combine them togeather in one <hi>Booke;</hi> that the same might be more entierely <hi>vsefull,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>for the arriuing vnto a true, and perfect <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Deuotion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ʋnion</hi> vvith God.</p>
   <p>I vvill not enter into further <hi>Discourse,</hi> in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se heerof; as vvell, not to be ouer-tedious to your <hi>LADISHIPPE;</hi> as not to hinder you from enioying the svveet <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> vvhich you vvill (no doubt) receaue, by the Perusall. As for the small <hi>Paines,</hi> I may haue taken in the publishing of it, the <hi>Benefit</hi> vvhich many
<pb facs="9"/>soules vvill reape heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, shalbe my <hi>Comfort;</hi> and my poore <hi>Prayers</hi> shall euer be attending You, for the perpetuall <hi>Increase</hi> of your spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Happines:</hi> Whereof I humbly beseech You, to make him Partaker, vvho hath dedicated Himselfe, to remayne euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your La</hi>
         <seg rend="sup">p</seg>. <hi>deuoted Seruant.</hi> I. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>