<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO▪ ARTHVRE Lord CHICHESTER, Baron of BELFAST, Lord high Treasurer of Jreland, and one of his Majesties most Honorable Priuy Counsell, of that KINGDOME.</title>
           <author>Bateson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123069_Fr2_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72612</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1587</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123069</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO▪ ARTHVRE Lord CHICHESTER, Baron of BELFAST, Lord high Treasurer of Jreland, and one of his Majesties most Honorable Priuy Counsell, of that KINGDOME.</title>
                 <author>Bateson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second set of madrigales to 3. 4. 5. and 6. parts : apt for viols and voyces. Newly composed by Thomas Bateson, Bacheler of Musicke, organist, and master of the children of the cathedrall church of the blessed Trinitie, Dublin, in the realme of Ireland</title>
                 <author>Bateson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>158 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="20"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="5 letters">
         <desc>•••••</desc>
      </gap>▪ <hi>ARTHVRE</hi> Lord <hi>CHICHESTER,</hi> Baron of BELFAST, Lord high Treasurer of <hi>Jreland,</hi> and one of his Majesties most Honorable Priuy Counsell, of that KINGDOME.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing to expose these my vnworthy Labours to publicke view, and vniuersall censure, I was imboldened in a double respect to become so humbly ambitious, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that they may take sanctuary vnder your Honors all pleasing name and safest patronage; First, because they were solely entended for your Honors priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, after your tedious imployments in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of the common-wealth, being then his Maiesties most worthy Deputy, and swaying the sword and scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of authority amongst vs, in this kingdome of <hi>Ireland;</hi> And as your Honour hath beene pleased to vouchsafe vnto them your priuate applause, and thereby to occasion me for more variety to enlarge them to this number: So I am bolde to father them vpon your Honor, not doubting but as in your allowance of them, I made vse of your goodnesse▪ so in your protection of them, I may make vse of your greatnesse. Secondly, it is not the least of your Honors fauours conferred vpon me, to grace me with your Honourable seruice, and to call me to a more immediate dependency vpon your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and therefore to auoide the blacke note of ingratitude, I held it my duty there to lay downe my worke, where I owe my seruice, and to desire to be no longer knowne, then I may be knowne with that relation I haue to your Honour; that so I might leaue a perpetuall testimony vnto the world of your Honours fauours vnto mee; of my affectionate desire, in some weake measure, to expresse my thankefulnesse to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. If I haue herein giuen content to these curious and hard-pleased times, the thankes belongs to your Honour, whose encouragements were my motiues with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse to vndertake this taske, with constancy to goe through it, with resolution to publish it to the censorious eare of the world. If I haue come short of popular expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, my hope is, that my mention of your Honorable name will procure pardon for a greater offence. And thus wishing vnto your Honor a continuall Harmony, composed of a comfortable delight of body, goods, and good name, with a daily increase of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, I humbly take leaue, crauing pardon for this boldnesse, and desiring alwaies to be accounted</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours to be commanded in the best of his seruices THOMAS BATESON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>