<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE OF THE Authour to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123835_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13141</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23433</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123835</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE OF THE Authour to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sum or a brief collection of holy signes, sacrifices and sacraments : euen since the beginning of the worlde. And the true originall of the sacrifice of the masse. Translated out of French into Englishe by N. Lynge</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE OF THE Authour to the Reader.</head>
   <p>COnsidering the controuersies stirred vp amōg those that cal thēselues chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stians (some striuing to hold the vain su<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perstitiōs descended vnto them, frō their predicessors, some also inuenting nevve sects, scismes, and heresies, and other in number fevver, desiring vtterly to roote out the darkenes of ignoraunce, that the light of the veritie might shine) me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that the moste daungerous poyson that Satan vseth to make men mad vvith all, hath bene dravven out of the myne of the Masse, stuffed vvith good end, &amp; couered vvith good intention. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though manye haue soore trauailed to discouer vvith discriptions, anatomies, &amp; other vvorks of the Masse, this mina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rocke yet alvvayes more &amp; more to mine, &amp; contermine this fort, vvhich se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnminable (after I had read the Elassopolitains cōmentaries treating of the number, dignitie, povver &amp; cōditiōs of the high bishops, chief priests &amp; sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers
<pb facs="3"/>
sins the creatiō of the vvorld) I haue dravvē out a brief sum of the holy signes sacrifices, &amp; sacramēts ordened of god frō time to time, the corruptiōs crept succes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>siuely into the church of god, &amp; specially here is described the true originall of the Masse, about the vvhich, presently men are fallen into so great cōtentiōs, &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siōs. For some inuey against it as lately forged, other defend it by long possessiō. And by these altrications the church of christ hath bene merueylously threshen vvith the flail of seditiō. But if thou (faith full reader) vvilt haue pacience of vvhat sect so euer thou be, papist, or protestant (reading this short discourse, &amp; tariyng til thou haue the bokes of the cōmētaries in their integritie) thou shalt knovv cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenly vvhat the originall of the masse is, partly very ancient &amp; partly nevv, vvho vvere her foūders &amp; patrons: &amp; to thend that thou maist beassured of the histories faithfully gathered: haue recourse to the authors coted in the mergent. Our good god inspire thee vvith his holy spirit.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>