<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123522_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10706</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20989.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123522</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Irish hubbub or, The English hue and crie : Breifely pursuing the base conditions, and most notorious offences of this vile, vaine, and wicked age. No lesse smarting then tickling. A merriment whereby to make the wise to laugh, and fooles to be angry. By Barnaby Rich gentleman, and seruant to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 61, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle-men, my custome is rather to lay mee downe to sleepe, then to sit idle: yet now to auoyd both, I haue betaken my selfe to my pen. And therfore if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that I write of, fall out to be but of a drowsie disposition, the wonder is not great. But hee that should keep a reckoning how hee spends his time, and would set downe an <hi>Item</hi> for thus many weekes, for thus many daies spent in idlenesse; and <hi>Item</hi> again, for thus many houres, for thus many minutes consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in sleepe; the Arethmetician that should cast vp the account, should finde the totall summe amount to iust nothing. If these lines therefore proue to bee any thing, they are better then either sleep or idlenesse.</p>
   <p>I haue meant them well; and I hope I shall not need with the Painter, that taking vpon him to picture forth the formes of sundry beasts, so vnperfectly performed them, that he was driuen to write ouer their heads, <hi>This is a Lyon, this is an Elephant, this is an Vnicorne:</hi> but what I haue aimed at, I haue gone so neere the marke, that although not leuelling at any mans priuate person, yet so directly expressing the condition of the time, that there is none (I thinke) to contradict it.</p>
   <p>But we are growne so wise and sharp-sighted in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding other mens writings; that those passages that are but meant and set downe in a generall manner, they will draw to such particular constructions, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour
<pb facs="4"/>
himselfe neuer so much as dreamt on.</p>
   <p>They can poison euery mans labours with their lookes, and of euery line they can make a libell. But thou that art not partiall in iudgement, nor doest, not beare a guilty conscience, iudge of these but as thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest them true. And so farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>