<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HER MAIESTIE OF BOHEMIA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123356_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08104</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22941.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HER MAIESTIE OF BOHEMIA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bausme de Galaad : pour la guérison, d'ún [sic] coeur navrè [sic] : offert a sa Maiesté de Boheme: en quatre langues</title>
                 <author>Souterius, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kranepoel, Herman Theunisz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Haarlem</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>302 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Wedding pamphlets</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HER MAIESTIE OF BOHEMIA.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riange,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Licke as in the time of sicknes, it is a misery, to be wholly destituit of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians; Also is it in the daye of heavinesse (Zepha. 1.15. of anguist Ier. 30.7. of tribulation 2. Esdr. 16. vers. 66.) of trouble Esay 22. 5. To haue no Comforter Lam. 1.21. No Physition Ier. 8.22. <hi>So that there might be sayde,</hi> I looked for some to haue pitty on me, but
<pb facs="3"/> there was none. Psal. 69.20. I streched out my hands, and there was none, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me. Lam. 1.17. They haue heard, that I morned, but there is none to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me vers. 21.</p>
   <p>Nevertheles <hi>the childeren of God</hi> sometimes want ont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde comfort, yet they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wāt the comfort of the Lord there God; For his mercy, comforteth them. Psal. 119.76. In like maner hath the Lord in former ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me comforted his People, and he hath redeemed Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem. Esay. 52.9. He is the Lord God, and in that great is his mercy towards
<pb facs="3"/> them that feare him. Psalm. 103.11. <hi>For vnto them he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,</hi> I, even I am he, that comforteth you. Esay 51.12. As one whome his mother comforteth, so will I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you, and ye shall be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. Esay 66.13. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore most <hi>Gratious Queene,</hi> I am assured that your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie in this (the which is the highest and most excelent comfort) can haue no want: for your Majestie keeps the wayes of the Lord, neyther doe you wickedly against your God. All his lawes are before you, and you cast not his commandements from you. Psal. 18.21.22. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="4"/> wants your M<seg rend="sup">tie</seg> for the present Godly comforters, the which saye vnto your M<seg rend="sup">tie</seg>. <hi>Be you stronge, feare not.</hi> Esay 35.4. <hi>The Lord is with you.</hi> Iudg. 6.12. <hi>Beholde your God cometh, he will saue you.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say 35.4. Neverthelesse that Christian feelinge which I haue suffered concerninge the lose of your M<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> sonne Fridericus (for it touched my hert) forceth me in this Dialogue te comfort your M<seg rend="sup">tie</seg> 2. Cor. 1.4. The which I haue also done, in six Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Latine, dedicated vnto his most Royall M<seg rend="sup">tie</seg> the Kinge of Bohemia, your Lord. I hope it will please
<pb facs="4"/> your M<seg rend="sup">tie</seg>, accordinge vnto your accostomed goodnes, and gratious favour, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this my on desyred ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Which althoug' it may seeme on timely, yet I haue till this present defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the same, accordinge to the rules of the best Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whoe in a vehement flux of Phlegma praescribe not a present remedie, but much rather vse outwarde application, sufficient to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest the Humor: Alsoo must we be silent when the grief is fresh, till the grieued in proces of time be more apt to admit true and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingh Consolation. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="5"/> I moste humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sech your gratious Majestie, to take it soo: Which bein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge done, it will bringe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at joye vnto me, and shall alwayes remaine your M<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> most affectioned servant, whoe will not cease contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually to pray vnto God, for your M<seg rend="sup">tie</seg>, and yours. Ephes. 1.16. In Haerlem.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Majesties Most humble Servant,</hi> DANIEL SOVTERIVS <hi>Minister of Gods Worde, in the Nederduch Church, in Haerlem.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>