<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR ROBERT DVCE, Knight Barronet, Lord Major of the City of LONDON: and to the Right Worship∣full the Sheriffes and Aldermen of the same; W. I. P. wisheth increase of knowledge and grace in Christ here, that you may reigne with him hereafter in glory.</title>
           <author>P., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S123301_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73282</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23505</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S123301</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR ROBERT DVCE, Knight Barronet, Lord Major of the City of LONDON: and to the Right Worship∣full the Sheriffes and Aldermen of the same; W. I. P. wisheth increase of knowledge and grace in Christ here, that you may reigne with him hereafter in glory.</title>
                 <author>P., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iethroes covnsell to Moses: or, A direction for magistrates : A sermon preached at St. Saviours in Southwarke. March 5. 1621. Before the honourable iudges by that reverent divine Thomas Svtton Dr. in Divinity</title>
                 <author>Sutton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 29, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR ROBERT DVCE, Knight Barronet, Lord Major of the City of LONDON: and to the Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the Sheriffes and Aldermen of the same; <hi>W. I.</hi> P. wisheth increase of knowledge and grace in Christ here, that you may reigne with him hereafter in glory.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING a Sermon come to my hands, of the Counsell of <hi>Iethro</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Moses</hi> the servant of the Lord, how hee might with more ease to himselfe and the people decide all controversies; as it was preached before the Iudges in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> by that Reverend and learned Divine, <hi>Mr. Dr. Sutton,</hi> late Preacher at <hi>Saviours:</hi> The which Sermon giveth direction, not onely to Iudges, but also to all Magistrates in the Land, how to carry themselves in their severall places against all offenders, and betwixt man and man: It being a subject of so necessary a use; it is thought meete to publish it in these evill times, because the seate of Iustice is now had in much contempt by many who live as if there were no God in heaven to behold their wickednesse, nor
<pb facs="3"/> Magistrate on earth to punish their horrible crimes. And seeking out for a Patron, I thought fit to dedicate it to your Honour, and Worships: To your Honour, who in your Shreivalty shewed your great zeale and love to the Gospell of Christ, that upon a discovery of the practises of Iesuites and Priests, rose at midnight to execute the warrant of <hi>Sir Robert Nanton,</hi> then Secretary to King <hi>Iames</hi> of most blessed memory; where was taken seventeene Altars for their Popish Masse, ten Copes, twelve or thirteene Surpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, above ten thousand Popish bookes, besides severall pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of Letters, partly come from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> and going to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> &amp;c. And seeing the Lord hath advanced your Honour into the chaire of <hi>Moses,</hi> under our gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King <hi>CHARLES,</hi> the Lord give you courage and zeale, against all Popish superstitition and Idolatry: requesting you that you would be pleased to peruse the short directions in it: That so you may with the rest of your Right Worshipfull Brethren, the better direct all and severall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in their severall places, under you in your severall Wards; that they also may be men of courage, fearing God. To that end I beseech the Lord of heaven, who directed his servant <hi>Moses,</hi> so to direct your hearts, that you may have both the courage and zeale of <hi>Moses,</hi> against all idolatrous Priests and Iesuites that swarme in the Land, whose trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous practises this worthy Sermon doth at large disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and so put them out of all hope of gaining any Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites here among you. Thus daily praying unto the Lord on your behalfe, I humbly take my leave.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours, and Worships, to be commanded in the Lord Iesus: <hi>W. I.</hi> P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>