<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROLOGVE TO THE FIRST PART OF THE Booke, intituled the Mount of Caluary. Com∣piled by the reuerend Father, lord Antonie de Gueuara, bishop of Mondonneda, prea∣cher, and chronicler vnto the empe∣rour Charles the fift.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124965_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72226</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12448.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124965</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROLOGVE TO THE FIRST PART OF THE Booke, intituled the Mount of Caluary. Com∣piled by the reuerend Father, lord Antonie de Gueuara, bishop of Mondonneda, prea∣cher, and chronicler vnto the empe∣rour Charles the fift.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mysteries of Mount Calvary : Made by the reverend father in God, lord Anthonie de Gueuara, bishop of Mondonnedo, preacher and chronicler, vnto Charles the fift, Emperour. In this booke the authour handleth all the mysteries, of the Mount of Caluarie, from the time tha Christ was condemned by Pilat, vntill he was put into the sepulchre, by Ioseph and Nichodemus</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 409, 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PROLOGVE TO THE FIRST PART OF THE Booke, intituled the Mount of Caluary. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by the reuerend Father, lord Antonie de Gueuara, bishop of Mondonneda, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and chronicler vnto the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Charles the fift.</head>
   <div type="section">
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vme tibi aromata, aequalis ponderis, &amp; cum in tenuissimum puluerum contunderis, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ex eo, in tabernaculo foederis.</hi> Said God vnto <hi>Moses,</hi> in the 30 chapter of <hi>Exod.</hi> As if he should say; Now <hi>Moses,</hi> thou doest know that I haue made thee a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle where thou mayst pray, and haue giuen thee priests with whom thou mayst pray, &amp; appointed thee sacrifices which thou shalt offer vp vnto me. Now I will teach thee how thou shalt offer vp incence vnto me, and with what. Thou shalt take therefore, sweet and odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous spices; as Baulme, Onicha, Galbanum, and pure Frankincense, and of ech of them, the like quantitie and waight, and cast them all into a morter, and pound them verie small, euen into dust; and then cast them on the coales in a golden censor, because that all the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle may smell sweet with it. Without all doubt this is a wonderfull figure: but yet the accomplishment of it more wonderfull; seeing that we are taught thereby what we shall offer vnto our Lord, and with what we
<pb facs="3"/> shall please him, and also with what we shall pacifie him. It seemeth by these words, that our Lord will exclude all offering of vncleane and vnsauoury thinges, to the end that all such things should not be offered in the san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: and thereupon it is, that our Lord did no lesse forbid vs to pollute his temple with vncleane things, than violate it with mans bloud. Agreeing vnto this, the Lord in the old law, did forbid him to be a priest in his temple, who had an vncomely nose, bleard &amp; drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping eies, a crooke backe, club feet, lame hands, a skabby body, or were otherwise deformed and mishapen of any member. The meaning of the giuer of the law was, that all which they should offer vnto him, should be cleane, and the priest which did offer very, sound and perfect; the reason is, because that our Lord doth not make so great reckoning of the thing which is offered, as he doth of him who doth offer. If as that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement was obserued in the old law, it should also be kept in the new: it would seeme a verie ridiculous thing, &amp; a <hi>Mosaicall</hi> ceremonie, because there are many priests in the church of God this day, the which although they be peraduenture lame in their lineaments, yet are good in their works, and holy in their desires. O how little the Lord doth regard, that the minister and priest of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, be straight or crooked, beautifull or not, because that the sacrifices which we offer vp vnto him, are not accepted for the hands which doth offer them, but for the offerer. <hi>S. Augustine</hi> saith, That that which in the old law was a figure, is now in the Church trueth; that which vnto them was the letter, is vnto vs the spirit; that which they did dreame of, we do see; and that which they did hope for, we hold. In so much, that in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the old law, we ought not to regard that which
<pb facs="3"/> the letter doth command, but that which the spirit doth teach. Tell me I pray thee, when God did command in the law that they should offer odoriferous sauours on his altar, and prohibit them to present vnsauourie ones; had he a nose like a man to smell the good, or head like a man to dislike or greeue at the bad? It is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, that when the giuer of the law did ordaine these things, and when the holy Ghost did write them, that he did leuell at higher matters, &amp; pretend profounder mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries than those which the <hi>Mosaicall</hi> law did sound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the true accompt which God doth make of Balme and Frankincense, is nothing els but the acceptance of a pure and cleane heart. Comming then vnto the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, it is to be noted, that with many &amp; sundry conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, God did cōmand in his law that they should offer vnto him those sweet and odoriferous spices; wherof, if there did want any one conditiō, al which they did offer was nothing worth. The law did thē cōmand, that those spices should be of a sweet sauour, verie clean and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; not such as the priest would, But such as the law did appoint: that is to say, Baulme, Onicha, Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, and Frankincense: and that of these none should be wanting, nor any added vnto them. God did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise command in the law, that they should all be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured and waighed so exactly, that there should not be so much as a dram more of the one than of the other. God did also command in the law, that all those aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall spices should be pounded very small, and sifted: and then by the hands of the Apothicary, molded and wrought. Insomuch, that if by the hand of the Priest they were to be offred, by the hands of the Apothicary, they should be compounded. The Lord did promise, &amp; giue his credit and word vnto all such as did offer this
<pb facs="4"/> high kind of oblation, and bestow their money vpon it, to heare them presently in the tabernacle, and yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their petitions. What is the holy tabernacle, where God did command those spices to be offered: but our God made man, the sonne of the liuing God? This is the high hill from whence we looke; this is the Tower whither we withdraw our selues; the Temple where we be baptized; the Tabernacle where we doe saue our selues, and the Sanctuary where we doe reforme our selues. What is the altar of incorruptible wood vpon which that holy incense was offered, but only the crosse, vpon which good Iesus was crucified? Thou art the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of incorruptible wood, O my good Iesus; seeing that in the old law the sacrifices which they did offer, the priest which did offer them, and the ceremonies with which he did offer them, are all at an end: but thy crosse, O my God, shall neuer haue an end. There is great reckoning to be made of the drie tree, on which Christ suffered; but farre greater of his tender members, with which he did suffer, considering that with the torments of them we were redeemed, &amp; with the loue of Christ pardoned. VVhat were the aromaticall and sweet spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were offered by the Priest vpon the altar of the tabernacle; but the most high workes, which on the mount of <hi>Caluary,</hi> were done by the son of God? VVith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all comparison, the workes which the sonne of God did in the mount of <hi>Caluary,</hi> were far greater than those which his father did in the captiuitie of Aegypt, because that there he did kill other mens children, but here he did kill his own proper sonne, whose life he did not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, because he would pardon our faults. O loue neuer heard of before! O infinite charitie! VVho did euer heare or see, that for to pardō the seruant, thou shouldst
<pb facs="4"/> put to death, the sonne? What clemency did ouercome thee? what charitie did bind thee? that freely without any interest of thine, thou shouldest lay the punishment vpon thy selfe, to vnload me of the fault? <hi>Adam</hi> did cast the fault vpon <hi>Eue,</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> vpon the Serpent, and the Serpent did cast it vpon all mankind. And thou, O good Iesus, doest thou excuse me, who am culpable, and blame thy selfe being innocent; and I hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the theft, doest thou yeeld to be punished? In a farre other maner and means thou didst deliuer me from the power of the diuell, than <hi>Moses</hi> did the Iewes out of the captiuitie of Aegypt, because that there the bloudy waters did stinke, and the flies which fell, the putrified frogges, the first borne children which were slaine, and the dead cattell. But on the mount of Caluary, what is there that did stincke, or what did not smell very sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? The teares which he dropped, the sighes which he gaue, the bloud which he shed, the side which he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the body which suffered, and the loue with which he suffered, were the true spices which God did worke, and the high Baulme, which the eternall father did perfume with. Before that the sonne of God did suffer on the mount of Caluary, it was a dreadfull place to behold, stincking to dwell in: but after that his sacred members were nailed on the crosse, like vnto pretious ointments, and sweete sauours, he did take away the stinke of all sinnes, which doe sauour worse than all the dead bodies. VVhat other things are those foure sweet perfumes, with the which God did command the holy sanctuary to be perfumed withall; but the will with which the sonne of God did suffer, the cruell death which he did suffer, the great patience which he had, and the infinite great charitie which did moue him? I
<pb facs="5"/> confesse that the martyrs did die of their owne will, but they will not denie me, but they died of necessitie, only the son of God was he who died without necessitie, and voluntarily. Vpon those wordes <hi>desiderio desideraui, S. Barnard</hi> saith, a good Iesus, O the loued of my soule, who among mortall men, doth so much desire to make his life perpetuall, as thou didst desire to loose thine for mine? VVhat pleasure and ioy wilt thou take aboue in the other world with thy elect, seeing that here vpon earth, thou didst call the day on which thou didst suffer, <hi>Aester?</hi> The Lord did also command, that the incense and Galbanū which they should offer vnto him, should be so iustly waighed, that they should put no more of the one than of the other, thereby to let vs vnderstand that the son of God did equally, and indifferently shed his bloud, for the small, and for the great; for the poore, and for the rich; for the dead, and for the liuing. <hi>Origen</hi> vpon the Canticles, saith; That oftentimes our Lord doth bestow his fauours and graces more or lesse, when he pleaseth, and how he pleaseth, and vnto whom he pleaseth: but in that which toucheth the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, he made all men equall, seeing he died no more for one than for another. <hi>Anselmus</hi> in an Epistle saith; VVhat do I care my brother, that thou art stronger than I, more noble in bloud, more beautifull in body, and more renowned in dignitie, seeing we are by one God created, by one Christ redeemed, and by one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost gouerned? VVhat doth it meane, that there should be as much Frankincense as Galbanum, and as much Galbanum as Frankincense; but that Christ did shed as much bloud for the labouring man, which cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth stubble, as for the Prince who sitteth in his thron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>▪ <hi>Chrisostome</hi> saith, When the sonne of God did impart
<pb facs="5"/> his pretious bloud, he did better it vpon no man, hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no man, nor depriued no man of it: but if afterward it had greater force in some, than in other some, it is not through the fault of him who gaue it, but of his who did not well employ it.</p>
      <p>What meaneth it, that all these sweete spices should not be offered vp in the holy temple, vntill they were pounded in a morter, and sifted through a siue: but that the mysteries of the passion of Christ, should be sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out with diligence, deeply considered and chewed with meditation; waighed with charitie, and wrought with many teares? <hi>Origen</hi> vpon this place saith, That if Storax and other sweet spices, be not broken, pounded, and cast into the fire, they giue no smell at all: In like manner, if the most high mysteries, and profound sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the passion of the sonne of God, be not well chewed and waighed, little profit and lesse consolation is reaped by them.</p>
      <p>The son of God hauing as he hath, his flesh so torne, his bloud so shed abroad, his bones so out of ioint, his sinews so wrested, his haire so cast about, and his friends so scattered; how wouldst thou tast and contemplat such high mysteries all at once: very well ground and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and also very well sifted in the brasen morter of thy heart, should all those holy mysteries be, and in such sort, that by the same steps that blessed Iesus doth go suffering, thou go following and contemplating, for otherwise thou shalt occupie much time, and receiue small pleasure. Vnground doth he offer vp incense, who in hast thinketh on the passion of Christ, and he small &amp; sifted doth offer vp sweet spices, who in those steps and stations which our Lord troad, suffering, doth go after him weeping. Is it much that thou shouldst shed teares
<pb facs="6"/> from thy eies, seeing that he did shed bloud for thee from his vains? <hi>S. Barnard</hi> saith, The sonne of God did not suffer himselfe to be beheaded, nor hanged, nor drowned, nor burnt, because they were all short deaths, but he would be crucified, because that that kind of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome was very long and greeuous: insomuch that as the loue was great with which he did die, so also his pleasure was, that the torment should be great and long which he did suffer. Seeing (saith <hi>Anselmus</hi>) that the son of God did not leaue bone, nor sinew, nor flesh, nor mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in all his body, in which he was not tormented, it is reason that thou leaue no mysterie, nor sentence of his passion, on which thou doest not occupie thy vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, because that he did much more for thee, in suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it, than thou for him in contemplating on it. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the sonne of God hath been so prodigall and stout, in shedding his own bloud for thee, why shouldst thou be so sparing in thinking so much as one houre in the day on his passion? Do not vaunt thy selfe my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thou art a christian, nor glory vainly that thou shalt die for the passion of Christ, for seeing that thou hast no heat nor feruor to thinke on it, it is not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that thou wilt haue the heart to die for it. For see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou doest not serue thy God and Lord, so much as with thy thoughts, how wilt thou offer the members of thy body to suffer torments in them?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Of the mysterie of the two waights which the sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue had.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>OMnis aestimatio, siclo sanctuarij ponderabitur,</hi> Said God in Leuit. the 27 chapter, as if he should say, All that which is much &amp; of a great value, shalbe waighed with
<pb facs="6"/> the waight of my sanctuary. Such as wil curiously looke into the booke of Leuiticus, shall find in it, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Iews, had two kinds of waights; whereof the one was called <hi>statera,</hi> a ballance or waight, which was the common waight, wherewith all things of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth were waighed: the other <hi>siclum,</hi> a sicle, that is a holy waight: and with this they did waigh euerie thing which was offered vp in the temple. Like vnto a man who would keepe an order in his house. VVhen God did ordaine his common-weale, he commanded that there should be a waight and a measure in it: that is, a waight to measure and waigh all prophane things; and a waight to waigh all holy and diuine things. The sweet perfumes which were waighed in the temple, were of equall waight, in figure of the equall loue and charitie, which were in all priests works, because the loue &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, with which he did worke thē was as entire in him, as when he did preach in the temple, &amp; when he did suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer on the tree of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>▪ <hi>Augustine</hi> saith, In thee and in me are of greater a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r value and waight, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes of our works, because that somtimes we do them with deuotion, and at other times with coldnesse: but in the sonne of God it is not so, but his loue and charitie was ardent to redeeme vs, that neither the time did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease it in him, nor trauell and trouble make it cold. What doth it meane, that of two waights which the sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue had, the one of them was a holy waight, and the other prophane; but that in the one they should waigh the workes of his sonne: and in the other all the workes of all the worlde The merites of one holy man may be measured with those of another holy man, and the torments of one martyr, may be measured with the torments of another marytr, because there is no man in
<pb facs="7"/> heauen, so great, but God can create another, which in life may with him be equall, and also go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond him. The heire of eternities, doth not enter into this accompt, nor doth not fight vnder this banner: he is not waighed where we are waighed, nor is not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured as we are measured, because it would be a farre ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier matter, to measure what the mountains do waigh, than measure that, that his merits do reach vnto. How is it possible that he should be waighed, who all thinges doth waigh? How is it possible to find a measure for him, who doth measure all things with his wisdome? Aboue in the resting place of the trinitie, and in the depth of the diuinitie, the sonne of the liuing God, hath his measure and waight, because the merites of him are so high, and the dolours which he suffered for vs, so greeuous; that there are no dolours of martyrs to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with him, nor holinesse of Angels to measure him; which doth it not seeme vnto thee, that the son of God hath in measure and waig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> by himselfe, seeing that he did merite more, eating in the wedding, and with <hi>Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> than the great <hi>S. Iohn Baptist,</hi> fasting in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? Being graunted that the works which the sonne of God did, as man, had limits and an end: the charitie with which he did them, had no end. And thereupon it is, that if vnto that which he did suffer, there was found a waight, to the loue, with which he did suffer, there was no measure. Thou mightest well O my Iesus, measure and waigh the bloud, which in the mount of Caluary thou didst shed: but who can be able to measure and waigh the loue, with the which thou didst shed it? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thy bloud should be waighed by pounds and ounces, who should be able to find waights to waigh thy bowels?</p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <p>In the waight of the sanctuary nothing was waig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> but that which was of the sanctuary, and so in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lance and waight of Christ, nothing is waighed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> workes of Christ: for if you would waigh any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> thing in him, all the holinesse of the angels, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> torments of the martyrs would not waigh so much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> one drop of the bloud which he shed. Seeing then, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> we cannot waigh our selues in the ballance of Christ, he came to waigh himselfe in ours, where in one bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance we did put our fault, and in the other he did put his paine, the which before the father was of such great waight, that it was sufficient to satisfie for our offence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ Who could satisfie for our fault, if he should not lend vs his paine and punishment, to pay with it our debt?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Whereof the ruler was, with which God did command, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and leuell Hierusalem.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>PErpendiculum extendetur super Hierusalem,</hi> said God by the prophet <hi>Zacharias,</hi> in the first chapter, As if he would say, I will and command, that all my holy City of Hierusalem, be measured with a cord, and be leuelled with a leuell. These words of our Lord are of very great feare vnto the wicked, and of great aduertisement vnto the good, seeing that in publicke place, and with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen crie, God did command it to be cried: that he will sit downe in compt with all, and that he will measure all men, to weet, with the leuell of his life, and with the line of his iustice. If thou be troubled, &amp; tremble when they aske thee an accompt of thy expences, what shall become of thee, when they shall aske it of thy soule? If thou yeeld vp an euill accompt vnto thy Lord, of the mony which thou hast spent: what wilt thou doe vnto
<pb facs="8"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Lord, of the benefites receiued? O good Iesus; O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ue of my soule: what will it be of me, and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> do before thee, when the life which I lead, shalbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ed and prooued with the booke of thy iustice: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> is it possible that he should giue a good accompt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> neither with his soule, nor with God hath no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>mpt? It is reason that we know what is the cord, with which we shalbe measured, and what the leuell with which we shalbe leuelled: because that thereby we shal see how our Lord doth vs no iniurie in asking vs an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of that which we haue receiued. The leuell and the line, with which all the world shalbe leuelled and measured, is the crosse; and he who is ruled &amp; leuelled, is Iesus Christ; because that he alone and none with him, can know vvhether vve go the vvay of saluation, or the path of perdition. Euen as the line is cast, to the end that the building may go straight; and also the leuell is put, because the vvall should not be vneuen, so God vvil that vve direct all our vvorkes to him, and vvorke them by him. That goeth not by line, vvhich is not done for him; nor that by leuell, vvhich is not done for his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; by reason vvhereof, vvhen our Lord doth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard come to measure and leuell the manner of our life vvith the leuell of his iustice, as he findeth our building vnleuelled, he throvveth it all to the ground. <hi>S. Augustine de verbis Domini,</hi> saith: The thing vvhich doth most of all deceiue mortal men is, that to giue an excuse to their errors, they vvill not measure themselues vvith men vvhich are good, but vvith others vvhich are naught like themselues: Insomuch that they are contented vvith being lesse euill than others: not caring at al to be good. One proud man doth measure himselfe vvith another proud man: one couetous man vvith another: one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie
<pb facs="8"/> man with another, and one glutton with another: and this measure which he maketh, is not to the end to amend himselfe of his errors, but to condemne the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a greater sinner than himselfe. When the Lord did say by the prophet, <hi>Iustificata est Sodoma in conspectu Samariae,</hi> did he happily cease from punishing of Sodom, because she was a lesser sinner than Samaria. To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy selfe which art a lesser sinner, vnto another who is a greater sinner: by this thou doest not excuse thy selfe from sinne, nor deliuer thy selfe from hell, because it is an infallible rule, that God will neuer forget to reward the good, nor neuer omit to punish the bad. When God did say in the authoritie aboue named, <hi>Perpendiculum extendetur super Hierusalem,</hi> what other thing would he there say, but that he and none other should giue the line, with the which all should be measured; and also the rule, with which all should be leuelled? Seeing that he would create vs, and he would redeeme vs: it is reason that he and none other, should measure and rule vs. It is likewise to be waighed, that God did not say vnto Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem that she should choose the line, with the which she should be measured, but that he the Lord himselfe would send it: to giue vs thereby to vnderstand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>at of all the thoughts which we conceiue, and of al the works which we do, onely God is the looker on, who most approueth them, and the true Lord who wil pay them. This word <hi>perpendiculum extēdetur,</hi> is also to be waighed, where God doth not tell Hierusalem, that he will send a line out of hand, but in processe of time; giuing vs by that prophesie to vnderstand, that there was neuer anie euen or right leuell in the world, vntill God did send his precious sonne into the world. To thinke and knowe that the synagogue had no right line or leuel: what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="9"/> testimonie can we seeke, than for God to say by the Prophet, <hi>Dedi eis legem non bonam, &amp; praecepta in quibus non viuerent.</hi> How shall we say that in the building of the sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, there was line and leuell, seeing that there it was permitted, to marrie the brothers wife, take vsurie of a stranger, giue a bill of diuorce to his owne wife, Marke how orderly diuine matters do proceed, and the eternall measures, in that that the people did measure the crosse, the crosse did measure Christ, Christ did mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure the Gospell, the Gospell doth rule and measure all the world: insomuch that he did first measure himselfe, before he did measure me. When was this prophesie of <hi>perpendiculum</hi> fulfilled vpon Hierusalem: but when the humanitie of the word was on the crosse, not onely stretched out, but also torne asunder? O glorious mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure! O happie leuell! such as thou art, Christ my redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; seeing that with such a rule and measure as thine is, the saints doe suffer themselues to be ruled and measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the heauenly Angels are glad to be leuelled. When holy <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romains did say in the 8 chap. <hi>Quos praedestinauit, conformauit fieri, &amp;c.</hi> What other thing would he say in these high wordes, but that all those whom God had predestinated, he did predestinat and chose them, that they might be like to the image of his sonne? What other thing is his perfect &amp; diuine image, but his perfect and his holy life? He is like vnto the image of his sonne who doth fulfill and keepe his holy gospell; because it was not the intention of the Apostle that we should imitate Christ, in the image and likenesse of his essence, but in the purenesse and perfection of his life. Of this patterne we should draw all our labours, by this image we should point our soules, with this le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell we should leuell our workes, and with this line we
<pb facs="9"/> should measure our steps: for otherwise like vnto an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuelled building, he will throw all our trauels on the ground. O good Iesus, O the loue of my soule, what will my life seeme before thy life, when it shalbe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with thine. O how filthy my cleannesse shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, how angry my meeknesse, how proud my humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, how ambitious my pouertie, how weake my strength, yea and how mercilesse my mercy. O how ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous my teares will seeme, how fained my griefe, how cruell my pitie, how niggish my liberalitie, how gluttonous my abstinence, how iniust my iustice, how false all my peace, and hovv vvithout virginitie all my chastitie. O hovv cold my praier vvill seem, hovv vveake my deuotion, hovv testie my patience, hovv vnperfect my obedience, hovv inconstant my perseuerance, hovv spotted my conscience, and also vvithout fruit all my life. Let it not seeme a hard matter vnto any man, that our life should be leuelled and ruled vvith the giuer of life; Seeing that our glorie shalbe made like vnto his glory, not because vve should make our selues equall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, but because in glorie vve may find our selues vvith him. This being presupposed to be true, as true it is, who shall more enioy Christ in glorie than hee vvho here vvas most conformable vnto his life. He vvho vvith this holy line and leuell, is not leuelled here on earth, shall haue no glorie aboue vvith Christ in heauen: for as he vvas not like vnto him in his maner of liuing, so neither shall he be like vnto him in his maner of raigning.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>How the son of God did more for vs, than for himselfe.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>FEcisti iudiciū meum, &amp; causam meā sedens super thropum, qui iudicas iustitiam,</hi> saith king <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 9 Psal. as if
<pb facs="10"/> he would say. Thou O my great God of Israel art he, who being set in thy royall seate, hast iudged iustice, hast made my iustice, and ended my cause. Many secrets, and many high Sacramentes, the good prophet doth touch in this prophesie▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> therfore it is requisit, that as the words are deep, so they be deeply expoūded. In this prophesie it is to be noted, who he is who doth iudge, &amp; this is God; what the place is where he doth iudge, and this is a throne, in what maner he doth iudge, &amp; he saith fitting; and what it is that he doth iudge, and he saith iustice; and of what he doth giue iudgment, and he saith, that of my proper cause. VVhat prince this day of the world, hath wrought such high thinges, being on foote or on horsebacke, as thou O my good Iesus, being set in thy throne? who hath euer attained so great a victorie fighting, as thou hast done suffering? What is the throne where thou wast sitting, but the holy and true crosse where thou wast crucified? O glorious throne, O happy throne, on which thou wast accompanied with theeues, crowned with thornes, empty of bloud, thy pores o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, thy sinews stretched, poore of friends, and compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with enemies.</p>
      <p>Seeing then, that in this throne he was iudged and sentenced by <hi>Pilat</hi> the viceroy, how doth the prophet say, that from thence he iudged all the world? Likewise, how is it possible, that from thence he did dispatch my fact and cause, seeing that he lost his honor and his life? Sitting vpon the throne of the crosse, the sonne of God did iudge him who iudged, who was the diuell: iudged that which did iudge, which was the world: iudged of that which did iudge, which was sinne: did iudge that with the which he did iudge, which was tyrannie; inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Pilat,</hi> executing iustice vpon him, he did also
<pb facs="10"/> iustice vpon our iustice. O how well the prophet said, in saying, <hi>fecisti causam meam,</hi> and not <hi>fecisti causam tuam;</hi> considering that in the throne of the crosse, thou hadst there no cause to go vp, no businesse there to <hi>negotiat,</hi> vnlesse it were there for me to die, and for my sins there to pay. With great reason they are accustomed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head homicides, stone runnagates, and hang theeues, and crucifie blasphemers: but thou, O good Iesus, what theft hadst thou done? what blasphemies hadst thou spoken, seeing that for them thou shouldst be crucified? On the mount of <hi>Caluary,</hi> thou didst wel know that thou hadst nothing to doe, seeing that there, there were no blind men to giue sight vnto, no lame men to heale, no diuels to cast out, nor temples to preach in: whereof we may inferre, that if thou didst goe to the mount of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary,</hi> thou didst go for thy friendes businesse. VVhen didst thou make <hi>iudicium meum;</hi> but vvhen to deliuer me from eternall iudgement, thou didst suffer thy selfe to be iudged and condemned by <hi>Pilat</hi> the tyrant? vvhen O good Iesus, vvhen didst thou plead my cause, but vvhen thou didst suffer such a great torment and paine, as though thou thy selfe hadst committed the fault? vvhen didst thou iudge iustice, but vvhen thou didst take avvay from the diuel his forces, because he should be no longer iudge of my offences? <hi>Fecisti causam meam,</hi> when of an ignorant man, thou didst make me vvise: of a slaue, a free-man: of a stranger, a neighbour: of a condemned man, a quit: of Gentile, a Christian, and of an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, a sonne. Then didst thou take my cause in hand, vvhen in preiudice of thy person, thou didst intend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the sauing of my soule, I say againe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of thy person, because that the more thou dids<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in me, the more thou didst vndoe thee: didst not tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="11"/> vndoe and preiudice thy selfe, and benefit me, when of God thou didst become man, of inuisible, visible: of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passible, passible: of immortall, mortall: of eternal, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and of the Lord of Angels a reproch of men? O how thou didst plead my cause, seeing that to lift vp me, thou didst pull downe thee, to giue vnto me honour, thou didst take to thee infamie, and to deliuer me, thou didst suffer thy selfe to be taken; and also to excuse me, didst permit thy selfe to be condemned: insomuch that thou didst plead my cause to thy owne great preiudice: <hi>fecisti causam meam</hi> on the crosse, where like an aduocate thou didst pray for me, where like a Iudge thou didst pardon me, where like a kinsman thou didst pay for me, where like a brother thou didst answere for me, where like a friend thou didst die for me, and also where like a father thou didst weepe for me. <hi>Fecisti causam meam,</hi> in the royal throne of thy crosse, when thou didst heare me and the diuell, the diuell and me, and were before thee in iustice, when he said that I was his, and I said that I was not, but thine; and he to accuse me, did lay open my fault; and I to excuse my selfe, did lay downe thy bloud, and in the end thou didst make my cause, seeing thou didst expulse him, and admit me. Thou didst plead my cause; with the father, seeing thou didst obtaine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of him. <hi>Fecisti causam meam</hi> with the Angels: seeing thou didst giue them me for my guard, <hi>fecisti causam meam,</hi> with the Church; seeing that in her thou didst in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporat me, thou didst make my cause with the diuell, seeing that out of his hands thou didst deliuer me: and also <hi>fecisti causam meam,</hi> with sinnes: seeing thou didst forgiue me them: <hi>fecisti causam meam,</hi> not hauing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or cause to do it, seeing thou didst create me to thy image, redeeme me with thy bloud, endue me with thy
<pb facs="11"/> merits, cure me with thy dolours, lighten me with thy doctrin, draw me to thy elect, &amp; reform me with thy sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, didst not happily forward my cause, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thine own, seeing that frō the first moment in which thou wast born, vntil the last instant, in which thou didst die, thou didst neuer go step which was to thine ease: nor neuer worke any heroicall fact, which was not to my profit. O the light of my eies, O the rest of my soule, vpon my knees I beseech thee, and with teares I aske thee, that thou wouldest lighten my vnderstanding, make cleane my heart, guide my tongue, direct my pen, to the end, that as thou, <hi>fecisti causam meam,</hi> dieng for me, so I may likewise plead thy cause, writing so great a passion, and setting forth and magnifieng such infinite dolours. How shall I be able O my good Iesus to extoll the perils which thou didst see thy selfe in, the dolours which thou didst suffer, the sweares which thou didst passe, the teares which thou didst weepe, the bloud which thou didst shed, the infamie which thou didst en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, the death which thou didst end with: If thou do not reforme and helpe my memorie, make cleane my entrails, amend my customes, and guide my fingers? O eternall father, O great and infinite goodnesse, seeing that the Carpenters of <hi>Moises,</hi> durst not labour in the <hi>Mosaicall</hi> tabernacle, not being first filled with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost, how shall I dare, without thy holy loue put my hand in the passion of thy sonne? If <hi>Moses</hi> dare not come neere the thornes, but without hose, how shall I dare, without thy holy loue put my hand in the passion of thy sonne, vnlesse I haue my heart cleane? create then O God a cleane heart in me, and renew a right spirite in my bowels: for then I shalbe able to extoll the bloud which thou didst shed out of thy vaines, when thou
<pb facs="12"/> shalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ane the spots of my bowels. O thou who wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> burne with a burning yron <hi>Esaias</hi> tongue, to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nto the people: will it not please thee to know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>y hurt, to contemplat in the passion of thy sonne? Workes so heroicall as those which thou hast done, O my good Iesus; a death so strange as this which thou didst suffer; a loue so excessiue as this which thou didst loue vs with; a redemption so perfect as this which thou didst end: what heart is able to thinke, what tongue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to rehearse, what handes worthie perfectly to write? Consider O my good Iesus, and marke that in giuing me light in this which I write, both of vs doe gaine; and if thou wilt not guide me, both loose: for if the worke doe fall out a right, thine is all the glorie; if it erre, mine is all the fault; insomuch that in that case, the readers would leaue off to praise in thee the grace which thou hadst giuen me, and would blame in me, the errour which I had committed. Seeing thou didst giue thy fauour, and grace to <hi>Moses,</hi> going in the palace: to <hi>Dauid</hi> keeping sheepe: to <hi>S. Paul</hi> going on the way, and to <hi>S. Peter</hi> going a fishing, and to <hi>S. Mathew</hi> being in the custome house. Why wilt not thou likewise giue it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, who do so heartily demand it, and with so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie teares craue it? If I doe aske for it, it is to the end with it to serue thee; and if I desire it, it is to hit a right in this worke, because thou doest know, O my good Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, that if I haue any small deuotion, it is in thy blessed and holy passion. Before thy presence, O good Iesus I appeare, and before thy goodnesse I present my selfe; and to thy omnipotencie I commend my selfe, and also to thy great clemencie, I offer all that which I shall write, and speake of thee in this booke, because no man in trueth can vtter high thinges of thee, nor yet
<pb facs="12"/> thinke of thee, but being in thee, or neere vnto thee. Let the conclusion of all be, that if thou, O good Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, <hi>labia me aperies,</hi> I am verie ceraine, <hi>quod os meum an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciabit laudem tnam:</hi> and to the end I may reach vnto this, prostrate on the ground, and my eies bathed in teares, I say, <hi>Deus in adiutorium meum intende,</hi> Lord make hast to helpe me: for if thou doe giue me thy grace, neither shall I omit to goe aright in this so high a worke, nor to attaine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward thy eternall glorie.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>