<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Deuout Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124739_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72089</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11315</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124739</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Deuout Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practise of Christian workes. Written in Spanish by the R. Father Francis Borgia, sometymes Duke of Gandia, and the third generall of the Society of Iesus. Togeather with a short rule, how to live well. Englished by a father of the same society. VVhereunto are adioyned certaine pious meditations vpon the beades: translated also out of the Spanish</title>
                 <author>Borja, Francisco de, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 163, that is 263, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <pb n="195" facs="109"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Deuout Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Catholique Church, for the profit of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their first conuersion, and afterwards as occasions require, maketh vse of the laudable customes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, adioyning to them pious considerations and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xercises, to aduaunce Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="196" facs="110"/> deuotion. And because the vse of the Beades is both easy and profitable, and for this respect receyued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in all Countries: in tymes past there were added to the <hi>Rosary</hi> of our Blessed Lady diuers Meditations and Contemplations. And heere (gentle Reader) thou shalt see adioyned to her Crowne or <hi>Coronary,</hi> others, for the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of <hi>Mortall synne</hi> aboue all thinges to be detested; for the obtayning of <hi>Christian Perfection,</hi> which is the scope of all our actions; and finally of the <hi>principall Mysteries</hi> of the Life &amp; Passion of Iesus Christ our Sauiour, which we should
<pb n="197" facs="110"/> keepe in perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, both to imitate his vertues, and to be thankefull for his benefits.</p>
   <p>For seeing we cā do nothing els for him, that hath done so much for vs: at least, our care &amp; deuotion should call once a day to memory, how much we are owing to his loue: and neuer be weary to thinke of those afflictiōs &amp; torments, which he was not weary to suffer for our sakes. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause variety in all exercises is a remedy against wearinesse, and especially in matters of deuotion; we haue done heere as in Musike is both permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and commended, where
<pb n="198" facs="111"/> many tymes they sing diuers ditties vnder one tune, when it is good.</p>
   <p>It wilbe easy for thee to accomodate these particuler considerations to the number of the Beades, beginning with the first three, &amp; ending with the same; and intermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xing the <hi>Pater Nosters,</hi> and Prayers according to the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers heere set downe. And at the first it will greatly helpe thy memory, to haue the Booke before thee, and reade the points one by one, as thou sayest the Prayers; till with custome thou shalt haue gotten them without booke. And whilest thou sayest the
<pb n="199" facs="111"/>
      <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> thou must haue reflexion to the point which thou hast read: &amp; so go from one to another, with leasure and attention, till thou haue passed them all ouer: and doubt not, but with a little patience for the first few dayes, thou shalt reape after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a great deale of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, deuotion, and benefit to thy soule.</p>
   <p>These Considerations or points of Meditation, were conceaued, and wrytten in Spanish in the yeare 1613. for intertaynment of the way between <hi>Madrid</hi> and <hi>Barcelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and there printed: &amp; from thēce sent to <hi>Don Philip</hi> Prince
<pb n="200" facs="112"/> of Spaine, and to his two brethren <hi>Charles</hi> &amp; <hi>Ferdinand</hi> for tokens, in respect that the Author, when be tooke his last leaue, left them saying their beads al three togeather: and comming after by some accident into England, and there translated by a deuout person, were sent to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and by chance brought to be viewed, before the printing, by the same per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that wrote them in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish six yeares before; he little thinking then, that they were to be published in any other language, which he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for priuate deuotion of those Princes. But by the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse,
<pb n="201" facs="112"/> it seemeth that God, of his holy prouidence, would haue some thing written for the instruction of such, as shal read thē, where the vse of the Beades is not knowen to all. And in this conformity he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded these few lines, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that deuotion be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the faithfull people, and God Almighty glorified, from whome all Grace &amp; goodnes descendeth, and to whome is due all honour and glory. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>