<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Blaxton, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124641_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73521</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3129.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124641</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Blaxton, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English vsurer; or Vsury condemned, by the most learned and famous diuines of the Church of England : and dedicated to all his Maiesties subiects, for the stay of further increase of the same. Collected by Iohn Blaxton, preacher of Gods VVord at Osmington, in Dorcet-shire</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Long, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 84 pages, bill (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are some commit vsury,<note place="margin">Why some are vsurers.</note> not knowing it to be sinne: eyther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they haue not the Word, or they vse not the Word for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning of their hearts.<note place="margin">See M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Mosse,</hi> Treatise of vsury Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the Reader.</note> Those that bee ignorant for want of the Word, are much to be pitied; and yet is their want that way, the iust punishment of sinne. Those that are ignorant for not vsing the Word, are sharpely to be reproued, as those whose ignorance accrewing from their owne negligence, is meere sinne vnto them.<note place="margin">August. ad Sextum Rom. presby Ep. <hi>105.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>In vtrisque non est iusta excusatio, sed iusta condemnatio,</hi> sayth <hi>Augustine,</hi> Neyther of both can iustly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused; nay eyther of both is iustly to be condemned. Others commit vsury, and stand to excuse it, alead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for themselues the authority of men: to these I answer, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> did to the Gentiles, who grounded their religion vpon the authority of their Ancestours, <hi>Id solum rectum est, quod ratio praescribit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lact. de Origine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
      </note> not that which men say, but that which reason war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteth, is right and to be approued.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note>To them that alleadge <hi>examples,</hi> I answer with the ancient prouerbe, <hi>Viuitur preceptis non exemplis:</hi> we must liue by precepts, and not by examples. And with that of <hi>Moses, Thou shalt not follow a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to doe euill.</hi> To them which iustifie vsury to be lawfull, I stand not heere to make answer: for to that end serueth the treatise following. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Cyprian. De Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorum.</note> I applie vnto them, that which <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> spake of some Teachers of his time, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulantes in tenebris, habere se lucem existimant:</hi> walking in darkenesse, they suppose they haue the light.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Distrust in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence the Vsurers sin.</note>To them that pretend, they cannot otherwise liue, I replie: that they may accuse themselues of sloth and idlenesse, of infidelity and distrust in Gods Prouidence: which is indeed the Vsurers sinne.</p>
   <p>Others yet there are, who knowing the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise to bee euill, and themselues not being able to excuse it, they turne their nose vpon the very winde,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> like the weather Cocke, and like mad men rage at those that would binde them for their benefit: and are like the Swine of which Christ speaketh in the Gospell,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> who when they haue Pearles throwne before them, turne againe, and all to rent those that cast them. God bee mercifull vnto these kind of Vsurers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> (if it bee his will,) for their case is desperate. They are like vnto a foolish pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, who is ready to flie into the face of the Chirurgian, when hee searcheth his wound vnto
<pb facs="6"/> the bottome, for the curing of it. What will follow hereupon? But the ruine of the Vsurer?</p>
   <p>Others, when the Minister preacheth against Vsury, encourage themselues in their vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table course of life, by this conceit: that it is but his priuate opinion. This treatise will make it euident, that, <hi>Vsury to bee vnlawfull,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The most iudicious Diuines condemne Vsury.</note> proceeds not out of the mouths of some few <hi>Humorists</hi> in the Country, (for so the Vsurers account them:) but it is the iudgement of those who sit at the Helme, and deseruedly are accounted pillars in the Church of God.</p>
   <p>As for the Author of this Treatise: vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that hee neyther lendeth, nor taketh vpon Vsury: for hee followes his calling,<note place="margin">Vsurers vile persons Ps. 15.</note> and doth not busy himselfe much with the affayers of the world. As for profest Vsurers, hee esteemes them as vile persons, in whose eyes they are most iustly contemned, but hee honoreth those that feare the Lord. which the Vsurers do not. And therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free from the guiltinesse of this sinne, he may the moore freely giue sentence vpon the vngodlinesse thereof <hi>Iudicet ille de alterius errore</hi> (sayth S. <hi>Ambrose) qui non habet in seipso quod condemnet: iudicet,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ambros. su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, beati im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculati.</note>
      <hi>qui non agit eadem quae in alio putauerit punienda.</hi> Let him iudge of another mans default, who hath not the same fault to condemne in himselfe: let him iudge of another who committeth not the same thing which hee deemeth worthy the punishing in another.</p>
   <p>Know moreouer, that he is a thorough conformable
<pb facs="7"/> Member and Minister of the Church of England. And for the Scope of this Treatise, it is for the information and saluation of thy soule, and his owne soule. Take the Treatise, and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Si quid ex vsu tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reperias, iuvame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus tuis apud deum; aliam mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem non defidero. vale.</note> giue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy fellow member in Christ Iesus, <hi>John Blaxton.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>