<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶An exhortacion to the reders by a broder of Syon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1530</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124473_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00875</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25421.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124473</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶An exhortacion to the reders by a broder of Syon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pomander of prayer : The greatest comfort in al temptacyon is the reme [m] braunce of Crystes passyon</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Copland, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1530</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶An exhortacion to the reders by a broder of Syon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsyderyng the mysery and infelicite of this our moost peryllous tyme / how the flode of synne hath ouer rōne all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> charyte and peas is almoost extynct fayth dyspersed / hope dyssolued / vertue &amp; pyte outlawed / sanctyte annulled / presthode dystay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / relygyon decayed. In maner no constancy in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peple / no fydelyte betwene neyghbour &amp; neyghbour neyther in byeng nor sellyng / nor any other contract. One scantly may trust another. And now suche is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> excesse of glotony / and so the people dooth nourysshe theyr bodyes: that abstynence is banysshed / and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery exalted. Vyrgyns hath lost theyr dyamonde of shamefastnes / and haue founde the rayle of boldnes / whiche is the noryce of wantonnes. Matrymony is torned the lust of the body. wolde god it were not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in to aduoutry. where vpon our moost holy fader in heuen / whiche was wonte with his swete rodde to correct vs. Now sore agreued and dyspleased with vs / maketh his terryble sworde of Iustyce ouer vs. yea dayly with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same dooth bete vs with famyne / derth / and pestylence. with sodayn dethe and straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge sekenesse in in oure bodyes. And all this is for the synne of our bodyes. And ouer all these with innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mo myseryes. what dyuysyon is amonge the prynces and heedes of the chyrche / I reporte me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. I do feare me to the great hurte and oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syon of the people. But very assured I am that
<pb facs="3"/> it is to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great domage of grace / &amp; losse of many a soule what kynde chylde of god is there in this worlde y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> seeth his fader so sore dyspleased / and also his moder the catholycall chyrche so sore decayed / but he wolde be sory / tremble / and quake / and seke alwayes for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy how he myght agayne be reconsyled to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; helpe to redresse his moder so wounded &amp; dyffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> fro the heed vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fote I wote not in what degre or state of Crystes chyrch I may say y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there is the lyfe / the helthe / &amp; the conuersacion y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sholde be and hath bene in chrystianite / our lorde Iesu remedy it / &amp; helpe it. For onely the werke of his insu{per}able mercy it muste nedes be. for it passeth the power of man / for of mannes behalfe I se no remedy / but penaunce and prayer. And now the hertes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people be so sore deie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; conuerted to the asfeccyōs of this worlde. &amp; so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely encōbred w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the study &amp; besynesse therof / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> theyr hertes can not pray. But whyles theyr moder dooth pray / theyr hartes be full of worldly cogytaciōs / &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stracciōs of mynd. They many tymes agaynst theyr wylles (to the great losse of the fruyt of theyr prayer) whiche yf it were pure nothynge myght resyste it / it wolde ascende to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throne of god as scrypture sayth. And fro thens it wolde not departe whyle it had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> petycion.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>cle. xxxv.</note> For as saynt Austyn sayth. Impos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>syble it is y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the prayer of many shall not be herde.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>d fratres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>heremo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.xliiii. et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>sa. Ad ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. xv. luce.</note> spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally whā it dooth {pro}cede of pure &amp; meke hertes. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gospell of Cryst dooth shewe vs y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> importune pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cōtynuall perseueraūce / albeit y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thyng seme im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possyble y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we aske of god <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>le.xxxv.</note> / it wyll at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> laste in lyne the eare of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mercy of god &amp; opteyne cōfort / as he shewed in the parable of .iij. loues. And not withstandyng
<pb facs="3"/> that we be not his frendes: but wretches &amp; synners: and therefore by reason of our synne he seeth in vs no cause to haue pyte on vs. yet contynuall prayer wyll vaynquysshe him / &amp; inclyne his mercy &amp; charyte to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue our necessytees satysfy: and our requestes.<note place="margin">Luce. xviii</note> As he shewed hymselfe in the symilytude of the wydowe &amp; the vnryght wyse iudge / whyche for the wydowes importune and contynuall cry and clamour was cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled &amp; fayne to gyue sentēce with her.<note place="margin">ps. xc clam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uit adme. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> So god wyll do / for so he promysed vnto his people. with what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer synne / temptacyon / sekenesse / losse of goodes / or other aduersyte of the worlde we be vexed / call and pray perseuerauntly and we shall haue conforte.<note place="margin">luce. xviii.</note> But he byddeth vs to pray and cease not. But alas for so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> prayer is in maner gone. I mene the contynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally affeccyon / mynde / &amp; desyre to god &amp; godly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> habundaunce of dedes of pyte &amp; almes / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to theyr abylite. For who hath these he cōtynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally dooth pray as this treatyse folowyng more lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely dooth declare. And sheweth also what is prayer and how we sholde order our prayer. &amp; our selfe in the tyme of prayer. And howe we sholde make our pety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> many other great cōmodytees &amp; benefytes whiche cometh by prayer. And specyally remedyes agaynst wandryng myndes &amp; vayne cogytacyons in tyme of prayer / whiche premysses consyderyng / &amp; se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng how charyte of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people is now very colde.<note place="margin">eccle. xxix.</note> And almes which hyd in the bosom of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poore was wont to pray instauntly / but now hath ceased / for lytell is gyuen in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> respecte as it hath bene. Therfore I was very glad y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this treatyse fortuned to come to my han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / syth I founde it bothe good / deuout / fruytfull / &amp;
<pb facs="4"/> catholycall / thynkyng how many hertes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple sholde be moche conforted therin / dyde cause it to be imprynted. And so moche more rather y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er and auctour of it / is one of the deuout fathers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cartherhous of Shene. whose vertue and lernynge is well approued. wherfore deuout reder I counsell the to bye this swete treatyse / &amp; exercyse thy selfe orde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge thy selfe there after. And I doubt not but thou shalt do moche honoure to god / suffrage to all crysten people / and to thy selfe moche profyte and edyfyeng. whiche almyghty god graunt to all the reders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>