<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124945_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72130</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11537.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124945</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brief treatise containing the most strange and horrible cruelty of Elizabeth Stile alias Rockingham and her confederates, executed at Abingdon, upon R. Galis</title>
                 <author>Galis, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <p>
      <pb facs="2"/>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S thou hast all ready moste (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der begun to satisfie thy greedye eyes with the freendly suruey of the late confession of <hi>Elizabeth Stile alias Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ckingam,</hi> comprehending not a handful to the number of their deuilish pageāts play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. So perseuer still I beseech thee with no lesse good will to peruse this true edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for thy sake and contentatiō only set foorth describing the strange, cruell and diabolicall tiranny practised through the little regarde and great necligence of Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gistrates in these our dayes winking at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faultes of the Offenders which neither re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garded the pitteful plaints of the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor the continuall plagues of the Tormentor powred out day by day vpon their honest and inocent Neighboures, some bereft of life, some of their wits and some of the naturall course of their lims.</p>
   <p>Emongst which I being one of the least that suffered moste and oftnest went to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pot, thought it good to set foorth some parte bothe of mine owne troubles and of diuers others for thy behoof, in reuoluīg wherof, if irō my hāds thou expect for my philed phrase or lerned stile being but mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp in a homely cuntrie Cabbin where the practise of the stayle and whip more ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="3"/>
is then lernings lore, thou shalt great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be deceiued. But if a plain Shepherds tale neither prophane or fained, oftner oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in the tarbox and sheephook, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments more fit for me then either pen or inck may serue thy turn: receiue thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire. Employe therfore thy paines in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsing the same, and if any thing thou find that either presently cōtenteth thy minde or that herafter prooue to thy proffit: giue thanks to them (and not to me) at whose instance I framed the same, which do on in requitall of my paines: I haue that which I doo expect. Thus farwel gentle Reader.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>RG.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>