<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER as much health as to my selfe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124178_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B01234</idno>
           <idno type="STC">772.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124178</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER as much health as to my selfe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foole vpon foole, or Sixe sortes of sottes : A flat foole, a leane foole, a merry foole, and a fatt foole, a cleane foole, a verrie foole. Shewing their liues, humours, and behauiours, with their want of wit in their shew of wisdome. Not so strange as true</title>
                 <author>Armin, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Ferbrand (Firebrand, Forbrand), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Stafford, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER as much health as to my selfe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Weete Signior, I salute thee kindly, how vnkindly so euer you salute my labour; desiring thy loue, not thy dislyke: Mee thinkes it were of all thinges more then strange, that men lyuing, should liue grieuing, and one to repine at an others prosperitie: it may be thou wilt wonder that I doe well; yet I wonder not that thou thinkest ill: for the common course is such, the more is the pittie. What, ist a new Booke sayes one? I, sayes another; tis call'd <hi>Foole vpon Foole:</hi> Nay like enough (sayes the first) Fooles write as their witte workes. Why, do we not know that sometimes the ayre purgeth with vncomfortable sleete, as profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table raine? Are all Wits euer prosperous? no, times are leaden, dull: Age weakens, and Wits must needes decline. Euery one then saue one, and do what a can, not what a would: But I am tedious to thee and to my selfe: bid my Booke welcome, it may be I may liue to make thee amendes: if not, no more but this; such a one dy'de in thy debt.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Adew, and read true.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>