<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To al that affect the famous exercise of ARCHERIE frequenting Finsburie fieldes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124682_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72029</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1025.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To al that affect the famous exercise of ARCHERIE frequenting Finsburie fieldes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ayme for Finsburie archers. Or An alphabetical table of the names of euerie marke within the same fields : with their true distances both by the map and dimensuration by the line. Published for the ease of the skilfull, and behoofe of the yong beginners in the famous exercise of archerie, by E.B. and I.I</title>
                 <author>E. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergeant, F</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 107, 9 pages, plates, illustrations, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To al that affect the famous exercise of ARCHERIE <hi>frequenting Finsburie</hi> fieldes.</head>
   <p>SHooting in the long bow being of it selfe very laudable, and our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish nation in all ages surpassing therein all others, yea neither the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Seythes, Parthians, Sarmathians, Armiaspes</hi> famous for that quality, nor any other people could become equall with English Archers. And yet (a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be lamented) this laudable exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of late dayes hath become cold in most places of this land, famous <hi>Londō</hi> retaining the most ardēt desire to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the same, as appeareth by the daily concourse of Citizens, to their great commendations, in diuerse companies in the conuenient fields about the citie, but most especially in that choise place <hi>Fins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> most especially garnished with many beautifull Markes in this little Treatise Alphabetically mentioned, whereby the benefactors therein shall haue perpetuall memorie recorded by the titles of their seuerall erections.</p>
   <p>And for that euery hand ought to bring some portion of helpe towards the preseruation and increase of so commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable actiuitie, we haue (by the helpe of our friends) cast in also our mite, wishing it to worke a continuing in the old, and a growing goodwill in such yong beginners as would become skilfull in this most acceptable qualitie, for whose sakes this litle worke is reuiewed, reuiued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>published, with such necessary, easie, and helpfull obseruations as may seeme best to satisfie those that are desirous to come to knowledge in the Markes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>