<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MVCH HONO∣red Ladie, the Ladie RVTH SCYDAMORE increase of peace and ioy in belee∣uing.</title>
           <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124755_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73612</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4236.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124755</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MVCH HONO∣red Ladie, the Ladie RVTH SCYDAMORE increase of peace and ioy in belee∣uing.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The spiritval tovchstone: or, The signes of a godly man : drawne in so plaine and profitable a maner, as all sorts of Christians may trie themselues thereby. Together with directions, how the weake Christian, by the vse of these signes may establish his assurance. By. N. Bifield preacher of Gods word at Isteworth in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 134 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MVCH HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Ladie, the Ladie RVTH SCYDAMORE increase of peace and ioy in belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow great the benefite of assurance of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and of our owne saluation is, those onely know that are either scourged with the conflicts and
<pb facs="3"/> terrors of their own doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, or that are solaced and established with the sweet dewes of refreshing that arise from a rooted and well grounded faith. If men studie assurances so much for their outward possessions in this world, how much more earnest and diligent should men be to assure Gods loue and the inheritance of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to come? There is not a clearer signe of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane heart, then to account these cares needlesse: nor do I know a iuster excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against any religion, then that it should teach,
<pb facs="3"/> that when a man hath done what he can to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the directions of that religion, yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be sure he shall go to heauen.</p>
   <p>But since I know that all that are possessed of the grace of Iesus Christ, do account assurance great riches, I therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hope that my paines about this subiect will not be altogether vnaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in this present trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise I haue endeuoured to expresse the signes of trial in a much more easie way then before; and besides
<pb facs="4"/> haue added directions, that shew how a weake Christian may establish himselfe in his assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
   <p>I make bold to dedicate my new Essay herein vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Ladiship. You haue heard the substance hereof preached, and receiued it with much gladnesse; and in the priuate vse of these signes, you haue bene plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to professe (to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God) that you haue found much contentment and establishment of your owne assurance. Your emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie in the sincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession and practise of
<pb facs="4"/> true religion, and the shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the graces here intreated of, long acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by many witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, haue made you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be publikly obserued and praised in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Christ: and your great respect and fauour shewed to me, hath made this way of testifying my thankfulnesse, but as a small pledge and assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my desire to do your Ladiship any seruice in the things of Iesus Christ. Thus beseeching God to enlarge the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of his Spirit in your heart, and to prosper you
<pb facs="5"/> in all things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the blessed hope of the appearing of Iesus Christ our mightie God and Sauiour, I end, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, N. Bifield.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>