<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Rules touching the vse of the Treatise.</title>
           <author>N., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124682_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72029</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1025.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Rules touching the vse of the Treatise.</title>
                 <author>N., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ayme for Finsburie archers. Or An alphabetical table of the names of euerie marke within the same fields : with their true distances both by the map and dimensuration by the line. Published for the ease of the skilfull, and behoofe of the yong beginners in the famous exercise of archerie, by E.B. and I.I</title>
                 <author>E. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergeant, F</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 107, 9 pages, plates, illustrations, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="directions_for_use">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Rules touching the vse of the Treatise.</head>
   <p n="1">1 First, you must note, that sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie Markes haue two or three wordes for their names, looke for the marke alwaies in the first word, as in the <hi>Kings Mace,</hi> looke not for <hi>Mace</hi> but for <hi>Kings:</hi> also the <hi>House of Lancaster,</hi> looke for <hi>House</hi> not for <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and so in the rest.</p>
   <p n="2">2 And it is further to be noted, that the first number sheweth the scores, the second the yards: you must shoote long ayme, because this is set downe by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the line</p>
   <p n="3">3 Againe you must note, that wee haue set downe the markes to be taken all going into the fields, and if you be coming homeward, looke for the marke you shoote at, and not for the marke you stand at. And we haue placed from
<pb facs="4"/> euery marke all the marks from the left hand to the right, leauing out none from 9. score to 18. or 19. score. And when a marke is found along a banke, you must alwayes looke for the marke from the West towards the East.</p>
   <p n="4">4 Also for the aide of yong shooters wee: haue set downe in the ende of the booke a Table of the names of all the marks, with direction in what page to find them, for the ease of those that are vnacquainted with the names of the markes.</p>
   <p>For the better aduertisement of such as are not acquainted with the order of the game and custome of the field, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by often arise controuersies, and diuerse times grow rash and vnaduised othes, to the derogation of Gods glory, we haue thought it good to set downe such orders as are sittest to be obserued in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p n="1">1 First for the finding of your marke, it must be within euery mans reach. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the precise naming of your marke preuenteth much cauill.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Secondly, for whites you may haue as many as you will, so they be all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and if you shoote at anie loose white, and it be striken out of sight, it is no marke.</p>
   <p n="3">3 Thirdly, for the highest of stakes, if the wood be aboue the pin, you are to measure at the wood, although the pin hath bene put in for the same purpose.</p>
   <p n="4">4 Fourthly, if you finde a bush or a blacke, whatsoeuer you finde highest in it, being within the compasse of the marke, you are to take it for the height.</p>
   <p n="5">5 Fiftly, for all trees you are to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure at foote and pole, except in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of it you say, at the naile in such a tree, or hole in such a tree, or being a tree of so small height, that you may
<pb facs="5"/> reach the top of it with halfe your bowe, then you may take the highest.</p>
   <p n="6">6 Sixtly, if there be so nigh a shoote that it cannot be giuen by the contrarie side, or by another companie, then the better of them two is to win the shoote at the next marke, and not to let it lye dead to the aduantage of the contrarie side. If in measuring of the shoote, by haste the marke is stirred, he is to lose the shoote that measureth it.</p>
   <p n="7">7 Seuenthly, when you come to the marke and claime two, and the contrary sides draw their arrowes, &amp; when your mate comes he saith his would win too, you are to win no more then you claime.</p>
   <p n="8">8 Lastly, if you name one marke and shoote at another, you are to lose your shoot, and they are to follow at the mark named.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>