<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his good Friend M. Anthony Mundy.</title>
           <author>C., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124829_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73047</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20366a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124829</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his good Friend M. Anthony Mundy.</title>
                 <author>C., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second booke of Primaleon of Greece.And Prince Edward of England : Continuing the course of their rare fortunes, knightly aduentures, successe in loue, and admirable escape from verie perillous enchauntments: as the like delightfull historie hath sildome been heard of Translated out of French by A.M. one of the messengers of her Maiesties chamber</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, + 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_translator">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To his good Friend M. <hi>Anthony Mundy.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing met <hi>Primaleons</hi> second Part in the Printing-house, whence I haue long loytered, and where it hath been longer looked for, I haue done all my diligence to further the Edition, the rather for that (in my simple conceit) I haue not seen a Historie more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectablie continued, nor (to be plaine with ye) anie thing by your selfe more pleasingly translated. I would not be here taken (for commending this) to be a condemner of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie VVorke by you before Englished: yet giue me leaue to note, that reproofe (how euer causelesse) makes him that can doo well, striue to make his good better, that his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun credite may be the more increased, and the needlesse find-faults absurditie, more worthely pointed at. This in you haue I especially obserued, since the Translator of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madis de Gaule</hi> his second Part, (seeming to dwell farre from neighbors) speaking in his owne praise saith. That betweene the first Part which you translated, and that of his, there should be found more than a dayes difference. This peremptorie conceipt of himselfe, made me expect somwhat extraordinarie, wherein I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> not dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>'d, for within a few lines I found where he tells vs of a King, that married the Emperour of <hi>Constantinople:</hi> which error (beeing but one among manie as grosse) this bolde Censurer will needes cast vpon the Printer. I tell ye M. <hi>Mundy,</hi> this tutcht me neere, for a hundred such bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
<pb facs="6"/>haue I borne. The custome is common, when an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or Translator (either ignorant or negligent) palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly erre, then the Printer (forsooth) as if hee had deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to stand with a paper on his head at euerie Stationers stall, must make a great <hi>Errata,</hi> calling the Title, <hi>Faults escaped in the Printing:</hi> when (God knowes) should he let but halfe the faults passe of manie such VVriters, he should make them be as well laught at, as an vpstart at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney lately was at a Leete: who beginning to open his Clients Title to the Iudge, said. Vnderstand Sir, that <hi>Robert Norman</hi> late of <hi>Brampton</hi> Yeoman, tooke to wife <hi>Iohn Beeden,</hi> daughter to <hi>Walter Beeden</hi> of the same parish widdow: whereat the whole Court laughing, he would haue laid the burden on his man, who in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Remembrances, had writ <hi>Iohn</hi> for <hi>Ione,</hi> &amp; <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> for <hi>winefride.</hi> I would wish that Translator so to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse his Kings marriage with the Emperour. Or, let him say, he found it so in the French Copie (for those Printers are far hence) and because he would be singular for tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating verbally, being an absurditie in French, he let it passe in English. But for our Printers in <hi>England</hi> (were he <hi>Diues,</hi> who in these dayes can doo more than <hi>Lazarus</hi>) I dare affirme there is none of them will let so grosse a fault passe, except of purpose to make a grosse Braggart ridiculous: So leauing him, and wishing you to hasten your Translation of the third part. I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your old Well-willer:</hi> H. C. Printer.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>