<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable, his singular good Mayster, Sir  Christopher Hatton, Knight, Ca∣pitaine of the Queenes Maiesties Garde, Vicechamberlaine to hir Highnesse, and one of hir Maiesties most honou∣rable priuie Counsayle.</title>
           <author>Binniman, H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124501_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20738</idno>
           <idno type="STC">712.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124501</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable, his singular good Mayster, Sir  Christopher Hatton, Knight, Ca∣pitaine of the Queenes Maiesties Garde, Vicechamberlaine to hir Highnesse, and one of hir Maiesties most honou∣rable priuie Counsayle.</title>
                 <author>Binniman, H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An avncient historie and exquisite chronicle of the Romanes warres, both ciuile and foren : Written in Greeke by the noble orator and historiographer, Appian of Alexandria, one of the learned counsell to the most mightie emperoures, Traiane and Adriane. In which is declared: their greedy desire to conquere others. Their mortall malice to destroy themselues. Their seeking of matters to make warre abroade. Their picking of quarels to fall out at home. All the degrees of sedition, and all the effects of ambition. A firme determination of fate, thorowe all the changes of fortune. And finally, an euident demonstration, that peoples rule must give place, and princes power preuayle. With a continuarion [sic], bicause that parte of Appian is not extant, from the death of Sextus Pompeius, second sonne to Pompey the Great, till the ouerthrow of Antonie and Cleopatra, after the vvhich time, Octauianus Cæsar, had the lordship of all, alone</title>
                 <author>Appianus, of Alexandria</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 370, 6, 371-398, 12, 12, 296, 443-445, 9 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, his singular good Mayster, Sir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Christopher Hatton, Knight, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaine</hi> of the Queenes Maiesties <hi>Garde, Vicechamberlaine to hir Highnesse, and one of hir Maiesties most honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuie Counsayle.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT care the almightie King of Heauen hathe, of the Princes and States of the earthe, though sacred Scripture did not teache vs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane doctrine might instruct vs.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Homer</hi> shevveth, that God thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth his shielde in the vvarre, to defende the Prince from harme, and that he appoynteth to euerye gouernour, a peculiar God for his protection.</p>
   <p>Hovv God plagueth them that conspire againste theyr Prince, this Historie declareth at the full. For of all them, that coniured against <hi>Caius Caesar,</hi> not one did escape violent death. The vvhich this Author hathe a pleasure to declare, bycause he vvould affray all men from disloyaltie tovvard their Soueraigne.</p>
   <p>The greatest seruice that men can doe, is to saue theyr Countrey from daunger. The <hi>Romanes</hi> gaue him a crovvne that saued one Citizen. Then hovv many crovvnes deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth he, that helpeth to saue a number?</p>
   <p>They vsed to make a coyne for his commendation, vvith this inscription: <hi>The Senate and people of Rome for Citizens saued.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Cicero</hi> vvas called, Father of the Countrey, bycause hee
<pb facs="3"/>
kept it from decay. All they that in theyr consultations, do seeke the like benefite to their Countrey, doe deserue the like revvard and prayse, and in the testimonie of good mēs hearts, they are sure to haue it.</p>
   <p>Then seeyng this Authoures onely purpose is, to extoll the princely rule, and to procure the safetie of the people, I haue presumed to make a presente of hym to youre Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, that you being in case to do the like good, maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the same triumph of your desert.</p>
   <p>Hovv vvorthy the VVryter is to be redde, I referre it to the vvitnesse of one vvorthy<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>The reuerend father in God T. C. Bishop of Lincolne, in his booke entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Thesau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus linguae Latinae &amp; Britannicae.</note> Prelate of this lāde, vvho (as he sayd of <hi>Plato</hi>) shal suffice for a multitude. Further, vvith the manner of the Authoures vvriting I doe not meane to trouble you, himselfe shall tell your Honour, that such as be in your case, may bring to passe that he desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, to the glory of God, the honour of the Prince, the benefite of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and renoume of your selfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honoures seruaunt most duetifully bounden:
H. BINNIMAN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>