<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Conclusion to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124945_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72130</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11537.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124945</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Conclusion to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brief treatise containing the most strange and horrible cruelty of Elizabeth Stile alias Rockingham and her confederates, executed at Abingdon, upon R. Galis</title>
                 <author>Galis, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="conclusion">
   <head>The Conclusion to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hhus hast thou heard héere moste loouing Reader how much the foolish pittie and slacknes of the Magistrates of Windesore in executing their office, hath giuen occasion to these wicked Imps
<pb facs="15"/>
the Daughters of the Deuil, to persist in their follye, thou hast heard also remembred vnto thée what drifts of deuelish de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises since the first time of mother Duttons apprehension and brought by mée before Maister Richard Redforth then Maior of Windesore, hath by them béen practised to the great hurt of the Inhabitaunts, their neighbours, and to thy great admiracion, which if at that present had béen as thorowely sifted out as it was but wincked at, and as to late (I may say) it hath béen by some, (since those persons in the afore confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion mentioned and by their enchauntments brought to their ends) not only had enioyed their liues vntil this day: but I also a moste loouing Father and they them selues an assured and stedfast rock in the time of their néed, where now by their sufferance wée be depriued of bothe. But sith to call thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nges long time past in obliuion to remembrance again, will but increace my gréef and renue my sorowe: I therfore will with the vale of scilence couer that which my hart desired to expresse. Only I beséech the heauenly Father who is the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all goodnes that this ensample past and now to all men most apparaunt, may be so printed and rooted in the harts of all Magistrates appointed for the execution of true and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iustice to the maintenaune of the good and pulling down of the wicked, that from hence foorth not only all poore mens causes may be pitied, their complaints accepted, and their wrongs redressed: but also that by their carefull industry and diligence employed, all Sorcerers, Witches and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merers may vtterly be weeded out from the face of the earth to the commeditie of a common welth and to the honor &amp; glory of God, to whome be all praise, laude, dominion and power for euer and euer Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>