<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124379_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73707</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4710.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124379</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine explanation of the vvhole Revelation of Saint John : Very necessary and comfortable in these dayes of trouble and affliction in the church. Penned by a faithfull preacher, now with God, for more priuate vse, and now published for the further benefit of the people of God</title>
                 <author>Cartwright, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 139, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatsoeuer things were written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures, might haue hope.</hi> Rom. 15. 4. <hi>And the Reuelation of</hi> Iesus Christ, <hi>which God gaue vnto him, to shew vnto his Seruants,</hi> Reu. 1. 1. was giuen and written for the comfort of the Church in her latest and greatest troubles, and sharpest afflictions and persecutions; wherein certes Gods loue and care of his Church, is abundantly manifested. For not any of the Primitiue persecutions, or latter Antichristian Seducions, and bloudy Combustions, wherewith at this day the Church is turmoyled: But they are foretold, with their Issue and Euents in this Booke; that so the chosen and elect of God might not be carried to euerlasting perdition, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed with sorrow and displeasure in their seeming inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable temporary calamities.</p>
   <p>Many Commentaries and Expositions of this Booke haue beene published by very Reuerend and excellent learned men, no doubt to the great comfort of Gods people; and therefore the lesse need there may be imagined to be of any more: but, (besides that this is more briefe and plain vpon the whole Book then any other; and so is more vsefull for the most, that haue most vse of it; if it shall serue but as a watch-word, euen now to direct Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their perplexities, whether to haue recourse for comfort and consolation, and so incite them to a more diligent reading, and
<pb facs="4"/> studious search of this holy <hi>Reuelation,</hi> it will be a sufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollogy for this publication; especially at this time; when so many wauer betweene hope and dispaire of the good successe, of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Christendome; which so nearely concerne the welfare of the Church, as that the Enemies begin to looke bigge againe; daily expecting the ruine of it, as if the hope of Gods people were vaine; or as if by their wicked pollicy and power they made sure account to disappoint God of his purpose, and decreed destruction of the Kingdome of Antichrist; not considering that the more they extend their malicious practises against the desolate Woman, the more and greater woes are due vnto them, and the more horrible iudgements shall come vpon them, and that happily by meanes of those weaklings whom they now so much scorne and trample vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For, vpon whom haue they gaped, at whom haue they hissed, but at the holy ones, and the annointed of God? Well, I say no more, but that God is wonderfull in all his workes, and so will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himselfe in the destruction of those his enemies; and in the deliuerance of his faithfull ones out of the hands, and from the rage of the Dragon, and his Instruments; the <hi>Beast,</hi> and the <hi>false Prophet,</hi> with all their Locusts and Frogs; let them cast abroad neuer so great flouds of deceits and persecutions to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme the Church, and to extirpate true Religion; onely it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooues the professors of truth, in this expectation to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with faith and patience, and to exercise themselues in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods holy Commandements; and then they may rest assured of the accomplishment (in Gods good time) of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises expressed in this Booke.</p>
   <p>Wherein to helpe vs, the Author (a man of excellent gifts) long since trauailed; and now by the prouidence of God, are his labours in this kinde published for our comfort. I pray God that we may be directed to make good vse both of the holly <hi>Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> it selfe; and of his labour in the Explanation of it.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>