<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO HIS SINGVLER good freend and loouing Cuntreyman, Maister Robert Handley Citizen and Grocer of London and Merchant Venterer into the Cuntries of Spaine Richard Galis wisheth long life and prosperitie to the pleasure of God and his soules helth.</title>
           <author>Galis, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124945_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72130</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11537.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124945</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO HIS SINGVLER good freend and loouing Cuntreyman, Maister Robert Handley Citizen and Grocer of London and Merchant Venterer into the Cuntries of Spaine Richard Galis wisheth long life and prosperitie to the pleasure of God and his soules helth.</title>
                 <author>Galis, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brief treatise containing the most strange and horrible cruelty of Elizabeth Stile alias Rockingham and her confederates, executed at Abingdon, upon R. Galis</title>
                 <author>Galis, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>¶ TO HIS SINGVLER good freend and loouing Cuntreyman, Maister Robert Handley Citizen and Grocer of London and Merchant Venterer into the Cuntries of Spaine Richard Galis wisheth long life and prosperitie to the pleasure of God and his soules helth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I was giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand of your safe return from Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish soyle (moste deer and singuler good Freend) and of your happy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall heer into this Cittie, I vvas often in hart more desirous, then in effects any vviaesable, vvith some small tokē of my good vvil to gratulate your vvelcome home, and to thentent I might not be touched vvith that odible vice of Ingratitude (a vice of all men moste to be detested) I imagined many times vvith my self vvhich vvay I might best frame myne habilitie, by vsing some parte of renuneration for your manifolde curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies (as vve vpon my self as for my sake vpon my Freendes imployed) to auoid the same, emongst vvhich my cogitations this handful of scribled and banerpapers conteining the vvunderfull and moste strange crueltie of Elizabeth Stile alias Roc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kingham and her associates lately at Abingdon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarded vvith the guerdō due for their demerits, came to my mind, vvhich after I had finished albeit at the first deeming them vnvvorthy of dedication to any: yet at the last incensed vvith the natuall
<pb facs="2"/>
instinct of your gentle disposition I vvas imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (the rather for that that you your self haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted of their cup of displeasure) to commend the same beeing the first frutes of my labour to the gathering of your loouing hands therby outvvardly to shevve vvhat the invvarde hart desireth if abilitie did not vvant, hoping that vvith the moste renovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Persian King Artaxerxes you vvil freendly vouchsafe thākfully to receiue this handfull of colde vvater, the entire cognisaunce of my vvilling minde, offered vnto you, desiring you as leasure may serue you thorovvly vvith your freends to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use it, by reuoluing vvherof if you finde any delight, gently to thinke of the vvriter vvho vvisheth you encrease of health, vvelth and felicitie vntil the tīe that Atrapos shall cut of the thread of this your mortall life and that after you haue passed the pace and run the race of this short voyage and iournye and of this brittle frail and vnconstant life yovv may be placed, sociated, knit and comined in that glittering light and blesfull life of that celestiall Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rusalem amongst the company of heauenly Soules and holy mindes vvhich do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the life that only may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led life and only Emire inuincible.</p>
   <p>‡</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶ Your assured Freend in the Lorde Richard Galis.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>