<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of the Authour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124501_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20738</idno>
           <idno type="STC">712.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124501</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of the Authour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An avncient historie and exquisite chronicle of the Romanes warres, both ciuile and foren : Written in Greeke by the noble orator and historiographer, Appian of Alexandria, one of the learned counsell to the most mightie emperoures, Traiane and Adriane. In which is declared: their greedy desire to conquere others. Their mortall malice to destroy themselues. Their seeking of matters to make warre abroade. Their picking of quarels to fall out at home. All the degrees of sedition, and all the effects of ambition. A firme determination of fate, thorowe all the changes of fortune. And finally, an euident demonstration, that peoples rule must give place, and princes power preuayle. With a continuarion [sic], bicause that parte of Appian is not extant, from the death of Sextus Pompeius, second sonne to Pompey the Great, till the ouerthrow of Antonie and Cleopatra, after the vvhich time, Octauianus Cæsar, had the lordship of all, alone</title>
                 <author>Appianus, of Alexandria</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 370, 6, 371-398, 12, 12, 296, 443-445, 9 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface of the Authour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Romaine people and the Senate, did many<note place="margin">Foure causes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> of discorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Romaines. Holy <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>upiter,</hi> three myles beyond Rome, ouer the riuer <hi>Aniene,</hi> novv <hi>Tiberone.</hi> Creation of the Tribune of the people. <hi>Volscians</hi> people betvvene <hi>Hosti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> and <hi>Circei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> times contend, for makyng of Lawes, releasing of debts, deuision of landes, or electiō of officers, yet was there no tumult nor vprore, but onlye discorde and debates in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iuill maner, and that was done with great reuerence one to another. The people, on a time hauing bene at warre, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into like contention, did not abuse their armour presentlye, but stept aside vnto an hil, which therof was called <hi>Holy,</hi> where was no violence done, but a creation made of an officer of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, whom they called Tribune of the people, to be a restraint to the Consuls chosen by the Senate, that they shoulde not haue the only rule▪ in the Common wealth. Of this great hatred and variance grew betwéene these officers: the Senate and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being deuided for them, and styrred by ambition, sought the<note place="margin">
         <hi>M. Coriolanus,</hi> the first that rose against his coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, his name vvas. <hi>C. Martius,</hi> bycause the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Coriolie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Volscians,</hi> vvas vvonne chiefly by his meane, he bare the name of the city The Romai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes had their proper names, as <hi>Caius, Quintus,</hi> or <hi>Marcus,</hi> the name of their house, as <hi>Martius Valerius, Tullius,</hi> and of some fact or figure, as <hi>Publicola, Corio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus, Affricanus</hi>
      </note> one to ouer-rule the other. <hi>Martius Coriolanus,</hi> in such a contētion beyng vniustly banished, fled to the <hi>Volscians,</hi> and made warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his countrey. This only feate of force, should a man finde among the old strifes, which neuerthelesse was the act of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawe. But in their common metings, was neuer weapon drawn, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iuill murder done, before <hi>Tiberius Gracchus</hi> Tribune of the people and a deuiser of the Lawes, did firste perishe in sedition, and many moe with him taken in the<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Capitol</hi> an H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vvhere vvas the chiefe palace and temple, so called of a mans heade that vvas found It vvas begunne of <hi>Tarquinius Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>scus,</hi> &amp; finished by <hi>Tarquinius Superbus,</hi> but not dedicated. In the foundation <hi>Tarquinius</hi> spente xl. M. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. vvaight of silver. <hi>M Horatius</hi> the secōde consul in <hi>Brutus</hi> place did dedicate it. It vvas burned in <hi>Sylla</hi> his time, and bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lded againe, and dedicated by <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ullus, Sylla</hi> being deade. Then vvas it burned in <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ellius</hi> time and restored by <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>spatian:</hi> and also after his death it vvas burned againe and his sonne <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nician<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> builded it, and dedicated it, and made it so sunip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in guilding and trimming of it, is he spente aboue xij. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>talentes vpon it, nor for no great holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but for his pleasure, for his Galieries and his banquetting houses passed thys.</note>
      <hi>Capitol,</hi> were slain about the Temple. Notwithstanding, discorde ceassed not by this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, euery man being euidently bente against other, bringing many times their weapons, and now one officer, and then an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (by this diuisiō) was dispatched, in the temples, in assemblies and in Courts, the Tribunes, Pretors, or Consuls, eyther prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to it, or working this occasion of it. Uncomely contumely of
<pb n="2" facs="4"/>
euery trifle, and foule contempt of law and right, did euer play a part. This euil growing great, manifest insurrections wer made against the state, mightie and fierce armyes were raysed against the countrey, banished mē striuing for restitutiō, or magistrates contending among themselues, for offices at home, or army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade. Some there were, in power like princes, and as Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, made leaders of seditious armies: some would not leaue the army that was deliuered them of the people: some without au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, would leuie straunge souldiers against their enimies, striuing whether of thē should first get the Citie, in word against the cōtrary factiō, but in déede against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> countrey: for they inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, as an enemy. Cruell murders were vsed in some, in others proscriptions to deathe, banishments, consiscations, &amp; torments intollerable, so as no kinde of crueltie was left undone, till <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Sylla,</hi> one of the mightie Captaines of rebellion, fifty yeares after <hi>Gracchus</hi> healing euil with euil, made himselfe a Monarke for a time: the which kinde of officers, they called <hi>Dictators,</hi> vsed in most daungerous times, and commonly giuen ouer after sixe monethes were ended. But <hi>Sylla,</hi> being in déede <hi>Dictator</hi> by force,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dictator,</hi> vvas he that ruled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, yet at the battell he might not be on horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe.</note> perpetuall, yet in speach pretending to be elected, when he had his fill of that rule alone, was the first man, (as I thinke) that durst fréely giue ouer a Tiranicall power, affirming he woulde aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere for his doings, if any woulde accuse him: and in the sighte of all sortes, as a priuate man, many times he went to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place, and returned home againe without hurte. Suche a feare was there yet of his aucthoritie, in them that beheld hym, or an astonishmente, of the resigning of it, or a reuerence, that hée offered to aunsweare for hys doyngs, or some other cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie and consideration, acknowledging his Tyranny to haue bene profitable to the countrey.</p>
   <p>Thus a while sedition ceassed with <hi>Sylla,</hi> and there was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie of the euils that <hi>Sylla</hi> had done: but after hym it began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Caesar,</hi> conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Fraunce, passed the floud <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>,</hi> and sayled into England.</note> til <hi>Caius Caesar,</hi> by election sent to gouerne <hi>Fraunce,</hi> &amp; after a long time being cōmaūded by the Senate to giue ouer, he aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, that it was <hi>Pompey</hi> his enimie, leading an army in <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="4"/>
repining at his authoritie in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> that sought to remoue him, &amp; not the Senate. Yet notwithstāding, he propounded cōditions.</p>
   <p>That eyther both of them shoulde reteyne their armyes, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyde<note place="margin">
         <hi>Caesar</hi> offreth conditions.</note> suspition of perill:</p>
   <p>Or that <hi>Pompey</hi> also, should leaue his power, and liue a priuate life according to the lawes.</p>
   <p>Obteyning neyther of these, he marched out of <hi>Fraunce</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Pompey</hi> and his countrey, the which he inuated, and hym,<note place="margin">The place vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> called <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>harsalia,</hi> from the vvhich <hi>Pompey</hi> fled into <hi>Egypt,</hi> vvhere he vvas killed of the yong Kings Counsellers.</note> being fledde, he pursued into <hi>Thessalie,</hi> and ouercame him verye victoriously in a valiant battayle, whom fléeing from thence, hée followed into <hi>Egipt,</hi> where he was slaine of that countrey men. And when he hadde tarried and set a stay among the princes of <hi>Egipt,</hi> and ouerthrown his greatest enemy, who for his worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in the warres, was surnamed <hi>Great,</hi> no man nowe being<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pompey,</hi> for hys valiantnesse, had the name of <hi>Megnus,</hi> that is Great, giuen vnto him.</note> bolde to do anything against him, he returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> and was chosen the second <hi>Dictator</hi> perpetuall after <hi>Sylla.</hi> Then al sedition ceassed out of hande, tyll <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Cassius,</hi> eyther for enuye of his greatnesse, or for zeale of their countrey, kylled him in the<note place="margin">Brutus, Cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius.</note> Senate house, being most accepted to the people, and most expert in gouernement. The people, of all other, most lamented him, &amp; required his strykers to be punished: they burned his body in the common place, where they erected a temple, and sacrifised vnto<note place="margin">These attendu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res the <hi>Romaines</hi> called proscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vvhen a decree vvas vvritten to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denme a man vvithout aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvere, and ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> him vvithout lavv. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>epid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s. Antonius. Octau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tes.</hi>
      </note> him as to a God. Then discord reuued and increased so farre, as slaughter, bannishmente, attendures, both of Senate men and Gentlemen followed confusedlye, the seditious of both sides sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to sequester his enemye, he cared not howe, not sparing friendes nor brethren. So muche did deadly desire of debate, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelme al natural friendship and alliaunce. Yea they wente so farre, as thrée men, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, <hi>Lepidus, Antony,</hi> and he that first was called <hi>Octauius,</hi> (who being of <hi>Caesars</hi> bloud, and his son by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, toke of him the name of <hi>Caesar</hi>) did deuide the Romaine Empire, as a priuate possession, after the whiche deuision, falling soone out, as was none other lyke, <hi>Octauius, Caesar</hi> excéeding them both in wysedome and experience, fyrste berefte <hi>Lepidus</hi> of <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bia,</hi> which fell vnto him by lotte, and then ouerthrew <hi>Antonie</hi> at<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o</hi> a place in <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>pir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> The Gulfe of <hi>Ionia</hi> is from <hi>Brun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>usia</hi> to <hi>Mont Gargone,</hi> the rest is called the Gulfe of <hi>Venice.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Actio,</hi> and toke frō him al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rule he had
<pb n="4" facs="5"/>
from <hi>syna</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Ioma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> after these most mightie actes, wherewith all men were amased, with hys nauy he wanne <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> the gretest kingdome and of longest continuance, after <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi>
      <note place="margin">Egypt.</note> reigne, and only lefte to make the Romaine state as it is, by the which, being yet aliue, he was of the people of Rome<note place="margin">
         <hi>Augustus</hi> is a name, by the vvhich the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines did cal their holy things 25. <hi>Augusta temple</hi> &amp; <hi>Auguri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m,</hi> and vvhatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Iupiter</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaseth by hys mightie povver. The Senate did consult to cal him <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>dus,</hi> but this name semed more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and reuerent, that vvhiles hee vvas aliue, hee might be conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rated as a god.</note> called <hi>Augustus,</hi> and the firste that so had that title. He shewed himselfe to be another <hi>Caesar,</hi> yea more mightie than <hi>Caesar</hi> was, as wel touching the subication of his owne countrey, as of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations, not néeding any election, or forme of creation, to be a pretence to his doings. In continuance of time, being setled in his state, and in all things happy and beloued, he left behind him a succession; and a lynage to raigne likewise after him. Thus the Common welth of the Romaines, after diuerse debates, came to vnitie, and the rule of one. How these things were done, I haue written, gathering the most notable matter, that they that lyste, may sée the vnsatiable ambition of men in gréedy desire of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ioyned with intollerable paynes, and innumerable kindes of calamities. The which I haue the rather takē in hand, bicause dealing with the Historie of <hi>Egipt,</hi> and al these things going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and ending there, I was compelled to make rehersal of thē. For by this occasion was <hi>Egipte</hi> also conquered, when <hi>Cleopatra</hi>
      <note place="margin">The order of the story, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is left out in the <hi>Italian</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation. VVhen <hi>Caesar Octauian</hi> had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome <hi>Antony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> &amp; made <hi>Egipt</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uince to the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pire of Rome, he made one <hi>Cornelius Gallus</hi> lieftenant there, and in token of the Conquering of that countrey firste by him, hee coyned a money, in the vvhiche vvas the picture of a Crocodile, vvhich is there only to be seene in the floud <hi>Nilus,</hi> chayned to a palme tree, &amp; trees of Palmes laide ouer him, vvith an inscription. <hi>Col. Nem.</hi> that is, <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>lligauit Nemo,</hi> signifiyng that hee triumphed of <hi>Egipt,</hi> sprinkling it vvith deavv instead of rayne, of vvhich there is none.</note> toke parte with <hi>Antony.</hi> Now bycause of the multitude of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I haue deuided them thus. The first shall shewe the thyngs done from <hi>Sempronius Gracchus,</hi> to <hi>Cornelius Sylla.</hi> The seconde shall conteine al the actes from that time vnto the death of <hi>Caesar.</hi> The rest shall declare all the dissention that was betwéene the thrée men, one against an other, and the Citizens of Rome and them, vntill the last and greatest feate of Ciuill force, in the whyche <hi>Augustus</hi> ouercame <hi>Antonie</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> at <hi>Actio,</hi> from the which time the Chronicle of <hi>Egipt</hi> shal take his beginning.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>