<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface into the Sermon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1552</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124552_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72490</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14992.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124552</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface into the Sermon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A funerall sermon that was prepared to haue b [i] ne preached, by Robert King doctour in diuinit [y] for a cert [e] in honourable lady then almoste deade, but afterward recouered, to who [m] in writing this sermon was giuen, that she being [e] alyue, mighte read [e] what should hau b [i] ne preached at her death: howbeit now [e] God hath done his will vpon her and hath called her (I doubt not) to himselfe. But now it is here set forth [e] as it was deliuered to her then be [i] nge al [i] ue</title>
                 <author>King, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1552</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A preface into the Sermon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am comen hether this daye (Christen audy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) to preche at the buriall of this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbe Lady, my good Lady and Maistres. That that shalbe preached heare at this time, shal be to her nothing profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: for lernynge tyme, wyth her is past, but this sermon may be vnto you al, that shalbe the hearers of thesame, if ye imprinte it wel in your mynd, and bere it wel away profitable. It may be (I sai) profitable to you al, of whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer state, condiciō or degree, ye be of.</p>
   <p>¶ I haue chosen he parable, that our Sauiour Christe speketh of in the xvj. chapiter of sainte Luke, to treate of this day: out of the which parable, euery man mai learne, that marketh it wel, bothe how he dothe and also how he shoulde liue. And howe that if he lyue heare well, he shall euer after lyue well in ioye and pleasure. The contrary, if that he lyue not heare<pb facs="7"/>well, he shall no lyue hereafter, that is, he shall be damned and suffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall payne in hell. That we all may heare the doctrine of this parable preched so, that it may be to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of goddes glory and to the profite and vtilitie of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you for to pray. &amp;c.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>