<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PRINCE OF GREAT BRITAINE FRANCE AND IRELAND THE GROWING GLORY of a Future Age.</title>
           <author>Q., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124505_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72146</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1167.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124505</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PRINCE OF GREAT BRITAINE FRANCE AND IRELAND THE GROWING GLORY of a Future Age.</title>
                 <author>Q., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the advancement and proficience of learning; or, The partitions of sciences· : Nine books. Written in Latin by the most eminent, illustrious, and famous Lord Francis Bacon Baron of Verulam, Vicount St. Alban, Councellor of Estate, and Lord Chancellor of England. Interpreted by Gilbert Watts</title>
                 <author>Bacon, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                            <distributor>Young (Junius), Robert</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 60, 14, 352, 351-477, 21 pages, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedicatory_material">
   <div type="dedication">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <p>SACRATISSIMO DN̄O NOSTRO CAROLO DEI GRATIA MAG. BRITANNIAE FRANCIAE ET HIBERNIAE REGI. TERRAE MARISQ. POTENTISSIMO PRINCIPI. OCEANI BRITANNICI AD QUATUOR MUNDI PLAGAS DISPARTITI IMPERATORI. DN̄O VIRGINIAE ET VASTORUM TERRITORIORUM ADJACENTIUM ET DISPERSARUM INSULARUM IN OCEANO OCCIDENTALI.</p>
      <p>CHRISTIANAE FIDEI DEFENSORI PACIS INSTAURATORI PUB. SECURITATIS AUCTORI PIO FEL. AUG.</p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <p>
         <hi>NEC-NON</hi> SUB SUI NUMINIS INFLUENTIA AC CLIENTELA DUOBUS MAX. MUNDI LUMINARIBUS PERPETUIS SAPIENTIAE FLAMMIS CERTISS. SCIENTIARUM CYNOSURIS UTRISQ. ANGLIAE ACADEMIIS <hi>INFIMƲS HƲMILLIMƲS</hi> VERULAMII INTERPRES HANC PRIMAM INSTAURATIONIS MAGNAE PARTEM</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>D. N. C. Q.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="dedication">
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>TO THE <hi>PRINCE</hi> OF GREAT BRITAINE <hi>FRANCE AND IRELAND</hi> THE GROWING GLORY <hi>of a Future Age.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE sacrifice of my Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Dedication of these Labours (<hi>excellent</hi> PRINCE) had gone a more humble way of Ambition, than through the hands of Kings and Princes, could I afterwards have justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied such humiliations. But the Tenure of this work is a Title-Royall, which no laps of time nor alteration of language can reverse. In the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall entitled to a King; so continued in the Translation, and so in a direct line descends upon <hi>Your Highnesse,</hi> as a part of a Royall Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which I durst not alienate by a lower inscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Author is Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> a name well known in the European world; a learned man, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily the learned'st, that ever lived, since the decay
<pb facs="6"/> of the Grecian and Romane Empires; when learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was at a high pitch; and Which rise and fell with those Monarchies; for Scepters and Sciences have the same revolutions, the same periods. In the vast spaces of time between those and these last Ages, Philosophy hath bin, as it were in a slumber, for many centuries of years. For after the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian faith grew up, the most writers betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to Theology, and some mistaking the right limits of Faith and Reason, fell fowle upon Aristotle and other Philosophers, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches of Eresy, which were the Patrons of Reason. Somewhat awaked from this slumber she was, by the Arabian writers, the Schoole-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Spanish Interpreters; made more active by the Chimique Philosophers, but never perfectly recovered untill the daies of this Author, who is the first that ever joynd Rationall &amp; Experimentall Philosophy in a regular correspondence; which before was either a subtlety of words, or a confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of matter. He after he had survaied all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Antiquity, after the volumnes of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himselfe to the study of the volumne of the world; and having conquerd what ever books pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest (his spacious spirit not thus bounded) set upon the Kingdome of Nature, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="6"/> that victory very farre; and which was more than those victories, himselfe being mortall, left such lawes behind him, as may suffice to subdue the rest, if Princes encourage men, and men be not wanting to themselves. This attempt of his was favour'd by the starres of his Nativity. For it was his felicity to live in the times of two <hi>Great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of Learning,</hi> K. IAMES <hi>Your Highnesse</hi> Grandfather of blessed memory, and Your Royall Father now Raigning; and it was their glory that he lived in their times; and will be the eternall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Nation, that the <hi>Greatest Kings</hi> and the <hi>Greatest Philosopher</hi> met togither in one age, in one Iland. By the favour of <hi>his Prince,</hi> who well knew the valew of Learning and Learned men, he was raised to the highest dignities in the Civile state; and by his own happie Genius, to the highest degree in the state of learning; which was the greater wonder of the two; being such incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible perfections, and divided, enough to fill up the sphere of the greatest abilities alive. Yet with great applause he acted both these high parts, of the greatest Scholler and the greatest States-man of his time: and so quit himselfe in both, as one and the same Person, in title and merit, became Lord Keeper of the Great seale of England, and of the
<pb facs="7"/> Great Seale of Nature both at once, which is a mystery beyond the comprehension of his own times, and a miracle requires a great measure of faith in Posterity, to believe it. This is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor I here present unto <hi>Your Highnesse,</hi> this his worke, which by the powerfull influence of Your favour shall prosper, and, it may be, be quickned to the regeneration of another Phoenix out of his ashes, to adorne your World: for it is only the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigne aspect &amp; irradiation of <hi>Princes,</hi> that inspires the Globe of learning, and makes Arts, and sciences grow up and florish. Heaven blesse <hi>Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> with blessings on the right hand and on the left, and make You Heire of all the virtues of your Royall Progenitors, that the Honour of Princes begun in them, may be continued in Your person; and that a future age may be so blessed in You, as the present is in Your Royall Father, <hi>the Glory of Kings and their Admiration.</hi>
      </p>
      <closer>
         <signed>YOUR HIGHNESSE <hi>most Humbly devoted</hi> GILBERT WATS.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="to_the_reader">
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <head>FAVOVRABLE READER.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE intended <hi>Apologetique,</hi> for the <hi>Instauration of Sciences,</hi> and the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification of <hi>this Author,</hi> which should have bin prefix'd this work, as a preparation thereto; is not publisht. Motives to this resolution, were diverse, whereof some are very concerning. <hi>Apologetiques</hi> for such Authors and such enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are intertained with jealousies, as if they threatned an innovation in the state of Learning; by reversing the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and the Placits of the <hi>Moderne;</hi> and by bringing in, a new <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> into the Jntellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Globe of Sciences, to the subversion of the Arts received. But these are groundlesse fears, fancied by such, who either understand not the intention of this attempt; <hi>or,</hi> engag'd in a <hi>Professory way,</hi> suspect their profit and reputation to be in danger, if such designes should take effect. Our Author pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tests against such dareing vanities, <hi>the raising of any new sect, upon the ruins of Antiquity;</hi> and every where endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to improve the labours of Ancient and Moderne writers,
<pb facs="8"/> and so must he doe who defends him, if he understands the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse he goes about. The point is not, touching what is already done; nor of the abilities of the Agents; nor of the capacity of their instruments; which could not be undertakē without emulous comparisons, both of Persons, Actions, and Things: but the point is touching <hi>propagation &amp; Advancement of Knowledges;</hi> the improvement, and not the conservation only, of the Patrimony of our Ancestors: and that by opening to the <hi>understanding</hi> a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent way, than hath bin known to former Ages; and clearing <hi>that glasse</hi> to the letting in of a more plentifull light. The waies and ends of these two knowledges (I meane of what we have, and of what we may have) thus different; and the principles upon which they proceed so divers; both may consist without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and confutations; or the invasions upon their distinguisht rights: &amp; so the <hi>propagation of Knowledge,</hi> by the assistance, <hi>of the Father of Lights,</hi> may be pursued, with the reservation of the honour of Ancient and Moderne Authors, and the Arts in use, which respecting the end whereto they were instituted, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputation, Redargution</hi> and the like, are very conducent, and in their way of perfection highly exalted. And this is the first mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of deliberating the publication of my Apologetique, the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of the businesse. <hi>Another is this.</hi> The times into which we are fallen, are learned Times, as ever were since the Grecian Philosophers, and, their seconds, the Arabian writers, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so through the great advantages, of the experiments of later A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the directions of Antiquity, in many particulars have out-gon their predecessors; so as he that dare adventure, as, some doe, to intrude unstudied thoughts upon so learned an age as this is, neither reverences the age as he ought, nor wisely consults his own reputation with Posterity. And as the Times are learned, so (which too frequently falls out) somewhat confident. Great wits, and which have fortified their conceptions by books and study, are strongly prepossest with almost impregnable anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and not so easily induced, as more inconcerned and disen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged natures are; to know or unknow any thing, that either should be farther inquired into, or should be for gotten. And much within these two orbs our Apology moves; in discovery of
<pb facs="8"/> Jgnorance &amp; of Error; of what we know not, and of what we should not know. For certainly much knowledge remaines yet conceal'd, and the way to this discovery is by forgoeing many unprofitable subtleties; and by a learn'd ignorance falling off from many aery speculations, to the solid simplicity of the Ancients. Were we to compose a Panegyrique in praise of the perfections of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our daies, which indeed merits such a sacrifice, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour were but halfe what it is, for laudatory hymnes seldome come out of season; they need no preparations, and what might be wanting in the waight of speech, would be supplied by an aptitude to accept and believe. But in the businesse in hand, the <hi>mind of man,</hi> the principall subject to be wrought upon, and <hi>her speculations,</hi> both which we so admire, are so immur'd and blockt up with corrupt notions, either from the placits of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers, the depraved lawes of Demonstration; or from inherent qualities in the generall nature of man, or individuate tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of particulars; that nothing can be done untill these be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced; at least, subjected to examination: which is another mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive that staies me upon the Land. <hi>An other Reason,</hi> (which is the last I will trouble the Reader withall is this. Time the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of all our Actions, without whose assistance our best concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are <hi>Abortives,</hi> by the intercurrence of other engagements (which I might have dispenced withall, had I rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the servile tenure of secular contracts) hath surpriz'd me. I conceive, which I pronounce with some passion, that a Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler for his studies, had bin the master of his own howres; but he-that trafiques with the world shall finde it otherwise. Time which I presum'd I could command, and stay as I doe my watch, hath commanded me. And these diversions were seconded <hi>(Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reader)</hi> by a sad Accident. It pleased God in the heat of my attendance on this businesse, to take away, by one of the terrors of mortality, the <hi>Stone,</hi> my deare brother <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> RICHARD SCOT,</hi> servant to the most Eminent <hi>Lord</hi> the <hi>Lo. Deputy Generall of Ireland;</hi> beloved of his deare <hi>Lord</hi> to the latest minute of life; honour'd with his presence to the farthest confines of mortality; and there, by his Noble Piety, deliver'd up, with as much solemnity, as a Kingdome could conferre, unto the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality
<pb facs="9"/> of another world. This deadly shaft passing through him, so wounded me, that I my selfe was arrived within few paces of the land of darknesse. Jn his <hi>silent</hi> Marble, the best part of that small portion of joy I had in the World; but <hi>all my hopes,</hi> are entombed. This pensive casualty so took me off from books and businesse, as for some months after, I could relish no thoughts but what were mingled with the contemplations of mortality. <hi>Sic fugit interea fugit irrevocabile tempus.</hi> These were the impediments to my <hi>Apologetique;</hi> which (if what is done be accepted) shall be prefix'd the <hi>NOV. ORG.</hi> For of this Translation this is the first part <hi>(Reader)</hi> if it please thee, if it please thee not, the last. But before I take my leave, here are some tacite objections, which I would meet halfe way, and so weaken their approaches, lest they fall too heavy upon me. <hi>The first is,</hi> touching the <hi>Division of the first book into Chapters,</hi> contrary to the mind of the Author, and the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the work. This exception may be thus satisfied, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit is to be preferred before artificiall contrivance, where both cannot so conveniently be had, and to this end, discretion to be followed before rule. Were the Author now alive and his vast Designes going on, this alteration had been somewhat bold: but the inimitable Architect now dead, having perfected litle more then the outward Courts, as it were, of his magnificent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration; and the whole summe of Sciences, and the stock of Arts in present possession, not able to defray the charges of fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing this Fabrique; I thought fit, by compartitions and distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions into severall roomes, to improve what we have, to our best advantage, so it might be done without prejudice to the Authors procedure, and apt coherence, which J hope it is: Having respect herein rather to accommodation than decoration; for <hi>Houses</hi> (as our Author saies) <hi>are built to live in and not to look on, and therefore use to be preferred before uniformity.</hi> Another Exception may be made against the draught of the Platforme into <hi>Analytique tables,</hi> which seems somewhat pedantique and against that common rule <hi>Artis est dissimulare Artem.</hi> To this J answer thus. <hi>Order</hi> and dependance is as it were, the soule of the World, of the Works of Nature and Art, and that which
<pb facs="9"/> keeps them united, without which all would fall asunder and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like the first Chaos before the production of light. And of all <hi>Methods</hi> that ever were, at least that ever came to our hands, our Authors is the most naturall and most dependent. For <hi>Truth,</hi> as it reflects on us, is a congruent conformity of the Jntellect to the Object; and of the different faculties thereof, to the difference of things: wherefore the truest <hi>Partition</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning, is that, which hath reference to humane facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; when the <hi>Intellectuall Globe,</hi> and the <hi>Globe of the World,</hi> intermixe their beams and irradiations in a direct line of projection, to the Generation of Sciences. This our Author hath perform'd to admiration; and in this gone beyond all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, yet upon their grounds; wherein he can never be out-gone, unlesse followed, by Posterity. The Ancients indeed, were men of most profound speculations, but in the delivery of themselves, somewhat involv'd, as appears by <hi>Plotinus, Proclus, Trisme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistus</hi> and others; and many of <hi>Platoes</hi> Schoole writ Dialogue-wise, which is no doctrinal way. As for <hi>Aristotle,</hi> his precepts touching <hi>method</hi> (if any such book was written) they are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risht; saving where he scatters such rules here and there, which should have been silenced, and are not so well followed by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. And for the <hi>Methods</hi> of the Modernes, <hi>Ramus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the improvement of <hi>German</hi> writers, impair'd; they knit the limmes of knowledge to soone; have bedwarfed Sciences, <hi>and are become an Art</hi> (as learned <hi>Hooker</hi> expresses it) <hi>which teaches the way of speedy discourse, and restrains the mind of man, that it may not waxe over-wise.</hi> The <hi>Excellency</hi> therefore of our Authors <hi>Partitions,</hi> induced me to these <hi>delineations,</hi> for their use only, who have not the leasure, or patience to observe it according to the merit; that by this <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> the junctures and arteries, as it were, of this great body might more visibly appeare. <hi>An other objection is,</hi> touching the <hi>Allegations in the Margin,</hi> contrary to the solemne cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of Antiquity, and the most of graver Authors. <hi>For this</hi> I had these reasons. It pleased our Author, thoe he was himselfe a living fountain of knowledge, and had a wealthy stock of his own, yet to tast of other waters, and to borrow from Antiquity, and to
<pb facs="10"/> acknowledge such borrowings, He thus nameing his Authors, I thought fit to note them. And as he was a man of a most elevated phansie and choice conceptions; so was he in the selection of his Authors, and the passages he pleas'd to make use of: and it is worth the labour to know with whom such great wits use to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse; to point to the <hi>Mines</hi> where they digge their Ore; and to the shadowes where they repose at noone. And as his selection of Authors was very choice, so was his application of their sayings, very curious; and in a strain beyond the vulgar reach. Places out of <hi>Sacred Scriptures</hi> are so explicated, so applied, as you may search all the Commenters that are extant, and not finde the like expositions, as you shall finde in him. As for humane Authors he betters his borrowings from them; teaching the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations out of them, a sense above the meaning of him that lent it him; and which he repaies too with double interest for what he borrowed. These considerations invited me to Marginall Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. These Reasons set apart, I cannot approve this weake am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; and doe, not without censure, read Moderne Authors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute to humane allegations; as if the <hi>Truth</hi> they deliver, were to be tried by voices; or having lost its primitive Innocence, must be cover'd with these fig-leaves; or as if the Authors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves were afraid that it should make an escape out of their text, if it were not beset in the Margin with Authorities as with a watch. <hi>The last exception is,</hi> touching the <hi>Prefaces,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Introductions</hi> prefix'd this worke, that make the Gates and Entries so wide, as they seem to invite the Citty to run away. This is thus answer'd. Jt must be remembred that this worke in the Designe was very spacious; and is in the performance of what is done so ample, that when the second and third Parts shall be added, as added they will be, the <hi>Porches</hi> and <hi>Ingresses,</hi> in the judgement of any good Architect, are proportionable enough. And if our <hi>Authors</hi> rule hold, that every faire Fabrique should have three Courts; a greene Court; a second Court more gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht; and a third to make a square with the Front; then have you here this Epistle as the mean Court; Iudgements upon this Author living and dead, as the middle Court; and the Authors own excellent Preface to confront with the work it selfe. <hi>Now
<pb facs="10"/> I should,</hi> say something touching <hi>Translation;</hi> and as it is mine. The very Action is somewhat obnoxious to censure; being of the nature of those, the failing whereof may disgrace more, than the carrying of it through, credit the undertaker. But, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the conscience of the deed done; for other ends I could not have; (the Author now dead, and alive <hi>mihi nec injuriis nec beneficiis notus</hi>) and that to be a <hi>Translator</hi> is more than to be an <hi>Author,</hi> some such as there be; and that it is no such mean office, to bear a light before a <hi>Lord Chancellor of England:</hi> I should excuse it, were the example mine: so, writes learned <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> so, eloquent <hi>Sandys;</hi> so, <hi>Malvezzi's Noble Interpreter;</hi> with whom conferred I am lesse than a shadow: So, many able and eminent names of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and other Nations; So the Ancients of former ages and of all Arguments. But if any be so solemne, so severe, and of such primitive tasts, they can away with no waters, which come not from the spring-head; nor endure to drink of <hi>Tiber,</hi> that passes through <hi>Thames;</hi> They may give over here, if they so please, and proceed no farther. This interpretation was not meant for such fastidious palates, and yet, it may be, for as distinguishing as theirs are. Now if this very action be thus liable to exception, much more must my performance be. Certainly books by <hi>Translation</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly take wind in the effusion; and for strength fall short of their <hi>Originals;</hi> as reflexed beams are weaker than direct: but then it must be understood of <hi>Originals,</hi> truly so. For if a <hi>Writer</hi> deliver himselfe out of his Native language, J see not why a <hi>Translator</hi> rendring him in it, may not come neare him: and in this case, the Author himselfe is the <hi>Interpreter,</hi> being he <hi>translates</hi> his own thoughts, which originally speak his mother tongue. Yet for all this, Errors I know there are, and some lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which require a Connivence; and a Reader hath this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that he may stay upon one period, as long as an Jnterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did on one page; besides his peculiar Genius to some studied passages. Some Errors (passing but a transient eye upon what is done) J see already; and could note them; but I would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly gratify some kind of Readers so farre. They that are Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious and ingenious too (for J would have no Readers that
<pb facs="11"/> have not these two ingredients in their compositions, thoe some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I name but one, which I would then, should be predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant) will in their judgements find them, and in their mercy pardon them. <hi>As for Sophists</hi> and <hi>Satyrists,</hi> a degenerate Race of men, that sit upon the lives and learning of all that write; who resolv'd to doe nothing themselves, may with more security censure others: and them too, who, as <hi>Learned DON</hi> deciphers them, <hi>forbid not bookes, but men; damning what ever such a name, hath, or shall write:</hi> they are <hi>things</hi> below the merit of my indignation; objects of Scorne; which a litle sligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and not inflamed by opposition, or countenanced to a reply by confutation, will within a while, of themselves, extinguish, and vanish: like some dispersed roving winds, which without encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre are dispirited and die. And it concernes me, Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to put on such a confidence as this; for being I am likely to appeare in mine own person, as I doe now in the Person of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to be too tender-fronted were to invite injuries, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute such unseasonable modesty to abuse. He that will to sea, must look for some cloudy daies; and to be too <hi>scrupulous</hi> or <hi>Ceremonious</hi> touching <hi>Times</hi> or <hi>Persons,</hi> is the bane of busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and of all well-meant endeavours: according to that of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, Qui observat ventum non seminat, &amp; qui conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Nubes, nunquam metet.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <head>
         <hi>TESTIMONIES</hi> CONSECRATE TO THE <hi>MERITE OF THE</hi> INCOMPARABLE PHILOSOPHER S<seg rend="sup">R</seg> FRANCIS BACON BY SOME OF THE BEST-LEARN'D <hi>OF THIS JNSTANT AGE.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough <hi>severe Jnquisitors of truth,</hi> and such who, by their learned Labours, stand upon pub. Record in the approv'd Archives of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, may, in an humble distance, lay claim and title to that sacred Prerogative — <hi>Ego autem ab homine Testimonium non Capto; ipsa enim Opera quae facio testantur de me,</hi>— yet because such <hi>Great Authors,</hi> in their high flight, are so lessen'd in the aire of unfrequented contemplations; &amp; take such unbeaten waies, as they become the <hi>weak won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of common Capacities, accustom'd to populare opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and authoriz'd Errors: and in this admiring Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the <hi>prejudicate objects</hi> of Emulation, Envy, Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, and such like impotent passions: Jt seems, in a sort, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, that the way be clear'd before such writers; and that they enter the Theatre, as well with the suffrage of <hi>voice,</hi> to gaine upon the <hi>will;</hi> as with the strength of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> to convince the <hi>Vnderstanding.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Wherefore, not so much for the honor of this Author,
<pb facs="12"/> (though that is intended too) as for the aid of some antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Readers, not yet manu-missed from a servile beliefe, to the liberty of their own judgements, (such J mean, as are yet under the minority of an implicite faith) J thought good to deliver this imperfect list of <hi>Deponents,</hi> which the precipitancy of this Edition, would not permit to fill up with some other <hi>Great Names,</hi> both of this Kingdome, and of forrain Nations. What is wanting here to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of this <hi>Catalogue,</hi> Time, <hi>the Parent of Truth,</hi> shall Consummate.</p>
      <p>LE SIEUR MAUGARS Counsilor and secretary to the K. of France, in the Epist. to his Translation of a Part of this Work, gives our Author this Testimony.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Amongst whom every one knows that S</hi>
         <seg rend="sup">r</seg> FRANCIS BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CON, <hi>by many degrees off, holds the first rank, both for the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity of his Spirit, eminency of his Learning, Elegancy of his stile. J have studied with diligence all his writings; and presume I may doe a performance of some merit and acceptation, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting to my Countrey his Books of the</hi> ADVANCEMENT OF LEARNING, <hi>a Work hath not bin seen in our Language. This is the</hi> Book <hi>which I have caused to passe the Seas; not as the Gold of the Jndies, to cherish vice, and corrupt our Manners; but as a soveraigne Plant of singular virtue, to cure the wounds, which ignorance and Pedantisme have given</hi> humane sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
      <p>M<seg rend="sup">R</seg> PEIRRE D'AMBOIS S<seg rend="sup">R</seg> DE LA MAGDELAINE In his just and elegant discourse upon the life of our <hi>Author,</hi> delivers his censure thus.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Judgement and Memory never met in any man in that height and measure they met in him; so as in short time he became</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>of all those</hi> Knowledges <hi>which are learnt in Schooles.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>A page after; <hi>But as he ever valewed himselfe, rather borne for other men, than himselfe; now that he could not, for want of imployment, any longer endow the publique with his</hi> Active perfections; <hi>he was desirous at least to become profitable
<pb facs="12"/> in a</hi> Contemplative way, <hi>by his writings and by his books, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents certainly meriting, to find entertainment in all the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braries of the world; and which deserve to be ranged with the fairest works of Antiquity.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The same noble French-man in his Advertisement to our Auctors <hi>Nat. History</hi> thus expresses him.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>For this</hi> Naturall History, <hi>where the quality of Metalls, the Nature of Elements, the Causes of Generation, and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the divers actions of Bodies one upon another, and such like impressions, are discoursed with such life and light, that he may seem to have learn'd his knowledge</hi> even in the Schoole of the First Man. <hi>And though herein he may be thought to have pass'd upon the breaches of</hi> Aristotle, Pliny, <hi>and</hi> Cardan; <hi>yet notwithstanding he borrowes nothing from them: as if he had a designe to make it appeare, that those great men, have not so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely possest themselves of this subject, but that there remains much to be discover'd. For my part, thoe it be farre from my intention, to raise the reputation of this</hi> Author <hi>upon the ruins of</hi> Antiquity; <hi>yet J think it may be avouched upon the grounds of reason, that in this present Argument he hath some advantage of them: being that the most of the</hi> Ancients <hi>which have written of</hi> things Natural, <hi>have satisfied themselves in reporting things, as the information of others have given them intelligence; and not considering, that oftentimes that which is deliver'd them for</hi> History, <hi>is farre esloign'd from all verity; they have chosen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by reasons to confirme the resolutions of another, than to make an exact enquiry and discovery themselves. But</hi> Mon<seg rend="sup">r</seg> BACON <hi>not relying upon the meer word and credit of such as went before him, will have</hi> Experience <hi>joyn'd with</hi> Reason; <hi>and examines the receiv'd principles of the Schooles, by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Nature; the speculations of the</hi> Intellectuall Globe, <hi>by the operations of the</hi> Corporale. <hi>By this means he hath found out so many rare secrets, whereof he hath bequeath'd us the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and made many axioms acknowledged for false, which hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to have gon current amongst Philosophers, and have bin held inviolable.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <p>TOB. ADAMI, In his Preface to the REALIS PHILOSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHIA, of that excellent Philosopher CAMPANELLA (who lives to enjoy that Fame, which many eminent for their learning, rarely possesse after death) speaks his opiniō thus.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>We erect no sect, establish no Placits of Eresie, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to transcribe universale and ever-veritable Philosophy out of the Ancient Originall Copy of the world: not according to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable and disputable speculations, but according to the Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of sense and irrefragable depositions of the Architect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, whose hand in works, dissents not from his word in writing. And if the</hi> GREAT INSTAURATION <hi>of the deep-mineing Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher,</hi> FRA. BACON LO. VERULAM Chancellor of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>a work of high expectation, and most worthy, as of Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, so of assistance, be brought to perfection, it will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance appeare, that we pursue the same ends, seeing we tread the same foot-steps intraceing, and as it were, hounding nature, by</hi> Sence <hi>and</hi> Experience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>S<seg rend="sup">•</seg> TOB. MATHEWS, In his Epist. to the Duke of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> prefixt his Italique Translation of my LO. BACON'S <hi>Essaies,</hi> amongst other Elogies deciphers him thus.</p>
      <p>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> AUSTEN, <hi>said of his illegitimate sonne</hi> Horrori mihi erat illud ingenium, <hi>and truly I have known a great number whom J much valew, many whom J admire, but none who hath so asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht me, and as it were, ravisht my sences, to see so many and so great parts, which in other men were wont to be incompatible, united, and that in an eminent degree in one sole Person. I know not whether this truth will find easy beliefe, that there can be found a man beyond the Alpes, of a most rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wit; most faithfull memory; most profound Iudgement; of a most rich and apt expression; universall in all kinds of knowledge, as in part may be seen by that rare incomparable piece, the</hi> ADVANCEMENT OF LEARNING, <hi>which future A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges shall render in different languages: But be the faith of other Nations what it will in this point, the matter J report is so well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood in</hi> England, <hi>that every man knowes &amp; acknowledges as much, nay hath bin an eye and eare witnesse thereof; nor if I
<pb facs="13"/> should expatiate upon this subject should J be held a flatterer, but rather a suffragan to truth, &amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> GEORGE SANDYS In his excellent Commentaries on his inimitable Translation of the stately METAMORPHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIS, rendred, in an equall felicity of expression, to the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fires of that <hi>sweet tongu'd Roman;</hi> often cites the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Author, from whose sentence he never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, but rather adores as an Oracle; and in an ingenious acknowledgement of assistance from him, thus delivers him to posterity.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Of Moderne writers J have receiv'd the greatest light from</hi> Geraldus, Pontanus, Ficinus, Vives, Comes, Scaliger, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus, <hi>and the</hi> CROWNE of the later the VICOUNT OF S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ALBANS; <hi>assisted, thoe lesse constantly, by other Authors, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of all Ages and Arguments. Having bin true to my first purpose, in making choice, for the most part, of those interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which either beare the stamp of</hi> Antiquity, <hi>or receive e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimation from the</hi> honor of the Author.</p>
      <p>MARIN MERSENNE An able man, but a declar'd ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary to our Authors designe (whose Arguments I shall encountre in my Apologetique for the <hi>Instaur. of Sciences</hi>) in his Bookes of the VERITY OF SCIENCES against the <hi>Sceptiques</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhonians Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> xvi. acknowledges thus much, which comming from an Adversary is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more valid.</p>
      <p>VERULAM, <hi>seems to have no other intention in his</hi> NEW METHOD, <hi>then to establish the</hi> VERITY OF SCIENCES; <hi>wherefore you must not anticipate, as granted, that he makes for you, or that he is of your opinion; he confesses we know litle, but he subverts not the Authority of</hi> Sense <hi>and of</hi> Reason, <hi>no, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to find out proper and proportionable instruments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to Conduct the understanding to the knowledge of Nature and her effects.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="authors_censure">
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <head>The Authors Censure upon himselfe.</head>
      <p>For in my judgement, it is a matter which concernes not only the Benefit of others; but our own Reputation also; that no man imagine that we have projected in our minds some slight super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall notion of these <hi>Designes;</hi> and that they are of the nature of those things, which we could <hi>Desire,</hi> and which we accept only as <hi>good wishes.</hi> For they are such as without question, are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the power and possibility of men to compasse, unlesse they be wanting to themselves; and hereof, we for our parts, have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and evident demonstration; <hi>for we come not hether, as Augures, to measure Countries in our mind, for Divinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but as Captaines, to invade them for a conquest.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="authors_response">
      <head>His answer to some Tacite Objections.</head>
      <p>I doe foresee that many of those things which I shall register as <hi>DEFICIENTS</hi> will incurre divers censures; as <hi>that some parts</hi> of this enterprize were done long agoe, and are now extant; <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> that they tast of curiosity &amp; promise no great fruit; <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> that they are impossible to be compassed by humane indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stries. <hi>For the two first,</hi> let the particulars speak for themselves. <hi>For the last touching impossibilities,</hi> I determine thus. All those things are to be held possible and performeable which may be accomplisht by some person, thoe not by every one; and which may be done by the united labours of many, thoe not by any one apart, and which may be effected in a succession of Ages, thoe not in the same Age; and in briefe which may be finisht by the care and charge of the pub., thoe not by the abilities and industry of private persons. Jf for all this there be any, who would rather take to himselfe that of Solomon, <hi>Dicit Piger Leo est in via,</hi> than that of Virgil <hi>Possunt quia posse videntur</hi> — it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me, if my labours may be estimed as votes yet the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sort of wishes: <hi>for as it askes some knowledge to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a Question not impertinent; so it requires some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, to make a wish not absurd.</hi> Proem. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="encomium">
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <head>IN HONOREM ILLVSTRISSIMI DNI FRANCISCI DE VERVLAMIO Vice-Comitis S<seg rend="sup">TI</seg> ALBANI POST EDITAM AB EO INSTAUR. MAG.</head>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Ʋis iste tandem? non enim vultu ambulat</l>
      <l>Quotidiano. Nescis Jgnare? audies,</l>
      <l>Dux Notionum; veritatis Pontifex;</l>
      <l>Jnductionis Dominus; &amp; Verulamii;</l>
      <l>Rerum Magister unicus, at non Artium:</l>
      <l>Profunditatis Pinus; at{que} Elegantiae:</l>
      <l>Naturae Aruspex intimus: Philosophiae</l>
      <l>Aerarium▪ Sequester Experientiae,</l>
      <l>Speculationis{que}: Aequitatis Signifer:</l>
      <l>Scientiarum sub pupillari statu</l>
      <l>Degentium olim Emancipator▪ luminis</l>
      <l>Promus: Fugator Jdolûm, at{que} Nubium:</l>
      <l>Collega Solis: Quadra Certitudinis:</l>
      <l>Sophismatum Mastix: Brutus Literarius,</l>
      <l>Authoritatis exuens Tyrannidem:</l>
      <l>Rationis &amp; sensus stupendus Arbiter;</l>
      <l>Repumicator Mentis: Atlas Physicus,</l>
      <l>Alcide succumbente <hi>STAGIRITICO:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Columba Noae, quae in vetustis Artibus</l>
      <l>Nullum locum, requiemve Cernens, praestitit</l>
      <l>Ad se suam{que} Matris Arcam regredi.</l>
      <l>Subtilitatis terebra; Temporis nepos</l>
      <l>Ex veritate matre: Mellis Alveus:</l>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <l>Mundi{que} &amp; Animarum, sacerdos unicus:</l>
      <l>Securis Errorum: in{que} Natalibus</l>
      <l>Granum sinapis, acre aliis, Crescens sibi.</l>
      <l>O me prope Lassum; Juvate Posteri.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>GEOR. HERBERT Orat. Pub. in Academ. Cantab.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="elegies">
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <head>MANES VERVLAMIANI SIVE <hi>IN OBITƲM INCOMPARABILIS</hi> FRANCISCI DE VERVLAMIO, &amp;c. <hi>EPICEDIA.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NCLYTA Academia CANTABRIGIENSIS, cujus felicitas fuit, <hi>viro</hi> ad salutem scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum <hi>nato,</hi> primas sapientiae mammas prebere; ac <hi>Philosophum,</hi> post occasum Graeciae, <hi>maximum,</hi> orbi dare: super fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Alumni sui Lacrymas effudit, doctas ac duraturas maestitias. Ex hoc integro Musarum fonte, modica haec sed facunda fluenta, collegit <hi>interpres;</hi> ut quod, viventi, seculum dederat decus, gliscente adhuc invidiâ; &amp; morienti dedisse constaret, cessante nunc adulatione. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua sui nominis aeternitati consecranda, continuatâ secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum serie ad ultimas us{que} mundi favillas, rependet po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritas: Quis supremam suis laudibus manum imponet, novit tantum, <hi>Fundator ille, ac simul eversor Seculorum.</hi>
      </p>
      <div type="poem">
         <pb facs="16"/>
         <lg>
            <l>ADhuc superbis insolente purpurâ</l>
            <l>Feretri rapinis Inclytos in tot viros</l>
            <l>Sterile Tribunal? cilicio dicas diem,</l>
            <l>Saccúm{que} totam facito luxuriem fori.</l>
            <l>A <hi>Themide libra</hi> nec geratur pensilis,</l>
            <l>Sed <hi>urna,</hi> praegravis urna <hi>Verulamii.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Expendat. Eheu! Ephorus haud lancē premit,</l>
            <l>Sed Areopagus; nec minor tantus sophos,</l>
            <l>Quā Porticus bracchata <hi>Nam vester, scholae,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Gemiscit axis, tanta dum moles ruit.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Orbis soluta cardo litterarii,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Ʋbi studio coluit togam &amp; trabeam pari.</l>
            <l>Qualis per umbras Ditis Euridice vagans</l>
            <l>Palpare gestiit Orphëum, quali Orphëus,</l>
            <l>Saliente tandem (vix prius crispâ) Styge,</l>
            <l>Alite fibras lyrae titillavit manu;</l>
            <l>Talis plicata Philologωn aenigmatis</l>
            <l>Petiit Baconum vindicem, tali manu</l>
            <l>Lactata cristas extulit Philosophia:</l>
            <l>Humi{que} soccis reptitantem Comicis</l>
            <l>Non proprio Ardelionibus molimine</l>
            <l>Sarsit, sed <hi>Instauravit.</hi> Hinc politiûs</l>
            <l>Surgit cothurno celsiore, &amp; <hi>Organo</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Stagirita virbius reviviscit <hi>Novo.</hi>
            </l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Calpen superbo Abylám{que} vincit remige</l>
            <l>Phoebi Columbus, artibus novis, <hi>Novum</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Daturus <hi>Orbem;</hi> promovet conamina</l>
            <l>Juvenilis ardor, us{que} ad invidiam trucem</l>
            <l>Fati minacis. Quis <hi>Senex</hi> vel <hi>Hannibal,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Oculi superstitis timens caliginem,</l>
            <l>Signis Suburram ventilat victricibus?</l>
            <l>Quis Milo inultus quercubus bilem movet,</l>
            <l>Senecta tauro gibba cùm gravior premit?</l>
            <l>Dum noster Heros traderet scientias</l>
            <l>Aeternitati, prorsus expeditior</l>
            <l>Sui sepulchri comperitur artifex.</l>
            <l>Placida videtur Ecstasis speculatio,</l>
            <pb facs="16"/>
            <l>Quâ mens tueri volucris Jdaeas boni</l>
            <l>Jn lacteos properat Olympi tramites.</l>
            <l>His immoratur sedibus Domestica,</l>
            <l>Peregrina propriis. Redit. Iocularitèr</l>
            <l>Fugax; vagatur rursus, &amp; rursus redit.</l>
            <l>Furtiva tandem seriò, se subtrahit</l>
            <l>Totam; gementi, morbido cadaveri</l>
            <l>Sic desuescit anima, sic jubet mori.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Agite lugubres Musae, &amp; à Libani jugis</l>
            <l>Cumulate thura. Sydus in pyram illius</l>
            <l>Scintillet omne; scelus sit accendi rogum</l>
            <l>Regum Prometheo culinari foco.</l>
            <l>Et si qua fortè ludat in cineres sacros</l>
            <l>Aura petulantior, fugam{que} suadeat,</l>
            <l>Tunc flete; lachrymis in amplexus ruent</l>
            <l>Globuli sequaces. Denuò fundamine</l>
            <l>Ergastuli everso radicitùs tui</l>
            <l>Evehere foelix anima, <hi>Iacobum</hi> pete,</l>
            <l>Ostende, &amp; illuc <hi>civicam fidem</hi> sequi.</l>
            <l>E Tripode juris, dictites oracula</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Themidos</hi> alumnis. Sic (Beati coelites)</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Astraea</hi> pristino fruatur vindice,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vel cum Bacono rursus Astraeam date.</hi>
            </l>
         </lg>
         <closer>
            <signed>R. P.</signed>
         </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem">
         <lg>
            <l>AƲdax exemplum quò Mens humana feratur,</l>
            <l>Et Saecli vindex ingeniose tui;</l>
            <l>Dum senio macras recoquis foeliciter artes,</l>
            <l>Subtrahis &amp; prisco libera colla jugo;</l>
            <l>Quo deflenda modo veniunt tua funera? quales</l>
            <l>Exposcunt lacrymas, quid sibi fata volunt?</l>
            <l>An timuit Natura parens ne nuda jaceret,</l>
            <l>Detraxit vestem dum tua dextra sacram?</l>
            <l>Jgnoti{que} oculis rerum patuere Recessus,</l>
            <l>Fugit &amp; aspectum Rimula nulla tuum?</l>
            <pb facs="17"/>
            <l>An veró, Antiquis olim data Sponsa Maritis,</l>
            <l>Conjugis amplexum respuit illa novi?</l>
            <l>An tandém damnosa piis at{que} invida caeptis,</l>
            <l>Corripuit vitae fila (trahenda) tuae?</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Archim.</note>Sic ultra vitreum <hi>Siculus</hi> ne pergeret orbem</l>
            <l>Privati cecidit militis ense <hi>Senex.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Tu{que} tuos manes ideò <hi>(Francisce)</hi> tulisti,</l>
            <l>Ne, non tentandum, perficeretur opus.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>SƲnt qui defuncti vivant in marmore, &amp; aevum</l>
            <l>Annosis credant postibus omne suum:</l>
            <l>Aere micant alii, aut fulvo spectantur in auro,</l>
            <l>Et, dum se ludunt, ludere fata putant.</l>
            <l>Altera pars hominum, numeros â prole superstes,</l>
            <l>Cum <hi>Niobe</hi> magnos temnit iniqua <hi>Deos.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>At tua caelatis haeret nec Fama Columnis,</l>
            <l>Nec tumulo legitur, <hi>Siste viator iter:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Si qua Patrem proles referat, non corporis illa est,</l>
            <l>Sed quasi de cerebro nata <hi>Minerva Jovis.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Primatibi virtus monumenta perennia praestat,</l>
            <l>Altera, nec citiùs corruitura, Libri:</l>
            <l>Tertia Nobilitas; ducant jam fata triumphos,</l>
            <l>Quae <hi>(Francisce)</hi> tui nil nisi corpus habent.</l>
            <l>Ʋtra{que} pars melior, Mens &amp; bona Fama supersunt,</l>
            <l>Non tanti ut redimas vile cadaver habes.</l>
         </lg>
         <closer>
            <signed>T. Vincent. T. C.</signed>
         </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem">
         <l>
            <hi>MUsae</hi> fundite nunc aquas perennes</l>
         <l>In Threnos, Lacrymás{que} <hi>Apollo</hi> fundat</l>
         <l>Quas vel <hi>Castalium</hi> tenet Fluentum:</l>
         <l>Nam Letho ne{que} convenire tanto</l>
         <l>Possint naenia parva, nec coronent</l>
         <l>Immensa haec modicae sepulchra guttae:</l>
         <l>Nervus ingenii, <hi>Medulla suadae</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Dicendi{que} <hi>Tagus,</hi> reconditarum</l>
         <pb facs="17"/>
         <l>Et gemma pretiosa Literarum,</l>
         <l>Fatis concidit, (heutrium Sororum</l>
         <l>Dura stamina) Nobilis <hi>Baconus.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>O quam te memorem <hi>Bacone</hi> summe</l>
         <l>Nostro carmine! &amp; illa gloriosa</l>
         <l>Cunctorum monumenta seculorum,</l>
         <l>Excusa ingenio tuo, &amp; <hi>Minervâ!</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Quam doctis, elegantibus, profundis,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Instauratio Magna,</hi> plena rebus!</l>
         <l>Quanto luminetineas Sophorum</l>
         <l>Dispellit veterum tenebricosas</l>
         <l>Ex chao procreans novam <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>:</l>
         <l>Sic ipse Deus inditum sepulchro</l>
         <l>Corpus restituet manu potenti:</l>
         <l>Ergo non moreris <hi>(Bacone)</hi> nam te</l>
         <l>A morte, &amp; tenebris, &amp; à sepulchro,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Instauratio Magna</hi> vindicabit.</l>
         <closer>
            <signed>R. C. T. C.</signed>
         </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem">
         <l>
            <hi>PArcite: Noster amat facunda silentia luctus,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Postquam obiit solus dicere qui potuit:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Dicere, quae stupeat Procerum generosa corona,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Nexa{que} sollicitis solvere Jurareis.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Vastum opus. At nostras etiam</hi> Verulamius <hi>artes</hi>
         </l>
         <l>INSTAURAT <hi>veteres, condit &amp; ille novas.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Non qua majores: Penitos verum ille recessus</hi>
         </l>
         <l>NATURAE, <hi>audaci provocat ingenio.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Ast Ea,</hi> siste gradum, seris{que} nepotibus, <hi>(inquit,)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Linque quod inventum saecla minora juvet.</l>
         <l>Sit satis, his sese quod nobilitata Jnventis,</l>
         <l>Jactent ingenio tempora nostra tuo.</l>
         <l>Est aliquid, quo mox ventura superbiet aetas;</l>
         <l>Est, soli notum quod decet esse mihi:</l>
         <l>Sit tua laus, pulchros Corpus duxisse per artus,</l>
         <l>Integra cui nemo reddere membra queat:</l>
         <pb facs="18"/>
         <l>Sic opus artificem in fectum commendat Apellem,</l>
         <l>Cum pingit reliquam nulla manus Venerem.</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Dixit, &amp; indulgens caeco</hi> Natura <hi>furori,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Praesecuit vitae Filum Operis{que} simul.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>At Tu, qui pendentem audes detexere telam,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Solus quem condant haec monumentascies.</hi>
         </l>
         <closer>
            <signed>H. T. Coll. Trin. Socius.</signed>
         </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem">
         <lg>
            <l>DƲm moriens tantam nostris <hi>Verulamius Heros</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Tristitiam <hi>Musis,</hi> lumina{que} uda facit:</l>
            <l>Credimus heu nullum fieri post fata beatum,</l>
            <l>Credimus &amp; <hi>Samium</hi> desipuisse senem.</l>
            <l>Scilicet hic miseris, foelix nequit esse, <hi>Camaenis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nec se quàm <hi>Musas</hi> plus amat iste suas.</l>
            <l>At luctantem animam <hi>Clotho</hi> imperiosa coëgit</l>
            <l>Ad coelum, invitos traxit in astra pedes.</l>
            <l>Ergone <hi>Phoebeias</hi> jacuisse putabimus artes?</l>
            <l>At{que} herbas <hi>Clarii</hi> nil valuisse Dei?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Phoebus</hi> idem potuit, nec virtus abfuit herbis,</l>
            <l>Hunc artem at{que} illas vim retinere putes:</l>
            <l>At <hi>Phoebum</hi> (ut metuit ne Rex foret iste <hi>Camaenis</hi>)</l>
            <l>Rivali medicam crede neg âsse manum.</l>
            <l>Hinc dolor est; quod cum <hi>Phoebo Verulamius Heros</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Major erat reliquis, hac foret arte minor.</l>
            <l>Vos tamen ô, tantum Manes at{que} Ʋmbra, <hi>Camaenae,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Et poenè inferni pallida turba <hi>Jovis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Si spiratis adhuc, &amp; non lusistis ocellos,</l>
            <l>Sed ne{que} post illum vos superesse putem:</l>
            <l>Si vos ergo aliquis de morte reduxerit Orpheus,</l>
            <l>Jsta{que} non aciem fallit imago meam:</l>
            <l>Discite nunc gemitus, &amp; lamentabile carmen,</l>
            <l>Ex oculis vestris lacryma multa fluat.</l>
            <l>En quam multa fluit? veras agnosco <hi>Camaenas</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Et lacrymas, <hi>Helicon</hi> vix satis unus erit;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Deucalionaeis:</hi> &amp; qui non mersus in undis</l>
            <pb facs="18"/>
            <l>
               <hi>Pernassus</hi> (mirum est) hisce latebit aquis.</l>
            <l>Scilicet hic periit, per quem vos vivitis, &amp; qui</l>
            <l>Multâ <hi>Pierias</hi> nutriit arte <hi>Deas▪</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Vidit ut hic artes nultâ radice retentas,</l>
            <l>Languere ut summo semina sparsa solo;</l>
            <l>Crescere <hi>Pegaseas</hi> docuit, velut Hasta <hi>Quirim</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Crevit, et exiguo tempore Laurus erat.</l>
            <l>Ergo <hi>Heliconiadas</hi> docuit cùm crescere <hi>divas,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Diminuent hujus secula nulla decus.</l>
            <l>Nec ferre ulterius generosi pectoris aestus</l>
            <l>Contemptum potuit, <hi>Diva Minerva,</hi> tuum.</l>
            <l>Restituit calamus solitum divinus honorem,</l>
            <l>Dispulit &amp; nubes alter <hi>Apollo</hi> tuas.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Dispulit &amp; tenebras sed quas obfusca vetustas,</l>
            <l>Temporis &amp; prisci lippa senecta tulit;</l>
            <l>At{que} alias methodos sacrum instauravit acumen,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Gnossia{que}</hi> eripuit, sed sua fila dedit.</l>
            <l>Scilicet antiquo sapientum vulgus in aevo▪</l>
            <l>Tam claros oculos non habuisse liquet;</l>
            <l>Hi velut <hi>Eoo</hi> surgens de littore <hi>Phoebus,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Hic velut in mediâ fulget <hi>Apollo</hi> die:</l>
            <l>Hi veluti <hi>Typhis</hi> tentârunt aequora primum,</l>
            <l>At vix deseruit littora prima ratis,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pleiadas</hi> hic <hi>Hyadas{que}</hi> at{que} omnia sydera noscens,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Syrtes,</hi> at{que} tuos, improba <hi>Sylla,</hi> canes;</l>
            <l>Scit quod vitandum est, quo dirigat aequore navem,</l>
            <l>Certiùs &amp; cursum nautica monstrat acus:</l>
            <l>Infantes illi <hi>Musas,</hi> hic gignit adultas;</l>
            <l>Mortales illi, gignit at iste <hi>Deas.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Palmam ideo reliquis <hi>Magna Instauratio</hi> libris</l>
            <l>Abstulit, &amp; cedunt squalida turba sophi.</l>
            <l>Et vestita novo <hi>Pallas</hi> modo prodit amictu,</l>
            <l>Anguis depositis ut nitet exuviis.</l>
            <l>Sic <hi>Phoenix</hi> cineres spectat modò nata paternos,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Aesonis</hi> &amp; rediit prima juventa senis.</l>
            <l>Jnstaurata suos &amp; sic <hi>Verulamia</hi> muros</l>
            <pb facs="19"/>
            <l>Jactat, &amp; antiquum sperat ab inde decus.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Sed quanta effulgent plus quam mortalis ocelli</l>
            <l>Lumina, dum regni mystica sacra canat?</l>
            <l>Dum sic naturae leges, arcana{que} Regum,</l>
            <l>Tanquam à secretis esset utrisque, canat:</l>
            <l>Dum canat <hi>Henricum,</hi> qui Rex, idem{que} Sacerdos,</l>
            <l>Connubio stabili junxit utram{que} Rosam.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Atqui haec sunt nostris longè majora <hi>Camaenis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Non haec infoelix <hi>Granta,</hi> sed <hi>Aula</hi> sciat:</l>
            <l>Sed cum <hi>Granta</hi> labris admoverit ubera tantis</l>
            <l>Ius habet in laudes (maxime <hi>Alumne</hi>) tuas.</l>
            <l>Ius habet, ut moestos lacrymis extingueret ignes,</l>
            <l>Posset ut è medio diripuisse rogo.</l>
            <l>At nostrae tibi nulla ferant encomia <hi>Musae,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Ipse canis, laudes &amp; canis inde tuas.</l>
            <l>Nos tamen &amp; laudes, quâ possumus arte, canemus,</l>
            <l>Si tamen ars desit, laus erit iste dolor.</l>
         </lg>
         <closer>
            <signed>Tho. Randolph. T.C.</signed>
         </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem">
         <l>SIc cadit <hi>Aonii</hi> rarissima Gloria coetûs?</l>
         <l>Et placet <hi>Aoniis</hi> credere semen agris?</l>
         <l>Frangantur Calami, disrumpantur{que} libelli,</l>
         <l>Hoc possint tetricae si modo jure <hi>Deae.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Heu quae lingua silet, quae jam facundia cessat,</l>
         <l>Quò fugit ingenii Nectar &amp; Escatui?</l>
         <l>Quomodo Musarum nobis contingit Alumnis</l>
         <l>Ʋt caderet nostri praeses <hi>Apollo</hi> chori?</l>
         <l>Si nil cura, fides, labor, aut vigilantia possint,</l>
         <l>Si{que} feret rapidas, de tribus una, manus;</l>
         <l>Cur nos multa brevi nobis proponimus aevo?</l>
         <l>Cur putri excutimus scripta sepulta situ?</l>
         <l>Scilicet ut dignos aliorum à Morte labores</l>
         <l>Dum rapimus, nos Mors in sua jura trahat.</l>
         <pb facs="19"/>
         <l>Quid tamen in cassum nil proficientia fundo</l>
         <l>Ʋerba? quis optabit te reticente, loqui?</l>
         <l>Nemo tuam spargat violis fragrantibus urnam,</l>
         <l>Nec tibi <hi>Pyramidum</hi> mole sepulchra locet;</l>
         <l>Nam tua conservant operosa volumina famam,</l>
         <l>Hoc satis, haec prohibent te monumenta mori.</l>
         <closer>
            <signed>Williams.</signed>
         </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
         <p>ORdine sequeretur descriptio Tumuli VERULAMIANI, monumentum Nobiliss. MUTISII, in honorem domini sui constructum; quâ pietate, &amp; dignitatem Patroni sui, quem (quod rari faciunt, etiam post cineres Coluit) consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit; Patriae suae opprobrium diluit; sibi nomen condidit. Busta haec nondum invisit Interpres, sed invisurus: Interim Lector tua cura Commoda, &amp; abi in rem tuam.</p>
      </div>
      <epigraph>
         <q>
            <l>Crescit occulto velut Arbor aevo</l>
            <l>Fama <hi>BACONI.</hi> —</l>
         </q>
      </epigraph>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="20"/>
      <pb facs="20"/>
      <head>FRANCISCVS BARO DE VERVLAMIO Vice-Comes SANCTI ALBANI.</head>
      <div type="section">
         <head>ALMAE MATRI <hi>INCLYTAE ACAD.</hi> CANTABRIGIENSI. <hi>S.</hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ebita Filii qualia pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum persolvo; quod vero facio, idem &amp; vos hortor, ut AUGMENTIS SCIEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIARUM strenuè incumbatis: &amp; in Animi modestia libertatem ingenii retineatis. Ne{que} talen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum à veteribus concreditum in sudario reponatis. Affuerit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul-dubiò
<pb facs="21"/> &amp; affulserit Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Luminis Gratia, si humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atâ &amp; submissâ RELIGIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NI PHILOSOPHIA cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vibus sensûs legitimè &amp; dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trè utamini: &amp; amoto omni con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictionis studio, Quis{que} cum alio, ac si ipse secum dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, <hi>Valete.</hi>
         </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
         <pb facs="20"/>
         <head>INCLYTAE <hi>ACADEMIAE</hi> OXONIENSI. <hi>S.</hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vm ALMAE MATRI meae inclytae ACADE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIAE CANTABRIGIENSI Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serim, deessem sanè officio, si simile Amoris pignus sorori e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus non deferrem. Sicut autem eos hortatus sum, ita &amp; vos hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ut SCIENTIARUM AUO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTIS strenuè incumbatis, &amp;
<pb facs="21"/> veterum labores, ne{que} nihil, ne{que} omnia esse putetis; sed vires eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am proprias modeste perpenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, subinde tamen experiamini, omnia cedent quam optimè; si Arma non alii in alios vertatis sed junctis copiis in Naturā rerū impressionē faciatis, sufficit quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe illa Honori &amp; Victoriae, <hi>Valete.</hi>
         </p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb n="1" facs="21"/>
      <head>FRANCIS LO. VERVLAM <hi>CONSƲLTED THƲS,</hi> AND THVS CONCLVDED WITH HIMSELFE; THE PUB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICATION WHEREOF HE <hi>CONCEIV'D DID CONCERNE THE PRESENT AND FƲTƲRE AGE.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EEING it was manifestly known unto HIM, that humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing creates it selfe much trouble; nor makes an apt and sober use of such Aides, as are within the Command of Man; from whence infinite igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Things; and from the ignorance of Things, innumerous disadvantages; his opinion was, that with all our industry we should endeavour, if hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily that same <hi>COMMERCE OF THE MIND AND OF THINGS</hi> (than which a greater blessing can hardly be found on Earth, certainly of earthly Felicities,) <hi>might by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny means be entirely restored; at least brought to termes of neerer correspondence.</hi> But that Errors, which have prevailed, and prevaile would for ever, one after another, (if the mind were left free to it self) should rectify themselves, either by the imbred pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="2" facs="22"/> of the understanding, or by the aides and assistan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Logick, there was no hope at all; because that the Primitive Notions of Things, which the mind with a too facile and supine attractive faculty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives in; treasures up and accumulates, from which all the rest are derived; are unsound, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and rashly abstracted from things. The like luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant vanity and inconstancy there is in the second and sequent Notions; whence it comes to passe, that all that human Reason which we employ, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Inquisition of Things, is not well digested and built; but like some magnificent Pile without foundation. For whilest men admire and celebrate the counterfeit forces of the mind; hir true powers which might be raised (were right directions admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred, and she taught to become obsequious to things, and not impotently to insult over them) they passe by and loose. This one way remaineth that the businesse be wholly reatempted with better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations; &amp; that there be throughout, <hi>AN IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STAƲRATION OF SCIENCES AND ARTS,</hi> and of all Human Learning rais'd from solid foundations. And this though it may seeme in a sort an infinit enterprize, and above mortall abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, yet the same will be found more sound and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised, than those performances which hetherto have bin atchieved: for in this there is some issue; but in the endeavours now undertaken about Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a perpetuall wheeling, Agitation and Circle. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he ignorant how unfrequented this <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
         <pb n="3" facs="22"/> is, how difficile and incredible to perswade a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, yet he thought not to desert the designe, nor himselfe, but to try and set upon the way, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is pervious and penetrable to the mind of Man. For it is better to give a beginning to a thing which may once come to an end, than with an eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention &amp; studie to be enwrapt in those mazes which are endlesse. And the waies of Contemplation for most part resemble those celebrated waies of Action; the one, at the first entrance hard and difficult, ends in an open plain; the other at first fight ready and easy, leads into by-waies and downfalls: And being he was uncertain when such considerations should hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come into any mans mind, induced especially from this argument, that there hath none hetherto appear'd, who hath applied his mind to such cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he resolv'd to publish, seperatly, the <hi>First parts</hi> as they could be perfected. Neither is this an ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous but sollicitous festination; that if in the mean space he should depart this mortall station; there might yet remain a designation and destination of the thing he comprehended in his mind; and withall some Demonstration of his sincere and propense af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to promote the good of Mankind. Truly he estimed other ambition whatsoever, inferior to the businesse he had in hand: For either the matter in consultation, and thus farre prosequuted, is nothing; or so much as the conscience of the merit it selfe, ought to give him contentment without seeking a recompence from abroad.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>