<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124923_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72054</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10635.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124923</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The saints legacies: or, A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God : Collected for private use, but published for the comfort of Gods people: by Anne Phoenix</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Swaine, Robert 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 203, 17 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An which at the beginning was created happy,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</note> having now lost God and his image,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.3.</note> is of all earthly creatures become most miserable, no lesse then a slave of the Devill, a child of wrath, and an heire of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4</note> This is not the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of a few onely, but of all man-kinde out of Christ; for we are all by nature under the curse.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10</note>
      <pb facs="26"/>The best,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> before their conversion, were by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture children of wrath, even as others: for every womans child did fall equally in <hi>Adam:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</note> hence it comes to passe, that no man by nature is now in better esteem with God then other. <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> as children of the first <hi>Adam</hi> onely were equally miserable; the like may be said of us all,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9.</note> for both Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles are come under sin. And as the <hi>Psalmist</hi> saith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ps.</hi> 14.3.</note> Wee are all gone out of the way, wee are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become filthy, there is none righteous, no not
<pb facs="26"/>one. Oh that men and women had their eyes enlightned, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments convinced of that woefull plight in which naturally they are! Oh! were their hearts thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly loaden therewith, surely they would not long content themselves therein. The truth is,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.19.</note> most in the world are spiritually blinde,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> and cannot discerne their owne miserie;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually dead too, &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee affected with it: The Holy Ghost saith thus of them;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 19.</note>
      <hi>They walke in the vanity of their mind, having their understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="27"/>darkned, and are stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the life of God, through the ignorance which is in them, because of the hardnes of their hearts: who being past feeling have given themselves unto wan tonnesse, to worke all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannesse with greedinesse.</hi> Such as these, are so farre from having any right to Gods promises, that for the present they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curse,<note place="margin">Deut. 27. ult. Deut. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>8.63.</note> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the dint of all the plagues and thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in Gods booke. Wherfore let not such as yet challenge any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the Promises, but let them rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="27"/>to the uttermost of their power, in using all good meanes to be made capable and sit subjects for mercy revealed in the Promises. Is it not pitty so many sweet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of life should bee made, and yet thou die and be damned notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing? Pray fervently to God that he would touch thy heart with griefe for all thy sinnes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37 <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.1 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 20, 21.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> &amp; worke in thee a cleare apprehension of thine owne unworthinesse, &amp; that hee would bestow faith on thee, that by it thou mayest be able to go wholly out of thy selfe
<pb facs="28"/>to God, through Jesus Christ for salvation.</p>
   <p>We having departed from him who is the God of all grace &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, are fallen into an estate of all basenesse desolation, and miserie; &amp; cannot bee recovered againe into the former estate of spirituall life &amp; happinesse, unlesse wee be brought againe to him who is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, even the living God: and brought to him wee can never bee, but by Faith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heh.</hi> 11.6.</note> which is nothing els but the going out of the soule to god through
<pb facs="28"/>Christ, to fetch a new principall of spirituall life and grace, which once in <hi>Adam</hi> wee lost, and now need.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8, 17.</note> The which worke of faith is not wrought but by the promises; and being wrought in our hearts gives us a most sure right and interest <hi>unto all the promises of grace.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heh.</hi> 6.12.17.</note> Thus wee through faith &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience are said to inherit the promises, therefore we are called the heires of the promise: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises are as well ours, who truely beleeve, as heaven it selfe is. Now by these heavenly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pct.</hi> 1.3.</note>
      <pb facs="29"/>God our Father hath engaged himselfe as a debtour to us his poore children for all things needfull to life &amp; godlinesse, untill that blessed time comes whē wee shall be put into full possession of all things which wee have now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in promise: at that time <hi>Faith</hi> shall end in fruition, and <hi>Promises</hi> in performance. As the soule is the life of the body, and faith the life of the soule, so are Gods promises the life of faith. For from whence hath faith his efficacie, but because it layes hold
<pb facs="29"/>on the free promises? but from whence have the promises their strength?<note place="margin">2, <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> even from the constant nature of <hi>Iehovah,</hi> who alwaies gives a beeing to his word. Desirest thou faith? then take notice of Gods promises: woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest thou have thy faith like the light in the Lords Sanctuary never to go out? then acquaint thy selfe with Gods <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,</hi> know them well, meditate on them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre about them: let them bee continually in thy minde, memorie, heart and tongue. Satan laboureth in nothing
<pb facs="30"/>more then to keepe us in unbeleefe, especially of particular Promises, for he knowes if we beleeve them,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.</note> wee shall in all things have the victory,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eph</hi> 2.</note> come before God with boldnesse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Heh.</hi> 11.</note> carry peace in our owne bosomes to our graves, and doe, and suffer any thing for God. Oh the abundance of sweet cordiall comfort which all humble belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers draw by faith out of every promise! Now beloved,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isay</hi> 66.11 12.</note> these precious <hi>Promises,</hi> (our breasts of consolation) whereupon our happinesse so much depends, lie hid in the
<pb facs="30"/>holy scripture, as veynes of gold in the earth. Surely, those that search those mynes to bring to light these treasures, are worthy of great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. Wherfore I doubt not but the good paines of this blessed &amp; faithfull servant of God will finde good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the promises, that hope to entertaine them, who hath with great care and good evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of sprituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding discovered and compiled the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and use of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises in matters tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="31"/>spirituall, &amp; eternal. So that here is a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine for every disease, &amp; a salve for every sore. Read them carefully and ponder them seriously, and apply them faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And I beseech the good Lord, who is the author of them, that by his holy spirit he would make them powerful, &amp; effectuall in us.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7.</note>
      <hi>Consider what is said, and the Lord give us understanding in all things.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>