<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124475_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72378</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13756.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124475</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine godly, and most necessarie annotations : vpon the thirteenth chapter to the Romanes: set forth by the right vigilant pastor: Iohn Hoper, by Gods calling, Bishop of Gloucester</title>
                 <author>Hooper, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </seg>He office &amp; duty of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian man, is contained in two parts. The firste, that be vse himselfe aright and reuerently with God. The seconde, that hee vse him comely and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly with man. In the Epistle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans from the beginning S. Paul hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and sufficiently declared the duty and office of man, towards God: towardes the end, he declareth how we may honestly do our duties towards men. Both these offices must diligently be knowne and exercised. And because a ciuil &amp; outward life, seeme it neuer so honest, is meere and very hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie, and can not please God, except the mind and soule inwardly bee well affected towards him: I thinke it conuenient brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to declare wherein S, Paul in this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle doth put the religion of the heart of man, towardes God: and then we shall the better descende vnto such dueties and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as appertaineth to all maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as well publique as priuate.</p>
   <p>First, S. Paule perceiueth that the grace and promises of God cannot be knowne of man, vntil such time as he be brought to
<pb facs="6"/>acknowledge and displeasure of his sinnes. The Phisition &amp; Phisicke be vnprofitable vnto such as know not that they be sicke, as Christ sayd,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math. 9.</hi>
      </note> I came not to cal the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st, but sinners to repentaunce. Therefore we must know the wound of our soules, and the sickenesse of sinne, before we can get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profit by the grace of God. We must confesse that all men and women, except Christ, are borne the children of yre and of Gods displeasure, and that we beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in vs synne, that alwayes repugneth the spirit, wherby we are acertayned that we be always subiect vnto synn as S.
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom. 11.</hi>
      </note> Paul sayth, be concludeth al men vnder synne, because he might haue mercy vpon al. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are all synners and the rewarde of synne,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom. 6. Ephe. 2.</hi>
      </note> S. Paules conclusion where be sayth, we are borne all the children of Gods displeasure, is true. How then may we be deliuered from this great yre and displeasure?
<note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Ioh. 4. Rom. 5.</hi>
      </note> By the mercye of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towards vs, that first loued vs, or we loued him, whiles we were yet his enemies But what is that, wherewith all we may be annexed and reconciled vnto God by his mercy, when there is no good thing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<pb facs="6"/>but all filthy &amp; sinful? It is Iesus Christ, the son of God, most dere beloued, in whom the father is contēted, &amp; by whō he is recō ciled vnto al sinners that repent &amp; beleue his promises,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat. 3.17. Ephe. 12. Col. 1.2. Rom. 8. Phil. 2.</hi>
      </note> for the merites &amp; sheding of Christs bloud, his dere beloued sonne. After that, we see and perceiue so great a mercy &amp; pitty of our heauenly father, that wold not fauour nor spare his only sonne, to dye for our redempio, but gaue him to the most cruel &amp; vile death of the crosse forvs, how should not we trust to so merciful a father in al our troubles &amp; aduersityes, whether they be of body or soul? Why should we not cal onely vpon so merciful a God.
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat 11.</hi>
      </note> If we do thus amend our liues, beleeue his promises and study a better lyfe,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> we shall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be saued by his mercy, but also glad to serue him, and walke before him in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency &amp; purenes of life: &amp; also obediently &amp; quietly in the world, giue reuerence and loue to all persons accordingly to whom? honor, honor: to whom loue, loue: to whom? iustice, iustce: to whom mercy, mercy. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this christian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uietnes, reuerence, loue and feare, doth at the scripture exhort vs, &amp; cheefly this present <hi>13.</hi> chap. to the Ro.
<pb facs="7"/>For the vnderstanding wherof the better I note at the beginning a certaine diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie and difference of persons. There be, and euer hath bene some publique persons and some priuate persons. Publique per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, be those that beare any office, rule, re giment or dominion, in a common wealth: as a king with all his iustices, Maiors, Sheriffes, Baliffes, Constables, and other. Priuate persons, be such as be subiectes, &amp; vnder these officers. These two persons must be diuersly vsed, &amp; the duety that is due vnto the one is not due vnto the other in ciuill respectes. And seeing we must liue with both these persons and states apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be in the world by almighty God. S. Paul in this Chapiter is very diligent to teach &amp; instruct vs how we should liue accordingly in truth and honesty towards them both.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>