<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1535</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124880_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14027.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124880</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triades or trinities of Rome translated in to Englyshe : Them that synne rebuke openly that other may feare and drede. Timo.v</title>
                 <author>Hutten, Ulrich von</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Godfray, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1535</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface</head>
   <p>GEntell reder / ye shal ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue here gadred togeder those thynges / the whiche be eyther sette by / vsed / or hated at Rome. That place trewly may be called Rome / where such enormities be moche vsed. For so / after the mynde of Nicolas de Lira and other Saynte Peter in the ende of his fyrst Epystell / <note place="margin">i. Pet. v.</note> called Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me by the name of Babilon / bycause it was in Idolatry / lechery / and pryde. &amp;c. at al poyntes lyke to it. And as it may be now called (for the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me thynges / yee / &amp; other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che worse / if worse may be) Sodoma or Gomurra / were it nat that they diffren in this one onely poynte / whiche is aboundaūce of brede &amp; wyne.
<pb facs="3"/>
For as in Gomurra &amp; Sodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me was great plentie of fode for euery man / so lykewise in Rome is the contrary therof / penury &amp; scarsenesse of vitell / yee of al goodnesse / howbeit in that thynge / I thynke they agreen eche with other / so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Rome may well be called Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morra. Thinges gathered to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gider / I say / to thentent that vice ones knowen / it may the better be eschewed / and nat of malyce / as many (who nowe be rubbed on the gall) sayen. For if it come of malyce open lye to reproue vyce in theym / whom he that hath but halfe an eye / may se daily w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out all shame / &amp; eke the drede &amp; feare of god styll to contynue &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte in their synne &amp; abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.
<pb facs="3"/>
Than surely / if it were nat to synne agaynst the holy gost to speke suche a blas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemy / I wolde saye that all the prophetes / that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes disciples / yee / that Christ him selfe: Alas that I am cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled nowe to open my lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes to pronoūce this worde / <note place="margin">Esa. xiii.</note> malicious / <note place="margin">Hier. l. li</note> who is all good &amp; full of the contrary to malyce that is charite / for my excuse.<note place="margin">Dan. iiii</note> Did / I pray you / Esaias / <note place="margin">i. Cor̄. iiii v. vi.</note> Hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eremias / &amp; Daniel / repreue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> babiloniēs / <note place="margin">Actuū. v.</note> &amp; also their kyng Nabugodonosor of malice?<note place="margin">Math. xxiii.</note> Rebuked sait Paule the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthiens of their lyght iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp;<note place="margin">Luc. x.</note> of fornication of maly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce?<note place="margin">Mat. xi.</note> Was saint Peter induced to blame Ananias &amp; his wyfe Saphira / of crafte &amp; auarice
<pb facs="4"/>
by malyce? Ye / to be shorte / dyd nat Christ laye hipocrisy to the scribes &amp; pharises char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / &amp; that opēly? Dyd he nat vpbrayde the cyte of Coroza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im / and other? but I hope ye wyll nat saye / inflamed with malyce. I passe ouer the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce / that saynt Ierome / saint Crisostome / &amp; Gyldas mona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus / vsen in reprofe of synne / writyng to bysshops / to mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / &amp; to all other kynde of pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple (wherof their workes be full) lest I shulde seme to fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this alredy written were nat of strength ynough to {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade you / that it is nat of malyce. But hoow syr? Sōe man wyll say / no mā douteth of the goodnesse of these men But thynke ye / that the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="4"/>
nowe a dayes be of that sort? Whether they be of that sort or no / I wyl nothyng dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pute / but me thinketh bicause it is an indifferent thynge / &amp; maye be lightly doone / ye are blame worthy them so to iuge For Christe sayth:<note place="margin">Mat. vii</note>
      <hi>Nolite iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare, et non iudicabimini.</hi> Whiche doctours expoūde to be mente of indifferēt thyng{is}. Agayn / either these thynges be fautes or nat fautes: that they be fautes / yee wyl nat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn say I trow. That there be no suche fautes there v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: I report me to your own cōscience / if this proue it nat / marke than commenly the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of these Rome rōners / who although / that a very fewe of them wyll denye it to
<pb facs="5"/>
be so at Rōe by their mouth / Shal I waraūt you / cōfesse it opēly in their lyuyng / Thā me semeth that it were better to go about amendemēt / than in dispraysynge &amp; leying ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to the auctors charge / se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me rather to holde and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de abusion / than here of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection / for we shulde rather consyder what is written thā the writer. And to conclude / if no man shulde rebuke synne other than suche / whō the Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayns call <hi>Missi.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Missus</hi> Seute</note> The sonne shulde soner lacke her lyght &amp; lease her heate / than they the desyre &amp; pleasure to contynue their abhomination. And mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ouer Pasquyll the playne sayth / if he shulde nat speke agaynst prelates vyces in Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="5"/>
openly / but to them selfes preuyly in their chābres / that the mone wolde soner tourne him from an harde stone in to melow waxe / than he shulde be suffred to come in to one of their Palacyes: and bycause I thynke that Pasquyl sayth trouth I haue torned this bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke out of latin in to englyshe as foloweth / for reformacion of synne.</p>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>