<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           <author>Barnes, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124289_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07186</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1477.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124289</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sions svveets: or The spouses spikenard; and mysticall myrrhe : By Thomas Barnes. Preacher of Gods VVord at St Margretts in New-Fish-streete. London</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Thomas, minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 77, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, the Lady <hi>Barrington,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Francis Barrington;</hi> the Lady <hi>Eliott,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>T. E.</hi> the Lady <hi>Barnardiston,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Nathan. B.</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
         <hi>Ioanna Mildmay,</hi> of <hi>Tarling</hi>-hall in <hi>Essex;</hi> the ioy of the justified, in <hi>Christ</hi> the justifier, wished.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen first I consulted with my selfe, vnder whose protection I might send abroad these <hi>Sweets of Sion, [THE SPOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES SPIKENARD,</hi> and <hi>MYSTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL MYRRHE]</hi> my thoughts fell <hi>(Right Worshipfull)</hi> vpon you foure. And, after some conflicts with inward cauills, I did resolue to make bold with <hi>all</hi> your names; and so much the rather, both because, in <hi>another</hi> Treatise sent forth with <hi>this,</hi> I haue made as bold with your Worshipfull yoake-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: as also in regard, the <hi>matter</hi> handled in these <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> is such, as be vsefull to <hi>your</hi> soules, as well as any of <hi>theirs,</hi> who are true members of <hi>that</hi> CHVRCH, and by faith made one with <hi>that</hi> SPOVSE, whom the whole Booke of <hi>Salomons Songs,</hi> (out of which I haue cull'd <hi>these</hi> Sweets) in a most sweete, and heauenly streine
<pb facs="3"/> doth treat of. I dare say, that were it not for the Authors wants, here you should finde, and meete with <hi>that,</hi> which would be both for <hi>direction,</hi> and <hi>consolation; Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in your carriage, in respect of what you <hi>owe</hi> to Christ; <hi>consolation,</hi> for your conscience, in regard of what you <hi>reape</hi> by Christ. For I am sure, <hi>that</hi> parcell of Scripture, vpon which these <hi>Meditations</hi> are, doth afford <hi>such Rules, such comforts</hi> pregnantly, plentifully. In <hi>it</hi> we haue <hi>Christ</hi> his <hi>loue,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> her <hi>loyaltie. Christ his loue</hi> vnto his Church, sitting as a <hi>King</hi> at Table with her, communicating his grace, and fauour vnto her, in the <hi>Ornaments,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> wherewith he hath endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. The Church her <hi>loyaltie</hi> vnto her Christ: first, <hi>presenting</hi> him with her <hi>Box of Spikenard,</hi> her <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Workes: secondly, <hi>praysing</hi> him for his <hi>Bundle of Myrrhe,</hi> the <hi>pardoning of her sinnes,</hi> the <hi>refreshing of her soule:</hi> thirdly, professing shee would neuer forget the <hi>greatnes</hi> of his loue, and would endeuour to keepe the <hi>sence</hi> of his kindnes. This loue of that <hi>great husband</hi> I wish you the sweet of, with a daily encrease of it, more and more. This loyaltie of the Spousesse I doubt not but hath beene yeelded by your Worships ere now, to Christ the head. The blessing vpon these labours, I craue of God; the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, the acceptance, of these endeuours I beg of you. Which <hi>(RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL)</hi> may I but obtaine: <hi>GOD,</hi> for <hi>that his blessing,</hi> shall haue my <hi>prayses, YOV for your acceptance</hi> shall haue his <hi>prayers,</hi> who is</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your <hi>Worships</hi> to be commanded in any Christian service to his power; <hi>THOMAS BARNES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>