<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Smith, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124609_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73183</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22872.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124609</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Smith, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Qvi non credit condemnabitvr Marc. 16. Or A discourse prouing, that a man who beleeueth in the Trinity, the Incarnation, the Passion &amp;c. &amp; yet beleeueth not all other inferiour articles of Christian fayth, cannot be saued : And consequently, that both the Catholike, and the Protestant (seeing the one necessarily wanteth true fayth) cannot be saued. Written by William Smith, Priest</title>
                 <author>Smith, William, priest</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>172 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, such are the lamentable times, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we liue, as that they not only bring forth men, who with great contention, and heat of dispute, do vndertake to maintaine particuler Errour, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly repugnant to the Scripture, and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christ his Church; but also, they affoard some others who (as if wickednes would striue to raise it selfe to its highest pitch) are not afraid to entertaine all Religions with such a cold indifferency, as that they would, that saluation may be obtayned in any Religiō; so that the professours therof do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue in the Trinity, the Incarnation, &amp; other such fundamental points of Christianity, whether they be Papists, Protestants, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptists, Brownists, or any other of these later Sects: They heereupon further do teach, that we are not obliged (vnder the paine of any spirituall losse) to embrace any one of these Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before another, scornefully traducing in their conceipts all others, who exact a more strict and articulate beliefe of our Christian mysteries: which later kind of men is far more daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and hurtfull, then the former; since those our of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posterous zeale (their vnderstanding being blinded and misin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) do only defende falshoods for verityes, so running them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vpon that rocke of Tertullian: <hi>Haeresis est, probata non crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, non probata praesumere. It is the propriety of Heresy, not to beleeue points proued, and to presume or take for graunted, things not proued.</hi> Whereas these <hi>Adiaphorists</hi> (whose secret pulse doth indeed beate vpon Atheisme) disclaime from all necessity of truth, iustifyinge
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> the defence of errours euen vnder the title of errours, and houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only this one maine controuersy in Christian Religion, to wit, that in Christian Religion there are no maine controuersies. Against these ambidexter Protestants (so to call them) who draw their soules perdition in the ropes of a supine and careles security, I haue thought good to vndergo the wryting of this short ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatise. The subiect of which discourse I find most necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euen from my owne experience, who for the space of thirty yeares and aboue (with infinite thankes to God) haue beene a Priest of the Catholike Roman Church, during which longe compasse of tyme, I haue dealt with many soules here in Englād; and haue found infinite of them openly professing Protestancy, yet inwardly perswaded (as is aboue touched) that men of most contrary fayths (so that in grosse they beleeue in Christ) may be saued; as if saluation were a Center, indifferently extending its lines, to the circumference of all Religions: yea diuers of these men were not ashamed to contest with me in the open defence of this wicked opinion; and fortifying themselues principally with this following reason.</p>
   <p n="2">2. God (say they) is most mercifull, and therfore it would be much repugnant to his infinite mercy, to damme for all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, any man that beleiueth in him, and in Iesus Christ, as his Redeemer; so that withall he forbeare dooing of all wronge, but leade a vertuous (or at least, a morall) lyfe, though in other articles of lesse importance he may erre. To this I answeare, with the Apostle.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>O altitudo diuitiarum sapientiae &amp; scientiae Dei!</hi> Gods iudgments are inscrutable, and to be admired, not to be ouercuriously pried into. If it was his diuine pleasure, for many ages to make choyce only of the Iewishe Nation (a very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the whole earth) for his elected people, and to suffer all the rest of the world (generaly speaking) to ly drowned in Idolatry, and therefore to be damned. And if also after our Sauiours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, he vouchafed not, for the space of many ages, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten whole Countreys with the Ghospel of Christ, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to continue (to their soules eternall perditiō) in their former Idolatry &amp; Heathenisme; yea suffering euen to this very day (and how long yet after, his diuine Maiesty only knoweth)
<pb n="5" facs="3"/> diuers vast Countreyes to perseuere in their foresaid Infidelity, if (I say) this proceeding in God is best liking to himselfe, and that for the same he cannot be truly chardged with Iniustice or cruelty, seeing he gaue them sufficient meanes of saluatiō by the law of Nature, and did not withdraw from them grace sufficient leauing them thereby without excuse. Then much lesse can any man expostulate God of iniustice or want of mercy (for his diuine goodnes is nothing but iustice and mercy it selfe) if he suffer men to perishe eternally, and damne them for want of an entire, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate, and perfit faithe in all the articles of Christianity; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in these times, when no Christian can pretend for excuse any inuincible ignorance in matters of faithe by reason that the true articles of Christian Religion, are sufficiently propounded and diuulged by Gods Church, to all Christians whatsoeuer; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore touching Gods secret iudgements and disposales heerein, we will conclude with<note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <hi>Cap.</hi> 30</note> Esay: <hi>Deus iudicij Dominus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">3. This then being thus, from hence it appeareth, how much the Protestants wronge the Catholikes in charging them with want of charity, for houlding that Protestants dying Protestants, cannot be saued, wheras on the contrary part, diuers learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants do (say they) graunt the hope of saluation to Catholikes or Papists, dying Papists. To this we reply, that here is no want of Charity, but rather a <hi>Seraphicall</hi> and burning Charity; for what greater charity can there be, then (seeing it is an indisputable ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that men dying in a false &amp; hereticall faith cannot be saued) to premonishe and forwarne withall conuenient sedulity &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour, <hi>opportunè, importunè,</hi> their Christian Brethren of so great a daunger, as the perdition of their soules commeth vnto? Noe, the soules interminable and endles weale or woe, is not a matter of complement, that so for ceremony sake it is to be forbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be inculcated and often spoaken of, especially where the most certanie truth of the matter insisted vpon, &amp; the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conscience of the speaker, do warrant the discourse. And if Catholikes must be accompted vncharitable for these their admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, then by the same reason they must insimulate the Apost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of the said fault of want of Charity, who<note n="(c)" place="margin">
         <hi>Tit. c.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Thessal</hi> 3.</note> seuerely chargeth vs to fly the company and society of an Heretike; and who ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">Gall. cap. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Rom. <hi>16.</hi>
      </note> schismes and heresies among those sinnes, the workers wherof shall not obtaine the kingdom of God. But to returne more particulerly to the subiect of this Treatise: I haue thought good to entitle it with the words of our Sauiour: <hi>Qui non credit, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur.</hi>
      <note n="(e)" place="margin">
         <hi>Marc.</hi> 16.</note>
      <hi>He that beleiueth not, shalbe condemned;</hi> as being a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which best sorteth to the matter here handled, and which indeede really (though breifly) inuolueth in it selfe the truth here discussed. The sourse, from whence this Libertinisme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife did take its first emanation and flowing, is the contempt of the authority of the Catholike Church: for thus reasoneth our Newtralist in Doctrine.</p>
   <p n="4">4. <hi>Both Papists and Protestants doe agree in beleiuing the Trinity, the Incarnation, the Paession &amp;c. but they mainly dissent touching Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Praying to Saints, Freewill, the sacrifice of the Masse, Iustification &amp;c. therfore I will embrace and follow that doctrine (meaning the doctrin of the Trinity, the Incarnation, Passion &amp;c. and hould it necessary to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, in which all sides doe agree. But since the dissentions and disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Religion, are of these secondary &amp; lesse principall points, to wit, Purgatory, Praying to Saints &amp;c. and since it is impossible, that both the Papist and Protestant, should teach truly in the said articles, (for they teach meere contrary doctrines therin.) And further seeing I haue no more reason to belieue the one side then the other (and it is impossible for me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue both) therfore my resolution is (contemning the authority of Gods Church in its definitions of these articles) peremptorily to stand to neither, but will hold the doctrine of Purgatory, Praying to Saints, and all other controuerted points of fayth at this day, betwene Papists and Protestants, matters meerly of indifferency, and of that nature, as that neyther the true nor false beleife of them, can eyther further or hinder a mans saluation.</hi> Thus disputeth our Newtralist. And thus whilest he wilbe of all Religions, he wilbe of no Religion. Then which (as if Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were only, but an intentionall, and no reall name or word) what can be inuented more impious and Atheistical in it selfe, more repugnant to sacred scriptures, more crosse to the practice of all antiquity, and (as herafter shalbe proued) more adueise to all naturall reason? so dangerous it is for a Christian once to dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber himselfe by pertinacy of iudgmēt from the Church of Christ; and so truly is verified of such a man, that sentence of Optatus:
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
      <hi>Deserta</hi>
      <note n="(f)" place="margin">Lib. contra Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentan.</note>
      <hi>matre Catholica impij filij, dum foras excurrunt &amp; se separant &amp; errando rebelles abscedunt. Our mother the Catholike Church being once forsaken, her wicked children do goe out and depart from her, and thus being become Rebells through erring, do hyde themselues.</hi> Thus we see, how these all reconciling Omnifidians, doe carry themselues, who through the pretended immensity of their pretended cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (forsooth) can promise saluations to al Religions, and who seeke to introduce a peace into Gods Church (by compounding al controuersies of faith) farre more dangerous, then are the warres &amp; contentions of Heretikes.</p>
   <p n="5">5. Now seeing all such men make no more accompt of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity of Religions, then others doe of wearing suits of apparrel of different coulours; and seeing by such their lukewamenes in matters of faithe, they seeme to be all Laodiceans, therfore wee may asure our selues, that the commination and threat denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced against the Church of Laodicea registred by the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Apoc. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list shall (without finall repentance) fall vpon them: <hi>Because thou art lukewarme, and neither colde, nor hot, I will vomit thee out of my mouth.</hi> But (good Reader) as vnwilling to transgresse the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed limits of a preface, I will detaine thee noe longer; only I haue thought good to put thee in mind (and so to end) with the sentence and iudgment of Saint Augustine passed vpon the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians (as for some delibation and tast of the subiect herafter han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled) who beleeued in the Trinity, in Christ, and his Passion, were men of moral and honest conuersation; yet for houlding that only by the force of nature, without the assistaunce of Gods grace, a man was able to exercise vertue and flye vice, (a point no more fundamentall thē most of the controuersies betweene the Catholikes and the Protestants) they are registred for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes by the saide S. Augustine, &amp; consequently not to be in state of Saluation: his words<note n="(h)" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 129.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>37.</note> are these: <hi>Nec tales sunt Pelagiani, quos facile contemnas, sed continenter viuentes, at{que} in bonis operibus lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabiles; nec falsum Christum, sed vnum verum equalem{que} patri &amp; coeter num, veraciter{que} hominem factum, &amp; venisse credentes, &amp; venturum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectantes: sed tamen ignorantes Dei iustitiam, suam cōstituere volentes, Heretici sunt.</hi> In English thus: <hi>Neither are the Pelagians such men, as are easily to be contemned for they doe liue continently, and are laudable
<pb n="6" facs="5"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="7" facs="5"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="8" facs="6"/> for their good workes. They further doe belieue, not in a false Christ, but in one true Christ who is equall &amp; coeternall with his father, and who was truly made man, They beleeue, that he is allready come, and they expect him hereafter to come; yet because they are ignorant of the iustice of God, and would make it their owne iustice,</hi> (meaning, because they taught it might be obtained by their owne naturall force) <hi>therfore they are Heretikes.</hi> Thus farre Sainct Augustine, with whome I end; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thee (Good Reader) to the deliberate and studious perusall of these ensuing leaues, and intreating most earnestly the praiers of all good Catholikes for the remission of my manifould and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite sinnes, and for an happy houre of the dissolution of my ould and decaied body.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your soules well-wishing friend William Smith.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>