<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In commendation of the Author.</title>
           <author>Roche, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124300_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124300</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In commendation of the Author.</title>
                 <author>Roche, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Popes Parliament : containing a pleasant and delightful historie, wherin are throughly deliuered and brightly blazed out, the paltry trash and trumperies of him and his pelting prelats, their mutinies, discord, and dissentions, their stomacke and malice at Pope Ioane, their shifting and foisting of matters for defence of her, and their antichristian practises, for maintenance of their pompe and auarice. Whereunto is annexed an Anatomie of Pope Ioane, more apparantly opening her whole life and storie. Written by Iohn Mayo</title>
                 <author>Mayo, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>In commendation of the Author.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>SWeete May is come, that winters frost opprest,</l>
      <l>Whereat the birds their siluer notes displaies,</l>
      <l>(As if that Bore as blastes had reau'd their rest,</l>
      <l>And Phoebus rousde from denne with golden raies,</l>
      <l>Comes with his shining beames, bringing them newes</l>
      <l>Of weather faire, which as they would ensewes.)</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The May is come that makes the shrubs to sing,</l>
      <l>Whose rubie streames descries the slow-worms watchs,</l>
      <l>And Philomela sits and feares no sting</l>
      <l>Of wrath, but quiet naps in rest she catchs.</l>
      <l>Each bird on toppe of tree with mirth resounds,</l>
      <l>Welcome sweete May, by whom our blisse rebounds.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Our May, faire knowledge is, error the frost</l>
      <l>That nipt truthes Laurell boughes and flowers faire,</l>
      <l>The Protestants the birds that sorrow lost</l>
      <l>To see vndoubted truth to them repaire:</l>
      <l>The Philomela shewes our noble Queene,</l>
      <l>The blindfold Pope, the slow-worme cloath'd with teene.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>May brings greene buds, blooming with blossoms bright,</l>
      <l>Flora yeelds Poesies, May yeelds flowers diuine,</l>
      <l>Surpassing May dimming her glittering light:</l>
      <l>As Sol doth cause sweete Cynthias beames to pine.</l>
      <l>No labour doth his reaching minde forgoe,</l>
      <l>Whereby (O Reader good) thy good may grow.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Sitting in harbours greene with vertues grace,</l>
      <l>Not in the chambers of fond Venus lust:</l>
      <l>He meanes to make his pen iourney apace,</l>
      <l>To shew the truth, and rub off errors rust.</l>
      <l>Then hither youth repaire with Echoes laude,</l>
      <l>Giue May due thankes, his praise deseru'd applaud.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Foord.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>