<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124864_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72313</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13399.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124864</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrine of the beginning of Christ : Short for memorie, plaine for capacity, deliuered almost in the expresse words of the text, for the more authority. By Samuell Hieron, minister of the Gospel</title>
                 <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <distributor>Cooke, Matthew</distributor>
                            <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>An Aduertisement to <hi>the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>I Offer here vnto thee, good Reader, this short catechisme, neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring it before other the like briefs of Religion, neither yet equalling it to any; but I willinglye submitte it to thy iudgement, to place it in what ranke thou wilt. Onely this; if thou are disposed, after thou hast viewed the title, to looke further into the thing it selfe: then I pray thee by the way, to take notice of this mine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting thee with the order and maner of that which followeth.</p>
   <p>For order, it sheweth thee first, what was the excellency of thy first makinge, by the eternall Trinitye: Secondly, it discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the depth of misery, into which thou hast plunged thy selfe by communicating with Adams Disobedience, together with thy vtter disability, so much as by a thought to desire, or to deserue thine owne recouery. Thirdly, it pointeth out Christ vnto thee, whom God the Father had sealed, to saue his people from their sinnes. Fourthly,<note place="margin">Mat 1.21 Iohn 6.2</note> it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth knowne vnto thee, the sufficiency of his sacrifice, and the means of applying it to thy owne soule.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Fiftly, it teacheth thee whence to expect faith, what meanes to vse for the attainment of it, and how to be assured that it is vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Sixtly, because the end of the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of grace is, that we should deny vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, therefore it vrgeth vpon thee the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of good works, that so thou maist be neither idle nor vnfruitfull in the knoledge of our Lord Iesus Christ. Seuenthly, foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the way of the righteous shineth, as the light that shineth more and more vnto the perfit day, therefore also it calleth vpon thee to grow in grace, and informeth thee by what helpes thou mayst bee ledde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vnto perfection. Eightly, least in this good course, being encountred with vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected tribulations, thou shouldst be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and faint in thy minde, it fore-aduiseth thee of the certainety of diuers afflictions, and teacheth thee both howe to frame thy selfe to the taking vp of thy crosse, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all what quiet fruit of righteousnesse to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, by beeing exercised thereby; in the middest of all, still looking for the blessed hope &amp; appearing of the glory of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty GOD, and of our Sauiour Iesus Christ. Ninthly, and lastly, the generall direction for Holinesse and Righteousnesse, it apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="3"/>
to particulars, both to thy daily cariage in the vse of things indifferent, as apparrel, meat, recreation, rest, and to thine age, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and calling, that so in euery respect, thy conuersation may bee such as becommeth the Gospell. This is the course and summe of this forme of Holy Doctrine, whereunto my desire is to deliuer thee, and in which I perswade my selfe I haue comprised the full some of True Religion.</p>
   <p>Now for the manner of it: I haue as neer as I could possibly, in each answere kept my selfe to the wordes of the holy Text: thou shalt finde me to haue fayled in a very few; and yet in those, if thou conferre with that Place to which I referre thee, thou shalte finde mee not to haue erred from the meaning of the Spirite of GOD there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. The reason of this course is, First to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thee with the Language of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture. Secondly, that each point may haue the more credit, when thy conscience shal see &amp; heare, as it were, God himself speaking in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Answere.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, that thou mayst acknowledge that (which many in their ignorance wil not beleeue) the Scripture is a rich Store-house, affoording directions for euery particular.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Now, where I haue supposed, some worde, or speaches to be such as might breede thee some trouble, not being rightly vnderstood, I haue in the margine, as it were, reached thee a light for the cleereing of all such dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker places, that thou mightest both knowe the sense, and acknowledg the certainty of those things wherein my desire is thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est be instructed. This is all, whereof I haue to admonish thee:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ke 1.4.</note> proceede now on Gods name, to the pervsing of the thing it selfe, &amp; the lord giue thee vnderstāding in al things. Al that I desire of thee by the way of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for my endeuour to do thee good,<note place="margin">Tim. 2.7.</note> is, that thou wouldest striue with me by praiers to God for me, that I may fulfill the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, which I haue receiued in the Lord: And so I commend thee to him,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>m. 15, 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>l. 4, 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. 20.32.</note> and to the word of his grace, wishing thee an Inhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among them that are sanctified.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Modbury</hi> in <hi>Deuon,</hi>
         <date>the fourth of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust.</hi> 1604.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>SAM. HIERON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>