<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Tho: Rat∣cliffe Esquire: Secre∣tary to the right Re∣verend and right Ho∣nourable William Lord Bishop of Lon∣don and Lord high Treasurer of ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>Mabb, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124182_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B01135</idno>
           <idno type="STC">630.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124182</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Tho: Rat∣cliffe Esquire: Secre∣tary to the right Re∣verend and right Ho∣nourable William Lord Bishop of Lon∣don and Lord high Treasurer of ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>Mabb, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true Israelite, or, The sincere Christian distinguished from the hypocrite. By Master William Andrewes, late minister of the word of God</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, William, minister of the word of God</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Greene, Charles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 216 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull <hi>Tho: Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> Esquire: Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to the right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>William</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and Lord high Treasurer of ENGLAND.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worth of the <hi>Author,</hi> the respects I
<pb facs="4"/> owe you, and your owne Innate good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse have incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged mee to chuse you the Patron of this <hi>Post-humus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For the <hi>Author,</hi> as hee was a Divine sound and orthodox in judgement, so hee was peaceable in the <hi>Church,</hi> and sincere in his life; for his learning, though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe (it may bee) was a stranger to you,
<pb facs="4"/> yet as hee that by <hi>Hercules</hi> his foote drew the proportion of his whole body, so in this little <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> (if J mistake not) you may perceive him to bee one that was <hi>brought up at the feete of Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liell, mighty in the Scriptures,</hi> and well studied in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The respects I owe to your selfe,
<pb facs="5"/> are such as that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to manifest my acknowledgement of them, I had (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse) incurred the censure of ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full negligence, if J should have let it slip and not improoved it to this end from your owne goodnesse. I gather an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance, both of this <hi>Orphan</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> and the <hi>presenter,</hi> who am put in trust to commend the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of it to some one, whose emminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the World for vertuous quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications might some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what shelter it from these blacke-mouth'd Calumniators that these times are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred with.</p>
   <p>These are the reasons (worthy Sir) why I have (though
<pb facs="6"/> without your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge) prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your name in the Front of this tract. I humbly crave your pardon, if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed any thing, and that you would bee pleased to doe the <hi>Author</hi> and me, so much honour as to suffer <hi>His Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite</hi> to come abroad into the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your worthy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage;
<pb facs="6"/> In the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance whereof I crave leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships to be commanded,</hi> Ralph Mabb.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>