<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S124283_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00150</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1314.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S124283</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short treatise: containing all the principall grounds of Christian religion : By way of questions and answers: very profitable for all men, but especially for housholders</title>
                 <author>Ball, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 246 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE offer here vnto thy view (good Christian Reader) the principles of Religion, with a short exposition vpon the same; for the explanation of what may seeme difficult, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the truth professed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst poperie, and the inforcing of sundrie duties of weighty and great importance. The method we haue followed is plaine and naturall, the matter wholsome, but not adorned with flowers of eloquence. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the maine end, that al men ought to aime at: because there can be no motion but for some end, as there can bee no effect but from some efficient. Thence we proceed to the meanes whereby the ende may bee attained: for it is in vaine
<pb facs="4"/> to propoūd an end vnto our selues, if either the way bee impossible, or imperfect; if either it cannot bee knowne, or do not leade to the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. In the meanes we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, whence direction is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and what is to be learned: and there we shew what, and who God is, how wee must conceiue of him, why hee ought to be worshipped, what couenant he made with <hi>Adam</hi> in the time of innocencie, and how <hi>Adam</hi> by transgression fell, and plunged himselfe, and his posterity into woe and miserie vnspeakable, intolerable, and eternall. In the next place we lay down the meanes that God hath ordained for mans recouerie: And there is handled, what Christ is, what hee hath done for vs, how we are made partakers of his benefits, how faith is wrought, and increased in vs, and what obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience wee owe to God in Christ, who is the obiect of Christian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<pb facs="4"/> And because the godly in this course of Christianitie are compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed about with infirmities, subiect to many falles, and assaulted with many tentations, which might dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and turne them out of the way: Therfore we haue added, what course a Christian should take to grow in grace, how he may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued from falling, how he should recouer after his fall, and of what priuiledges the godly are, or may be partakers in this life. And in the last place, the blessednesse of the Saints after this life is ended, is touched in few words; whereby the sufficiencie of the meanes is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested. For as it is a way prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of God; so it leadeth vs vnto God, the first, chiefe, and al-suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Good. Our desire herein is to teach the simple Christian, how he may grow from grace to grace, and from faith to faith: and to further such godly householders, as desire
<pb facs="5"/> to instruct and traine vp their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and seruants in the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and feare of the Lord; but want leisure or abilitie to furnish themselues, out of larger and more learned Treatises. For their sakes wee haue aduentured to compile this poore treatise, and to make it common; that they might haue some helpe at hand, whereby they might be confirmed in the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the vaine cauils of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, and the better inabled to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them that be committed to their charge. If any such shal vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to make vse of this booke, wee would desire him to marke and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue these few things. First that the letters, <hi>a,</hi> and <hi>b,</hi> and <hi>c,</hi> &amp;c. set ouer the Answere, doe direct, what part of the answere the Testimonies of Scripture alleaged do serue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. And the figures 1. 2. 3. &amp;c. doe intimate what words, or which parts of the answere, are explaned
<pb facs="5"/> in the exposition. Secondly, in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Questions and Answers, take the paines to search into the proofes which are alleaged for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the matter; and if the same thing word for word bee not found in the verses of Scripture ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then be pleased further to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what reasons or arguments may bee drawne from the place, to proue what is intended. This wee commend, because it is a course be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houefull for the obtaining of well grounded knowledge, the getting of stedfast and assured faith and comfort, and growing to bee fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly acquainted with the word. Thirdly, in reading the exposition of euery answere, take notice what is deliuered by way of explication or confirmation, and what reasons, &amp; how many are brought to proue any point. Thereby a man shall be inabled to referre that which hee heareth in the publike assemblie, or
<pb facs="6"/> readeth in other learned bookes, to some head, apply it to right pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, treasure it vp safely in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for vse in the time of neede, and haue in readinesse to answere the gainsaiers. Lastly, because in such a multitude of quotations it cannot bee, but some will be mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; if in the places quoted thou finde not that which makes to the purpose, looke into the <hi>Errata,</hi> and see whether it bee not there amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and before thou begin to reade, take notice of, and amend especially these more grosse ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sights in the printing. Page 102, line 21, for resisting; reade resting. Page 109, line 24, for voide; reade, good. Page 147, line 3, for, is sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; reade, is not sealed. Page 174, line 11, insert, We may not vow. Pag. 177, lin. 5, for, can more; reade, can no more.</p>
   <p>Thus heartily desiring and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping (good Reader) that thou wilt
<pb facs="6"/> make vse of these directions giuen, profitably to guide thee through this small worke; we commit thee to God, and the word of his grace, who is able to direct, and safelie leade thee vnto eternal happinesse; crauing that, if thou receiue benefit from God vpon the perusall of this simple treatise, thou be carefull to poure out thy soule vnto God for vs, that he would enrich vs with his grace more and more, for the glory of God, the good of his Church, and the comfort of our owne soules.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>