<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A sonnet to the translatour.</title>
           <author>Fyldinge, Ferd.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125742_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08033</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21315</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125742</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A sonnet to the translatour.</title>
                 <author>Fyldinge, Ferd.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discours of the present troobles in Fraunce, and miseries of this tyme : compyled by Peter Ronsard gentilman of Vandome, and dedicated unto the quene mother, translated in to English by Thomas Ieney gentilman</title>
                 <author>Ronsard, Pierre de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_translator">
   <head>A sonnet to the translatour.</head>
   <l>As Homers streaminge source, of springinge head doth flovv</l>
   <l>In Grekishe cloustred camps, by Troians reard to fame:</l>
   <l>As Virgils matchinge stile, doth vveaue in smothed frame,</l>
   <l>The peased pliant vvoordes, of vvightes that lye ful lovv:</l>
   <l>So <hi>RONSARDS</hi> blovvminge grafte (from them as you may knovve</l>
   <l>By ruthful mourners minde) doth vvoordes from parentes fame,</l>
   <l>VVaylinge vvhith brokken seighes the fyerie kinghtes of name,</l>
   <l>That braue vvhith glitternige svvord in fielde to smyte the blovv</l>
   <l>Of dedlye massie fiste, (most deu to vvaylful Fraunce)</l>
   <l>Sent from myld God, that doth vvhich splayed armes inhaunce,</l>
   <l>The lastinge painful scourge, to vvhippe the thanckles flockee.</l>
   <l>If creed may credit geue, to dysmalles iudgmentes day,</l>
   <l>I thincke the same hath taught, <hi>IENEY</hi> to outforth bray,</l>
   <l>An Englishe pleasant phrase, not far from <hi>RONSARDS</hi> stocke.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ferd: Fyldinge.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>