<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>GEORGE BISHOP OF
CHICHESTER, TO WILLIAM
BELVSS Knight, wisheth sal∣vation
in Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125899_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17988</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4647</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>GEORGE BISHOP OF
CHICHESTER, TO WILLIAM
BELVSS Knight, wisheth sal∣vation
in Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of Bernard Gilpin : a man most holy and renowned among the northerne English. Faithfully written by the Right Reverend Father in God George Carleton Lord Bishop of Chichester, and published for the satisfaction of his countrimen, by whom it was long since earnestly desired</title>
                 <author>Carleton, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>GEORGE BISHOP OF
CHICHESTER, TO WILLIAM
BELVSS Knight, wisheth sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
in Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F in the Church of God,
there were many such as
<hi>Gilpin</hi> was, I should holde
it needlesse, to recommend
the memoriall of this Man
vnto the world. But seeing
there are so few, or (to speak freely what I
think) none at all, who (following the rule of
sorare piety, and sanctimony) have propounded
so notable an example, to all those who doe aspire
to ablessed life, and constantly walked in the
same) I conceiue that such a patterne, would
kindle the zeale of many good men, to walke in
so faire a way, though happily they were not able
to attaine to the perfection thereof. Examples of
<pb facs="3"/>
the like piety in holy men we haue heard of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
in auncient histories, &amp; often read of them in
their writings, but in men of this our age it is
not to be found: For so farre short are we from
this zeale in furtherance of piety, that now it is
to be feared, left Religion (so eagerly and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
vndertaken, and professed at first) will come
to be euen <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oathed, and reiected of many, and so
finally come to confusion: seeing experience of
former times hath confirmed this truth vnto vs
that profanesse of life and manners hath drawne
withall the ruine of Religion, thereby to giue vs
a taste now of what it is like to doe hereafter;
Now we make no doubt, but (in so great a decay
of auncient holinesse) <hi>Gilpins</hi> name (like the
Owle amongst other Birds) when it comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
will proue hatefull to many; Yet I held
this no sufficient reason why to suppresse it:
Wherein though some pick out matter for their
derision and scorne, yet other some may meete
with matter for their admiration, others for
their Imitation to work on. As for you (Worthy
Sir) you hereby inioy the harvest of your earnest
and often desire. Many yeeres this writing hath
lyne by me from the common view, the edition
whereof I did therefore of purpose defer, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb facs="3"/>
them, (who may seeme to stand at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
farre off from this forme of holinesse)
from iudging themselues preiudized hereby: But
as my purpose is to further all, as much as I
might, so it was not to hurt any: If any good or
furtherance redound to any by this my labour, he
must thank you whose importunity hath extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
it, such as it is, out of my hands. And seeing
you liue in the very place, where <hi>Gilpins</hi> life
and vertue was notoriously famous, and your
selfe haue beene so earnest with me for the same,
this very carefull desire of yours to preserue
and perpetuate <hi>Gilpins</hi> memory, is a most preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
proofe and an vndeniable testimony of the
ingenuity and goodnesse of our owne minde:
which worthy disposition of yours hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
me to dedicate this little work to your name,
to stand for euer as a pledge of your Religious
affection to <hi>Gilpin,</hi> and my true loue vnto you.
So Fare you well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>