<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right honorable Syr Fraunces Knolls Knyght, Treasurer of her Maiesties house∣hold, and one of the most honora∣ble priuy Counsel, grace, and peace from the father of our Lord Iesus Christ with increase of all Godly honour.</title>
           <author>Elviden, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125321_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73859</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7166</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125321</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right honorable Syr Fraunces Knolls Knyght, Treasurer of her Maiesties house∣hold, and one of the most honora∣ble priuy Counsel, grace, and peace from the father of our Lord Iesus Christ with increase of all Godly honour.</title>
                 <author>Elviden, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fruitfull and necessary sermon, specially concernyng almes geuing, preached the Twisday [sic] in Easter weeke : The yere of our Lord. 1572. at S. Maries Spittle. By Thomas Drant, bachelor in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Drant, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div rend="blackletterType" type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right honorable Syr Fraunces Knolls Knyght, Treasurer of her Maiesties house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and one of the most honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priuy Counsel, grace, and peace from the father of our Lord Iesus Christ with increase of all Godly honour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man can well Iudge of that which he knoweth not, and of that which he knoweth a mā may iudge most fitly: Your honour both heard this Sermō, for your learnynge you can iudge of it, and for your vertuous zeale to God, and your common wealth you will not iudge amisse of it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a very good will I geue, and present it vnto your honors patronage.</p>
   <p>This Sermon hath three specialties in it. The first is it speaketh, &amp; pleadeth much for the relief of pouertie. Secondly, it is earnest for the saftie of the Prince, &amp; weale publicke as it now is: Thirdly it is tarte, &amp; vehement agaynst sinne: as bribery, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, vsury, hypocrisie, flattery, hard har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes, vitiousnes, trouthelesnes. &amp;c. The first point no man with an honest face can speake agaynst. The second (God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) as the case is come to passe, fewe, or none dare speake agaynste. The thyrde
<pb facs="3"/> hath alwayes bene vnto the preachers most daungerous. And therfore I was to craue your honorable protection.</p>
   <p>Of my selfe I could with a good will haue suffered this treatise to haue gone no farther, but so would not other, Both Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, and Gentlemē of good vertue, and vnderstandyng. Furthermore that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation which that learned man Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour <hi>Humfred</hi> gaue it at Paules crosse did some thyng persuade me therunto. Lastly your honours so harry, &amp; ready receauyng of it hath concluded the matter.</p>
   <p>The Lord God blesse you (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Coūcellour) and all yours, increase, and continue the knowledge, and loue of his truth in you. And bryng you hereafter vnto that lyfe whiche through Christ Iesus aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to your for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours in Christ most humble to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. <hi rend="roman">Thomas Drant.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>