<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY MVCH HONORED FRIEND RICHARD KNIGHTLEY, Esquire.</title>
           <author>Farmer, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125386_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72056</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10699</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125386</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY MVCH HONORED FRIEND RICHARD KNIGHTLEY, Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Farmer, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on Sunday, the eight and twentieth day of Iune. 1629. By Richard Farmer, sometimes of Pembrooke-Hall in Cambridge, now parson of Charwelton in the county of Northampton</title>
                 <author>Farmer, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY MVCH HONORED FRIEND RICHARD KNIGHTLEY, Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, being moued by some of better iudgement than my selfe, to print this Sermon, I haue made bold to inscribe it to your Name: both that it may weare it as a fauour, like a Iewell hanging in the forehead; and also, it being of forme, not to presse into so publike a presence, without a leader, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping you will take it by the hand. Yet it is not my desire you should Patronise any thing in it; For the Text is a good Text, and he that was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of it, will make that good; He will also beare me out in that I haue spoken of it, agreeable to his Spirit and meaning. And if any thing haue slip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="3"/> from me otherwise, so soone as I shall heare of my faults (which will not be long, in this censori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous age) I will not haue them Patronised, for I will aske pardon, and amend. But it is bold to come to you, first, because being a Sermon, I haue assured it, it will be welcome. I haue beene fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so hold, as to tell it, it will not he vnwelcome being mine, whose paines in this kind sometimes you are pleased to accept. But chiefly it comes to you, to certifie you, that as I doe deseruedly and vnfainedly honour you, so by giuing notice hereof to the world, I doe ingage my selfe before witnesse and vpon record, to be alwayes</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all Christian affection and duty, RICHARD FARMER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>