<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE GOODE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>C., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125583_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73451</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25972.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125583</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE GOODE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>C., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bels trial examined that is a refutation of his late treatise, intituled. The triall of the nevve religion : By B.C. student in diuinitie. VVherein his many &amp; grosse vntruthes, with diuers contradictions are discouered: together with an examination of the principal partes of that vaine pamphlet: and the antiquitie &amp; veritie of sundry Catholike articles, which he calleth rotten ragges of the newe religion, are defended against the newe ragmaster of rascal. In the preface likewise, a short viewe of one Thomas Rogers vntruthes is sett downe, taken out of his booke called The faith doctrine and religion, professed and protected in the realme of England, &amp;c. with a short memorandum for T.V. otherwise called Th. Vdal</title>
                 <author>Woodward, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 168 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE GOODE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my last booke (goode Reader) which I published against the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging minister intituled.</hi> The Dolefull knell of Thomas Bell: <hi>I very well remember, that I freed my self from writing ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, vntill I had sett forth his Blacke Buriall, contayning an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swear to the mayne of all his blasphemous bookes and pestilent pamphlets, ys iust reasons there specified hindred not my desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnement: notwithstanding meeting not longe since with a newe toy of his, tricked and trimmed vp, with diuers patches and rusty ragges, drawen from the dunghille of his former monuments, and called by him,</hi> The Trial of the newe religion: <hi>I resolued to examine his depositions, and to try the truth of his newe treatise: and that both because it falleth out very fittely and in order, that hauing rung Bels</hi> Dolefull knell, <hi>this examination of his</hi> Triall, <hi>as his winding sheete should follow, before the solemnity of his foule Funerals and interring of his carcasse be kept: and also for that I feare by</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>the disastrous coniunction of the planets, that a could frost of pouerty, will yet keepe backe the springe of the promised worke, and therefore I thought it not amisse to publishe this Treatise being not of any such bulke, but that a fewe crownes may dispatch the impression. And lastly, to giue Bell sure and certaine intelligence, that it was contempt of him, and his bookes, that made them passe so longe without answear, and not any rare learning, or stinginge stuffe, as in the light of his darke dreaming conceipt, proceeding from much vanity and litle humility, small grace &amp; great pride, he framed to himself.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>His eies I hope by this time be opened to see, that albeit he were an importune challenger, yet he lay not so close, but that his sides haue bene soundly bombasted, and his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters kindely curried ouer. That disdainfull stile of his which before trampled vpon our silence: those mounting words which in former tymes menaced nothing but death and destruction: that insulting vaine which did so contemptibly caper vpon our quiet carcasses, is nowe becom bankrupt and fled the countrey. Those ouerlooking termes and fiery phrases, those terrible taunts, which with restlesse penne he runge in our eares, and neuer ceased to iangle both in towne and countrey are vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and blowne away like the locusts of Egipt. The world is altered,</hi> To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nam <hi>is turned French: his hoat courage is cooled, the gospelling</hi> Golias <hi>lyeth sweating vpon the earth fetching his last gaspe, and the false pleasinge lustre of his boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes faded and coin to nothing. In former tymes this and such like were his vsuall songes.</hi> No no they do in effect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse <note place="margin">Funeral. lib. 1. cap. 2. pag. 6.</note> so much, whiles they neither dare answear any one booke at all, nor any one chapter wholy, but here and there an odde piece or sentence, I protest vnto the gentle Reader I partly blushe on their behalf. <hi>But neuer as I thinke shall I liue so longe to heare any more such musicke. No no that tune is out of date,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>the bloud hath left his cheekes; and runne in poste to comfort his faintinge heart.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>It was also no question a braue pangue of his vauntinge spirit, when he came ouer vs in this insulting manner.</hi> They <note place="margin">Funeral. lib. 2. cap. 1. pag. 4.</note> are so nettled, so pricked and goared with my boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and their religion so battered with their owne best learned doctors, and most skillefull Proctors, that gladly they would satisfy their Iesuited Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, &amp; wipe away that discredit, which hangeth at their beardes, for which ende they vse many coosenlnge trickes, iuglings, and lieger-demains, so to stay the outcries of the people vntill I be dead, and then by your fauour, they will com vpon me with good speed. Canis mortuus non mordet: but before that day, my life I gage in that behalfe, they dare not for their guttes publishe any direct &amp; full āswear <hi>etc.</hi> because to snatch here a piece &amp; there a piece, is no answear at all, but a mere toy for young children to play withall. <hi>But pardon him this, &amp; he will neuer do so any more whiles he liueth, it was the heate of his zeale and the longe gaping after an ouerseeing benefice, that made so many madde and lofty words to runne forth, whiles the doore was open.</hi> Balams <hi>eies be now illuminated, and he seeth verie well, and the world knoweth, that his bookes be not only answearable, but also som of thē answered.</hi> His Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefall of Popery <hi>which in the highe pitche of his soaringe pride he affirmed to be such tickling stuffe that</hi> euery arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <note place="margin">Funeral. lib. 2. cap. 4 pag. 10.</note> cōclusiō, &amp; propositiō therein cōtained, might truly be called, Noli me tangere, because they dare not <hi>(quoth he)</hi> for ten thousād milliōs of gould touch the same fully &amp; directly: <hi>whē as for al that, euery article hath bene examined, euery cōclusiō cōfuted &amp; euery propositiō perused, answered, &amp; beaten in pieces, so that the Minister</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>may truly be called</hi> Noli mihi credere, <hi>and deserueth for this and hundreds more of like qualitie, ten thousand mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of whetstones for the rewarde of his workes, the trophees of his labours, and the perpetuall ensigne of his false, foolishe, and phantasticall monuments.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But to prosecute further in particular this present Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, the due examination whereof I haue vndertaken, two speciall things remayne yet to be spoken of. The first concerning my self: the second touchinge the Minister. As for my self, thou shalt vnderstand (good Reader) that I was once determined, to haue answeared the treatise fully and wholy, as thou maist perceiue by the first and second chapters: but afterward infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of body hindering the course of my studies, and desire of minde to haue it dispatched with all speed, caused an other resolution which may perhaps reuiue Bels dead spirits, and inflame his cooled bloud, and make him com out once againe with his old complaint, that I haue answeared him by pieces and patches, and for my lugges and guttes durst not deale with</hi>
      <note place="margin">Such are Bels phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note>
      <hi>the whole, and that I haue after much labour and study, much siftinge and searching, out of the whole tome of his</hi> Triall, <hi>consisting almost of fiue and twenty leaues in quarto, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red only eight and fifty vntruthes, and not past some fiue or sixe contradictions. If the winde be gotte againe into that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, no remedy but I must beare of his storme with the cloake of patience, hopinge that the good reader will consider, how as I was not bound to meddle with his Pamphlet at all, so it was also at my choice to leaue what I listed and take what I pleased, especially making open profession of this my course ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken therein, and haue not any way abused the good Reader, as Bell hath, who in his</hi> Funeral <hi>doth make the world beleue, that he hath wholy answeared my</hi> Forerunner, <hi>consisting only of fower sheetes of paper, and yet omitteth many notable and principall points, as I noted in the</hi> Dolefull knell <hi>as for</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 61.</note>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>example, where his congregation is challenged by me to haue bene vnknowen for many hundred years together, (as they are inforced to confesse) our Church all that while bearinge saile in the sight of the world: and also charged to maintayne the heresies of</hi> Aerius, Vigilantius, <hi>and to take part with</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian <hi>the Apostata, and Turkishe Mahumetans: to all which troublsom obiections, he maketh silence to giue the solution.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The irreconciliable dissensions likewise of the Protestants in Germaeny, and the endles brawles of our Minīsters at home, not in triuiall toies, but in matters of maine moment and importance, beinge vpon iust occasion sett before him, he fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himself blinde, and will not see any more then pleaseth himself: and the better to cloake this his dealinge, he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted the whole order, chopping and chaunginge all thinges, as best serueth for the concealing of his treachery, as in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the Preface a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ende.</note>
      <hi>booke is handled. But as for me, albeit I haue not taken vpon me any intiere reply, yet shall the good Reader finde euery chapter examined in order, no one omitted, and not much worth the speaking of, to be lette passe: so that in very truth it may serue for a iust confutation. An other thinge also Bell is to vnderstand, viz, that he hath entred into an obligation of all losse of creditte for euer, if he can be conuinced guilty of one only vntruth. Be not these his owne words, breathing out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but an argument of a timorous conscience, and vpright dealing, to the commendation of his doctrine, and winninge popular applause and likinge.</hi> And my procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings <note place="margin">Motiues pag. 17.</note>
      <hi>(quoth he)</hi> throughout this whole treatise, shall be such and so sincere, as if I can be conuinced by the aduersary, either to alleadge any writer corruptly, or to quote any place guilefully, or to charge any author falsely, I will neuer require cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit at the Readers hand, neither in this worke, nor in any other, that I shall publishe at any tyme
<pb facs="5"/> hereafter: <hi>of which promise he maketh also mention in his</hi> Downefall. <hi>This being so, can Bell iustly complayne if his</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the Preface.</note>
      <hi>bookes be not wholy answeared, when as one only certaine corruption or vntrue charge of any author proued against him doth cassiere his creditt, and giue him his deaths wound or with what face can he iustly complayne, when as in this Treatise not one or two, but almost therscore of his vntruths be displayed, or how can he denie all his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to be loste, and his creditte crackt for euer. VVill he say that he is not truly charged, and pleade still for his innocency and sincerity in proceedinge? So he may I graunt, but whether truly or no, that I remitte to the sequele: desiring the good Reader in: he meane tyme, only to pervse ouer the xx. xxv. xxvj. and xxvij. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s, and if he sindeth not that he hath alleadged wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters corruptly, quoted</hi> Iosephus Angles <hi>guilefully, and charged authors falsly, then a Gods name, lett him be still liked and loued, still culled and imbraced for the stoute champion, and sure pillar of the congregation. But if triall shall teache him that he hath forfeited his obligation. no reason or conscience, but the condition should be performed Thus much touching my self.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Concerning Bell and his Pamphlett, two things occurre worthy of consideration. The first is, that as his Pamphlets called.</hi> The hunting of the Romishe Foxe, <hi>his</hi> woefull cry, &amp;c. <hi>be either wholy, or principally bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from his other bookes, though a newe title, and an other manner of order and methode, may cause the Reader to thinke it otherwise, and thereby to haue him in admiration, for his abundant matter and flowinge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention: so this his</hi> Triall of the new religion, <hi>will be found vpon triall, to be nothing els, but old patches</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>and pieces of his former workes, especially of his</hi> Suruey <hi>and only stitched together, and botched vp after a new fashion. For I assure the good Reader, except it be the first chapter, entreatinge</hi> Of the Popes name, <hi>not only all the rest, (and that in many places almost</hi> verbatim) <hi>is dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen from his</hi> Suruey <hi>(and his other bookes) but also the very Epistle dedicatory it self, such a rare iewell hath he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to his Patrones. VVhether this be so or no, lett vs briefly runne ouer the particulars.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>His Epistle dedicatory, is taken from his</hi> Suruey <hi>pag. 341. 342. except a very flewe lines, and the recapitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which he hath annexed to the ende) of the chapters following after. Of the first chapter I haue already spoken. The second chapter</hi> Of the Popes superroiall power <hi>is borrowed from his</hi> Suruey <hi>pag. 189. where his eight ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments against the supreame spirituall iurisdiction of the Pope be contayned. His third chapter,</hi> Of the marriage of Priests, &amp;c. <hi>consisting of fiue paragraffes, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed from the same booke of his</hi> Suruey. <hi>The first paragraffe, is found pag. 216. The second, pag. 224. pag. 233. and 234. and 228. The third pag. 267. and 269. The fourth pag. 268. and 269. and that which he sayeth of</hi> Aeneas Syluius, <hi>or</hi> Pius <hi>the second is in his</hi> woefull cry <hi>pag. 25. and lastly that which he bringeth of</hi> S. Gregory, &amp;c. <hi>cometh from his</hi> Suruey <hi>pag. 222. His fift paragraffe, is nothing els but a recitall, or recapitulation of the whole chapter: which fashion he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth also in his other chapters to make perhappes the bulke the bigger for the greater commendation of his labours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The fourth chapter</hi> Of Pardons, <hi>is fetched partly</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>from his</hi> Suruey, <hi>pag. 278. 279. and wholy from his</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full crye <hi>pag. 17. and 18. The fist chapter</hi> Of Purgatory, <hi>taketh his first Originall from his</hi> Motiues <hi>pag. 3. 4. and 5. (where the authority of</hi> Roffensis <hi>is spunne out at length) and also from his</hi> Suruay, <hi>pag. 297. His sixt chapter,</hi> Of Auricular confession, <hi>is deriued from the same</hi> Suruay, <hi>pag. 501. and 502. And partly from the same sincke, partly from the puddles of his</hi> Downefall, <hi>stewe the principall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of his seauenth chapter, which is</hi> Of veniall sinnes. <hi>See his</hi> Suruey <hi>pag. 381. 382. and</hi> Downfall <hi>pag.</hi> 383.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>His eight chapter,</hi> Of the Popes fayth, <hi>as touching the former part, he tooke from his</hi> Anatomy, <hi>as himself noteth in the margent, and that which in the later part he saith of</hi> So to <hi>and</hi> Alphonsus <hi>is fetched from his</hi> Ballance, <hi>fol. 9. a, and fol. 13. b. His ninth chapter,</hi> Of the meritt of workes <hi>excepting that which he disputeth against</hi> S. R. <hi>is transported from his</hi> Suruey <hi>pag. 396. 397: and from his</hi> Downefall, <hi>pag. 61. 75. and</hi> 69.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>His tenth chapter</hi> Of Transubstantiation, <hi>is but a fewe ragges, gathered from his</hi> Suruey, <hi>pag. 436. 437. and his</hi> Downefall <hi>pag. 34. The eleauenth chapter</hi> Of Popish inuocation of Saintes, <hi>is shreds of his</hi> Suruay <hi>pag. 331. and 340. where the same tales of</hi> S. Thomas <hi>and</hi> Polan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus <hi>were broached before. His twelfth chapter,</hi> Of the communion vnder one kinde, <hi>proceedeth from his</hi> Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey <hi>pag. 402. and 409. The thirtenth chapter,</hi> Of <hi>priuate Masse, springeth from the same roote of his</hi> Suruey <hi>pag. 414. and 415. The sourtenth chapter,</hi> Of Pope Martins dispensation, <hi>is drawne from his</hi> Downefall, <hi>pag. 40. and his</hi> Funerall, <hi>lib. 2. cap. 7. The fiftenth chapter,</hi> Of worshipping of images, <hi>is a wofull slippe, of his</hi> wofull cry <hi>pag. 62. and 63. The sixtenth chapter,</hi> Of Church seruice in the vulgar tongue, <hi>descendeth from his</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> Suruey <hi>pag.</hi> 476. 477. &amp;c. <hi>The seauenteth chapter</hi> Of the antiquity of Popishe Masse, and the parts the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, <hi>acknowledgeth the same</hi> Suruey <hi>for syre, pag. 480. and 481. The eightenth chapter,</hi> Of the profound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of Popishe Masse <hi>yssueth from the same booke, pag. 484. The ninetenth chapter,</hi> Of kissing the Popes feete, <hi>hath his first head and origen, in the same</hi> Suruey <hi>pag.</hi> 487.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The twentith chapter,</hi> Of praying vpon beades. <hi>The one and twentith,</hi> Of chaunging the Popes name. <hi>The two and twentith,</hi> Of the Paschall torch. <hi>The three and twentith,</hi> Of the Popishe Pax, <hi>be fower brethren, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by his</hi> Suruey, <hi>pag. 487. 486. 488. and 482. The fower and twentith chapter.</hi> Of the Popes Bulles. <hi>The fiue and twentith,</hi> Of the Popishe Agnus Dei. <hi>The sixe and twentith,</hi> Of Candlemas day, <hi>be three sisters, descending from the very same father, pag. 492. and 491. The seauen and twentith chapter,</hi> Of the doubtfull oath, &amp;c. <hi>receiueth his generation from his</hi> Motiues <hi>pag. 60. and his</hi> Downefall <hi>pag.</hi> 124, &amp;c. <hi>The eight and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith chapter,</hi> Of fasting, <hi>hath his creation, from his</hi> Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey, <hi>pag.</hi> 68. &amp;c. <hi>The nine and twentith chapter,</hi> Of the annulling of Popish wedlock <hi>was first handled in his</hi> Motiues <hi>pag. 63. and 64. and afterward rehandled in his</hi> Downefall, <hi>pag. 36. The thirtith and last chapter receiued his first life from his</hi> Motiues <hi>pag. 56. and</hi> 57.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>This is the Anatomy, and liuely description of his</hi> Triall, <hi>which discouereth the rare dexterity he hath in writing, and from whatfountayne his great shewe of abundāce floweth. His choice of newe bookes is not vnlike the variety of</hi> Esopes sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, or the skilof som poore fidler, that with two or three cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se daunces scraped vpon a sluttishe crowde, serueth the whole countrey, and maketh his good masters mery. This is the first thing which I had to say concerning Bell, and his bookes.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>
      <hi>The second pointe which I meant to entreat of, and would haue the Reader to note is, that whereas Bels former bookes did continually ringe out bragges and brauinges, darings and redarings, challenges and Larums, and the world was filled with his dayly outcriestin this last l'amphlet of his</hi> Triall, <hi>as also in his</hi> Antepast, <hi>(sor so much as I have readde) I meete with no suche swelling words, nor finde any smoake of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aunting humor. Those windes are allaid, that terrible tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest is ouerblowne, and the surginge seas, and mounting waues of such extrauagant insolency calnied and at quiet. Besore we could heare no other musicke but the battaile and such quarter braules as these.</hi> In regard hereof most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <note place="margin">In the Epistle ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his Funeral.</note> and dread Soueraigne, I now prostrate <hi>(quoth Bell)</hi> vpon my knees, doe most humbly bese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che your most excellent Maiesty, that it will plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se your Highnes, of your most princely fauour, to graunt your roiall licence and safe conduct, for any Englishe lesuit or lesuited Bapist in the whole world, that shall haue courage to appeare, for the true performance of the challenge, in such manner as is in this reply expressed; Oh most gracious Soueraigne I am ioyfull when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this future combate, I wishe in my hart that it may be effected with all expedition, for I confidently perswade my self in our Lord Iesus, that his name shall thereby be glorified, your Maiesty highely honoured, the Papists stricken dead, and all true harted Englishe sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects receiue vnspeakable endlesse comfort. Yf it shall fall out otherwise, and that I shall not be found euen in your Maiesties iudgement to haue the victory and vpper hand, I will be content to loose my life for my iust reward, as one that
<pb facs="7"/> dishonoured your Maiesty and the cause: <hi>where also the Echo of the margent returneth backe againe, the like triumphant tune.</hi> O noble king <hi>(quoth he)</hi> for Christs sake graunt my request, the victory is already gotten, none of them dare vndertake the quarrell. Let me be hanged, bowelled, and quartered, yea and my corps cast to the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the aire, if the victory fall not on my side.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Againe in an other place.</hi> I dare and redare all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe <note place="margin">Funeral. lib. 2. cap. 2. pag. 5.</note> Iesuits and Iesuited Papists, whosoeuer and wheresoeuer, to let me haue their speedy answear, and the acceptance of this challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No no they dare neuer do such an act, dum spiritus hos artus: what they dare do when I am dead I knowe not. <hi>And againe he not only reneweth his challenge, but also enlargeth it with many bigge and terrible wordes, protesting his burninge desire, and great readines in this marginall note.</hi> A newe <note place="margin">Fun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>val. lib. 2. cap. 5. pag. 12. Annexed to the and of his Funeral.</note> challenge which I desire with all my hart to be performed as knoweth our mereifull God. <hi>And yet once againe he is vpon our bones with</hi> A freshe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, or newe challenge, to all Englishe Iesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Iesuited Papists in the vniuersall world tagge and ragge, none at all excepted, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer shall appeare in the shape of man. <hi>This was the braue vaine and exalted spirit of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimous Minister, neuer at quiet but still vrginge and pricking vs forward, goading ad goaringe vs to the combate with his continuall scoffes, tauntes, girds, glickes, with incessant and insupportable scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and in most contemptible and disdainfull manner,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>a sample whereof I haue here in the former sentences pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented before the (good Reader) a more large viewe may be had in the</hi> Dolefull knel, <hi>and that taken only out of the one booke of his</hi> Funerall.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>But he that before, like a princely Eagle soared a lost in the skies, creepeth now like a poore frozen snake in the lowe vautes and valleis.</hi> Esops <hi>rumbling mountayne that terrified all the borders, with the feare of som mishapen and formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble monster, is at last deliuered of a ridiculous mouse. Bell that thus assaulted vs with his challenges, and gaue vs no rest from his darings and Larums, hath now giuen ouer that stately stile and manner of writing, That which the mercifull God knewe before he desired with his whole hart, knoweth now that he longeth for no such thinge, the eadge of his zeale is abated, the ouerboiling heate of his courage is coaled: In this his</hi> Triall, <hi>not one sentence, word, or syllable of any challenge, offer of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputation, or acceptance of Conserence is mentioned, and as little (for that little which I haue readde) doe I finde in his</hi> Antepast. Quantum mutatus ab illo. <hi>From whence co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this suddaine change or what hath wrought this vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and strange alteration. Nothing els good Reader but that Bell as at the first surprized with the desire of vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and the worldes applause made his first challenge yet with a clause to preuent afterclaps, viz yf it might stande with the liking of higher powers: so was he afterwarde deceiued in his accoutes, erred in his conceipts, &amp; made a wronge reckening: For he verily persuaded himself because he had remained so many yeares vnāsweared, that the same world would stil haue continued: and that the terror of his challenges, had so benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our fingers, that no pēne could or would haue bene stirred against him.</hi> None of them <hi>(quoth he to his Maiesty as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was noted)</hi> dare vndertake the quarrell: <hi>and in his Latum.</hi> But on the other side yf either no Papist
<pb facs="8"/> dare appeare, to performe and answear the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge: and to speake playne Englishe, I thincke it will fall out so &amp;c. <hi>VVhereupon he followed the chace so eagerly, that no rest or peace could be had from his darings, challenges, and Larums: but finding now that he was in a wronge boxe, and that it was rather contempt, then any feare which caused so long silence, our terrible kilcowe hath pulled in his hornes, and he that before like a proude palfry prickt vp with prouander kept a snorting and flinginge, is now become so poore, so lame and leane, that the kites and crowes assure them selues shortly to be the executors of his last will and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>He hath mette with</hi> S. R. <hi>his answear to his insolent and challenging</hi> Downefall: <hi>or rather that hath mette</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the Epistle to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie.</note>
      <hi>with him, which hath giuene him this deadly greeting.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore seing that of late Thomas Bell, a fugitiue once from Protestants religion, as he is now from Catholiques, hath not only accused but also slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the vniuersal Catholique cause, in a booke which he hath dedicated to your Maiesty, and tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, <hi>The Downefall of Poperye,</hi> and withall challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, dareth, yea adiureth, (in which case our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sauiour though with daunger of his life made answear) all Englishe Iesuits, Seminary Priests, and as he speaketh Iesuited Papists to answear him: I haue presumed vpon your gratious fauour to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his challenge, and am ready to performe it hand to hand, if your Maiesty graunt license, and in the meane tyme to dedicate to your name this my Confutation of his arguments and slaunders. <hi>After this dismoll newes, no small coolinge carde to the gallant gamster, and so much the more grieuous, by how much he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer expected any such thinge: behould, out cometh an other</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>booke of mine against him, called.</hi> The Dolefull knell, <hi>in</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the Epistle a little from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and also not far from the end.</note>
      <hi>which I haue made most humble sute vnto the right honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord Chancelor of</hi> England, <hi>(to whom the booke is dedicated) for the fauour of an indifferent conference as passed in</hi> France, <hi>and that in such serious and effectuall manner, as Bell can not but perceiue that we be in earnest. In that booke also, after I had sett downe many of his proude and presumpteous speaches, of his vaine vaunting, and craking challenges, I did as it were prophecy, that the world should shortly knowe how</hi> he would slippe his necke out of <note place="margin">In the Preface: about so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me seuen pages from the end. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> Chap. 3.</note> the collar, and not withstanding all his daringe and redaringe, all his braue boastinge and solemne protestation, find out som one cauilling shift or other, neuer to appeare in publique conference, least he shamed him self and the congregation for euer. <hi>There likewise shall the good Reader finde, that I haue answered him so home, &amp; so roundly ioyned yssue with him touching his challenges, in a chapter intreatinge of that speciall point, that I suppose he can not desire more, and make no doubt but that Bell neuer desired so much.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Finally in my</hi> Scholasticall defiance <hi>to his</hi> Freshe larum <hi>in the end of the</hi> Dolefull Knell, <hi>I haue said so abundantly in answear to the particulars thereof (setting down the same wholy and entierly) that it is no question with me, but that Bell may say more truly thereof, then he doth when he acknowledgeth his synnes before the receiuing of their Communion, viz that the burthen thereof is to him intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. And here to the perpetuall disgrace of challenging Sr. Thomas, and perfect satisfaction of the Reader, that he may fully vnderstand, how we are more willinge to take vp his gauntlet, then euer he was in the height of his greatest vanity to throw it to vs, I will adioyn what for the last par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I say to his</hi> Larum, <hi>my words be these.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb facs="9"/> this pointe, whereof I haue said before so sufficiently both in the Epistle dedicatory, and in answear to his third chapter, that I make no doubt the Reader remayneth with full satisfaction: here not to followe the wandringe Minister in his vaine of vauntinge, to leaue words, and to come vnto dedes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Non cauponantes bellum sed belligerantes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I the meanest of millions, doe accept of his challenge here made, and doe vndertake to defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, not only those two points of <hi>Iosephus</hi> doctrine and Pope <hi>Martins</hi> dispensation, which he hath sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled out as matters important: but also all the rest; so it may be, (which is but reason) with that equity and fauour, which was graunted to the Protestants in France: and vpon the same condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do prouoke him with a counter-challenge, to the defence of his bookes, according to his inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and manifold daring offers: and for triall of both these twayne, in manner a foresaid, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure him, for the credit of the congregation, and adiure him by the maiesty of the Ministry, and exorcise him by all those Larums and challenges, by all those brauings and braggings which be foūd in his bookes, by all that reputation which he hath gotten with his silly dependants, and that mighty expectatiō, which he hath moued in the minds of many, that he would procure this safe-conducte, of which he much speaketh, but we can not yet gett any sight: and the more to vrge and presse him: the more to pricke and spurre him, to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of so notable and memorable a pece of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: the more to styrre, prouoke, and inflame his
<pb facs="10"/> ministeriall mounting spirit, impatient of disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and to fire the zeale of his fury forward, I send him this scholasticall denance, with as many chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges, as will stand between <hi>Charing Crosse</hi> and <hi>Chester,</hi> and as many dares, as will reache from <hi>Darby</hi> to <hi>Darington.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>These, these dolefull newes, haue cast him into such dumps, that he hath small list to heare either of disputation, or any indifferent Conference and therefore though he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth still, and vseth that as a poore proppe to vphould his fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge reputation, least the infamy of cowardize and dast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rdly feare, with no small desgrace to theire cause, should suddainly seaze vpon him yet the tickling stringe and mountinge Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nekin of brauinge and challenging is not once touched, that kinde of desc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nie is now out of date. He is no true friend of his that will so much as mention any such matter. If this be not the cause what is the reason that he which was so furious before like a little lion, is now become so gentle like a tame cosset? Be it that his haughty and insolent maner of crakinge, vpon better adi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ise of friends disliked him, yet should he in temperat and modest sort, still haue prosecuted his former quarrell, for the creditt of their gospell, and reputation of his learninge, which in the opinion of his dependants is very great, and in his owne incomparable, and accepted of the offer of</hi> S. R. <hi>and vtterly confounded him in disputation: for he nothing doubteth or at least in former tymes hath not, yf his wordes did truly deliuer his meaning, but that such an act would</hi> tend to the glory of God, to the seruice of his Soueraigne; the honour of his countrey, the edification of his auditors, and the comfort of his owne soule, <hi>as in his</hi> Motiues <hi>he speaketh: or if disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 36.</note>
      <hi>liketh him not, why hath he not procured a Safeconduct for such an indifferent Conference, for the due triall, and</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>examination of the authorities alleadged in his bookes, as passed in</hi> Fraunce <hi>betwixt the reuerend Bishoppe of</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reux <hi>and now Cardinall, and the Lord of</hi> Plessi Marlie: <hi>for if that sincerity be vsed which he often protesteth, what readyer way could he haue wished, either for the procuringe to himself eternal renowme, and vnspeakable creditt to his cause, or euerlasting shame to me, and thereby some disgrace to Catholike religion. Seing then he is now so mute, that before was so tonguy: now so dead, that before was so liuely: can any other true cause thereof be assigned, then that his owne conscience, not ignorant of his bad quarrell, and priuy to so many corrupt citations as be founde in his bookes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him willing, after so great expectation moued in mens mindes, to shift his hāds from any such busines, &amp; slily to steale away, as though</hi> Englāds Ioye <hi>were againe in actinge. Or yf the humour of self love doth so dazele his eies, that he can not yet see, into what dangerous straigtes by his many &amp; manifest vntruthes, he hath brought the reputation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: and so would for his owne part still venture for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: VVhat can be thought otherwise, of any that penetrate into the matter as they ought, but that superior authority hath commaunded the clapper to silence, for his foolishe and dāgerous iangling. But he that hath hetherto behaued himself in such insolent and dominiringe manner, odious to God and the world must not thus passe away: wherefore I giue him once again to vnderstand, that we expect the Safeconduct, which he hath so often spoken of: this we require, vrge, and exact at his hands: wherein if he fayle, well may his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers saye: Farewell fidelity, the glory of the Gospell is ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, shame hath shaken handes with the congregation, and no remedy but it must be proclaimed by vs in towne and country, that Bell, euen the Minister Bell, that daringe Doctor, that craking challenger, that couragious champion,</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>that Larum ringer is desperately fled the field, not daringe to indure the encounter of his auersaries, and hath left all the fraternity egregiously cousined, abused and gulled: or els: which turneth as much to his perpetuall infamy, and disgrace: that his mouth is musseled by authority, for hauing spoken more, then be can with his owne honesty, or reputation to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cause, defend and maintayne, VVherefore what remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but that hauing runge his</hi> Dolefull knell, <hi>and left him speacheles, and ready to giue vp his last gaspe: and hauing also prouided here a winding sheet, for the shrow dinge of his carcasse, but that I should with what conuenient speed I can, make reddy his Blacke Buriall, that he may according to his deserts be interred, to the perpetuall ignominy of his name, and euerlasting confusion of the congregation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Before I ende, I can not (gentle Reader) but say som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge, concerning a booke that came lately to my handes, of one</hi> Thomas Rogers: <hi>which as it is a commentary vpon nine and thirtie articles,</hi> contayning the faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion professed in England, and concordably agreed vpon <hi>(as he saith)</hi> by the reuerend Bishoppes and cleargy, at two seuerall Conuocations: <hi>so is it graced with this Embleme.</hi> Perused, and by the lawfull authority of the Church of England allowed to be publique. <hi>In this booke, proceeding from so graue a man, as he insinuateth himself to be: from the chaplin, to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of their cleargy: intreating of so waighty, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a subiect, as the Synodicall decrees of their church: and commended to the world, in such singular and speciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, what can of reason be expected, but that the truth should sincerely be sett forth, without all suspition of cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge conueyance: all feare of sinister relation, or any scruple, or doubt of hatefull corruption: seing the stayne of such crymes, should not only touch</hi> Mr. Rogers,
<pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>but redound also as it were, to the infamy of the whole body of their cleargy, and religion. For any, yea of meane insight, may soone make this discourse: that if the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of</hi> England <hi>were sounde, and ours false and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, no indirect proceding needed or woulde be practised, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the aduancinge of their owne, or depressing of ours: and contrarywise, if corrupt courses, be made the buckler to defend themselues, and the weapon to offend vs: what can be thought, but that there is a flawe in that faith, which is by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maintayned: and impregnable veritie in our religion, which is by such godles shiftes assaulted: now whether this be so or no, and in that grosse manner, as not only those which be of capacity and learninge, but euen of the meanest and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant sort, shall (especially in som of them) thinke vs to be noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously abused &amp; iniuried, remayneth to be hadled. VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore to runne ouer briefly, some fewe vntruths, and a little to touch the corrupt dealing of</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>as my short tyme shal giue leaue, &amp; the straight cōfines of a Preface will permitte.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 14. He setteth vpon vs in the manner.</hi> One Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">A. short list of Mr. Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes.</note> Iane <hi>(quoth he)</hi> is the Sauiour of women: a most execrable assertion, of Postellus the Iesuit. <hi>Nay rather it is a most execrable vntruth of</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>the Preacher. Can a man of his profession, charge vs with so strange, paradoxicall, and blasphemous an assertion, and so iniurious to the sacred bloud of the Redeemer of the whole world, and that both of men and women, without recoilinge of Conscience: we denye what he saith, how doth he proue what so boldly he affirmeth.</hi> Postellus the Iesuit <hi>(quoth he)</hi> teacheth this execrable dnctrine: <hi>which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth out of the Iesuits Cathechisme. That</hi> Postellus <hi>was one of that order, is more then I doe knowe, or more then I list yet to beleue, vntill I see better prooffes: but yf he were, he was no other, then such a religious man as</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/> Luther <hi>was, that ranne out of his cloister to lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Gospell. I finde him in the</hi> Indice <hi>of the Councell of</hi> Trent, <hi>commonly annexed thereunto, enrolde for an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike and so discharged from vs: albeit I can hardly beleue, that euer he could be so madde, as to broach any such ridiculous, sensles, and blasphemous doctrine. To iustify this of</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stellus, Mr. Rogers <hi>voucheth the Iesuits Catachisme, that is a most scandalous and slaunderous libel, made by one</hi> Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiere <hi>a French heretike, in disgrace of that renowmed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as he knoweth full well, when he citeth out of the same Catachisme two infamous verses, tendinge deepely to the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 187.</note>
      <hi>touch of their liues, which none so simple to thinke, that they would publishe of themselues. They are so far from being the authors of that filthie and hereticall booke, that one</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheome <hi>a learned man of that Society, hath sette forth a confutation thereof. Should a Catholike compose a like trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, bearinge title. The Church of Englands Catechisme, fraught with abhominable and most odious opinions, and such in truth as they vtterly detest: and should I produce out of it most loathsom stuffe, against them in disgracè of their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, would he not condemne both the author, for a monster of the world, and me for an extreame malitious slaunderer, to presse them with any such damnable testimony? I leaue the application to himself.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 17. He condemneth it in vs as an error and drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that Christ descended downe into hell, to deliuer the Soules of our forefathers: and that most iniuriously, for (to omitte what may be brought out of sacred scripture) we can not be condemned herein but the auncient fathers, must beare vs company, and that by the testimony of our aduersaries.</hi> The fable <hi>(quoth</hi> Casuin) of a place vnder the <note place="margin">2. Instit. cap. 16. §. 9.</note> ground, called Limbus, albeit it hath greate au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, yet it is nothing els then a fable. Sutcliffe
<pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>confesseth, that</hi> S. Hierom <hi>and other fathers beleued, that</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Purgato. cap. 4.</note>
      <hi>there was a</hi> simbus patrum <hi>before the comming of Christ. But he addeth, that they affirmed it rather scholasticaliy then dogmatically, which yet he neither doth nor can proue: we take what he graunteth of their beleuinge, the other we deny.</hi> Willet <hi>also can not gainesay the same.</hi> We confesse <note place="margin">In his s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nopsis of the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō 1600. pag. 353.</note>
      <hi>(quoth he)</hi> that the fathers for the most part of them, to haue bene in this error. <hi>To conclude this doctrine is taught by the church of Englande, when as in the Geneua Psalms, allowed and authorized by receiued custome amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest them: this article of the Crede:</hi> He descended into hell. <hi>is turned thus into meeter.</hi>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <l>His soule did after this discende,</l>
      <l>into the lower parts.</l>
      <l>To them that longe in darkenes were,</l>
      <l>the true light of their harts.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>
      <hi>By what warrant therfore</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>expoundeth them here to the contrary I know not, him selfe can best tell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 23. many Papistes <hi>(quoth he)</hi> and namely the Franciscans, blushe not to say that S. Francis is the Holy Ghost. Mr. Rogers <hi>blusheth not notoriously to iniury vs with the imputation of so blasphemous an assertion. He quoteth in the margent for prooffe, the Alcaron of the Franciscans, a most shamelesse and scurrilous booke, sett out by modern heretikes against that worthy and religious order. It seemeth he bestoweth much of his tyme in such spirituall books as these, and willingly entertaineth such witnes against vs, as the Scribes and Phariseis did against Christ: vntill he dischargeth himself better, this iniurious and blasphemous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth must ly vpon him self.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 29. Speaking of our behauiour to the scriptures, he</hi>
      <note place="margin">Antidot. euang in Luc. 16. p. 528.</note>
      <hi>saith.</hi> To the same purpose but more blasphemously Stapleton saith, as the Iewes were to beleue Christ
<pb facs="13"/> so are we simply and in euery thinge to beleue the Church of Rome, whether it teacheth truth or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. <hi>He fathereth a grosse vntruth vpon</hi> Stapleton; <hi>his words be these.</hi> Certum est, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is certayne that the Iewes ought to haue obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed Christ, so far forth, as he gaue testimony to the truth, but whether he did that or no, belonged not to the Iewes to make any doubt of, but simply to beleue. Wherefore as the Iewes ought to haue beleued Christ, so ought we simply to beleue the Churche: not verily whether <note place="margin">Note the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se wordes against Mr. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> it teacheth true thinges or not; but whether that be certayne to vs or not. We ought not to doubt but as the father sending Christ; &amp; cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to be heard: so Christ sending his church and commaunding that to be heard, hath by his wisdom disposed, that without all daunger of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as well the Churche should be heard of vs, as Christ of the Iewes. <hi>True therefore it is not, that</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton <hi>saith we are simply and in euery thinge to beleue the Church, whether it teacheth truth or errors, for he affirmeth the contrary, and his words contayne not any impious or absurd doctrine, though</hi> Mr. Rogers, <hi>by ouerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing, and not reciting his wordes truly, would make him to speake both impiously and falsely.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 49. He taxeth vs, for teachinge free will: and these words he citeth as out of the Councell of</hi> Trent. Man <note place="margin">Ses. 6. cap. 1.</note> hath free will, to performe euen spirituall and heauenly thinges. <hi>VVhat error can this be; when straight after</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>setteth downe this proposition.</hi> Man may performe and do good works, when he is preuented by the grace of Christ, and renued by the Holy Ghost. <hi>But he will say, that the Councell of</hi> Trent <hi>teacheth, that good workes may be done without</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>the grace of Christ, and therefore he citeth this doctrine of ours as erroneous, and contrary to a former proposition of his, which is this.</hi> Man can not do any good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that good is and godly, being not yet regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. <hi>But herein he doth slaunder the Councell of</hi> Trent. <hi>In the very place by him quoted it rather hath the contrary: and in the first Canon of that Session most plainely; which is this.</hi> Yfany shall say, that a man is iustified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Ses. 6. can. 1.</note> God by his workes, which are done either by the force of humane nature, or the doctrine of the lawe, without diuine grace by Iesus Christ, be he accursed. <hi>Iudge nowe (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) whether</hi> Mr. Rogers, <hi>hath dealt truly with vs, and the Councell of</hi> Trent <hi>or no, when he would perswade the world, that we beleue, that man hath free will, to performe euen spiritual &amp; heauenly things, without the grace of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the same page, and very next line, he entreateth the</hi> Rhemists <hi>in like manner, where he citeth these words of theirs.</hi> Men beleue not but of there owne free will. <hi>True it is they say so, but they exclude not in those wordes Gods grace, as moste iniuriously he chargeth them, alleadging their words for that purpose, for els where they acknowledge that Gods grace and free will must both concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. in ver. 5. pag. 447.</note>
      <hi>Beside, the better to infame them, he hath corrupted the sentence, chopping of the last words, which be these.</hi> August. lib. 1. ad Simplicianum q. 2. <hi>so that the charg of heresy or error toucheth</hi> S. Augustin, <hi>from whom those words be drawne</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>without all scruple, cutteth those away, to make his slaunder the more colourable against the</hi> Rhemists, <hi>not hauing any list to quarrell with</hi> S. Augustin.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 65. S. Francis <hi>(quoth he)</hi> attayned vnto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of holines and could not synne at all. <hi>A most</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <hi>iniurious slaunder. In the margent, he may seeme to quote somethinge to the ignorant, sor iustification of his bold asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō, but there is nothing saue a latin sentece, which in Englishe is this.</hi> Wilt thou come to the toppe or perfection, attend to the life and manners of Blessed Francis: <hi>but these words proue not, that he could not synne, and who is the author of them, none is here named at all. Is not this great sincerity of</hi> Mr. Rogers, <hi>to vent out such an egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vntruth and then to cousin his ignorant Reader, with a quotation of his owne, which yet proueth not that, for which it is alleadged.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 97. Speaking of the Popes, he enrolleth, diuers of them for heretikes.</hi> Some <hi>(quoth he)</hi> haue bene here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. For Siricius, Calixtus, Leo 9. &amp; Paschalis, condemned the marriage of Priests. <hi>A notorious vntruth, proceeding from a soule insected with heresy. Let Mr. Rogers name is he can, any old approued father or later writer, not tainted with his leuin, that euer condemned</hi> S. Siricius <hi>for an heretike. For if it be heresy to condemne the marriage of Priests, then was the auncient and holy Councell of</hi> Carthage <hi>heretikes: nay then were their forefathers, yea and the Apostles them selues heretikes, yf</hi>
      <note place="margin">Concil. Carth. 2. can. 2.</note>
      <hi>we may beleue them.</hi> It doth please vs all <hi>(saith that Councell)</hi> that Bishoppes, Priests, and deacons, and such as handle the Sacraments, being keepers of chastity, should abstaine them selues from wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that what the Apostles taught, and antiquity it self hath kept, we also should obserue. <hi>And if it please him to reade Bels 12. &amp; 13. vntruths in this treatise, he shall finde other authenticall authorities for the single life of the clergye, yea euen by the testimony of his owne dere brethren the Lutherans of</hi> Magdeburge: <hi>which being so, I make no doubt but that the discreet Reader, will rather</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <hi>condemne this moderne Minister, of a notable vntruth, then so many worthy fathers of the Primatiue Church for heretikes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 102. He slaundereth vs most palpably, as though we taught this doctrine, viz that</hi> The Church hath power to chaunge the Sacramēts ordained euen by Christ himself. <hi>we vtterly deny it, what euidence doth he bring to conuince vs He quoteth in the margent Concil.</hi> Trid. <hi>ses. 5. cap. 2. where no such thing is to be foūd. He must giue vs leaue to suspect, that he vsed art in setting downe the quotation, when the thing is most false which he obiecteth against vs. The place he meaneth is Ses. 21. cap. 2. where the Councell deliuereth this doctrine.</hi> Praeterea declarat <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Furthermore the Councell declareth, that this power hath alwaies bene in the Church, that it might in the dispensation of the Sacramentes, their substance remayning sound and vntouched, appoint or change those things, which it should iudge to be more expedient for the profit of those that receiue them, or that veneration which is due to the Sacraments, according to the varietie of things, tymes, and places. <hi>The Councell in expresse termes affirmeth, that the substance of the Sacraments can not be altered, and consequently that the Sacraments ordained by Christ can not be changed, which yet</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>directly contrary to their owne words, fathereth vpon them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 112. Som write <hi>(quoth he)</hi> as Busgradus, that yf the Pope beleue that there is no life to come, <hi>(as som Popes haue done)</hi> we must beleue it as an article of our faith. <hi>VVho this Busgradus is I knowe not, and as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle where the place is to be founde: neither am I like by</hi> Mr. Rogers: <hi>for he neither telleth the one, nor quoteth the other. It is not vnlike, but that he is one of his Suersbies, some</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>odde compannion or other, which he hath in store for such holy purposes. The vntruth is so abhominable, that it smelleth before God and man. Himself must father it, vntill he can name some knowne Catholike for author thereof which he will neuer doe before the wordls ende.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 115. Yf S. Hierom <hi>(quoth he)</hi> had bene away at Chalcedon, that Councell had erred. <hi>Then surely did it erre, seing certaine it is, that he could not be there, hauinge ended his daies before, vnder</hi> Honorius <hi>the Emperour. The authority of</hi> Iewell <note place="margin">Prosper in Chronico. anno Christi 422.</note>
      <hi>(who died most miserably in our memorie whom he quoteth) is to light for so waighty a matter. No maruail if</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>runne into many vntruths, yf he followeth such a lying master, as was of rare note for that qualitie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 116. By Councels <hi>(quoth he)</hi> the Traditions and bookes of foolishe men, haue bene made of <note place="margin">Ses. 4, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</note> equall authority with the word of God: as by the Councell of Trent. <hi>He meaneth the Histories of</hi> Toby, Iudith, <hi>and the</hi> Machabees &amp;c. <hi>as I suppose, and not all there admitted for Canonicall, least he sweepe away the whole Bible. And were not I beseche him, these bookes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorised also for Canonicall, by the third Councel of Carthage twelue hundred yeares ago, in which glorious</hi> S. Augustin <note place="margin">Can. 47.</note>
      <hi>was present: VVill he also lightely reiect this Councell as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishe, and condemne them also for authorising the bookes of foolishe men: it were plaine dealing I confesse, but far better manners rather so to censure himself for contradictinge such a learned, auncient, and venerable Synode. Again, shall the</hi> Apocalyps, <hi>or</hi> Reuelation <hi>of</hi> S. Iohn, <hi>be the booke of a foolishe man, because it was made Canonicall by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of</hi> Trent, <hi>and the third of Carthage. For as the bookes of</hi> Toby <hi>and the</hi> Machabees <hi>were before doubted of by diuers, and not ratified by the decree of any Councell</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>before that of</hi> Carthage, <hi>so was the</hi> Apocalypse <hi>of</hi> S. Iohn, <hi>and therefore theire case is all one. Furthermore be it, that</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>alloweth them not for Canonicall, yet ought he not to terme them the bookes of foolishe men: for then may we giue that name to all the bookes of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, yea to their Synode of nine and thirty articles, vpon which he maketh his commemary: and that which were moste pitty of all, both this, and other bookes of his owne may claime interest to the same title. Lastly doth not the congregation of</hi> England <hi>publikely reade both</hi> soble <hi>and</hi> Iudith <hi>in their Church seruice, in the same ranke and order with the other scriptures: and yet with</hi> Mr. Rogers, <hi>they be the bookes of foolishe men: verily in this pointe, he seemeth to be one of the disciplinarian fraternity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pap.</hi> 121. <hi>He citeth</hi> Eckius <hi>for houlding that not only veniall synnes but mortall also, are purged after this life. He slaundereth that learned man, he teacheth no such thinge, for then it would followe, that all men should finally be saued: It may be that he saith, the temporvll payne due to mortall syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, after the eternall is forgiuen, is purged after this life: of mortall synne it self he speaketh not, and I doe without all feare accuse him of an vntruth, though for lacke of the booke, I can not pervse the place he alleadgeth, so learned was the man knowne, and so sounde in religion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the same page he abuseth</hi> Durandus <hi>affirminge him to thinke that the soules in Purgatory haue rest som tymes vpon Sundayes and Holy daies. In the place by him quoted</hi> de officio mortuorum lib. 7. <hi>no such thing is founde.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 124. He chargeth vs moste vntruly to hold that repentance is not of necessity vnto the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō of mā: For without the same a Popishe pardon <hi>(quoth he)</hi> may serue. <hi>A great vntruth for a pardon profiteth not any man, but such as is in the state of Gods grace, which</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
      <hi>presupposeth pennance or repentance. No Catholike author he noteth that teacheth any such doctrine: &amp; no maruail, for none can be named. Thus is a gener all vntruth receiued amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest them, and theresore it should seme that they haue obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned some pardon for that purpose, to imitate their phrase of speakinge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 158. <hi>He chargeth vs to abuse the sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisem.</hi> So haue the Papists <hi>(saith he)</hi> baptized both Bels and Babels. <hi>Before he noted it in vs as an error, that we teach the Sacraments to conferre grace</hi> ex opere ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato. <hi>But I hope he is not so grosse as to imagin, that we should suppose that either Bels or Babels be capable of grace. The Sacramet of baptisme is only with vs, giuen to reasonable creatures: and though bels (for babels we leaue to him for his recreation) and other thinges be hallowed, with holy water, and other praiers, and haue sometyme a name giuen them, by reason whereof they are said by the common people to be baptized or Christened, in an improper and metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall sense: yet none whom malice possesseth not, will either say or thinke, that they be truly and properly baptized, when as the necessary and formall words of Baptisme, viz,</hi> I baptise thee in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghost, <hi>are not vsed. It would better become</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>grauity, to dispute formally like a diuine, then to cauill vpon the improper speache of the vulgar people, like a wranglinge Sophister.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag 159. speaking of the Eucharist, he chargeth vs most falsely</hi> to vse it magically as a salue against bodily sickenes and aduersity: <hi>citing no author for proffe of so bould and false an assertion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 157. Entreatinge of the Sacrament of Exteme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he commeth vpon vs with this false charge.</hi> The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister thereof vsually is a Priest, but may be any
<pb facs="16"/> other Christian: <hi>and a little after he affirmeth vs to houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that a woman may be the minister of that sacrament. A most grosse and palpable vntruth, jorged as it semeth by him selfe, when as he nameth not any other author. They are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed by vs that shall say, that the proper minister of Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi>
      <note place="margin">Concil. Trid. se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 14. can. 4. de extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione.</note>
      <hi>vnction is not only a Priest, which sheweth vs to be free from his false imputation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 168. He laboureth to insame vs after this manner.</hi> Baptisme <hi>(quoth he)</hi> serueth for the putting away of Originall synne only: <hi>and that we teach this doctrine he proueth out of</hi> S. Thomas <hi>of</hi> Aquine, <hi>whom he quoteth in the margent, but in such sort, that it seemeth he meant not that we should euer finde it: he reserreth vs to his booke,</hi> De Sac. altar: <hi>which hath two and thirty longe chapters, not specifying any one in particular: ensorcinge his Reader by this meanes either to beleue him, or to great labour before he can reproue him: but this cunninge must not serue his turne. I challenge him confidently of an vntruth: neuer shall he be able to iustify either out of that booke, or any other what he obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth against that myrrhour of learninge glorious</hi> S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas <hi>of</hi> Aquine <hi>as who teacheth far otherwise, as I will by more particular reference nowe declare. VVherefore in the</hi>
      <note place="margin">3 part. q 69. Artic. 1.</note>
      <hi>third part of his Summe he propoundeth this question.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Baptisme all synnes be taken away: <hi>to which he answeareth affirmatiuely. And in the articles followinge, he confirmeth the same verity especially in the seauenth: VVhere he moueth the question,</hi> whether the opening of the gare of the kingdome of heauen be an effect of Baptisme, <hi>which he resolueth in this manner.</hi> I answer and say, that to open the gate of the kingdome of heauen, is to remoue the impediment, by which one is hindered to enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and this impediment is synne, and the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishement
<pb facs="17"/> due to synne: but before it was proued that by Baptisme all synne, and all punnishement due to synne, is taken awaye, whereof it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the openinge of the gate of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, is the effect of Baptisme. <hi>Let</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>now go and tell such as will beleue him, that</hi> S. thomas <hi>taught Baptisme to take away Originall sinne only.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 169. and 170. He accuseth vs as though we taught Baptisme giuen to infants by Protestant ministers, not to be lawfull. An vntruth, as he may learne out of the Councell</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ses. 7. Can. 4. de Bapt.</note>
      <hi>of</hi> Trent, <hi>where this Canon is deliuered.</hi> Yf any shall say that Baptisme which is giuen of Heretikes in the name of the father, and the some, &amp; the Holy Ghost, with intention to do that which the Church doth, not to be true Baptisme, be he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed. <hi>But saith he, in</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Flanders <hi>the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hath bene practised: for prosse whereof, he sendeth vs to an other place of his booke, where no such thinge is founde, and neuer shall he showe vs to teach, that any Baptised by Protestants, with due matter, forme, and intention, ought to be baptised againe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag,</hi> 183. Christ hath satisfied <hi>(quoth he)</hi> and was offered only for Originall synne: an error of Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas. <hi>Nay rather, it is a most shamelesse vntruth of</hi> Thomas Rogers: <hi>no place doth he quote, and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qaile, when he knoweth not where to finde it, Is this the fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, this the sincerity &amp; conscience of the pretended preacher of the word? Yf the good Reader vouchsafe to reade</hi> S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas <hi>he shal find in him the cleane contrary doctrine, to <note place="margin">3. part. q. 49. art. 5.</note> witte, that we are by the passion of Christ, deliuered both from Originall and all actuall synne whatsoeuer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Pag. 198. <hi>He runneth vpon the Iesuits thus.</hi> The Iesuits
<pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>(quoth he)</hi> can not brooke Episcopall preheminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: and in their high court of reformation, haue made a lawe for the vtter abrogation of all Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall iurisdiction. <hi>A most notorious slaunder, as the whole world knoweth? They liue vnder Bishoppes, without any mislike of their dignity, nay with condemninge them of heresy, that teach otherwise, as is apparante in Cardinall</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Clericis cap. 14. Commēt. in 2. 2. disput. 10. quast. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1.</note> Bellarmin <hi>and</hi> Gregorius de Valentia. <hi>The booke which he quoteth I haue not seene, yet I make no doubt but the author is one of trust, some false brother or other. The thing it self is so false, as I maruaile he blusheth not to putt it in printe. That they haue made a lawe to abrogate Episcopall iurisdiction, is most ridiculoue: as though forsoth it were in their power to effect any such thinge, and as though they labour not both in word and writinge, for the vpholding of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity against disciplinarian Caluinists. The author he allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth for proffe is some Quodlibet arian minister, though poore VVat son beareth the name. So palpable an vntruth knowne to those that knowe any thinge, is sufficient, both to cassier the credit of those Quodlibets, and other like libellaticall pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plets, published vnder his name, and also deepely to touch the reputation of</hi> Mr. Rogers. <hi>True it is, that those religious and learned men to stoppe all suggestions of ambition, which hath bene the bane of many, haue a seuere constitution amongest themselues, ratified by vowe, that none shall not only not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure any Ecclesiasticall Prelacy, but also resist what he may, (reseruing due obedience to whom he is subiect) not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to any such dignity: yet may they when it shall seme so good to the Pastor of Gods Church, be promoted to prelacy: as that worthy mā</hi> Bellarmine <hi>was not only created Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but also made Archbishoppe of</hi> Capua. Mr. Rogers <hi>as I suppose, is not acquai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d with any such scrupulous nicenes, beinge more like of the twayne to haue made a vowe, that he</hi>
      <pb facs="18"/>
      <hi>will not refuse any Episcopall promotion if he can tell how to com by it.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag. 220. To bring our religion into extreame hatred, with all that be of contrary faith, he chargeth vs with this doctrine, viz,</hi> That faith is not to be kept with here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques. <hi>An odious slander and not only of</hi> Mr. Rogers, <hi>but commonly receiued amongest all Protestants. How doth he proue it? forsoth out of the Councell of</hi> Constance <hi>which he quoteth in the margent, but noteth not any particular place: which argueth false dealing, the Councell being passing longe. Gods Church assembled in that sacred Synode, is notoriously abused, and we dayly iniuried by the licentious pennes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testats. No such thing is in that Coūcel defined. And I desire no more, then that the good Reader will not giue</hi> Mr. Rogers <hi>or others creditte, before they truly bring forth in particular words, what they so confidently auouche in generall terms.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus haue I briefely by a sufficient iury of vntruths, conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> Mr. Rogers, <hi>of false dealinge, and most iniurious and godlesse proceedinge, against Catholike religion. To prosecute all, were a worke of more labour: for neuer was booke as I thinke, comming forth from such a one, of such a subiect, with that authority, and that carried outwardly so braue and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a showe, and inwardly was so vgly, foule, and deformed, to the infamy of the author, discredit of the booke, disgrace of their religion, and high commendation of our fayth, which standeth vpon so sure grounds, that it can not be impugned but by those meanes, by which the author of it Christ himself, was condemned to the shamefull and opprobrious death of the crosse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Being thus dispatched of</hi> Mr. Rogers: <hi>it remayneth to speake a word or two of another booke, which was not longe since sent me and is intitled.</hi> A briefe viewe of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke groundes of Popery, <hi>compiled together by one</hi>
      <pb facs="18"/> Mr. Vdall, <hi>a lay gentleman out of diuers Englishe Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertists, as himself semeth to insinuate, and in all probabilitie can not otherwise be thought, and so no maruaile, yf the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be not sounde, when they were drawen from corrupt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, &amp; who can euer looke for a wel shapen garment, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de after a crooked measure.</hi> Grapes are not gathered <note place="margin">Math. 8. v. 16.</note> of thornes, nor figges of thistles, <hi>as our Sauiour saith: yet doth it so much please</hi> Mr. Vdall, <hi>that he doth seeme to take great heart of grace, for that he was not answeared with that expedition he expected. The more hast he maketh, the more he vrgeth his owne disgrace, yf malice hath sette him a worke: but if it be true zeale of truth, and sauing his soule as he pretendeth, I despaire not of his conuersion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either for the spirituall profitt of himself, or the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of other, or common good of both, I will nowe present him with a short sample of suche soule flawes as be in his booke, minding afterward with more full hand to prosecute that subiect.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In his Preface to his deare Cousins, (whom with poyson lurking vnder sugred wordes he laboureth to inuenime) he accuseth vs of open blasphemie against the sacred scriptures: which I thinke wil rather proue a grosse vntruth on his parte and where is this blasphemy contayned? in a booke as he telleth vs of Cardinall</hi> Cusanus, <hi>which is intitled</hi> De authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of the authority of the Church &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, aboue and against the scriptures. <hi>But I besech him, did he euer see this booke, which so confidently he allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth: yf he hath, then should he haue done well to haue noted where, that the Reader also might haue found it, seing it is not amongest the three Tomes of his workes, sett out at</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sill, <note place="margin">In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eare 1565.</note>
      <hi>neither mentioned by</hi> Trithemius, <hi>who hath diligently gathered together, the workes of learned writers: nor yet by</hi> Posseuinus <hi>who hath lately entreated of the same matter.</hi>
      <pb facs="19"/>
      <hi>If he hath not: what indiscretion is it, in so waighty a pointe, to rely vpon the creditt of others. Veryly, would such as reade Protestants bookes, but vouchafe sometyme to examine the quotations, it were not possible that they could be so pittifully deceiued, as they dayly be:</hi> Cusanus <hi>is abused, he ueuer wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te any suche booke. This vntruth it may be he borrowed from</hi> Mr. Iewell, <hi>who doth not only cite that booke, but also (as</hi>
      <note place="margin">Det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ction lib. 5. pag. 410.</note>
      <hi>though he had knowne it very well) quote very many places out of the same, as he is charged by Doctor</hi> Hardinge: <hi>which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth that out of true bookes he could haue proued any thinge for himself, that out of one, which was neuer written, found so many testimonies to serue his turne. I would not wishe</hi> Mr. Vdall, <hi>to imploy his tyme so badly, as with the touch of his creditt, and perill of his owne soule, to retale the vntruths of such grosse merchants.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In his fourth page, thus he writeth.</hi> Yea Arias Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus a chief Papist, in his Hebrew bible, writeth in the forefromt and principall leaf of the booke, There are added (saith he) in this edition, the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes written in Greeke, which the Catholike Church following the Canon of the Hebrewes, reckoneth amongest the Apocrypha. <hi>The true sence of</hi> Arias Montanus <hi>words is corrupted, either by</hi> Mr. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, <hi>or some other from whom he had them, by foysting in diuers of their owne. That learned man in the edition of the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Antuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piae ex os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoph. Plant. 1584.</note>
      <hi>Hebrue Bible, with the latin interlineall interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the title page saith.</hi> There are adioyned to this edition, the bookes written in Greeke, which are called Apocrypha. <hi>He saith not, they be Apocrypha: but that they are so called by some, that is the Iewes, who exclude them from their Hebrue Canon which he had there sett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> forth. That other addition;</hi> viz which the Catholike Church following the Canon of the Hebrues
<pb facs="19"/> reckoneth amongest the (Apocrypha) <hi>vpon which the force of his charge dependeth, are not in</hi> Arias Montanus: <hi>where</hi> Mr. Vdall <hi>had them, himself best knoweth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In fift page he writeth thus.</hi> The Councell of Laodicea, assured by a generall Councell in Trul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo did sett downe the same Canon of the script urs <note place="margin">Can. 59.</note> which both the old Church had, and our Church houldeth: and commaundeth. Ne aliqui, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that none besides be read, and receiued in to authority. <hi>How many things of note, are comprised in these fewe lines against</hi> Mr. Vdall. <hi>First he seemeth greatly to reuerence these two Councels, which yet is but a copy of his countenance, to delude the ignorant Reader, for I doe not thinke that he will stande either to the one or the other, though content he is, to presse vs with their authority. For example, the Councell of</hi> Loadicea, <hi>commaundeth Chrisme to be receiued after</hi>
      <note place="margin">Can. 48. Can. 50.</note>
      <hi>Baptisme: and that the fast of lent be obserued: neither of which, I am sure, pleaseth</hi> Mr. Vdall. <hi>Likewise the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of</hi> Constantinople <hi>holden in</hi> Trullo <hi>alloweth of images, and their veneration, when it calleth them,</hi> imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes venerabiles: venerable images: <hi>which I make no doubt nothing pleaseth his tast. The same Councell forbiddeth</hi>
      <note place="margin">Can 82. Can. 6. Can. 58.</note>
      <hi>Bishoppes, Priests, Deacons, and Subdeacons, to marry wiues after taking of Orders: and commaundeth Bishoppes not to dwell with their wiues, which they marryed before they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the higher Orders of the Clergy: which seuerity of theirs must vtterly dislike him, as being in his opinion, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the word of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Secondly this Councell of</hi> Constantinople <hi>in</hi> Trullo <hi>is of no authority, as in which the Pope neither by him self, nor by his Legates, was present, and Pope</hi> Sergius, <hi>who then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. de sex aetatibus. in Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niano.</note>
      <hi>did disanulle that erraticall Synode, as venerable</hi> Bede <hi>writetht with what conscience then can</hi> Mr. Vdal <hi>call that</hi>
      <pb facs="20"/>
      <hi>agenerall Councell, and vrge the authority thereof as authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall: when as not only we, but also the Protestants vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect it, albeit in this point we for our parts see no cause to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse it. Thirdly true it is not, that the Councell of</hi> Laodicea, <hi>setteth downe the same Canon of the scriptures, which the Church of England alloweth: for the</hi> Apocalypse <hi>or Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> S. Iohn <hi>is omitted. Fourthly, this Councell forbiddeth the readinge of others, not there expressed: yet the Church of</hi> England <hi>readeth the histories of</hi> Iudith, <hi>and</hi> Toby <hi>in their publike assemblies: which</hi> Mr. Vdall <hi>I suppose, will har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly shewe, howe it agreeth with the decree of that Councell. Fiftly he hath corrupted the Councell by addinge somwhatof his owne: for these words:</hi> and receiued into authority <hi>be not there found. VVould any euer haue thought, that so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, could haue bene notedagainst him, in so small a sentence. If</hi> Mr. Vdall <hi>hath viewed the Originall, hardly can he be excused from malice: yf he hath not, let him beshrewe their fingers, vpon whose creditt, he committed them to writinge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the same fift page, he maketh vs to allowe the fourth booke of</hi> Esdras <hi>most vntruly, and that contrary to his owne knowledge, when as in the second page he confesseth, that we account both the third and fourth of</hi> Esdras <hi>for Apocrypha.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Page 51. To eneruat the force of generall Councels thus he writeth.</hi> Bellarmine reiecteth wholy seauen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib. 1. de Concil. cap. 6. and not lib. 10. cap. 60. as</hi> Mr. Vdal quoteth it.</note> Councels. <hi>That learned Prelate is iniuriousoy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, for who would not thinke, that</hi> Mr. Vdall <hi>spake of lawfull and true generall Councels, as though such were reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>which is nothing so: for he speaketh of certaine detestable conuenticles, assembled by the Arrians and other like perfidious heretikes which they called generall.</hi> Primum generale &amp;c. The first general Councell <hi>(saith</hi> Bellarmine) in the opinion of the Arrians
<pb facs="20"/> which is reiected, is the Councell of Antioch, &amp;c. <hi>Ys these be detested by Protestants also for vnlawfull and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, why is Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine <hi>singled out as though he alone refused them? or the matter so cunningly deliuered, as though they were reuerenced by</hi> Mr. Vdall <hi>and Protestants for lawfull generall Councels? This is not to deale sincerly, and to seeke truth with a pure and vpright heart, vnlesse he be so carelesse, as to receiue all vpon the report of others, which yet can not wholy be excused.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus much shall serue at this tyme, for by Gods asistance, I intend hereafter more to lay open the manifould maladies of his treatise, and to shewe with what weake engines he laboureth to vndermine the impregnable grounds of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Churche. God graunte that the happy newes of his conuersion, may crosse these my designements, wherof I see no cause to dispaire, if truly zeale of religion, and desire of saluation, which so much he would seme to thirst after, hath embouldened him being a lay man, to launch into the depth of these mysticall matters. Let him not rely too much vnto tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, from whō he receiueth the substāce of that he writeth, least together with the losse of his reputation, he incurre also the daunger of eternall damnation: and yf vpon this small war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he findeth himself to haue bene deceiued, wisdom would, he should more carefully looke how he trusteth, where he hath bene abused: &amp; with greater diligence both to examine his owne writers, and also to reade our, namely Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>where he shall finde the most of his obiections answeared, as the Catholique author of that letter, which he hath putte downe in his booke truly enformeth him. To which, that giueth no satisfaction, alleadged by</hi> Mr. Vdall <hi>for answeare, to witt, that</hi> Bellarmins <hi>reasons, are by the learned of his side sufficiently handled and replied vnto: when as the most of the arguments in his booke be answeared by</hi>
      <pb facs="21"/> Bellarmine <hi>and nothinge doe I finde brought by</hi> Mr. Vdal <hi>to insringe his solutions: which giueth me iust cause to suspect that he is with the preconceipted sincerity of his owne doctors, carryed away into error, and so looketh little into the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals: which if he did, he could not but finde that which he pretendeth to seeke for, if he shutte not his eies against the truth, as he professeth he will not. VVhich that he may doe, I shall not forgett to cōmend him to his mercy, who desireth not the death of a sinner, but that all should com to the knowledg of his name. But yf it shall sal out, that he will stil proceede for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his fourmer course, yet I would wishe him in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, to abstayne from all biting and bitter words, which somtyme he breaketh into, that the quarrell of God may not he prosecuted like the quarrels of this world; but with that modesty, which becometh the prosessors of diuinity and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And for my part sory I am, that Bell hath so far giuen the raynes to his passion, as with such virulent termes, and insup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable insolency, to cast forth his gantlet of defiance, and to insult against the whole Church of God, which hath made my stile before in the Preface, more stirring and quicke, then otherwise I would or thought conuenient, least we might be condemned of cowardize or seare, (to the preiudice of truth) which so often, and so opprobriously he obiecteth against vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus much of these matters: now it remaineth to encounter Bell, and to examin, and make triall, what substantiall stuffe is contayned in his</hi> Triall of the newe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>B. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>