<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND worthilie regarded, Sir RO∣BERT CHICHESTER, Knight of the noble Order of the BATH, &amp;c. increase of all grace and true happi∣nesse heere, and the blessednesse of immortality hereafter.</title>
           <author>Carpenter, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125294_Fr4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73706</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4683.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125294</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND worthilie regarded, Sir RO∣BERT CHICHESTER, Knight of the noble Order of the BATH, &amp;c. increase of all grace and true happi∣nesse heere, and the blessednesse of immortality hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three profitable sermons. 1. A pastorall charge. 2. Christs Larum-bell. 3. The soules sentinell : Preached at seuerall times vpon sundry occasions, by Richard Carpenter pastor of Sherwill in Devon</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Constable, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 71, 9, 66, 8, 112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="79"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND worthilie regarded, Sir RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT CHICHESTER, <hi>Knight of</hi> the noble Order of the BATH, &amp;c. <hi>increase of all grace and true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      </hi>nesse heere, and the blessednesse of immortality hereafter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, Beeing often sollicited by the earnest entreaty of men of no meane quality, to publish these slender fruits of some few daies labour, and to let them passe to the eie of this censori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous world, as things in their iudgement worthy longer life, then to fade with the houre or two, to which they were desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated: I haue at length after
<pb facs="80"/> much reluctancie, yeelded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to satisfie their importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, addressing my selfe with the more alacritie to the businesse, because I saw oportunity of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered thereby, to let the world see, how I reuerence your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, regard your place, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly desire to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like acknowledgement of my bounden seruice to you, for all such beneficiall fauours as haue bin at any time vouchsafed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, in that place and calling wherein by Gods grace I stand Sentinell, for the soule-sauing good of you and many others I hope, whom the Lord of grace hath ordained to glory: beeing in duty and conscience obliged, so farre as the nature of my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisteriall functiō shall guide me, and the power of my poore abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity can reach, to returne vnto you the interest of spiritual bles
<pb facs="80"/> sings &amp; the comforts of a better life eternall, in lieu of such cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefits as vnder Gods prouidence, &amp; your patronage, I do enioy, for the maintenance of this fraile life temporall.</p>
   <p>As a pledge of which duty, I doe here humbly present vnto your eies that funerall sermon, which lately you heard with your eares, presuming that by your fauorable acceptance and benigne countenance, you will giue vnto the same a kind of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond life, especially, because it was penned &amp; preached vpon the occasion of your much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed friends death, &amp; at the solemnising of his buriall. In the which if there bee any sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of instruction, rule of dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, example of religious reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, whereof your christian wisdom (according to the preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of your wit &amp; apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion)
<pb facs="81"/> shall make a conscionable and comfortable vse, to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of your saluation; the matter &amp; occasiō of my thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing to God, for his blessing on my poore labours shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by greatly be enlarged, and my respectfull readines, vpon your encouragement to vndergo the like employment, shalbe much augmented. Thus humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching your Worship to rest assured, that (how weake and meane soeuer my counsels and endeauours bee) my vowes and praiers (for your truest happines and honour, and your vertuous and worthily honoured Ladies greatest welfare) are, and shalbe euer, most powerfull and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, I rest alwaies prest, to be proued your Worships, in all</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Christian obseruancy truly deuoted, RICH. CARPENTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>