<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the most high and mightie Princesse, Eliza∣beth by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland: defen∣dresse of the true, auncient, Catho∣lique, and Apostolique faith. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125490_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72855</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17122.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125490</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the most high and mightie Princesse, Eliza∣beth by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland: defen∣dresse of the true, auncient, Catho∣lique, and Apostolique faith. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The light of Britayne. A recorde of the honorable originall &amp; antiquitie of Britaine</title>
                 <author>Lyte, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, illustrations, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To the most high and mightie Princesse, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland: defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse of the true, auncient, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and Apostolique faith. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST dread soueraigne Ladie Elizabeth, by the grace of God: The Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix of the worlde: The Angell of Englande: The bright Britona of Britayne: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Britomartis President of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: The chast Diana of Calydonia sylua Britanniae, <hi>terror syluestry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus apris:</hi> The most noble Lyonesse Atalanta: that keepeth Calydonia sylua Britanniae: from Romish wolues and Foxes: And from the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian wilde Boare figured by the wilde Boare of Calydon that was chased:
<pb facs="4"/>
hunted: and firste wounded by the chaste Maiden Atalanta, a figure (as J take it) of your maiestie, that hath wounded the wilde Boare, that raunged ouer all Calydonia sylua Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanniae, and spoiled the principall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the fruitfull vines of Calydonia sylua: and the fruitfull trees of Æto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, euen at Parth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>n the principall towne of Ætolia, now called Atholl, in Britannia secunda.</p>
   <p>To your most excellent maiestie, whom I doubt not but our Meleager (euen Iesus Christe the righteous) when he hath cut off the head of that monstrous wilde Boare, shall at last take you to his spouse: and encrese your ioy with an eternall Diademe, and crowne of glorie. To your Maiestie: to your grace: <hi>O Diua potens Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabetha:</hi> my deere and dreade Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne: whom this day I doe beholde and see, (after diuers dangers &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles past, to the great ioy and comfort and to the good example of all your Subiects) to come to the Church and house of God amongst his Saints in the
<pb facs="4"/>
congregation: to giue all the honour and glorie vnto God: and in the zeale of a most Christian Prince, to offer your selfe, and Scepter, a liuely sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lorde God of Hostes, who hath wrought wonders in your daies, by deliuering you his handmaiden and your faithfull Subiects (his people of Britayne) from the handes of your and our cruell enemies. To you I am come with this small offering, for lack of a better, <hi>(The light of Britayne)</hi> my fealtie and bounden duety to your most excellent maiestie, and my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Country, whom I pray GOD al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to blesse in his mercy, &amp; graunt your maiestie, alwaies to tryumphe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all your enemies, and to raigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs for euer, if it be his blessed will.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble and faithfull Subiect. Henry Lite, of Lytescarie.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>