<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface touch∣ing the Christian Combate or Af∣fliction.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125927_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B01212</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7316</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125927</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface touch∣ing the Christian Combate or Af∣fliction.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian combate, or, A treatise of afflictions : with a prayer and meditation of the faithfull soule, and a sermon vpon the 50. Psal. vers. 15. By Master Peter Du Moulin, minister of the word of God, and professor of diuinity, in the Vniuersity of Sedan. Faithfully translated into English by Iohn Bulteel, minister of the word of God, in the French church of Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 326, 10 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <head>The Preface touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Christian Combate or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>AS Peace is a thing to be desired: so the Prince that will long enioy it, ought to be prepared for warre. The like is of the Church of God, whose prosperity we ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and pray for the peace of Ierusalem; but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the dayes of prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wee are to be alwayes prepared for aduersity; for seeing that God afflicteth his children to amend
<pb facs="18"/>them, the right way to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew affliction, is to better our selues before wee be strucken, and preuent his chastisements by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
   <p>And if by reason of the sinnes of a part of the flock, it pleaseth God to visit his Church with his rods; they who by continuall prayers, by the contempt of the world, by the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Gods Word, by the exercise of good workes, haue kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues ready for the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to come, will haue this aduantage aboue the rest, that they will haue the plaster ready before the blow, and shall not be asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished as at a thing not expected; for affliction
<pb facs="18"/>beats downe onely those whom it surprizeth, and none is ouercome by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity, but hee that hath beene corrupted or lulled asleepe by prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
   <p>Seeing then that it hath pleased God, whose coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels are vnsearchable, and iudgement righteous, and whose hand is vnauoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to send vs dayes of weeping and of lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to scatter in his anger those flockes, which he had gathered together in his mercy; it is our part now to apply the remedies, wherewith euery one fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, ought to haue beene prouided before the euill happened; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fitly applied, will serue
<pb facs="19"/>to make the afflictions not onely lighter, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so profitable, and to extract sweetnesse out of bitternesse, as <hi>Sampson</hi> did, and make that the euill themselues become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.</p>
   <p>An enterprize truely full of difficulty, and which Philosophy neuer vndertooke without rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and hath nener ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted himselfe without deceit; for in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wee haue it selfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to it; and wee are contradicted by humane iudgement, and vulgar opinion.</p>
   <p>The condition of the faithfull is like vnto that of the Planets, that mooue themselues against
<pb facs="19"/>the course of the world; and to the nature of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fishes, that swim al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes against the streame, and tend towards the spring; for wee are called to goe against the current of customes, and of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like opinions, that wee may tend vnto the spring of life, which is with God: Whose counsels march contrarie to our thoughts; to whom the wisdome of man is meere blindnesse; who from the beginning of the world, hauing drawne the Light out of darkenesse, hath not since ceased to draw good out of euill, and his glory from ignominy it selfe.</p>
   <p>But before wee come to set open to the view, these
<pb facs="20"/>spirituall comforts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, it is necessary to discerne in a Christian man these two conditions; the one, whereby hee is a man, the other, whereby hee is a Christian, that wee may discerne the euils that doe befall him as hee is a man, and subiect to the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities with other men, from those that befall him as hee is a Christian, and for the profession of the Gospell; for according to the diuersitie of these euils, we must apply the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>