<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE MISTRESSE Mrs ANNE CARIE DAVGHTER TO THE LORD VICOVN OF FAVKLAND.</title>
           <author>T., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125237_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72216</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12350.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125237</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE MISTRESSE Mrs ANNE CARIE DAVGHTER TO THE LORD VICOVN OF FAVKLAND.</title>
                 <author>T., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second booke of the dialogues of S. Gregorie the Greate : the first pope of that name containinge the life and miracles of our Holie father S. Benedict. To which is adioined the Rule of the same holie patriarche translated into the Englishe tonge by C.F. priest &amp; monk of the same order</title>
                 <author>Gregory, I., pope</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 108, 6, 130, 14, 62 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE MISTRESSE M<seg rend="sup">rs</seg> ANNE CARIE DAVGHTER TO THE LORD VICOVN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> OF FAVKLAND.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ISTRESSE CARIE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Since my first zeale of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge this worke I haue had two notable obiections: the first because I could not vse means more effectuall to discouer my owne vnworthines: the other
<pb facs="4"/> (if in the Epistle Dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which was left to mee) I should speake of your worth and vertue, accordinge to my owne conscience, to them whoe know you not I should be thought extreamlie to flatter; to that them that know you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious or ignorant. These are the reasons which staied the printinge of it, &amp; caused mee to seeke to ingage some in the makinge of an Epistle, whoe by reason of the are neerenes to you, might seeme to some to be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from it, but to mee most fitt, thinkinge noe other worthie to commende you. Hee that trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb facs="4"/> part of it (whoe I am sure hath a prime place in your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie) intended it to you, but since death preuēted him from doinge this (though I hope it hath ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleled him to doe you better ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice by prayinge for you &amp; all your familie in heauen) I haue taken vpon mee to supplie his place in finishinge &amp; dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge this to you. Our holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther S. Benedict whose Rule in our time hath neuer bene wholie translated in to the English tonge, deserues a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerēt respect from all the world, but especially from English men, since his children cannot
<pb facs="5"/> be denied the honor of conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge this country to the faith of Christ. And for this present of S. Benedicts to my country, part of the obligation is due to you for whom it was principallie done. God blesse you with perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerāce in those giftes hee hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon you, and to that end hee shall be often solicited by.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your deuoted beadsman. B. E. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>