<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Worshipfull Maister Benedic Barnam, Esquire, Al∣derman and Sheriffe of this honorable Citty of London: health and happinesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125749_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07987</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19974.6</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Worshipfull Maister Benedic Barnam, Esquire, Al∣derman and Sheriffe of this honorable Citty of London: health and happinesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Axiochus. A most excellent dialogue, written in Greeke by Plato the phylosopher : concerning the shortnesse and vncertainty of this life, with the contrary ends of the good and wicked. Translated out of Greeke by Edw. Spenser. Heereto is annexed a sweet speech or oration, spoken at the tryumphe at White-hall before her Maiestie, by the page to the right noble Earle of Oxenforde</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Worshipfull Maister <hi>Benedic Barnam,</hi> Esquire, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman and Sheriffe of this honorable Citty of London: health and happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipfull Sir, I am bold (by way of dedication) to giue yee this excellent Dialogue of <hi>Plato</hi> the Phylosopher, for two reasons. The first, that so singuler a worke, doone by a Heathen man, might as wel flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish in our vulgare speech, as of long time it hath doone both in Greeke and Latine.</p>
   <p>The seconde, that your counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce might shaddowe it from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochefull slaunders, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon censures too lightly bolt out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the best endeuours. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="3"/> the speciall matter, to wit, my presumption, without first acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting yee heere-with: thus I protect my selfe. My familiarity with yee in your younger yeeres, when some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wee were Schollers together, and my present ioy, to see ye so hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie a succeeder both in your Fathers vertues, place, and Office: imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee to shew a remembrance of the one, yet reuerently, and gladnes of the other as well becommeth me.</p>
   <p>If in thys small gift, ye make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance both of the one and other, yee shall declare no lesse then each one well discernes in ye, and ioy him that euery way is at your cōmaund.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>