<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE describing the Glori∣ous estate of the Saints on earth and the true Nature, and Right vse of Prayer. To the excellent that are on earth, all things pertaining to life and glo∣ry through the spirit of Grace and Supplication.</title>
           <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125308_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73805</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6690</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE describing the Glori∣ous estate of the Saints on earth and the true Nature, and Right vse of Prayer. To the excellent that are on earth, all things pertaining to life and glo∣ry through the spirit of Grace and Supplication.</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mr. Edward Dering, his godly priuate prayers for Christian families : Whereunto is annexed, his briefe and necessary catechisme for housholders</title>
                 <author>Dering, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, Alice.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 55, 3, 57-157, 180-475, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A PREFACE describing the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>estate of the Saints on earth</hi> and the true Nature, <hi>and Right vse of Prayer.</hi> To the excellent that are on earth, all things pertaining to life and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry through the spirit of Grace and Supplication.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Beloued in the Lord Iesus,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the loue of God hath heerein exceedingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded vnto vs, that we are called the Sons of God;
<pb facs="3"/> so there is not a more pregnant Embleme of our Adoption to be his Children, then that wee cry Abba, Father; nor a more liuely pledge of our loue vnto God, then that we doe cast our selues into the armes of his mercy, by faithfull prayer. Oh how much better is it to bee a doore-keeper in the House of God, then to sit on the Throne with Princes? How exceeding were the riches of Gods mercie towards vs, that spared not his onely Sonne vnto death, to restore vs from death, to life? That the Lord of Glory became a Seruant vnto all, that hee might redeeme vs from the bondage of sinne, into tbe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the Sonnes of God? That life it selfe became death, that hee might deliuer vs from death vnto life: That
<pb facs="3"/> he that knew no sinne, but was perfect holinesse it selfe, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came sinne for our sakes, that we might be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of God in him. Surely, if <hi>Dauid</hi> thought it an high aduancement to bee the sonne in law to an earthly &amp; wicked King, How much more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is our aduancement, that we are become the adopted sons of the Almighty, and Holyest God, who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords? And if the Queene of Saba counted the seruants of <hi>Salomon</hi> happie, because they enioyed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and were partakers of the worldly and fading Comforts as abounded in his Court: Oh how much more happie is the condition of the Saints of God that do not only enioy the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious presence of God with open
<pb facs="4"/> face, in whose fauour is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, but are thereby tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into the same image, frō glory to glory, as by the Spirit of GOD, that so they may bee made meete partakers of that glorious inheritance with the Saints in light; euen that light which is immortall and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, which fadeth not? If to be rich in faith &amp; good workes be the true and dureable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure which fayleth not; If the ioy of the Spirit be that which none can take away from vs; If all earthly honor be as dung in comparison of that inward glory wherewith the Kinges daughter is adorned; If theyr safety be impregnable, which haue a wall of fire to beguirt them, &amp; therein walking most secure that haue the Lord of Hosts to protect &amp; guide them;
<pb facs="4"/> then happy surely, and thrice happy is the condition of Gods Children, who haue God to bee their Portion, and may enioy durable riches, pure and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Comfort, honor that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fadeth, and security with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out securitie. For as our secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in God makes vs watchful ouer our owne waies, and iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of our owne inability, so heereby are we daily cast vpon the riches of Christ, and from him encrease and grow in grace. And as we grow in grace so do we attaine to, and prosper more and more in peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and thereby abound with ioy in the holy Ghost. And the more we are filled with ioy and peace in beleeuing, the more do we glorify our God in cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience, and so as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are more intirely interes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="5"/> in the glorie of our head, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching heereby neerer to the life of Glory, the more wee tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer all our oppositions, and are more throughly abased and excluded of all glorying in our selues, that so dooing all things to the glory of our God, we may be aduanced by him in abasing our sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, and weaned from all carnall &amp; fading glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that we may bee fitted for the glory of the life to come. And what can now hinder vs heerefrom, whereto all things shall further? No trouble can do it, seeing it prepares thereto: No, not sinne shall hinder, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is not imputed; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther auailes to the imputation of righteousnesse, that so the sting of sinne may be remoued. It is not life can doe it, because we are dead vnto sinne; neither
<pb facs="5"/> shall death auaile hereunto, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are aliue vnto GOD. Much lesse may Angels hinder, because they are ministring spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits for our good, to keepe vs in all our waies: Nor Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties can preuaile, because the Kingdomes are the Lords, and so ouerseers to the Saints: It is not powers shall hinder, seeing all power is giuen to our Head; and so in him we are able to doe all things: Neither things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent should ought auaile hereto, because we liue by Faith, &amp; not by sight, and so can lay vp a good Foundation by them ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inst the life to come. Neither shall things to come hinder vs, which are alreadie ours by Faith, whereby wee apprehend them, though yet we enioy them not, and so in patience wait for them; and so by continuance in
<pb facs="6"/> wel-doing, make ready for thē. And how shal height hinder vs who haue the Highest to bee our hope, whom lowlinesse aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, and highnesse abaseth? Can depth preuent vs, vvhen our Head is aboue water, nay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the highest Heauens, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will draw vs vp all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, out of the deepest snares? No, no, it is not hell can hinder vs seeing it is destroyed, nor Satan shall preuaile, for see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we haue the shield of Faith to resist him, hee will flye from vs</p>
   <p>Behold the wonderfull and glorious priuiledges of the sons of God! And by this wee know, that we haue this glorious vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fellowship with God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by his Spirit that hee hath giuen vs. And hereby we know effectually, that the Spirit
<pb facs="6"/> dwelleth in vs euen by this bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed libertie and boldnes in pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to the throne of Grace, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abba, Father, with all Son-like importunity; and challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his promise in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. Thus by the Spirit, wee know our Adoption, and by the Spirit of Prayer, we pleade the same. And can we be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when the Spirite helpes our Infirmities, and knovves our Wants? Shall wee not preuaile aboue whatsoeuer wee can aske or thinke, seeing our Sauiour is our Aduocate to make interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for vs, who knowes what is best for vs, who heares before we aske, and askes that we may be heard?</p>
   <p>Behold here the ground and necessitie of Prayer. If the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit be in vs, we shall pray in the Spirit; and if we pray in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie
<pb facs="7"/> of the Spirit, wee are set at liberty thereby, euen the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the Sonnes of GOD. Onely be we wise to try the Spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit by the Spirit, that so vvee may not offer the sacrifice of Fooles.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> It is the Spirit of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and so wee must pray in knowledge.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> It is the Spirit of Christ that is in vs, and so wee must pray in the Name of Christ by the Spirit.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> It is the Spirit of Faith, and so wee must pray in Faith without doubting.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> And it is the Spirit of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and so we must waite in Prayer.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> It is the Spirit of Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, teaching vs what to pray for, &amp; so we must pray in wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for such things as be most
<pb facs="7"/> soueraigne and necessary. For spirituall graces absolutely, for temporall with condition.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6</hi> It is the Spirit of Humi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lity, teaching vs to denie our owne wisedome, and not rest in our owne righteousnesse, and so to submit to the will of God, as not to faint in our labour, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we faile in our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar desire.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7</hi> It is the Spirit of Perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and so we must pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and perseuere therein with all thankfulnesse.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8</hi> It is a quickning &amp; powr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Spirit, working mightily in vs, and so wee must pray in all zeale and feruency of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, because if they bee feruent, they shall preuaile.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <hi>9.</hi> It is the holy and blessed Spirit, and therefore whosoeuer calleth on the name of the Lord
<pb facs="8"/> must depart from Iniquity; if we regard iniquity in our harts the Lord will not heare our prayers.</p>
   <p>Thus may we pray in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Neither may such prescript forme of Prayer preiudice or stint the same. But we must be carefull of the sense of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular wants, and apprehension of Gods fauour in Iesus Christ, to powre out our hearts vnto our GOD, who is onely priuy hereunto, and loueth trueth in the inward parts: so shall the words of our mouths be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto him, whether wee speake by the mediate direction of holy men, who are inspired by the holy Ghost, or immediately by the inspiration of the holie and blessed Spirit.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1</hi> Being wise in either to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd formality, customaries, &amp;
<pb facs="8"/> superstition, as if the thing how soeuer done, would preuaile.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> Labouring still to quicken vppe our hearts in the loue of Christ, that so we may continue with all patience and perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance therein.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3</hi> Vsing carefully to search and prepare our hearts, vvhen we come before the Lord.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4</hi> Preparing our hearts by holy Meditation of the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, power, and goodnes of God, to quicken our faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found carnall Wisedome.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5</hi> Renewing our Vowes and Couenants with the Lord, when soeuer wee looke to speede well from him.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6</hi> And yet not building any further in the issue vppon our God, then may stand vvith his good pleasure for our cheefest good in his Time and Manner,
<pb facs="9"/> which shall be fittest for vs.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7</hi> Comforting our selues ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the sense of that diuine assistance, quickening our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, and continuing powre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully therein, then in any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent sensible issue concerning our selues: that still wee may haue to reioyce in our God, and not in our selues.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8</hi> And so quieting our harts that we haue done the vvill of our GOD, that the vvill of God may bee done in vs, to the satisfying of our best desires in that manner and measure, as best pleaseth him for our maine and principall good. Thus may we preuaile in Prayer.</p>
   <p>And to this end mayest thou make vse of these helpes, rather as Directions to informe thee aright in the matter and order of Prayer; thē any strict bounds
<pb facs="9"/> to confine thee to the letter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Wishing thee in the feare of God, so to make vse thereof, as to make them rather meanes to stir vp the Spirit in thee, then to stint or prescribe the same. Which thou shalt do, if that thou dost seriously meditate on each particular Model before thou vse the same to informe thine vnderstanding, &amp; kindle thine affections to the loue therof: &amp; then so vse the Forme as not to rest heerein, but rather to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it as a patterne for thy better direction in the like, and so to sample it as neere as thou maist, or rather euen to put life vnto it, and better the same.</p>
   <p>And so the Lord giue thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in all things, in whom I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Tho: Cooper.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>