<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the good Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125530_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73178</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22816</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125530</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the good Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bouclier of the catholike fayth of Christes church : conteynyng diuers matters now of late called into controuersy, by the newe gospellers. Made by Richard Smith, doctour of diuinitee, [and] the Quenes hyghnes reader of the same I her graces vniuersite of oxford</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 80 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To the good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Remēbrīg good Reader, how the people of this our countrey are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned in theyr soules, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> new preachers euil sermons, and wicked bookes, and that as yet few bookes haue been set foorth for the confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of them, to reduce the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto the catholike fayth, dyd thynke it my duetie to trauayle and labour, therī, especially seyng euery man must make a straite accompt &amp; reckonyng to Christ at domes daye for his talentes, and giftes receiued <note place="margin">Mat: xxv.</note> of god. When he that hath encreased
<pb facs="7"/> those giftes by godly vsyng of them <note place="margin">Roma. ii.</note> shall receiue a reward of god accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to his doynges, and he whiche hath not so done, shall bee punished therfore. The whiche thinges, with other moe, moued me to write, and set foorth this traicte for the defence of the truth, not to enstruct the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Diuinitie, whiche nede not much my teachyng, but to teach the vnlearned, to stay and establish the waueryng, to assure and certify the doubtfull of the trouth, to bryng thē agayne vnto the trouth of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like churche, whiche were disceaued through ignoraunce, and are willīg to learne, and embrace the veritye, gladlye refusyng the faulsitie, and vntrouth, and to confounde the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and obstinate defendours, &amp; folowers of heresy. Seke here good
<pb facs="8"/> Reader, no eloquēce, which serueth (as Lactance sayth) the worlde, and <note place="margin">Lactātius Euse bius. lib. 3. ca. 24. hist. ecclesi. De doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, it.</note> which the simple trouth nedeth not, but the trouth playnely and rudelye taught for the edifying of the symple and rude people. For what auaileth (as Sainct Augustine sayth) a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den keye, if it cannot open the locke, which I woulde haue opened? And what matier is it, if the key be made of woode, so it can open my locke? Euen so what profiteth the speakers teachers, or writers eloquence, yfit open not the doore, or locke of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures vnto the people? Also what hurteth his rude speaking and playne grosse manier of preachyng, teachyng, or wrytyng, yf he thereby do open the Scriptures to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for theyr instruccion.</p>
   <p>Sayde not Sayncte Paule,
<pb facs="8"/> that he came not to preache in wyse, eloquente, Rhethorike woordes, least therby hys preachyng of Christ <note place="margin">i. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. ii</note> and hys death, should be voyd, and of none effecte.</p>
   <p>Why then shoulde I (yf I could as well as any other manne can) vse paynted termes, sekyng thereby the vayn prayse of menne, edifying not the people, and loosyng my reward of God? Wherfore I wyll be playne and vse no eloquence at all, heartily <note place="margin">Math. vi.</note> desyryng thee good Reader, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my endeuour, and traueile takē in this enterprise, to amend y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fautes if thou findest any, in this traict, and eyther to vse the same my labours, with thankes geuyng to god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from whom all goodnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <note place="margin">Iacobi. i.</note>) as s. Iames witnesseth, or els to setfoorth something better of thy own study.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p> More I beseche euery man, whiche shall reade this my booke, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally all them that are yet of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belyefe, than I teache herein, to reade this treatise, &amp; other my bokes nowe printed, &amp; which shalbe short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set foorth in print, without al cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted affeccion, and then I doubt nothyng, but they shall bee edyfyed therby. For I dooe teache nothyng, in this my booke, but onely the faith and trouth of the catholyke churche, whiche erreth not therin, as the fyrst <note place="margin">Mat. xvi &amp; vlt. Cōsiliū Nicenū. c. 9</note> generall counsayle, holden at Nicea about a thousand two hūdred yeres passed, witnesseth, saying: <hi>Quod irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensibile est, catholica defendit ecclesia,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The catholike church defendeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thīg, which is not reprouable. And <note place="margin">To. ii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pist ex viii. ad Ianuarum</note> s. Austē sayth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the catholike church doth not approue nor kepe in silence,
<pb facs="9"/> nor doe any thyng against the faith or good lyfe. Wherfore let thē, which are gone out of this church, willīgly deuidyng themselues from the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of it, retourne home agayne to her, theyr louyng mother, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geatyng that as no manne nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whyche was out of Noes ship in the tyme of the floude, eschaped <note place="margin">Ciprian.</note> death, euen so no manne, nor womā <note place="margin">Austen.</note> whych is out of thys Saincte Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters shippe, the catholike Churche, as a Schismatike, can be saued frō the peryll of that death both of body <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> and soule, whyche shall neuer haue ende, because Christ is (as Sainct Paule sayeth) the sauiour of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, <note place="margin">Ephesia. v.</note> whiche is the Churche, and he is made the cause meritorious of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastyng <note place="margin">Hebrues. v</note> saluacion onely to al thē (as he witnesseth also) that obey him
<pb facs="10"/> whiche commaundeth vs to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto hys spouse the Churche, <note place="margin">Math. xviii.</note> S. Ciprian a great goodly clarke, and a blessed Martyr, whyche was about. M. CCC. yeares passed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth <note place="margin">Lib. i. epi. 3.</note> playnly the cause of heresies schismes, diuisions in religion, and of the contempt of the cleargye, and of Priestes, when he wryteth thus. <note place="margin">Heresies, schismes, &amp; cōtempt of priestes; doe rise of that onelye, that there is not one head Priest, and iudge obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the church of Christ, as his vicaire.</note>
      <hi>Ne que aliunde haereses, aborte sunt, aut nata sunt schismata nisi inde quod sacerdoti dei non obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratur, nec vinis in ecclesia ad tempussacerdos, et ad tempus iudex, vice christi cogitatur: cui si secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum magisteria obtemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>raret fraternitas vniuersa nemo aduersus sacerdotum collegium quidquam moueret.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Heresyes (sayeth Cyprian) are rysen vp, or schismes sprong of no o-other thyng, but therof that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pryest of god (he ment the Pope) is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, and that there is not for the tyme one priest &amp; one iudge thought vpon, or esteamed, in the churche, as
<pb facs="10"/> Christes vicaire. Vnto whom if the whole brotherhoode, that is to saye, all christians, woulde accordyng to <note place="margin">Note thys wel.</note> the Maysters teachynges obey, no mā should moue any thyng against the college or company of Priestes. <note place="margin">I wil short<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly write of this matter at large by gods grace</note>
   </p>
   <p>Is not thys manifestly spoken of this auncyent Martir, to declare &amp; setforth the cause of deuisions in our fayth, of heresies, and despysyng of priestes? Haue we not founde thys his godly saying most true nowe of late in this our coūtrey? But I lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng thys mattier vntyll an other tyme, dooe exhorte all men, that are deuided from thys catholike church and the generall heade of it, for the loue of Iesus Christ, which shedde his precious bloude for them, vs, &amp; for all the world (as Sainct Paule and Sainct Iohn dooe testifye) to <note place="margin">i. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mo. ii. i. Iohn. ii.</note>
      <pb facs="11"/> come again vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnity of thē both, &amp; forsakyng al their errours, and all opinions, to receiue the trouth again obeying euer the kinges highnes, sēt hyther of god for the wealth of thys realme, and the Quenes grace, the chosen and elected of God, to bryng vs again vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd vnitye &amp; vnto grace &amp; godlines, which was of late wonderfully decayed amongst vs. <note place="margin">Geus abs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que consilio est, et sine prudentia, vtinam, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rit, et ī<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telligerēt, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouissima {pro}<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viderent. Deute. 32.</note> For if they styl abyding in their blid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; errors obstinately, will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey gods trouth, &amp; our most noble &amp; godly king, &amp; vertuous Quene, let thē nothing doubt, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> god will be auēged vpō thē, as he hath alreadye vpon some of their graund captains for theyr euyll religion &amp; malicious disobedience against our souereigne Lady, &amp; very ryght enheriter of this realme, &amp; wil be vpō the rest of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sort
<pb facs="11"/> if they be not obedient vnto hī, &amp; her yea although that her hyghnes vsed neuer so great piety, and clemencye towardes them, willyng thereby to win thē. For what vengeaunce toke <note place="margin">Nume. xvi.</note> god vpon Chore, Dathan, &amp; Abirō, for their rebellion against his seruāt Moses? Dyd not the earth opē, and swalowed thē vp? Wer not their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herentes, that toke parte with them, all brent with fyer? Why wyl not mē remember this historye, and such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <note place="margin">Roma. xv</note> wrytten in the scryptures (as all other thynges are) for theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struccion? Why read they not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of England, that they maye learne, that rebellion neuer came to good ende? Why remember they not that all rebellions of our age &amp; tyme whatsoeuer cause they haue preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue for to rebell, came to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion?
<pb facs="12"/> will men bee so blynded, that nothyng can make them see the daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of rebellion? who is so ignoraūt, but he knoweth, that Sainct Paul, and Saincte Peter commaundeth <note place="margin">Roma. xiii. Titus. iii. 1. Petri. ii.</note> vs to obey our Kyng, Quene, and the higher powers, vnder them, and that (as Sainct Paule wylleth) not onely for to auoide temporal punish<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente, <note place="margin">Roma. xiii.</note> but also for oure conscyence sake. Dyd our new ghospellers fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thys commaundemente, when they conspyred and rebelled agaynst our kyng and Quene, yea agaynste <note place="margin">Proue. viii.</note> god hymselfe, of whō thei haue theyr authoritie, &amp; by whom they raygne? God hytherto hath been y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Quenes hyghnes bouclier, and mightye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour agaynst all her enemyes, &amp; wyll bee, whyles she lyueth in thys worlde.</p>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <p> Wherfore I say once agayne let no man resyste her hyghnes procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges, nay gods proceadinges ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the catholyke Churches, least they win nothyng els thereby, than extreame misery, &amp; theyr vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most vndoyng, as many haue done, afore thys time, wherof they are not ignorant. For there is no counsel, no policy, nor wisdō) as Salomō saith) <note place="margin">Prouer. xxi</note> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> can anithing preuaile against our lord. The which hath by his especial goodnes toward her grace, and this whole realme, geuen to her highnes grace to conceiue a childe, wherfore it is euery true &amp; faythfull subiectes bounden duety, heartily to geue him thankes, to reioice, and be glad ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and deuoutely to praye nyghte and day vnto hym, that as she hath conceiued by his singuler grace, euē
<pb facs="13"/> so he would ayde, and strengthē her, highnes in her birth, as he dyd Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Abrahams wife, Rachel, Isaacs <note place="margin">Gene. xxi. Gene, xxx i. regum. ii. Luce. i.</note> wife, Anna Helchanaes wife, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beth zacharies wife, mother of sainct Iohn Baptist, with diuers others, verye aged women, that she maye easily without greate payne, and al dauger of her life, bring forth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> her child into this world, &amp; that it maye long lyue here amongest vs, &amp; raygne ouer vs, quietelye in much {pro}sperity, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to gods glory, vnto whō bee all praise for euen.</p>
   <p>AMEN.</p>
   <p>¶ The second boke shalbe pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted shortely by gods grace,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>