<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The occasion of the loue betwene Elissa the Quene of Cartage, after called Dido, and the Troian lord Aeneas, briefely gathered out of Virgyll.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125720_Bo2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08192</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24810a.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125720</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The occasion of the loue betwene Elissa the Quene of Cartage, after called Dido, and the Troian lord Aeneas, briefely gathered out of Virgyll.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fourth boke of Virgill, intreating of the loue betwene Aeneas &amp; Dido, translated into English, and drawne into a strau [n] ge metre by Henry late Earle of Surrey, worthy to be embraced</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Awen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The occasion of the loue betwene Elissa the Quene of Cartage, after called Dido, and the Troian lord Aeneas, briefely gathered out of Virgyll.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Eneas a man of great prowes, and one that had the Gods, his parentes and coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey in muche reuerence and loue, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed wyth cruel Iunos wrathe, in see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Italy, roued vpon the seas of Sicil, tyl after much tossyng, at the last he arry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the coastes of Libia: not knowyng the same what countrey it was. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng with hym hys assured companyon Achates, he learned by hys mother, that the Lady Elissa was Queue thereof. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, conneighed vnder acloude he came to the cytye of Cartage, where the Quene was resident: and there meeting with others of his compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye, who by the lyke fortune were dryuen into the same costes, he was of the bountiful Quene receiued with much honour. To hys compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye also whyche were vppon the sea costes, she sent .xx. bullockes .C. porkes .C. lambes together with theyr dammes, and thereto of wyne great plenty: gyftes fyt for theyr entertainment, as that tyme, and as theyr necessity asked. The whyche Achates, sent by Aeneas to the sea, presented to them, and at his returning brought with him yong Iulus Aeneas sonne, who by hys fathers commaundement shoulde for the Troians part lykewyse present to the Quene certayne ryche gyftes, ornamentes of the fayre Elen, which they had got from the Grecians handes at theyr spoyle of Troy. But the Goddes Venus, mother to Aeneas, who alwayes douted what wold be the end of this her sōnes so great entertainment in a straunge land, thought that thus she shuld best make all thynges sure, yf she myghte by any meanes bryng the Quene in loue with hym. Whych thyng to do she wrought thys feat, she byds her sonne Cupid (who was the God of Loue) addresse hym selfe in the lykenes of Iulus to go present the gyftes, and in daliaunce wyth the Quene priuely to inspyre her with vnquenched fyre of loue. The childe therefore Iulus commyng with giftes to be to the Quene presented, she brought on sleepe, &amp; so carying him in her lappe into the
<pb facs="4"/>mount Idalium, left hym there amongst the floures. In thys meane tyme Cupid (as hys mother had bydden hym before) tooke vpon hym the shape of Iulus, goeth lyke to him accompanied with Achates, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth the giftes, and in stede of Iulus presēteth the same to the quene. She setteth her down to meate, causeth the Troians to syt down. The Tirians come together, whyche also syt downe, commaunded by her. They wonder at Aeneas hys gyftes, and at the goodly boy, whō they toke to be Iulus: but of al others, vnhappy Dido could neuer inough be hold eyther the swete boye, or yet the presentes, but styl more &amp; more is she enflamed, &amp; what wyth the gyftes, and with the chyld maruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously styred. This child after he had hanged in the necke of Aeneas, so to begyle the loue of hys fayned father, setteth vpon the Quene. He goth to her: she is with him maturilosly rauished, she imbraseth hym, she takes him in her lap, and thus with kyssyng and colling, she deligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth her selfe. But the suttle boy Cupid, remembring what his mother had sayd to hym, amongst these kysses breathed fyre into the Quenes brest, whych nought but death it selfe, or scarse that, could quench. He begyns to make her by lytle and lytle to forgeite quite her former hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Sichens: he styrs vp her mynde so loth to be kindled, &amp; assanltes that hart of hyrs, out of vse wyth loue. After meate, the bord the bords remoued, the mighty boles of golde set wyth stones, were plyed wyth the wyne, drynkyng there was, quassyng one to an other, wyth great myrth and gladnes. The Lord Inpas wyth hys long tresses, kyng of Affricke, played on hys gildē Lute, synging of the course of the sunne, the Mooue, of the original of mankynde, of brute, of water and fyre, of the rysyng of sygnes, of the shortuesse of dayes, and lengthe of the nightes. The Tyrians make hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fyng chere, the Troians do the lyke. Selye Dido also passyng the uyghte wyth dyuers talke, drynckes a draught of loue (alas) al to deepe. Many a question she demaundes of the kyng Priam, many a one of Hector, in what armour cam Vulcan, what maner horses Diomedes were: yea, she desires her new guest be gynning at thoriginal of the matter, to tel her of the Greekes disceite, of the Troians chaunce, of hys aduentures by sea and lande, in that hys seuen yeares trauayle. Whych thynges by that tyme he had told from the begynning to the ende, she was so enflamed in loue, that shee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne will what wai to take. And thus arose the loue betwene Dido, and Aeneas, whych is at large expressed in Virgils fourth booke of the Aenedes.</p>
   <p>(⁂)</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>