<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125498_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72942</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18596</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125498</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Svvethland and Poland vvarres : A souldiers returne out of Sweden, and his newes from the warres: or, Sweden and Poland vp in armes. And the entertainement of English souldiers there: with the fortunes and successe of those 1200. men that lately went thither</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ountrymen, I haue for your sakes drawne a Picture, both of my owne, and other Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmens miseries: You may in halfe an hower runne ouer these afflictions, which I and the rest (that smarted by them) were many months enduring. I know it shall be a pleasure to you, to reade what wee haue selt; and as great a happinesse to me (who haue published this:) if the Story of a poore Souldiers trauels, can bring you any contentment, let me finde at your handes (I intreate you) the selfe same loue which Sicke-men receiue from their friendes, when they begin to recouer; And that is a kinde visitation and reioycing, to see a crazed and weake body reduced to his former strength: Mine (I thanke God) is now so, and shall grow
<pb facs="4"/>more and more into health, by how much the more you pittie my misfortunes: you cannot pittie them, vnlesse you know them, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know them vnlesse you reade this ouer which I sende you; and I would not willingly haue you read, vnlesse you buy, because you should pay for the Warres somewhat as well as I: not doubting therefore of the one, because I hope you desire the other: I wish your owne wishes to you: and so farewell.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>