<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL AND
TRVLY RELIGIOVS S. ROBERT
Iermine Knight, &amp; M. Robert Ashfield Esquire,
Iustices of her Maiesties peace for the county
of Suffolke, the continuance and increase
of all needefull blessings spirituall and
temporall in this time, and euerla∣sting
life after death.
{inverted ⁂}</title>
           <author>Bownde, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125128_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72913</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18074.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL AND
TRVLY RELIGIOVS S. ROBERT
Iermine Knight, &amp; M. Robert Ashfield Esquire,
Iustices of her Maiesties peace for the county
of Suffolke, the continuance and increase
of all needefull blessings spirituall and
temporall in this time, and euerla∣sting
life after death.
{inverted ⁂}</title>
                 <author>Bownde, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three godly and fruitfull sermons : declaring first how we may be saved in the day of iudgement, and so come to life everlasting: secondly, how we ought to liue according to Gods will during our life: which are the two things that every one ought to be most carefull of as long as they liue. Preached and written by the reverend &amp; godly learned M. Iohn More, late preacher in the citie of Norwitch. And now first published by M. Nicholas Bovvnd: whereunto he hath adioyned of his owne, A sermon of comfort for the afflicted: and, A short treatise of a contented mind</title>
                 <author>More, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Kitson, Abraham.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 96, 4, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="55"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL AND
TRVLY RELIGIOVS S. ROBERT
Iermine Knight, &amp; M. Robert Ashfield Esquire,
Iustices of her Maiesties peace for the county
of Suffolke, the continuance and increase
of all needefull blessings spirituall and
temporall in this time, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
life after death.
{inverted ⁂}</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it please your Worships to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand,
that I haue many yeares
since, by the request of you both,
committed these Sermons to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;
at which time I thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
lesse then of the publishing of
them, especially in these daies in
which by the grace of God there is
such varietie and store of sermons, both preached and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
as it may seeme nothing can be added vnto thē: yet since
it hath so fallen out, that these copies haue beene multiplied,
and are diuersly dispersed in the hands of many, and are still
desired of some: whereupon I haue thought it good by this
one labour, both to ease my selfe of this burden in time to
come, and also to satisfie the earnest desire of those, which
<pb facs="56"/>
haue beene lingring about it this long time. Not that I haue
any hope in this argument to adde any thing to the treatises
before written, (for what can be said in this great plentie and
diuersitie of writing which we enioy, that hath not beene
spoken before?) but that by saying the same thing againe,
yet after an other manner, I might somewhat deceiue, and
so in part satisfie the vnquiet mindes of some, who in their
trouble can not long sauour any old comfort, be it neuer so
good, but through a loathsomnes in themselues are still in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring
after newe. And if we in loue thus stoope to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie
of the sicke patient, by preparing the same meate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
waies to deceiue his tast for his good, when he abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
the daintiest meate: then seeing in the soule of man there
is much more loathsomnes, whereby they sometimes refuse
all comfort, (as the Psalmist complaineth in the person of the
whole Church) if they may be delighted with any thing
here, as seeming new vnto them, and so feede vpō it to their
comfort: neither my labour herein shall seeme superfluous
in doing that which seemed to be done before, nor they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
them for tasting of that as it were in an other kinde
which they refused before, yea if through weaknes in long
sicknes, all places are so wearisome to them that it is an ease
vnto them sometimes to be brought backe againe vnto that
place which they were wearie of before: why then may
there not be hope also in the tyred soules of men, through
the continuance of their trouble, that by bringing them back
againe vnto those places of holy Scripture (as it were of rest)
which they had left lōg before as finding no ease in thē, euē
in the very same they should finde some comfort at the last,
and lie downe in peace in them, as it were in their old lodge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
dressed &amp; prepared for them: In which kind if I shall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
vnto any thing, its all that I desire, or hope to performe.
<pb facs="56"/>
The argumēt of the latter Sermon agreeth with the former,
for commonly in trouble we are discontented with our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
estate, &amp; that makes us impatiēt, therefore it is necessarie
that such shoulde be perswaded to thinke well of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
as that which the Lorde knoweth to be best for them:
and therefore to determine to beare that, and to be quiet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
it; which if they doe not, they shall finde, that vvhen
they be out of it, some other thing will disquiet them, and
so they shall neuer be contented. In handling of which I
haue not so much tyed my selfe to that speciall text chosen
for that purpose, as laboured out of that, and other partes
of the word to conclude a generall proposition of a conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
minde. Herein I craue pardon of your Worshippes,
that for these causes I haue made that common to others,
which was first proper to your selues: which I hope so
much the more easily to obtaine of you, because hereby
(in imparting it unto others) I take nothing from you,
when, as it were by lighting others mens candles at yours,
you haue notwithstanding still the whole light of your
owne, if it gaue any light vnto you before. Desiring also
of your Worshippes, that as at the first you did fauourably
accept it in writing, so now it might not seeme tedious
unto you, to haue it the second time after this manner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
unto you. I acknowledge it is unworthy of either of
your Worshippes, much more of you both, who haue
deserued so well a long time of thr common-wealth and
Church in our countrey, especially my selfe in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectes
am much bound unto you both: but seeing God
hath so neerely ioyned you in situation of the countrey, in
office and calling, in friendship, in kindred, and yet neerest in
profession and religion; I hope you will be contented euen
in this small treatise not to be sundred. And thus praying
<pb facs="57"/>
God to make you still more and more one in Christ, and
one anothers in him, and so long to preserue you both
for the further good of our countrey, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
take my leaue of your Worships.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Norton. <date>26. August. 1594.</date>
      </dateline>
Your Worships at all times
in the Lorde,
<signed>Nicholas Bownde.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>