<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           <author>Sergier, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125625_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73201</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22997</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125625</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Sergier, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The present state of Spaine. Translated out of French</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Sergier, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>TO THE WORTHIE, AND FAVOROR OF ALL VERTVES, MASTER RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD SONDS, SONNE and heire to the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, Michael Sondes Esquier.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir the duetie I owe vnto you, proceeding of so many &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit curtisies, in all bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful measure receiued, as well in your forraine trauailes, as in your home aboad, haue of long time been a continuall spurre to my weake forces; to finde some defence against that threatning monster ingratitude; &amp; fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wayward fortune still waspishe in her wonted manner, euen loath to affoord me a good looke: am constrained, lest I should be of you and the worlde condemned, to take this poore occasion to shew mine affectionate mind,
<pb facs="33"/>not meaning thereby to make this a shew of a satisfaction for so great a debt, but onely in part in cutte off the consuming interest, and to confesse vnto you in the witnesse of the world a further duetie to bee accomplished. And knowing in parte the earnest desire you haue alwaies had; to see into forraine States, and acquaint your selfe with the diuers manners of nations. I finding here a wandering stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by chance, whom I perceiued fit to informe you of somewhat worthy the inquirie: hauing now procured him a poore English weede, I am bold to commend him vnto you, hoping you wil not deny him your friendly patronage, nor me your wonted fauour.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours wholly deuoted,</hi> Richard Sergier.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="33"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>