<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the Iustices of Peace.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125901_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22844</idno>
           <idno type="STC">9342</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125901</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the Iustices of Peace.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine statvtes especially selected, and commanded by his Maiestie to be carefully put in execution by all iustices, and other officers of the peace throughout the realme : with his Maiesties proclamation for further direction for executing the same. Also certaine orders thought meete by his Maiestie and his Priuie Counsell, to bee put in execution, together with sundry good rules, preseruatiues, and medicines against the infection of the plague, set downe by the Colledge of the Physicians vpon his Maiesties speciall command: as also a decree of the Starre-Chamber concerning buildings and in-mates</title>
                 <author>England and Wales</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 68, 32, 85-95, 1, 107-117, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧To the Iustices of Peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the want of Lawes occasioneth wrongs to be committed wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly; And want of knowledge of Lawes carieth men into offences ignorantly: So are Lawes thēselues a burthen when they are too many, and their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry number is a cause that few are executed: where Penall Lawes haue otherwise no life, but in their execution. And certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Magistrate who knowes but few, and causeth those to be
<pb facs="4"/>
duely obserued, deserueth better of the Common-wealth, then he that knoweth many, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes but few. Therefore is the Composition of this Volume, that those few Lawes, and other Ordinances being most needfull for the time, may bee easily had, soone knowne, and duely execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Which is required by his MAIESTIE.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>