<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the most puissant prince Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Wyllyam Awen hys most humble Oratour wysheth perpe∣tual health and felicitie</title>
           <author>Owen, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125720_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08192</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24810a.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125720</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the most puissant prince Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Wyllyam Awen hys most humble Oratour wysheth perpe∣tual health and felicitie</title>
                 <author>Owen, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fourth boke of Virgill, intreating of the loue betwene Aeneas &amp; Dido, translated into English, and drawne into a strau [n] ge metre by Henry late Earle of Surrey, worthy to be embraced</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Awen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the most puissant prince Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Wyllyam Awen hys most humble Oratour wysheth perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual health and felicitie</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen it chaūced a copye of thys part of Virgill, traunslated by your graces father (right hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable Lord) by the meanes of a friend of myne, to come to my hāds: I not onely held y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same as no smal treasure, because I had heard it, lyke as others the monumētes of that noble wyt of hys, whych was in thys kynde no doute incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, of al men to be commēded: but also my desyre was great, at one time or other, yf by a meanes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient I might, to publyshe the same: and that the rather, because I coulde vnderstand of no man that had a copye thereof, but he was more wyllyng the same should be kept as a priuate treasure in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of a fewe, then publyshed to the common profyt and delectacion of many. But forasmuch as my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py although it were taken of one, wrytten wyth the authors owne hande, was not yet so certaine, that it myghte be thought of it selfe sufficient to be publy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, partly for that the writer had not tyme sufficiēt to the due examinacion thereof, after it was wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and also because the reding of the authors copy it selfe, by reason of speedye wrytyng thereof was somewhat doutful: for these causes, gettyng two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther copies also, written out by other men, I caused
<pb facs="3"/>myne to be conferred with them both, and of theym y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> to be receiued, as most worthy to be alowed, whych was bothe to the latyn moste agreable, and also best standing with the dignity of that kynde of mytre.</p>
   <p>And this my doing I trust no honest man shall be able to reproue, but rather it shall be an occasion, to such as fauour the monimentes of so noble a wyt, if they haue a better copy to publyshe the same. As for the vnthankeful, I passe not how much they repyne at my dede: so that I may vnderstand your grace to take in good part my good wyl herein. Which if you do (as I nothyng doute of your graces goodnesse) it shal no lytle encourage me hereafter to bring other hys workes to light, as they shal come to my hands. Thus beseching our Lord god to cōtinue your grace in welth and increase of vertue, I wyshe you hartelye well to fare.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶ Your graces most humble Oratour Wyllyam Owen.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>