<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125497_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18557</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125497</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Exhortatio. I : The first exhortation of H.N. to his children, and to the famelye of loue. by him newlye perused, and more distinctlye declared. Translated out of Base-almayne into English</title>
                 <author>Niclaes, Hendrik</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bohmberg (van Bohmbergen), Nikolaus, pseud.?</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Cologne</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>54, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <p>WIth thissame holsome or godlie Exhortation / H. N. exhorteth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmeth {reversed ;}with many good Documentes and groundlie Instructions; hys Children / and the Famelye of Loue / vnto all Goodnes / Nourtour / and Edifyinge: and expresseth or witnesseth in thesame, the vpright Righteousnes, in diuers and sondrye Sentences / To thend that the Disciples or Youngons of Vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, should becom quickened or delighted in their zeale to the Righteousnes / as also stand-inclyned somuch-the-more to the vpright Righteousnes.</p>
   <p>Which Exhortation {reversed ;}with the manifolde distinct In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founations of thesame; is also very commodious and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable for all Howsholde-fathers {reversed ;}which are comprehended in the Howse of Loue / or submitting themselues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnder; to a good Information of their Children or Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / To thend that the Heart of all Fathers / mought eauenso {reversed ;}with thesame Exhortation and the good Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes therof;<note place="margin">Luk. 1. b.</note> becom turned to the Children. and the Heart of the Children {reversed ;}in all Obedience of the holie and gratious Woord / and his Seruice of Loue; to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and that they monght cauenso becom taught to the Prudent-vnderstanding of the Righteous / for to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to an vpright People, for the Lorde.</p>
   <p>To thesame now therfore, eueryone {reversed ;}which loueth the Righteousnes; ought presentlie to endenour himself, vnder the Obedience of the Loue. and eauenso, diligentlie to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye himself {reversed ;}with his whole Famelie; to the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Righteousnes / To thend that Althinges mought now go in their right course / and that it all mought eauenso become ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled / which is writen in the Lawe of Moyses / in the Propheates / and in the Euangelistes.</p>
   <p>Let eueryone take it to Heart.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>