<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, WILLIAM Lord Bishop of EXON: the in∣crease of Grace and Peace in this life, and the complete happinesse of that to come.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125294_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73706</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4683.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125294</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, my very good Lord, WILLIAM Lord Bishop of EXON: the in∣crease of Grace and Peace in this life, and the complete happinesse of that to come.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three profitable sermons. 1. A pastorall charge. 2. Christs Larum-bell. 3. The soules sentinell : Preached at seuerall times vpon sundry occasions, by Richard Carpenter pastor of Sherwill in Devon</title>
                 <author>Carpenter, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Constable, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 71, 9, 66, 8, 112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> Reuerend Father in God, my <hi>very good Lord, WILLIAM Lord Bishop of EXON: the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of Grace and Peace in this life, and the complete happinesse</hi> of that to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Reuerend,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O whom should this Sermon preached by a Reuerend man of your Diocesse vpon your iniunction, and countenanced by your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable presence and patient at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, haue recourse for pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage
<pb facs="5"/> but onely to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; to whom for many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects it doth especially belong. Which hauing gained from the Author by much intreaty, I was (after the reading thereof) so full and pregnant of the birth, that I could beare no longer, but must needs bring forth the same, and lay it in the lap of Gods children. In doing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of albeit I had no warrant or allowance from the Author, yet I presume that herein I shall the better satisfie him, because I haue made so good choice of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating it vnto you. Whom he is bound (as I haue heard him professe) not onely in dutie to
<pb facs="5"/> honour, but in affection to loue for many respectfull fauours &amp; encouragements vouchsafed vnto him in his Ministry. In whose behalfe, as an vnfained well-willer of his, I cannot but be humbly thankfull vnto your Lordship; and in token thereof doe in all dutifull submission, consecrate to your suruey and seruice these his ministeriall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, this paper-present, and spirituall gift, in steed of some more sightly oblation: hoping that it will be as acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordship, being now wout alteration truly presented to your eyes, as it was not long since being without affectation
<pb facs="6"/> plainely deliuered vnto your eares. And so vsing no other oliue branch of intercession but the vowed sacrifice of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deuotion, submitting the premisses to your fauourable construction, and committing your Lordship to the Almighties gratious protection, I humbly take my leaue; resting euer prest to bee proued, what (though vnknowne) I desire to be accounted,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all Christian obseruancy tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuoted, <hi>R. C.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the</hi> 18 <hi>of September</hi> 1616.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>