<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125701_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08187</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24765.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125701</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Les singuliers et nouueaux pourtraicts, pir touttes sortes s'ouurages de lingerie</title>
                 <author>Vinciolo, Federico de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6 pages, 60 leaves of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing framed a body of the best &amp; rarest ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in true perfection, of sundrie sortes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises or workes, aswell for frame workes, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Needle workes: I deuised with all dilligence and industruous studie to satisfy the gentle mindes of virtuous women, by bringing to light thinges neuer before as yet seene, nor commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to print: All which deuises are so framed in due proportion, as taking thē in order, the one is formed or made by the other, &amp; so proceedeth forward, whereby with more ease they may bee sewed &amp; wrought in cloth, and keping true accompt of the threads, maintaine the bewty of the worke. And more, who desyreth to bring the worke into a
<pb facs="4"/> lesser form, let them make the squares lesse, and if greater, then enlarge them, and so may you worke in diuers sortes either by stitch, pouncing or pouldering vpon the same as you please. Also it is to be vnderstood, that these squares serue not onely for cut workes, but also for all other manner of sewing or stit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: noting withall, that they are made to keepe the worke or deuise in good order, and euen proportion. And if yee will that the squares be greater, make of two one, and of foure two, and so they will be larger: And in this maner may you proceed in all.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>God prosper your desires.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>