<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The prologue of the translatoure.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1532</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125866_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07168</idno>
           <idno type="STC">708.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125866</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The prologue of the translatoure.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Kynge Appolyn of Thyre</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Worde, Wynkyn de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1532</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶The prologue of the translatoure.</head>
   <p>FOr that ī tyme past hystoriagraphes dayly wrote and dyurnally do the hygh feates of nobles &amp; chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrous champyons of theyr marcyall dedes / of theyr lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue / and of they aduentures and fortunes happy and mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate to theyr vnyuersall renownes by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reasō wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of theyr glorie is eternally regystred in the boke of fame. Therfore to thende that theyr lawde maye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ferder spre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de amonde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people it is cōuenyent that translacyons be vsed to our recreacyon and exemplyfycacyon in the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of osiuyte and ydlenes portresse of synne doȳge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> good and eschewynge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euyll (All this consydered) my worshypfull mayster Wynkyn de Worde hauynge a lytell boke of an aūcyent hystory of a kynge somtyme rey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gnynge in the countree of Thyre called Appolyn concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge his malfortunes and peryllous aduentures right espouētables / bryefly compyled and pyteous for to here. The which booke I Robert Coplande haue me applyed for to translate out of the Frensshe language in to our ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternal Englysshe tongue at thexhortacyon of my forsayd mayster / accordynge dyrectly to myn auctour. Gladly fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge the trace of my mayster Caxton / begynnyng w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> small storyes and pamfletes and so to other. Wherfore I beseche all the reders and herers of this present hystorye yf there be ony thyng amysse in the translacyon to pardō myn ygnoraūt youth / &amp; yf it be fruytfull to gader therof to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nourysshynge of theyr soules / thākynge our lorde of his grace / &amp; to pray to hym y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I may perseuer to do some thynge to his honour. And I shall pray for thē that they may come to his glory / to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche he brȳge vs all. Amē</p>
   <trailer>¶Explicit prologus.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>