<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right hono∣rable and his singuler good Lord Sir Hen∣ry Sidney Knight of the moste honorable Order of the Garter, Lord Presi¦dent of Wales, and Marches of the same.</title>
           <author>F., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125021_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72861</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125021</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right hono∣rable and his singuler good Lord Sir Hen∣ry Sidney Knight of the moste honorable Order of the Garter, Lord Presi¦dent of Wales, and Marches of the same.</title>
                 <author>F., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves from Malta : written by a gentleman of that iland, to a friend of his in Fraunce. Shewing the desperate assault and surprising of two castles of the Turkes, by the Italians forces, vpon the eight day of September last past. Translated according to the Italian copie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hippon, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 3, 1, 88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right <hi>hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and his singuler good Lord Sir Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Sidney Knight of the moste honorable <hi>Order of the</hi> Garter, <hi>Lord Presi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent</hi> of Wales, and Marches of the same.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there can be no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reendship (right Honorable and my singuler good Lord) to speak properly whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e there is no equallitie between the pa ties, yet may the simplest and the meanest looue and honor the highest and gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atest, yea so much the more as their inequallitie is the greater. But that is not properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led freendship but rather a dutifull looue and is harde to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed and shewed for the inequalitie aforesaid. For F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eendship is between equalls, or at the least where the inequalliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is not so very great that the Offices and duties of Freendship which are the bondes and sinewes therof can haue no entercours<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. I speak this for my self that haue long desired occasion to she<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> my har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie goodwil and affection vnto your Lordship which hath been somewhat hard for me to doo for the cause abooue remembred. And therfore hauing gathered this little conference: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ade bold to dedicate it vnto my good Lord. A thing meeter to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> my gift then woorthy to be presented vnto your Honor or to go further vnder the name of such a Patron. Howbeit, my trust is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat your Lordship of your accustomed clemency will accept a simple thing of him at whose hands nothing at al was looked for, and will alowe my good will towards the reparation of such faults and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as are heerin.</p>
   <p>So praying God to blesse your Lordship and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London <date>the twentie six of Nouember. 1579.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all humillitie. T. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>