<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Church of God, which is at Paris, and to all those that loue Iesus Christ, and suffer for his Name; Grace to you, and peace from God our Fa∣ther, and the Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Moulin, Du</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125927_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B01212</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7316</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125927</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Church of God, which is at Paris, and to all those that loue Iesus Christ, and suffer for his Name; Grace to you, and peace from God our Fa∣ther, and the Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Moulin, Du</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian combate, or, A treatise of afflictions : with a prayer and meditation of the faithfull soule, and a sermon vpon the 50. Psal. vers. 15. By Master Peter Du Moulin, minister of the word of God, and professor of diuinity, in the Vniuersity of Sedan. Faithfully translated into English by Iohn Bulteel, minister of the word of God, in the French church of Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 326, 10 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Church of God, which is at Paris, and to all those that loue Iesus Christ, and suffer for <hi>his Name; Grace to you, and peace from God our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Lord Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earely beloued in Christ, wee commonly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the value of things, when we haue lost them. It is that whereof ye haue experience in this time of calamity, wherein your
<pb facs="9"/>holy assemblies being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed, you acknowledge the excellency of those goods which God hath taken from you, and doe lament the inestimable grace with <hi>compassion</hi> and holy <hi>alteration.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is that which hath moued me to impart to you what spirituall comforts I can, and indeuour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute something to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swage your griefe; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that heauinesse duls the Spirit, &amp; causeth the conceits to bee more drooping; notwithstanding I hope, that God will helpe this want with the aide of his Spirit, and that the
<pb facs="9"/>defect, which griefe may cause mee, may be suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with affection, and with that cordiall loue, which a faithfull Pastour beares to his flocke.</p>
   <p>For God is my witnesse, how greatly your afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons sting mee, how many sighes and groanes they plucke out from mee euery houre; how bitter my life is to me since my separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it being impossible for me to put my hand else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where then vpon the sore, and to thinke on any thing else then vpon your affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: it is this griefe that hath moued me to make this draught of consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="10"/>written with teares, and interrupted with sighes; so that euen that which moued me to write, was vnto me a trouble and a hindrance.</p>
   <p>I hope notwithstanding, that you will accept this gift, remembring him whom you haue loued in presence, and who hath serued you the space of two and twenty yeeres, if not with such successe and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency required, at least with much feruour and affection: for the loue which ye haue shewed me, was vnto me an incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement; and the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing which God did powre
<pb facs="10"/>vpon the Ministery of your Pastors, made mee hope, that God would vouchsafe me that fauour, that I might end my daies amongst you, in my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery. Now although that I haue not lost altogether this hope, notwithstanding beholding Gods Church on the brim of a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deepe downefall, and not knowing how it will please God to dispose of you and me; I thought it my duty to speake vnto you once againe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to comfort my selfe, in comforting you; for in drawing out to you these comforts, I haue represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="11"/>to my selfe the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for so many yeeres, in diuiding the Word of God among you, and haue felt a pleasure mixed with griefe, and in my heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse a sweete diuertion.</p>
   <p>Besides that, I haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to expose vnto your view these remedies, which I haue had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of, and those com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts which haue staid me in my afflictions; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which I had wholy fainted, and it had beene impossible for mee to haue ouerliued so many Churches broken downe, and the prosperity of my
<pb facs="11"/>flocke, from the which I haue found my selfe snatched away in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Gods will was, that the first clap of this thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der should light on my head, and that my afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on should be a fore-runner of yours.</p>
   <p>Wherein notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I acknowledge the prouidence of God, who knowing that my abode amongst you in so dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a time, would be a kindling of the aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hatred, and would haue beene an occasion of trouble and persecution on the flocke, hath caused a particular occasion to
<pb facs="12"/>rise; for the which my fellow labourers in the worke of the Lord haue thought it expedient, that I should yeeld vnto the present necessity; and by absenting my selfe for a time, looke both to your rest, and my safety; for they hoped that God would ere long appease this tempest, and that I should be quickly restored vnto you.</p>
   <p>But it is happened otherwise: for it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God to prolong the dayes of affliction, and aggrauate our euils; whereby our sinnes doe make vs acknowledge his
<pb facs="12"/>Iustice, and the succeeding euents will make vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his Wisdome, and feele the profit thereof.</p>
   <p>Amidst this desolation, that which is the most grieuous vnto me, is the fall of some, whom Satan hath snatched away from vs, that had not imployed the time of prosperity, in preparing themselues for aduersity. They haue beene contented to follow Iesus Christ while he distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread, but they had not the will to follow him, when he calleth them to beare his Crosse after him. And if those instructions which
<pb facs="13"/>we haue often propounded vnto you, are yet ingraued in your memories, you will not haue forgotten, that often wee haue fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the vicious, that shortly God would put them to the triall; and that it was a very difficult thing to hope, that those would perseuere in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the Gospell, that serue their vanity or belly, which is a bad Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellor in the matter of Gods seruice; that those that are weake against vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hardly would they be firme against griefe; that those that are hot in their owne quarrels, would be
<pb facs="13"/>found effeminate and faint-hearted in Gods quarrell.</p>
   <p>It may be, that some of them casting their eye vpon this booke, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging therein the language of him that hath spoken so long time to them in the Name of the Lord, will feele themselues pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their hearts, and finding thēelues brought to huskes, and fed with meates that nourish not, will wish for the bread of the Fathers house, and will returne to God. It may be, that others also already standing on the Pinacle, and ready to cast them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="14"/>headlong, will be kept backe by the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which we propound in this booke, and will be possessed with a godly feare to saluation, and with a holy astonishment.</p>
   <p>As for those whom the feare of God, and faith in his promises make stedfast against these temptations, they may couple these les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons with their holy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, and may adde thereunto that, which their study, or griefe, or hope may furnish them with, to make therewith a web of holy thoughts, and a subiect of their ordinary entertainement with God.
<pb facs="14"/>In which entertainement there is a sweetnesse, which humane reason cannot taste of, and a soueraigne comfort; for it is also the end for the which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth vs of the delights of the world, that wee may seeke our delight in this communication with him.</p>
   <p>To this end wee must aboue all things aske for this Spirit, who is the Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, this Spirit of Peace, this reioycing vnction; for they are not our words that comfort the heart, but the efficacie of Gods Spirit that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them; without the which we sowe vpon the
<pb facs="15"/>stone, and tickle the eare, without mouing the heart, and comfort those that haue more neede of threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then of comfort.</p>
   <p>It is this Spirit that frames vs to hope against all appearance, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes our spirits to pray without ceasing by a holy obstinacie; Considering that God is our Father, who hath deliuered his Sonne vnto death for vs, who giueth vs his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for a couerture, his Spirit for a guide, his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels for Gardiens, his Word for instruction, his Kingdome for inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; the first fruits
<pb facs="15"/>of his Spirit for an earnest of that Inheritance. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering also, that his Church is his owne pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase, that our Religion is his cause, that his Counsels are hidden, his Wayes se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, his Decrees vnauoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, his Iudgements iust and wholsome, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises certaine, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passions tender, &amp; his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction immutable; He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth marueilous workes with little meanes, yea without meanes, yea against all meanes, and against all appearance. Let vs not therefore put limits to his power, let vs not controll his Wisedome,
<pb facs="16"/>nor let vs doubt of his Truth, and of the firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his promises.</p>
   <p>Who knoweth if God sayth not in himselfe, This people is not as yet low enough to be raised vp with miracle? I will bring them to that passe, that their deliuerance shall be a kinde of resurrection; for God, who hath beene dishonoured by vs in pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, will make his Name glorious both by chastisements, and by our deliuerance. And if his Fatherly goodnesse wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assemble vs after this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sipation; it must be our duty to offer vp to him
<pb facs="16"/>Sacrifices of thankesgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and to labour with all our power to raise vp the ruines of his Temple. But if he hath otherwise determined, he will shortly gather vs together aboue, and bring vs into his Temple, the stones whereof are liuing, whose builder is God, and foundation Iesus Christ; a Temple which the mutinie of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious people cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammage: while that men shall triumph ouer vs here on earth, wee shall triumph with God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; wayting for the time wherein the enemies of God shall appeare before
<pb facs="17"/>the Iudgement seate of our Sauiour Iesus Christ, and that God will render to euery man according to his deeds.</p>
   <p>The Father of mercies and of all comfort, asswage your euils, strengthen your faith, crowne your labour, and giue me the grace to be alwayes</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your faithfull and<lb/> most affected Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stour<lb/> and seruant<lb/> in the Lord:<lb/> DV MOVLIN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>