<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the moste gratious, and vertuous Ladye oure soue∣reigne Maystres, Quene Mary, Quene of Eng∣land France. &amp;c. and defenders of the faith Richard Smith, her highnes Chaplin, and her Reader of Diuinitie at Oxforde, wysheth longe health both of body and soule, encrease of Honour, and Grace, from God the Father, and our Lorde Iesus Christe hys sonne.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125530_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73178</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22816</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125530</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the moste gratious, and vertuous Ladye oure soue∣reigne Maystres, Quene Mary, Quene of Eng∣land France. &amp;c. and defenders of the faith Richard Smith, her highnes Chaplin, and her Reader of Diuinitie at Oxforde, wysheth longe health both of body and soule, encrease of Honour, and Grace, from God the Father, and our Lorde Iesus Christe hys sonne.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bouclier of the catholike fayth of Christes church : conteynyng diuers matters now of late called into controuersy, by the newe gospellers. Made by Richard Smith, doctour of diuinitee, [and] the Quenes hyghnes reader of the same I her graces vniuersite of oxford</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 80 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the moste gratious, and vertuous Ladye oure <hi>soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Maystres, Quene Mary, Quene of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land France. &amp;c. and defenders of the faith Richard Smith, her highnes Chaplin, and her Reader of Diuinitie at Oxforde, wysheth longe health both of body and soule, encrease of Honour, and Grace, from God the Father, and our Lorde Iesus Christe hys sonne.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet (moste vertuous Quene) cōsidrīg <note place="margin">Psal. cxvii.</note> Gods wonderful worke in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaūcing of christ, whom y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnkinde and vnfaithfull Iewes, had refused amongest other woordes sayde. <hi>A domino factum est istud, &amp; est mirabile in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis nostris.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This thing is done of our Lord, &amp;
<pb facs="3"/> it is a meruayle in our syght. Maye we not say the same, gratious quene when we doe remember how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully god hath hitherto, the space of many yeres preserued your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cruelhāds of your enemies and at the length exaltyng the same vnto her ryght enherytaunce of the royall croune of Englande? Maye we not truly say: <hi>A domino factū est istud, &amp;c</hi> This is the worke of our lorde, and it is merueylous, to our eyes? For is it not a straunge thyng, and a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull worke of God, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> manye puis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant myghty, and ryche princes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the furniture and present aide of all thynges, that mans polytyke, worldly wyse wit coulde iudge, and deuise necessary to bryng theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and enterprise about, for theyr own aduauncement, and your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="3"/> destruccion, were ouerthrowen of god, and of your hyghnes, by hys especyall goodnes, and singuler help without any great ryches, policye, power, and ayde of men? Maye not your grace then iustlye say with the Prophete. <hi>Dextra dominifeict virtutem, dextra</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. cxvii. wo moued al the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōs her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es to serue your grace at the fyrste rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst you was it not god.</note>
      <hi>domini exaltauit me?</hi> Our Lordes hande hath wroughte myghtylye, oure Lordes hande hath exalted me? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn, may not we, your graces loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all faythfull, and obeysant subiectes truely saye, that god (which geueth al victorye) dyd fyght for your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as he euer dyd for his people y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iewes when they beleued in hym, <note place="margin">Exod. xiiii. Except he an indurate Pharao or a Iudas. Hester. vi.</note> woorshipped hym, and serued hym, deuoutly? What man is so blind, but that he may see plainely the mightye hande of god defended your grace? The haulty, high, emuous, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious.
<pb facs="4"/> A man prepared a gibbit to hang the good humble seruaunte of god, Mardocheus vpō, <hi>ced scidit ī foueī</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psalm. vii.</note>
      <hi>quam fecit,</hi> but he fel downe into the pit whiche he had made, and was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon that galoes hymself. And dyd not god take semblable venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce vpon youre hyghnes mortall enemyes, the rebels, whych soughte your graces destruccion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many of them, iustly perished thē selfes, your highnes mercifully spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the rest? Are not they thē, which your grace pardoned, highly boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be true and faithful subiectes hereafter vnto your grace? Let them remember, that Christ sayde vnto a synner, to whom he hadde forgeuen his offences. <hi>Vade et noliamplius peccare, ne</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioan. v.</note>
      <hi>quid deterius tibi contingat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Goe thy way and synne no more,
<pb facs="4"/> least some woorse thyng chaunce to thee. For god hath spared them, and your exceadyng clemencie, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they should amende theyr lyues and obey bothe him, and your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whyche thing if they dooe not, a farre greater plague is to come v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pō them vndoubtedly, as the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said christs wordes, declare plainly.</p>
   <p>Lette them bee ware, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake their newe wycked religion, and retourne agayne to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke Churche, euer hauyng in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, <note place="margin">Actorū .v. Iosephus. li. 18. ca. 2 &amp; antiquiattū</note> vnto what confusyon came Iudas Galileus, and Theu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das (of whom Saincte Luke wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) and such other sedicious setters <note place="margin">Eusebius. li. i. ca, 3. hist eccle. Actorū. v.</note> vp, defenders, and folowers of new doctrine against Christ, &amp; the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, Of whō note y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saint Luke wrote, as ensamples do declare that
<pb facs="5"/> which he afore had saide of Christes Apostles preachyng, when he wrote thus. <hi>Discedite ab hominibus istis, &amp; smite illos, quoniam si est ex hominibus consilium hoc, aut opus dissoluetur, si vero ex deo est, non poteritis dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>soluere, ne forte &amp; deo repugnate videamini,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That is to say, depart ye hence frō these mē, and let them alone, suffrīg them styll to preache, for as muche as yf thys counsayle, or woorke bee commen of men, it shall bee broken, but yf it be of God, ye cannot loose, dissolue, or breake it, least parauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ye may seme to fyght agaynste God. Doth not this lesson sufficiētly and manifestly instruct vs, that the olde beliefe (which hath been euer in this realm, sence it was last conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the fayth) is the very true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, because it hath been at all tymes folowed of good christen people, and <note place="margin">Beda. lib. i. hist. Ang.</note> not only of vs English men, vntil of
<pb facs="5"/> late yeares, and nowe is restored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto vs, by Gods mercifull goodnesse, our moste noble &amp; gonly kinges help, your graces trauaile, &amp; aide y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord Cardinals grace, beyng a meane and great helper to cōpasse and bryng that thyng about, preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God vnto that propose? See we not also euidently that this newe beliefe, yea an vnbeliefe rather, was not of god, according to Gamaliels rule, seeyng it was neuer taught a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōgest vs vntill of late, nor amōgst any other Christian nation, &amp; seyng also that it is nowe ouerthrowen so soone agayne? Dooeth not men then striue against the wind and streame and spurne agaynste the pricke, (as Christ sayd vnto Saule,) when thei <note place="margin">Actes .ix.</note> labor to suppresse that Christes true fayth, &amp; to set vp, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> steade of it,
<pb facs="6"/> their own fond dreames? Vnto whō your highnes may say, <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nite consilium, et</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isaye .viii.</note>
      <hi>discipabitur, loquimini verbum, et non fiet, quia dū<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> est nobiscum.</hi> Enter ye into counsell, &amp; it shalbe broken, speake ye a woorde, &amp; it shal not be done, because our lorde is with vs. Wherfore I considering most vertuous Quene, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gret good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God declared towarde your grace, &amp; toward this whole realm, &amp; coūtrey, in restoring againe the true religion of Christ into it, &amp; also seing your hyghnes ernest zeale towards the trouth, &amp; exceading trauel of the same in setting it forth, did thynke it my boundē duety to put my helping hand therunto, especially forasmuch as Christe our sauior said y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he came into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world to beare witnes vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> trouth, &amp; died for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> defence of it. For which causes I haue made this boke
<pb facs="6"/> and ētitled it y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bouclier of the fayth. Which I haue dedicated vnto your grace, most humbly beseching your highnes, to take in good worth thys my labor, takē (as god is my record) only for the defence and declaracion of the trouth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thereby your graces subiectes, which haue bene seduced, &amp; deceiued by the late new prechers, teachers, &amp; writers, may plainly see, how thei wer led bi thē out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right way into many manifest &amp; shameful errors, &amp; returne again out of them vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> catholike verity, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the trouth may deliuer thē frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peril of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting dānatiō, &amp; at their mortal lifes <note place="margin">Ioan. viii.</note> end, bring thē to the endles ioyes of heauē, through gods gret mercy &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> desertes of Christ our sauiour, vnto whō with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> father, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy goost be honor &amp; glory, for euer &amp; euer. Amē.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>