<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Christo∣pher, Earle of Anglesey, and his most vertuous Lady, Grace and Peace.</title>
           <author>Jay, Georce</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1252_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68255</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14479</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Christo∣pher, Earle of Anglesey, and his most vertuous Lady, Grace and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Jay, Georce</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preacht at the funerall of the Lady Mary Villiers, eldest daughter of the Right Hon [ora] ble Christopher Earle of Anglesey : who dyed the xxi. of Ianuary 1625. at Horningold in Leicester shire, and was buried the xxiiij. at Goadeby in the Sepulchres of her ancestor / preacht by George Iay</title>
                 <author>Jay, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Harper, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, <hi>Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> Earle of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> and his most vertuous Lady, Grace and Peace.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord, my Lady;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onour shal it ever be to me, to obey your cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; at my Lords I preacht, at my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies I printed: but the disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of so short an allowance of time as two daies, &amp; mine inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities besides, will shew this not to be a Sermon fit for, though it hath past, the Presse. This will
<pb facs="3"/>be spoken when tis read; but hee riseth betimes, that thinkes worse of it than I doe. I made a covenant with mine eyes, that they should neither goe out in sleepe nor slumber, untill they had lighted mee to performe my Lords pleasure; which if I have done I have a protection▪ and no man shall dare to arrest me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I was imploi'd in his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. I know in these times of war, I shall meet with some tall men of their hands, that will put every syllable to the sword: but tis an honour to me to die in my Commanders service. Some mouthes are Musket-bore, and doe so scatter, that though I passe the Pikes, yet I cannot
<pb facs="3"/>scape them: yet I shall thinke my selfe out of Gunne-shot, when your Lordship hath given mee a dispensation for not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a due honour to the most promising, Lady (if I flatter, I flatter my self) that ever mine eyes beheld. The Leviticall law gives a large restitution for a dammage; God, out of his mercy, when hee thinkes fit, a greater for what hee takes. I will therefore make bold with my Reader, and change my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle into a Prayer. May the God of fruitfulnesse give your Honours a numerous, and an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient issue, in supplement of her that's gone now to him, that you and yours after a length of
<pb facs="4"/>happinesse heere may succeed, exceed her in glory, shall ever be the praier of him who is, and professeth still to continue,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>your Honours in all humble duty and observance at command,</hi>
         <hi>GEORCE IAY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>