<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL AND
SVCH AS FEARE GOD, THE
Knights, and Esquires, Iustices for the preseruation
of her Maiesties peace in the Countie of Norf∣folke,
and to euery one of them, Grace,
mercie, and peace from God the Father,
and from Iesus Christ our
Lorde.</title>
           <author>Bownde, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S125128_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72913</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18074.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S125128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL AND
SVCH AS FEARE GOD, THE
Knights, and Esquires, Iustices for the preseruation
of her Maiesties peace in the Countie of Norf∣folke,
and to euery one of them, Grace,
mercie, and peace from God the Father,
and from Iesus Christ our
Lorde.</title>
                 <author>Bownde, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three godly and fruitfull sermons : declaring first how we may be saved in the day of iudgement, and so come to life everlasting: secondly, how we ought to liue according to Gods will during our life: which are the two things that every one ought to be most carefull of as long as they liue. Preached and written by the reverend &amp; godly learned M. Iohn More, late preacher in the citie of Norwitch. And now first published by M. Nicholas Bovvnd: whereunto he hath adioyned of his owne, A sermon of comfort for the afflicted: and, A short treatise of a contented mind</title>
                 <author>More, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Kitson, Abraham.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 96, 4, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL AND
SVCH AS FEARE GOD, THE
Knights, and Esquires, Iustices for the preseruation
of her Maiesties peace in the Countie of Norf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke,
and to euery one of them, Grace,
mercie, and peace from God the Father,
and from Iesus Christ our
Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas among the many hundred
Sermons, or rather certaine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandes
preached by this graue and
learned father, by the space of more
then twentie yeares, in which hee
was licensed thereunto by the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versitie
of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> he left no
such notes at large whereby the
principall heades or chiefe matter of any of them almost
might be well collected for the better vnderstanding of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
sauing onely of these, which he wrote out worde for
worde as you haue them: It seemed vnto me, that his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and purpose was, thereby to commende the most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie
doctrine in them cōtained, to as many as he mought,
and that it should not be proper to them onely, to whome it
was first vttered, but stretch out it selfe further: neither
<pb facs="3"/>
that the fruit of it should perish with the sound thereof, but
remaine afterwards, yea liue when himselfe should be dead.
Which moued me thus to publish them, that so they might
more speedily be caried farre and nere, and more easily be in
the hands and eyes of all them, to whome they were meant.
And as they intreat of that matter principally, which was
most common in all his preachings, as being most necessary,
(namely how we may be saued in death, and how we ought
to lead our life) which can neuer be too much preached of,
or too often heard of any; and therefore if he had still li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
he would still haue preached of this; so nowe because
he is fallen asleepe in the Lord, and can speake no more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
vs, and these points are but shortly set downe of him in
the beginning of his Catechisme, (which yet with great
fruite these many yeares hath beene often printed) this lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
discourse of his might be in steade of a continuall prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
vnto all those that are desirous still to be confirmed in
them: In which besides the matter whole and intire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any alteration, you haue his owne very wordes also as
they were penned by himselfe, that so by the graue simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
or simple grauitie appearing in them, all that were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
with his preaching, might thereby as it were by the
colour &amp; lineaments of it, easily discerne that it is altogether
his owne doing in deede: especially so many as then hearde
him, might therby as it were by his footing, trase out the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
himselfe. Seeing then, vpon this occasion these sermons
come abroad, I thought it expedient, or rather necessarie to
commend them to your Worships godly consideration &amp;
Christian protection; because that being first preached in a
Right worshipfull assembly and meeting of yours helde at
Ocle for the quarter Sessions then; and afterwards (the Lord
so effectually blessing him, and mouing some of you with
<pb facs="3"/>
his holy spirit) beeing written at the earnest request (as it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth)
of your Worships, him selfe in his life time dedicated
them after a sort vnto you: so that I could not now after his
death, haue alienated them from you: vnlesse I would of
purpose haue violated the will, and made frustrate the good
intent of the deade: which yet if I had inconsiderately done,
your Worships might haue chalenged them, and recouered
them into your handes. Hoping therefore that your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships
will fauourably interpret my boldnes, who beeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
euen in the face vnto the greatest part, yea almost all
of you, haue presumed thus farre: seeing that therein I haue
not so much disorderly intruded any thing vpō you against
your wils, as dutifully tēdered &amp; deliuered vp vnto you your
own: (as herafter you may for my credit herein, heare in this
treatise the author him selfe speaking vnto you by name) I
humbly beseech you to receiue it as your own: I count it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
needlesse to write in the commendations of it, (nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
are my praises any thing, if they were needfull) the name
of the preacher and writer of them commends them suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently,
especially vnto so many of you, as knew his great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
both in all the liberall arts, and almost all languages, and
also in other studies meete for so great a Divine: with his
great godlines and continuall graue cariage of himselfe in the
whole course of his life, which worthily did purchase him
great reuerence amongst all: besides his feruent zeale for the
house of God, which at the last did eat him vp: &amp; his endlesse
paines in preaching the Gospell in season and out of season:
sometimes almost euery day in the weeke, for the space of
certain yeres, and euery Lords day three or fowre times: and
when he did least, so often as ordinarily the strength of man
will permit, as many of your Worships are credible and eie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnesses
of it, besides many hundreds more: By all which
<pb facs="4"/>
it may seeme he vntimely shortned his daies, yet seeing the
ende of our life is to doe good, and he by making hast, did in
so short a time, as much good, as if by sparing him selfe he
had drawne out the same in length, if he could possibly so
haue liued an hundred or two hundred yeares: what cause
had he in his death thereof to repent, or we now in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
to be sorie for him? But I will keepe your Worships
no longer from him; you shall heare him selfe speaking vnto
you, or rather the Lord by him: vnto whose gratious bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing,
for the fruit of this, and all other his good ordinances
towards vs, for our direction in this life, and saluation in the
life to come,<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 8. 9.</note> commending all your Worships, I humbly
take my leaue, praying you to thinke on these things, which
ye haue both learned and receiued, and heard, and seene in
him: those things doe, and the God of peace shalbe with you
<hi>Norton</hi> in <hi>Suffolke. 26 August.</hi> 1594.</p>
   <closer>Your Worships in all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
duties for the Lords sake,
<signed>Nicholas Bownde.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>