<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vvilliam Turner to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S126460_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12685</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23004</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S126460</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vvilliam Turner to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The su [m] of diuinitie : drawen out of the holy scripture very necessarye, not onlye for curates [and] yong studentes in diuinitie: but also for al christen men and women what soeuer age thei be of. Drawen out of Latine into Englishe by Roberte Hutten. Anno. 1548</title>
                 <author>Spangenberg, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Seres, William 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>284 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Vvilliam Turner to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that my scholer sūtime, and seruaunte Robert huttē, had traunsla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thys boke oute of latyne into Englyshe, he mystrustynge hys owne Iudgement to be suffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent to iudge whether the cōpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of this boke had in his writing done al thinges according to the veine of holy scripture: offered y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> boke vnto me that I should exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men it wyth the touchestone of the scripture, whyche thynge I haue done as diligentelye as the tyme that I had to spare would suffer me. The boke, I dare saye, is godlye and full of holsome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and is veri necessary for all studētes of diuinitie, for curates,
<pb facs="3"/>
for yong children and for al them that haue anye rule ouer anye greate houshoulde, ye may haue bokes that shall promise more thē this doeth: but none that intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of thys kynde of matter that performeth more then thys doth It hath not so many newe frēch englyshe blossomes as many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes haue: but better fruyte then thys hath, I thinke ye shal finde either none y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> writteth of thys ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gumēt or else very few. This trā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latour hath applied hym selfe as much as he cā to find out y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moste playn &amp; vsed wordes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be in eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lād y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> men of all shyres of Englād maye the more eassy perceiue the meanynge of the boke. Some nowe a dayes more sekyng their owne glorye then the profyte of the readers: write so frenche En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe and so latine that no man excepte he be both a latine man, a french man and also an englyshe
<pb facs="3"/>
man: shal be able to vnderstande their writinge whose example I woulde disswade all men to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people if they shoulde haue any profyte by such mennes laboures had nede of two dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries euer by thē, one in french and an other in englysh. Whych thyng because it is to tedious, it would plucke back all men from the redynge of suche good and christen bokes as they do tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate.</p>
   <p>But thys boke is boeth playne in sentence and easy in style and nothynge swarueinge from the comon speache. Therefore reade and examyne it wyth the word of God &amp; as far as it doeth agree wyth the scripture alow it and no farther</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>