<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>Barnes, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S126454_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04141</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14280</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S126454</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archidamus, or, The councell of warre : Being 2000. yeares old, and written by Isocrates the couragious orator, translated by a Tho: Barnes</title>
                 <author>Isocrates</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing in my apprentiship of Grammar Schoole, I cast a view
vpon that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and most famous <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrique</hi> Oration, about
which as some say, that flower of oratorie <hi>Isocrates</hi> was in
hammering ten yeares or more. But mine eye glauncing a little further, I
chanced to reade that little lesse admirable Oration to King
<hi>Philip,</hi> which the Grecians so reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, inasmuch as King
<hi>Philip</hi> and his sonne and heire <hi>Alexander</hi> by reading
thereof, were stirred vp to set vpon the kingdome of <hi>Persia.</hi> But
proceeding, I hapned vpon this no lesse famous then the rest, entituled
<hi>Archidamus;</hi> in the beginning whereof I found such excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of
elocution, that it still more inflamed the scorching heate of my desire
to reade it more exactly then the othets. First, because it was vndertaken
in so important a cause, and for so <pb facs="3"/> Potent, and so Noble
descended a young <hi>Prince:</hi> Secondly, because in this Oration was
required varietie of matter, Monarchicall, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie, publike and priuate,
either aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ruine; and lastly because it seemes to mee the
Orator spent his best vigour and strength of wit, and learning at least
to paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell, if not to excell his other Orations.</p>
   <p>But the noise I now heare of preparation for warre, hath made
these his Arguments, and whole discourse not only to run in my minde, but
also to run out at my pen. Hath my plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull instructor
<hi>Isocrates</hi> taught me to speake any Greeke? why should not I teach
him to speake a little English? In attempting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I doe but pay a
part of that gratitude, which I owe him as a reward for mine educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which
kinde of duty he in this Oration calleth by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.
If any man thinke that I soare too high in medling with Orations that
concerne politique affaires. I answer that in our Schooles we reade all
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Histories and discourses, wherein we looke after only the
outward barke of the phrase, and Rhetoricall figures. My end and <pb facs="3"/>
taske is only a <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, not of souldiers, but of words,
construction of Phrases, not applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Histories. Therefore (good
Reader) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my petty labours, and pardon mine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, remembring that thy
selfe either art a yong learner, (like my selfe) or, hauing beene so,
hast learned at least this lesson <hi>Minori par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> (that is)
not to strike with deeper censure those that haue not withdrawne their
hand from the ferula.</p>
   <p>Courtious Reader, farewell, and prosper, which is the word
wherewith now I salute <hi>Westminster</hi> Schoole, thence hoysing
sayle for <hi>Eton.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Barnes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>