<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull Sir Iohn Grange, Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of the Peace and Quorum, in the County of Middlesex: and to that right vertuous, the Lady Katherine his wife, all earthly and heauen∣ly true happinesse.</title>
           <author>Burt, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S126041_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00991</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4132</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S126041</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull Sir Iohn Grange, Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of the Peace and Quorum, in the County of Middlesex: and to that right vertuous, the Lady Katherine his wife, all earthly and heauen∣ly true happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Burt, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nicke for neuters : A most godly and fruitfull sermon, begun and preached at Paules Crosse, the 30. day of October last, and continued &amp; finished in Paules Church, on New-yeeres day at night. By Thomas Burt, preacher of the Word. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Burt, Thomas, preacher of the word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull Sir Iohn <hi>Grange, Knight, one of his Maiesties</hi> Iustices of the Peace and Quorum, in <hi>the County of Middlesex: and to that</hi> right vertuous, the Lady Katherine his wife, all earthly and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this dangerous time of Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, raging in this our Mother City, and places adiacent, it might be sayd, as sometimes it was of Rome, <hi>Paucorum vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus cuncta Romae patrauit.</hi> Your Worship, right worthy Knight, being one of this paucity, incumbēt on your office in these places, euen alone <hi>Moses</hi>-like, from the Morning to the Euening, bearing the burthen of the people, in hearing, deciding, ending their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies, mayntayning the vertuous, &amp; punishing the malefactors; and like a broad Fig tree, sustay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the weake and little shrubs, making shaddow to the weary, giuing fruite to the hungry, and bearing your selfe strongly against all peruerse &amp; importune winds of contradictions and discouragements, yea, sowing vertue, and reaping fame; with griefe haue seene, and well doe know, that it might be sayd yet agayne (notwithstanding Gods reuealed wrath and sharpe punishments) as sometimes it was of Rome:
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Moribus antiquis res stat Romana virisque.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Chrisostome.</hi> fayeth, If thou seest a tree doeth beare no fruit, the cause is in the root. The cause of the barren leaues of the peoples trees, and their vayne words, and abominable workes, I take it to be want of Religion, and Neutrality in Religion: I haue therefore made choyce of this text.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I entitle this booke, <hi>A Nicke for Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> because this our age hath brought forth many a prodigious <hi>Polypus,</hi> and vayne ayre-full Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. The diuine Angels of our Churches haue bene vilipended, God hath bene offended, and our City grieuously punished.</p>
   <p>God auert his future further plagues, &amp; turne his Iustice into mercy, and giue vs grace by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to meet with his iudgements. The Lord stirre vp the heart, and blesse with all wisdome, our pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent succeeding <hi>Salomon:</hi> inspire with his spirit, and giue fit ability &amp; cunning to <hi>Bezaleel,</hi> &amp; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holiab,</hi> to promote the worke of the Tabernacle. God rayse vp (especially now) trusty <hi>Chusa,</hi> prouidēt <hi>Ioseph,</hi> and iust <hi>Samuel,</hi> bold <hi>Elias,</hi> playne <hi>Iohn the Baptist,</hi> instant <hi>Paul,</hi> and feeding <hi>Peter:</hi> and extirpate and explode wicked <hi>Achitophel,</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous <hi>Iudas,</hi> blind <hi>Elymas,</hi> and paltry <hi>Magus,</hi> and graunt, that the Fig leaues of authority, paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, selfe-loue, flattery, dessembling, and fond fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, may be pulled off from Madam <hi>Psacentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>the noble Lady <hi>Verona</hi> may shew her liniaments, in vninuested &amp; vnobscured nakednes: so that with circumcised hearts and catechized soules, we may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one bring the Arke of God into our houses, while we may; that our houses may be blessed, as those houses were where the Arke was: and that this famous City with the Suburbs, and adioyning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes, now after their late sorrowfull sighing of that <hi>Hei mihi, quanta de spe decidi,</hi> may (as it was sayd of Christ) <hi>gustare post fella fauos,</hi> to the glory of God, the Church, Common wealth, and our priuate good, And as by good desert induced, it is my bounden duty, I beseech the most Highest, to stretch out his hand of protection, &amp; defend, receiue vnder the couerture of his wings, and preserue your Worship, and your vertuous Lady, with those toward Imps, your two gracious sonnes, &amp; modest courteous daughters: and to send with this my New-yeeres gift (such as I haue to giue) which I commend vnto you, many new yeeres, and continuall new and true ioyes, benedictions and graces temporall, corporall, spirituall, celestiall, and eternall, for his Christes sake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships in the Lord,</hi> Thomas Burt,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>