<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Proctor, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1281_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10151</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20410</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1281</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Proctor, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The right of Kings : conteyning a defence of their supremacy, over all persons and in all causes, as well ecclesiasticall as civill, within their severall dominions : herewithall is proved by testimony of Holy Scripture, that Christian Kinges are to haue such dignity, and execute such office in the Christian church, as Gods kinges had exercised in the church under the lawe : which part of the mysterie of Gods will, as it hath been wickedly under poperie shut up from men, so it is in our tymes right needfull that the same be opened to all Christian nations</title>
                 <author>Procter, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 31 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho that considers the evills done unto the Sonne of God by Kings: Who that considers that
most cruel persecution of the Church by Kings in the primitive tymes, &amp; this also for
about three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares of continuance: yea, who that considers the Churches persecution by
Kings in these last tymes, wherein our Princes being miss-led by the delusions of the
Romane Bishop, haue persecuted them who suffered their faith and service of God, to be
instructed and ordered by the word of God: who (I say) that considers these things, would
not expect, that the Lord, even our most blessed God, should utterly reject them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying
them any dignity or office in his Church upon earth? But the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings,
Righteous beyond our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, and mercifull beyond all expectation, hath contrarywise
reveiled from heaven by his word, and witnessed unto it with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous power, that the Kings
among the Nations of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, are accepted by him for his Ministers, unto whom, as unto
Kings allowed by God, all Christians must be subiect. By how much the lesse therefore their
desert hath been, by so much the more is this Grace of God to be magnified: By how much the
lesse their desert of this grace hath been, by so much the more are they bound, to attend
diligently to the due execution of the will of God. Is it not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that Kings being
miss-lead, partly by Heathenisme before their conversion to Christianity, partly by Poperie
after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, haue heretofore bloudily persecuted and slaine those, who haue
yeilded obedience to the word of God? Shall the Saints, euen to this day also, be butchered by
their power? when the Lord is so gratious as to mainteyne the right of Kings, will not they doe
<pb facs="3"/>right to the children of God? how long shall a falfe word misslead the most of
them? how long will they be, before they by the light of the word of God discerne the Lords
sheepe from others? Blessed be God, who hath opened the eyes of many of them, and moved their
harts to be Protectors of his flock. His Flock are those, who, if not fully, yet most neerely
conforme their faith, their life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, to the reveiled will of God, as it is
preserved in the sacred scriptures. As therefore the Lord is mercifull to Kings, so ought
they in duety to God, by the word of God in scripture to discerne, and discerning to protect
the people of the Lord. Much of the Lords people are miss-lead by Teachers, who teach evilly in
some things, and hardly finde we any wholly conformable to the instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords word in
Scripture; but yet difference is to be put, betweene those who in the greatest part obey the
word of the Lord, &amp; those who in the greatest part walk in disobedience. And my hope is,
that as by this Treatise I move Gods people, to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der advisedly the great Dignity and
Office of Princes, so Princes will be gratious to those, who most neerely Beleeve and live as
becommeth Saints. Neyther would I haue my Reader here to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that I would iudge who or who are
lawfully Kings; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that these who are Kinges by the permission and grace of God, may
be put in minde of their Dignity and Office in the Church &amp; be also obeyed by those of the
Church, as God by his instruction reveiled to the Church gives direction. This is the end of my
writing this following Treatise: this the aime of my heart; which having now showen in this
epistle, I think fit to put an end to the same, and to proceed to the Treatise it
selfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, Thomas Proctor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>