<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1280_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10114</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20372</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1280</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short treatise of the sacraments generally, and in speciall of baptisme, and of the Supper written by Iohn Prime</title>
                 <author>Prime, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>95 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the vse of all things is most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, so is their abuse most perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. Many excellent thinges are spoken of the Sacraments of Christian faith: They are the Lordes owne ordinances, memorials of diuine promises, monuments of our duety, signes to the word which we professe, assured seales of his good will, strong bandes whereby we stande bounde first to God in obedience, and then in mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al loue amongst our selues. Notwithstanding, these sacred mysteries, the very instrumentes of the holy Ghost, haue they not bene of olde, or are they not now either vnthankefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused, or vnworthily receiued, or lesse dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully regarded, then was, and is behoofeful? Ful hands can not apprehend any other thing, they are full already: fowle handes and soy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the clay and brickeworke of sinfull thoughtes and deedes, they are profane, and should not presume to touch his Iewels. Want of true knowledge in the worde of God, hath bred sundry distemperatures and diseases, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and heresies in the body of Christes Church in this behalfe. When the writing is not knowen, the seales are lesse or more then duely, and neuer aright esteemed of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb facs="3"/>man. Whē the light of the Scriptures was hidde vnder the busshel of a strange tōgue, the Sacramēts also in the darke were most irreligiously contemned, superstitiously abused, carnally and grosly mistaken. As good haue a seale to a blancke, as to a writing drawen in strange characters and letters that cannot be read, or if read, yet vnderstoode but of a fewe, and of them no further then it pleased the masters of corrupt time at their leasure, or begging Fryers for their gaine, to expounde in miserable maner, to hungry, poore, and sterued soules. And then as good no bread at all, as so vile a prouender made of mixtures, eyther hard, or dowbaked and clammie: eyther they coulde not chewe it, or it coulde not nourishe them.</p>
   <p>Thus was the Lordes inheritance abused,<note place="margin">Iren. lib. 3. cap. 19.</note> famished for want of true foode, or fedde as Irenee speaketh, with lyme &amp; water, in stead of milke. The Deuil knewe he could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile in the light, and therefore no sleight of Satan euer like to this to deceiue men,<note place="margin">Mar. 12.24.</note> and slay soules. Whiles that Christians were wise, they neuer sought in pilgrimage from shrine to shrine,<note place="margin">S. P. Q. R. Beda.</note> neyther to Rome, nor to Ierusalem, nor to any singular place vnder heaven, with
<pb facs="3"/>obseruation of the place,<note place="margin">Luke 17.20.</note> as if God were more tyed to this region, then to that, one or other. The true worshippers worshipped in spirit &amp; trueth. In trueth, without hypocrisie,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.23.</note> and in spirite, without externall respectes. For as the Conye is acquainted with his owne burrowe &amp; safe rocke:<note place="margin">Prou. 30.26.</note> so Christians then knew where to seeke, whither to runne, and howe to finde rest in heauē for their soules. They asked help alwayes of an able hande, trode the kings high way, knocked at the right gate, builded their house on the onely foundation: that is, they beleeued in Christ, called vpon God, were guyded by his spirite, trusted in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, hoped in his mercies manifestly layde abroad, and sufficiently reuealed in his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde,<note place="margin">Iohn 20.31.</note> and as certainely confirmed by the pledges of his will the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: whereof this treatise is intended for all such as can be content to learne in fewe wordes of a simple teacher.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>