<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the indifferent Readers, be they Protestants, Papists, or neyther, I. R. Catholike Protestant, Professour of Iesus Christ, wisheth all wisdome, and all constancie to hold the trueth being found.</title>
           <author>R., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1295_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10684</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20959</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1295</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the indifferent Readers, be they Protestants, Papists, or neyther, I. R. Catholike Protestant, Professour of Iesus Christ, wisheth all wisdome, and all constancie to hold the trueth being found.</title>
                 <author>R., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a Romish rime lately printed, and entituled, A proper new ballad wherein are contayned Catholike questions to the Protestant : the which ballad was put foorth without date or day, name of authour or printer, libell-like scattered and sent abroad, to withdra the simple from the fayth of Christ, vnto the doctrine of Antichrist the pope of Rome / written by that Protestant Catholike, I.R</title>
                 <author>Rhodes, John, minister of Enborne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>39 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the indifferent Readers, be they Protestants, Papists, or neyther, I. R. Catholike Protestant, Professour of Iesus Christ, wisheth all wisdome, and all constancie to hold the trueth being found.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Readers whosoeuer, you shall vnderstand, that not many moneths ago, I, together with others in a search, found some good English bookes, and some two or three English Pamphlets of another stampe and nature, viz. A Popish Rosary of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and diuers Popish pictures in it, circled about with the forme of Beads, (as if all were the holyer, that comes within that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe.) We found there amōg other things also, a Toy in Rime, entituled, A proper new Ballad, wherein are certaine Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like questions (for so he termeth them) to the Protestant. These two, with an other note booke, written of like argument, I keep by me: and, onely of zeale to the trueth, and of loue to such sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple soules, as might be snared with such petty bayts as this Ballad is, I haue taken a little paynes in answering the same as well as I could, being a man of small skill to meddle in greater matters. A Minister of the Citie told me of the same Ballad, before I met with this, and desired me to vndertake the answering of it, &amp; he would helpe me to it, but could not: and therefore till now, by this good occasion, I thought no more of it; although I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, there are many such Pāphlets, together with other like Romish wares, that are sent abroad among the common people, both Protestants and Papists in London and in the countrey, &amp; that, by certaine women Brokers and Pedlers (as of late in Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordshire there was) who with baskets on their armes, shal come and offer you other wares vnder a colour, and so sell you these, where they see and know any likelyhood to vtter them. God graunt, that all Magistrates may haue the spirit of Nehemias &amp; Zorobabel, to take and finde them out, and finding them, not to let them go, but to punish them according as the quality of their offence deserueth: for vnder the habit of such, many young
<pb facs="3"/>
Iesuites, and olde Masse-priests range abroade, and drawe disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples after them. But because I feare I may exceed the bounds of an Epistle, I will draw towards an end: onely I will shewe you how I haue dealt and ordered things in the answering hereof.</p>
   <p>First, I found it set to no certaine tune: but because it goeth most neere to the olde tune of <hi>Labandalashot,</hi> therefore I haue made, that all may be sung to that tune, if neede be.</p>
   <p>Secondly, the Authour of this Ballad, his skill seemed to me, to be as bad in Poetry, as in Diuinity, and therefore I am here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in driuen sometimes to adde and abbreuiate the Authours par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular words, but I faile him not a iote for his owne sense and false meaning: let this bee considered of therefore of all men.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, this Ballad-monger hath deuided his worke into 9. principall parts or heads: and I obserue them in a sort, as shall appeare by the figures set before euery part.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, whereas the conclusion of the Ballad is long, I giue him leaue to goe it through, and then I followe him with mine answere all together, And so with my Epilogue, and a short song of Popery, made long agoe in scorne of Papists foolery, I end, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Readers for further satisfaction in this poynt, to M. Crowly his booke, which is an answere in prose to the like questions, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1588.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, I. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>