<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY, KING IAMES, by the especiall Grace of God, of Great Bri∣taine, France and Ireland King, and in all causes, whether Ecclesiasticall or Ciuill, next vnder CHRIST su∣preme Head, and a most faithfull De∣fender of the true Catholique and Apostolique Faith, in all his Realmes and Dominions; Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplyed.</title>
           <author>Mason, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1299_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07226</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17623</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY, KING IAMES, by the especiall Grace of God, of Great Bri∣taine, France and Ireland King, and in all causes, whether Ecclesiasticall or Ciuill, next vnder CHRIST su∣preme Head, and a most faithfull De∣fender of the true Catholique and Apostolique Faith, in all his Realmes and Dominions; Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplyed.</title>
                 <author>Mason, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A revelation of the Revelation : wherein is contayned, a most true, plaine, and briefe manifestation of the meaning and scope of all the Reuelation, and of euery mystery of the same : whereby the pope is most plainely declared and proued to bee Antichrist / by Thomas Mason</title>
                 <author>Mason, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 102 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY, KING IAMES, by the especiall Grace of God, of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, and in all causes, whether Ecclesiasticall or Ciuill, next vnder CHRIST su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head, and a most faithfull De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the true Catholique and Apostolique Faith, in all his <hi>Realmes and Dominions;</hi> Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplyed.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Excellent Soueraigne:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing attained vnto some cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of the scope and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation,</hi> and of the Mysteries
<pb facs="3"/>thereof, by earnest prayer, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsing of Expositors, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Prophesies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the Ecclesiasticall Histories; and being desirous to inlighten others, I haue cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled, in as briefe and easie manner as I could deuise, the true scope and meaning of the same, and of euery Mysterie thereof: And being well as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, that as God gaue vnto the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> a rich measure of his Spirit, so he hath bequeathed vnto your Highnesse most abundantly, his holy Ghost: so that none more knoweth the minde of Christ then you Maiesty doth.
<pb facs="3"/>Which imboldened me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate this my Worke vnto your Highnesse, most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crauing, that this little shew of my dutifull loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maiestie, may obtaine pardon for my too much boldnesse: so, as it is my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den dutie, I will neuer cease to offer vppe supplications vnto God and vnto Iesus Christ, for the dewe of his Spirit to be daily distilled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Royall heart, for your direction, and that God would alwayes charge his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels for the preseruation of your Maiesties person, and of our most gracious Queene,
<pb facs="4"/>our most Royall Prince, and all your Highnesse Kingly Progenie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties</hi> most faithfull and dutifull Subiect, THOMAS MASON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>