<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVE∣REND FATHER IN God, the Lord Byshop of Bath and Wells, my very good Lord, heauenlie grace, and earthlie peace.</title>
           <author>Myriell, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1309_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07953</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18323</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1309</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVE∣REND FATHER IN God, the Lord Byshop of Bath and Wells, my very good Lord, heauenlie grace, and earthlie peace.</title>
                 <author>Myriell, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The devovt sovles search : With the happie issue of comfort found. In a sermon, preached at Paules Crosse, Ian. 14. 1610. By Thomas Myriell, preacher of the word of God, at Barnet</title>
                 <author>Myriell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 91, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND <hi>FATHER IN</hi> God, the Lord Byshop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> my very good Lord, heauenlie grace, and earthlie peace.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, &amp; my very good Lord.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>THere is no such mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, to giue life, nor meanes to preserue life in the affection of loue, as
<pb facs="3"/>loue it selfe. Neither is anie thing so kindely to mans nature, or so naturall to mankinde, as to loue, when one is beloued.</p>
   <p>Therefore euen hee, which is loue it selfe, takes this course, hee loues vs first, that wee may loue him first, and last; <hi>Quid tam populare quam gratia?</hi> saieth that generous By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop. Fauour and grace, as we affect and desire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more; So, nothing so much affecteth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth vs. Hence, my Lord it is, that as by du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="3"/>I must not, but honor; so by affection, I cannot, but loue your Lordship: my selfe in particular, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uīg receiued as good cause to doe this, as you giue to others in generall, iust rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to doe that.</p>
   <p>Your Lordships pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, that you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mee, doth make me vowe, neuer to forget you. Your kinde affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in wishing you might do me good, did me much good presently, as soone as you wished it. And <hi>certes,</hi> I no wayes doubt, (such is
<pb facs="4"/>your Lordships loue and respect, with God himself in heauen, and his vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, &amp; vice-regēt in earth: such your dignitie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencie in the Church and Court,) that anie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable matter is, or can be so difficult, that your Lordship may wish for it, and yet not haue it.</p>
   <p>I know your Lordship looke for no requitall, and indeed I can make none. Yet, if I should not so much, as once shew some willingnes, I should more then make shewe of great
<pb facs="4"/>vnworthinesse.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Aeschines,</hi> a poore scholler to <hi>Socrates,</hi> when hee saw manie of his companions bestow great gifts on their maister, himselfe grieuing, hee could not be a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them in giuing rewards, as hee was in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Learning: thus said, <hi>Nihil dignum te, quod dare tibi possim, inuenio: Et hoc vno modo pauperem me, esse sentio. Itaque dono tibi, quod vnum habeo meipsum. Hoc munus, rogo, qualecun{que} est, boni consulas, cogite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>{que} a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios, cum multum tibi darent,
<pb facs="5"/>plus sibi reliquisse.</hi> I can finde nothing to giue you, which is anie way wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of you; and heerein onely, I finde my selfe to be poore. Therefore, loe, euen all that I haue, I giue you, that is, My selfe. This gift, I desire you, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so simple, to take in good worth, and to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon of others, that though they gaue much to you, yet they kept more for thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. To whom <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> made this answere.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Quidni tu mihi magnum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dederis, nisi forte paruo te
<pb facs="5"/>aestimas? Habebo itaque curae, vt te meliorē tibi reddam, quàm accepi.</hi> Without doubt, thou hast giuen me a great gift, vnlesse thou accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test thy selfe little worth: I will therefore endeuour, that I may restore thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto thy selfe, better worth then I tooke thee at the first. The like gift, my Lord, I a poore <hi>Aeschines, doe most willingly</hi> bequeath to your Lordship; &amp; that because I verelie hope, that, with graue and wise <hi>Socrates,</hi> you will, ere long, restore mee to my selfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="6"/>(now scarcely <hi>apud me,</hi> through an Ocean of worldlie crosses) much better then you now find me.</p>
   <p>And for a pledge of this gift, I beseech your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to accept this rude ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and to giue it your countenance to grace it, and protection, to defend it. And then I doubt not, but, as it was once care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully attended from my mouth, by honorable and religious hearers, since, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly requested from my hands, by worshipful and
<pb facs="6"/>deare friends: So, now, much more, it will be thankfully receiued in the hearts of all deuout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, not, because it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer mine, but for that it is become whollie your Lordships. And so, humblie crauing pardon of your Lo: for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I cease further to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you: euer resting, your Lordships humbly to be commanded,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Myriell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>