<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the loving Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1306_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07789</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18166</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1306</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the loving Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nyne songs collected out of the Holy Scriptures of Old and New Testament, drawne foorth of the pure fountaines of Hebreuu and Greeke ; translated, paraphrased in prose, summed, analysed, notted vpon, grounds for vse and doctrine observed in every one of them, and finally paraphrased in English meeter, by Mr. William Moray</title>
                 <author>Morray, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 100 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the loving Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>LOving Christian Reader, wit: when long sicknesse brought v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee so great inability and weaknesse, that I was not able to goe without doores, farre lesse to prosecute the dispensation of my ministrie in publick: I set my selfe at the intervals of any little respiration from paine, to the reading and meditating of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the light of knowledge and faith might more and more shyne in my mynde, and abyde in my memory, and the sense of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioy and peace, might possesse my heart and conscience: For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly: As water if it stand long and runne not, want good aire or lyvelie spring, will rotte and stinke: So the soule of man if it bee not mooving about good, and mooved by the breath of the holy Spirit, that it may bee a <hi>well of water of lyfe: Ioh.</hi> 7.38. It will soone die in corruption and sinne, and stinke in the nost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les of GOD <hi>Deut. 32.19.</hi> Amongst other Scriptures I read these Songs contained in this little Treatise, and did meditate vpon them: I wrote my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which when I shew them to some godly learned Brethren, they thought if they were published they might do good to others. I thinke my selfe that they may serue for good vse, to two sorts of people: First to good Christian men and women, who delyte to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in the Law of GOD both day and night. <hi>Ps. 1.</hi> Next to yong students of Theologie, aspyring to be Preachers and Ministers of Gods word: The particulars set down in order in this Treatise serveth to help such. For <hi>1.</hi> a yong Divyne should be acquaint in some good measure, with the originall languages wherein the holy Scriptures were first writen, namely the Hebrew and Greeke that he may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand <hi>Id est</hi> and <hi>Hoc est</hi> of everie word of his Text, and not to be addicted to any one mans interpretation; so in a manner living by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans faith, but labour to haue in himselfe, a full plerophory of faith. 2. Hee should labour to make plaine the Hebraismes and Hellenismes in holy Scripture by proper paraphrase to the purpose. 3. Hee should take good heed to his method in preaching. Loving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>There bee chiefely one of two methods that the best preachers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue in preaching The one cryptick, the other open, or by the practise of Logicall analysis. The 2 I preferre to the 1. for these rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. 1. The Cryptik method requyreth long practise, a great witte and memorie: which yongue scollers cannot suddenly attaine vnto. 2. The Cryptick method doth more mooue the affections, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the minde, so that after such Sermons are well delyvered, if yee will aske the auditors iudgement thereof▪ they will say to you, that the man preached verie well, but they haue forgote what hee said: but the open method vsed by a good man and of good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, serveth to teach, delyte, mooue, both himselfe and his hearers, and to helpe their memories. 3. The Cryptick method being in continuall discourse maketh not the vses of the word mentioned by the Apostle: <hi>2. Tim. 3.16.</hi> But the open method, may verie well vse the word accordingly, when grounds for the vses are found in the Text. And this purpose my analysis respects. The 4. vse a yongue Divyne may make of this booke, is: hee may learne in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp the summe of his text, to see that it bee it indeed, and not a summe of purposes, flying first to his phantasie which hee maketh the summe of the text. The 5. vse is to teach him to draw out his doctrines properly out of the words or purpose of the text either as Apodeictik conclusions or by way of necessarie consequence, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefrom: &amp; not make <hi>quid libet ex quolibet.</hi> Seeing the whole word of God is full of principals which should not bee denyed. For if <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>ipse dixit,</hi> was eneugh to <hi>Pithagoras</hi> schollers: How much more should <hi>Thus sayeth the LORD:</hi> bee eneugh to all men, fearing God and loving him. The 6▪ vse is to teach him to put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betwixt <hi>Methodum textus,</hi> and <hi>Methodum doctrinae:</hi> that is to say, that this method bee, by the naturall logick analysis of the text: whither in simple enunciations, propositions, Enthememes, or Syllogismes, considering well subiects and attributs, whether they bee proper, or figurat, examining the force of the words in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, comparing Scripture with Scripture: so shall hee haue many doores open to him for varietie of doctrine, and shall bee saved from confusion and idle repetition of purposes. A practicall glance of these vses I giue in this Treatise: How well or ill, I submit my selfe to thy charitable iudgement. Now commending mee to thy prayers to God for mee; that I may fight out the good sight of faith, &amp; finish my course with ioy. I commend thee to the grace of GOD.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>