<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian reader,
wisdome &amp; grace.</title>
           <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1318_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08219</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18553</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1318</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian reader,
wisdome &amp; grace.</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epistle sent unto tvvo daughters of VVarwick from H.N. the oldest father of the Familie of Love : VVith a refutation of the errors that are therin; by H.A</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian reader,
wisdome &amp; grace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ther are many enimies of the truth of the
gospel, and many that write to broach and
spread their errors: so is it needful that some
write against them, least troden truth be quite
forsaken; and silly sowles be wrapped in error,
vnto perdition. It is not easy for al men to espie Satans
subtilties, nor the deceitful sophismes of his ministers:
both he &amp; they, can trāsforme themselves like Angels of
light. Such therfore as discern them through the grace of
God, should give warning vnto others; that as the <hi>foolish
womā</hi> is<note n="†" place="margin">Pro 7. 11. &amp; 9. 13. 18</note> troublesome, babling &amp; lowd, inviting her ghests
to the depth of hel: so the<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 9. 3.</note>
      <hi>maidens of wisdom,</hi> may lift vp
also their voice; and make their crie be heard, on the
highest places of the citie.</p>
   <p>What wormwood and bitternes &amp; even deadly poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
is sparsed abroad in <hi>Henry Nicholas</hi> his writings, (who
caleth himself the <note n="|" place="margin">1 Exhort. cap. 11. See. 1.</note>
      <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Family of Love;)</hi> the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
of wisdome that do read the same, may by the light
of Gods law soon perceive: yet with faire and flattering
speeches, he hath beguiled many vnstable sowles; &amp; such
as have had no love to the truth, have been givē over vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his lies. And never had Satan a fitter time to work his
malicious wil on the sons of Adam: then in these last
evil dayes, when Atheisme and iniquity, doe so much
abound. Never had he a fitter religion for Atheists and
carnal hypocrites, then that which H. N. out of his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
and fleshly hart hath set abroach. It taketh away
the crosse of Christ, &amp; persecution for righteousnes sake:
and teacheth men to cōmunicate with al religions, servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
and ceremonies; so as they cleave in hart to his feigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned


<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
      <hi>service of the Love;</hi> It maketh them pure and without
al syn, in their own foolish imaginations; yea (more then
which the Serpent himself did never teach,) it deifieth
them with God. In a word, it bringeth a fretting lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
vpon al religion, &amp; overthroweth the grounds of faith
layd in holy scriptures, which <hi>H. N.</hi> by foolish allegories,
perverteth to the destruction of himself and his Family.
And for the principles of theologie, he hath written more
blasphemously and absurdly then ever did <hi>Mahomet</hi> in
his <hi>Alcoran.</hi> For this cause, in answering this his letter,
(as I was requested by some that heard how much it was
boasted of, among the <hi>Nicholaitans;)</hi> I have touched by
the way some of the impious heresies that are in his other
writings, without knowledge wherof, his frawd in this
Epistle cannot easily be perceived. For as a child of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
he laboureth to be obscure in his words, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> men may
admire the deepnes of Satan by which he speaketh; and
himself when he is folowed, &amp; can no other way escape,
may have this for his last refuge, that men <hi>vnderstand him
not.</hi> But<note n="*" place="margin">Ephe. 5. 13.</note> al things when they are reproved of the light,
are manifest: for the light is that which maketh al things
manifest. Now the <note n="|" place="margin">Ps. 119. 105 Pro 6. 13.</note>word of the Lord is a lantern, &amp; his
Law a light; by it therfore have I assayed to discover the
snares of this seducer: not doubting but God, who cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
the Morning to know his place, that it may take
hold of the corners of the earth, <note n="†" place="margin">Iob. 38. 13</note>&amp; that the wicked may
be shaken out of it; wil, notwithstanding al the dark
delphick speeches, and glozing allegories of these falsers,
declare their works and manifest their impieties, and wil
<note n="|" place="margin">Iob. 34. 25.</note>turn the night, (in the darknes wherof they think to be
shrowded) and they shalbe destroyed.</p>
   <p>Let therfore the prudent reader, make trial of that


<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
which on both sides is said, by the word of truth: least,
as the serpent beguiled Evah through his subtilty, so their
harts be withdrawn from the sincerity of Christ. And
the Lord give them vnderstanding in al things; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
them <note n="‡" place="margin">Ps. 12. 7. 8.</note>from this generation for ever;
for the wicked walk on every side,
whiles vilenes is extolled
among the sons
of Adam.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Henry Ainsworth.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>