<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OF THE END AND CON∣TENTS OF THIS DE∣CLARATION.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1329_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08846</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19130</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OF THE END AND CON∣TENTS OF THIS DE∣CLARATION.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A full declaration of the faith and ceremonies : professed in the dominions of the most illustrious and noble Prince Fredericke, 5. Prince, Elector Palatine. Published for the benefit and satisfaction of all Gods people. According to the originall printed in the High Dutch tongue. Translated into English by Iohn Rolte</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 188 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>OF THE END AND CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENTS OF THIS DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLARATION.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian louing Reader, it cannot bee vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, what mischiefe the contention about the Sacrament hath done, and yet dailie doth, and is to be feared will doe more and more in the Protestant Churches. Now we for our parts are not only readie to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace peace continually, and for that ende haue tried all meanes to purchase the same, whatsoeuer any Christians are bound to doe therein: but so there are also many God fearing people on the aduerse part, both of high and low degree, who desire peace as gladly euen as we doe, and would further it to the vttermost of their powers, who also acknowledge that the meanes thereto propounded by vs <hi>(that we, namely, whilest we agree in the foundation of faith, should not condemne each other for difference in opinion about by-questions: considering that it is vnpossible in this life, that the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and vniforme confession of all the misteries of God, should be holden by all members of Christ in all things: as the Scripture witnesseth, and experience hath alwaies ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested)</hi> are Christian, and agreeable to the word and will of God. Onely they are hindrered by part of their portly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: who say and write, that it standeth not alone vpon some few by-questions: but also that there is difference in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, in the foundation of Christian faith, and that we haue so many detestable errours, that no Christian man can with good conscience acknowledge vs for brethren in Christ, and
<pb facs="12"/>
according to the same, hold peace and brothership with vs.</p>
   <p>That now this obstacle may bee remooued, and that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted people may know what to trust vnto about vs; wee are willing once more (adding to full measure) to declare, what we beleeue or doe not beleeue, of all and euery point of doctrine, and thereby also declare, what wee vse for Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or doe not vse in our Churches: with the causes added thereto, wherefore we doe the one, and not the other.</p>
   <p>The merciful true God and Father be pleased to bestow his grace and blessing on such a work, that the eies of many people may be opened thereby, to the honor of him, and benefit of his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>