<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the most high and mighty Prince, James, by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, Fraunce and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1335_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68396</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16627</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1335</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the most high and mighty Prince, James, by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, Fraunce and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practice of policy. VVritten by Lodowike Lloyd, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Lloyd, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the most high and mighty <hi>Prince, James, by the grace of God,</hi> King of England, Scotland, Fraunce <hi>and Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>RATERVS</hi> contending with <hi>Ephestion</hi> (most gracious Prince) which of them two loued <hi>Alexāder</hi> best, appealed to the king for iudgement, who iudged that <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi> loued the king, and <hi>Ephestion</hi> loued <hi>Alexander:</hi> but both alike loued <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the king. So the Brytaynes and the English loue your Maiesty in like sort, that you can hardly iudge which of them loues you best, vnlesse you do as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> did, to iudge the English as <hi>Craterus,</hi> &amp; the Brytaynes as <hi>Ephestion.</hi> but both Brytaines &amp; English with equall loue and loyalty loue King <hi>lames</hi> alike, that all hauing the like cause of ioy, all should so reioyce to enioy such a Iewell, that in one day enriched England &amp; Ireland with a king, and the whole Empire of Brytayne with a Prince, to whome it was reserued and continued from <hi>Brutus</hi> the first King, to your Maiesty the second King, not as to a stranger, but to a iust &amp; a lawfull king of the stocke and linage of <hi>Brutus,</hi> to succeed and sit on <hi>Brutus</hi> seat 2800. yeeres after <hi>Brutus,</hi> where your Maiesty may better say then <hi>Caesar, Veni, vidi, vici,</hi> for that you haue conquered Time, came to your owne kingdomes, and may see in your selfe such a succession, that neyther the Macedonians, who much bragged of their <hi>Hercules,</hi> whose lyne ended in <hi>Alexander:</hi> neyther the Romanes, who much gloried of <hi>Gens Iulia,</hi> whose stocke extincted in <hi>Nero:</hi> nor any nation vnder heauen (which can boast of their antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties most) can say so much.</p>
   <p>The Scythians with their Acornes in their heads, and the Athenians with their Grassehoppers in their haires, may wel bragge of their Acornes and Grassehoppers, but not of the like Empires: for as <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> sayd to <hi>Pericles</hi> of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb facs="3"/>
of Greece, so <hi>Cratippus</hi> spake to <hi>Pompey</hi> of the Romane Empire, that periods of times are limited.</p>
   <p>Embrace you therefore (most mighty Prince) the great blessings of God, which so embraced your Maiesty, &amp; elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you King, to gouerne his people, and to maintayne his lawes, without which, neither king nor kingdome can stand, for that is the rich Tablet, which <hi>Moses</hi> brought from Mount Sinay, to set about Israels neck. It is that long ladder, which <hi>Iacob</hi> saw in his dreame at Bethel, that reached frō the earth into heauen: and it is that bright-shining Starre, which guyded the kings from the East, vnto Christ at Bethlehem.</p>
   <p>The only Pearle that we should buy, and the only Iewel that wee should weare, not as gards on our garments, or frontiers on our forheads, as the Iewes wore <hi>Phylacterium,</hi> but rather printed in our hearts, where we ought to giue thanks for our King, which for 50. yeeres haue bene without either King or Prince, and now wee enioy a King, a Queene, a Prince, and Princes, with no lesse blessings by the comming of your Maiesty ouer the riuer Tweede, from Scotland to England, to incorporate both to the ancient name of great Brytaine, then by the comming of Israel from Mesopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, ouer the riuer Iordan, to alter the name of Canaan into Iuda; whose posterity, as they were wrought on <hi>Aarons</hi> garment, to remember Israel, so your princely progeny may bee sure set on the vnseamed coate of Christ, to remember the house of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most bounden and dutyfull seruant,
Lodowike Lloyd.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>