<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1352_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68419</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16951.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1352</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Siuqila : Too good, to be true: omen. Though so at a vewe, yet all that I tolde you, is true, I vpholde you: now cease to aske why? for I can not lye. Herein is shewed by way of dialogue, the wonderful maners of the people of Mauqsun, with other talke not friuolous. Seen an allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 178 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I haue published this (gentle Reader) to pleasure and profit many, so I wish the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof not to be hyd from any, which though I haue described at large in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Epistle, yet for that I thinke many will not reade the same (as I wish they woulde,) herin I haue displayed the effect and discourse thereof, which is, that one SIVQILA, a man that lyued godlye, loued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie, and esteemed equitie, was so wearie with the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, naughtinesse, falsehode and other great enormities of his owne Countrie, that he trauelled to finde out a Countrie and people that were agreable to his owne affection. Who, at the last, when he had trauelled thorowout the whole world, as he thought, chanced to meete with one whose name was OMEN, dwelling in a countrie there called MAVQSVN: wherein, as he sayde, generally be such blessed Byshops, such perfect Preachers, suche vertuous Ministers, suche godly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, suche merciful Magistrates, suche iust Iudges, suche worthie Lawes, suche charitable Lawyers, such honest Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, suche pitifull Physitions, such friendlie Surgeons, suche liberal Lordes, suche lowlie Ladies, such gentle Gentlemen, such louing Husbandes, such obedient Wiues, suche humble Children, such modest Maydes, such diligent Seruantes, such good and plaine Dealing, such Hospitalitie, such wonderfull Charitie, such practizing of Godlinesse, and such stryuing to Do wel, that the same SIVQVILA did wonder at it, saying, It is TOO GOOD TO BE TRVE: wherof this Booke hath his title, which if the Discourse therof be wel marked, I doubt not but that it will like the Godlie, please the Honest, and warne the Wicked. And therefore, as I haue taken long paynes in framing it, so I beseech thee take a little paynes to reade it thorowly, which is al that I wish. And thus I ende.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>THOMAS LVPTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>