<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           <author>Sedgwick, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1374_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13540</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23829</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1374</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 <author>Sedgwick, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A good husband and a good vvife : layd open in a sermon, preached by Mr. Thomas Taylor, preacher of Gods Word in Aldermanbury London: and published by Iohn Sedgvvicke</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Miller, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheffard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 27, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <p>and board here. The best aduise in this cause wee haue
in the sacred word of God; next vnto that, in the paines
of holy and godly men, who haue both gone before vs,
and are now, through Gods mercy, continued to vs. In
the number of which, let me commend vnto thee, the
labours of this iudicious and learned Diuine, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
of this ensuing Sermon. God, by him, hath giuen
vnto his Church, many helps in points of Diuinity; and
especially, in regard of this subiect: his directions alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
this now, and others shortly to be printed, may serue
for a Christian rule this way. I must confesse, that it
had beene ere this time printed, had not the humility
and modesty of the Author hindred it: Willing hee is,
and hath beene to doe good by preaching, but I am sure,
he glorieth not with many, in voluntary printing of
those things that are very vsefull for the Church of God.
Secondly, the expectation of an other Sermon, which by
importunity I obtained; the Coppy whereof (as soone as
it is corrected by the Author himselfe, and returned to
me, according to promise) you shall haue for your further
direction, in the holy choise &amp; godly vsage of your selues
in this so honourable estate. The God of Grace guide
your hearts that read this, to the conscionable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
of it, that you may all blesse God for such worthy
helpe, and helpe them with your prayers, who desire to
further you in the way to saluation.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the seruice of Christ,
IOHN SEDGVVICKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>