<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY-NOBLE KNIGHT Sr. Anthony Sainct-Iohn sauing health.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1413_Fr5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00888</idno>
           <idno type="STC">110.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY-NOBLE KNIGHT Sr. Anthony Sainct-Iohn sauing health.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The deuills banket : Described in foure sermons. 1. The banket propounded; begunne. 2. The second seruice. 3. The breaking vp of the feast. 4. The shot or reckoning. The sinners passing-bell. Together with Phisicke from heauen. Published by Thomas Adams, preacher of Gods word at Willington in Bedfordshire</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 341, 3, pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY-NOBLE KNIGHT S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Anthony Sainct-Iohn</hi> sauing health.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He sicknesse of this <hi>World</hi> is growne so lethargicall, that his recouery is almost despaired: and therefore his <hi>Phisitians,</hi> finding by infallible symptoms that his consumption is not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, leaue him to the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancie of his disease. For the <hi>eye</hi> of his <hi>faith</hi> is blinde, the <hi>eare</hi> of his <hi>attention</hi> deafe, the <hi>foote</hi> of his <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> lame, the <hi>hand</hi> of his <hi>charitie</hi> numm'd, and shut vp with a griping couetousnesse. All his vitall parts, whereby he should liue to goodnesse, are in a swoune: he lies bed-rid in his <hi>securitie,</hi> and hath little lesse then giuen vp the <hi>(Holy)</hi> Ghost. It cannot be denied, but that he lies at the <hi>mercie</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> It is therefore too late to tolle his <hi>Passing-bell,</hi> that hath no breath of obedience left in him: I might rather ring out his knell. Yet because there are many in this world, that are not of this world: many sicke of the generall disease of <hi>Sin,</hi> whose recouerie is not hopelesse, though their present state be happelesse; and some, that if they knew but themselues sicke, would resort to the <hi>Poole of Bethes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,
<pb facs="110"/>
the waters of life,</hi> to be cured. I haue therefore presumed to take them apart, and tell them impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially their owne illnesse. Oh that to performe the cure were no more difficult then to describe the Maladie, or prescribe the remedie. I haue endeuoured the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: the other to <hi>God;</hi> who can both <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>giue life:</hi> who is yet pleased, by his <hi>word,</hi> to worke our recouery; and to make me one (vnworthy) instrument, to administer his <hi>Phisicke.</hi> Now as the most accurate <hi>Phisitians,</hi> ancient or moderne, though they deliuered precepts in their facultie, worthy of the worlds accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and vse; yet they set them forth vnder some No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Patronage: so I haue presumed, vnder the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of your protection, to publish this (phisicall or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) metaphysicall Treatise: for as the Sicknesse is spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, so the cure must be supernaturall. Assuring my selfe, that if you shall vse any obseruation here, and giue it your good word of <hi>Probatum est,</hi> many others wil be induced the more redily to embrace it. My intent is to doe good: and if I had any better Receite, I would not (like some <hi>Phisitians,</hi> I know not whither more enuious or couetous, with an excellent Medicine) let it liue and die with my selfe. God conserue your (either) health; and giue you, with a sound body, a sounder faith; whereby you may liue the life of <hi>Grace</hi> heere, of <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your VVorships</hi> humbly deuoted <hi>THOMAS ADAMS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>