<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶T. N. to the curteous, friendlye,
and indifferent Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S141_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03434</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1356.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S141</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶T. N. to the curteous, friendlye,
and indifferent Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Straunge, lamentable, and tragicall hystories : Translated out of French into Englishe, by R.S</title>
                 <author>Bandello, Matteo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jackson, Hugh</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>118 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶T. N. to the curteous, friendlye,
and indifferent Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Bookes be many, and the deuyses sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,
which now a days in great swarmes are
sent abroade, and publyshed: so lykewyse,
pregnaunt are the wittes, and rype are the
iudgementes of a great number, which busy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
bestow their trauayles, and learnedly lend
the practyses of their pennes to display, discipher, and offer
out to the gazing view of the world, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> store of their cunning,
and the gallauntnesse of their inuentions: Some tende to
good, and Godly purposes: some to vayne and tryfeling fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasyes:
some conduce to the aduauncement of vertue &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
of the wel deseruing: some to the suppressing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling,
beating downe, and subduing of vyce, with a detes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of the loathsome lyfe of the wicked, and the ruynous
end of their pestiferous dealinges. And Tome (she more pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye)
serue altogither to noorish wantonnesse, and mayntayne
lasciuious lustes. But howsoeuer they deale herein, well I
wot, that they eyther doe, or else ought, and should euery one
according to his ability, to further and promote vertue, and
by al conuenyent meanes to rehate lose lyfe, &amp; to bring vyce
into contempte among all men: the very practise whereof,
bringeth detestation, and the end wherof bredeth confusyon.
And because no way séemeth so redy to exhort, anymate, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyse,
and incourage to well doing, neyther any course so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
to dehort, terrifye, abash, and discorage from euill doing,
and especially them of the yonger sorte (wherein is moste
daunger, and who yet stand tottering and balauncing in the
scales of aduysement, vncertayne which way to wende, or
what path to trace) from the ordinary pursuit of their wilful
affections and inordinate appetites, then by the Examples
of others, that haue trodden the way afore, whose successe
they may applye to their owne direction: therfore haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
good Aucthours, both old and new, peculyarlye intituled
<pb facs="4"/>
their workes by the name and tytle of Examples, Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically
couched in playne Historyes: wherein be lyuely pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes
set downe &amp; expressed, testifying what gaynes is gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by voluptuous lyfe, and what guerdon ensueth sensuall
appetite: wherein as in a Table, is forcibly delineated, how
some for vertue, haue rysen to honour, fame, dignitie, and
renowne, and some for vyce haue bene throwne downe, and
buryed in the pit of dishonour, shame, reproch, and eternall
infamy. So that the worthy aduancement of the one, maye
be a sharp spurre to styrre vp to goodnesse, and the lothsome
beastlynesse of the other, a brydle to reine our appetytes frō
these inconueniences, wherein we sée them to haue bene for
their demerytes, condignly plunged, to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> open ouerthrowes
of their present estates, and obloquious stayn to all their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie.
For certaynelye the view and consideration of the
accidentes that haue dryuen others (for notoryous enormy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
committed, and lose lyfe lewdely lead,) vpon the rufull
rockes, and sandy shelues of lamentale losse, and doleful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye,
is in my opynyon a good document for vs to beware of
semblable folly, &amp; to kéepe our selues within the prescripte
boundes of modest behauyour. To this ende Hystoryes and
Pamphlets, as well of the good successe of well doers, as of
the ill happes of the wicked, doe generally tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely
serue, and are alyke expedient, so that they be simply
interpreted, and rightly applyed. In the number of whiche
well meanyng wryters, I dare to enrole the wryter, and
translator of these present Hystoryes, &amp; Tragicall troubles,
out of French, into this our English tongue, meaning not
hereby to open any moe wyndowes, to vnstayed youth,
whereby to egge them to spende their golden tyme, in peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
peeuish, paltring, and poysonous Pamphlets, and so to
corrupte their vnsetled dispositions, but by modeste and
seasonable aduertisementes, to reclayme their fonde fyckle
fantasyes, and to quallifye their vntemperate and headye
humours. For the bringing of which matter to better passe,
the penner hereof, thought himself to haue taken a good and
direct course, by enterlacing pleasure with profyte, and by
<pb facs="5"/>
reducing the ground of his conceyued meaning, into a méete
Methode of Historycal occurrence. And for that it is none of
the least part of mercy, to father the Fatherlesse, and protect
the pore Orphane, from the gréedy iawes of rauenous ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
I haue héere restored to him his due, and set forth hys
trauayle euen as he lefte it, without any iniury eyther to his
person, or any iot gelding his honest and painful endeuours:
for I accoumpt it no good dealing, that any mā should thrust
his lyeth into an others Haruest, or lyke Esopes Crow to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpe
and iette abroade, deckte with the Feathers of
other bewtifuller Byrds: or to haue such a tyckling ytche,
or rather scabbe of vaynegloryous fame, to arrogate that to
himselfe, which an other mans toyle hath enterprysed and
brought to passe. Beséeching thée gētle Reader to accept wel
in worth this prety Pamplet, little (I confesse) in bulk, but
fraught with such matter, as may, if thou wilt, yéeld thée good
&amp; wholesome instruction: which as it now perchaūce lacketh
not here and there his imperfections, so (had God lent to the
Authour longer lyfe) would haue bene better poolyshed, &amp; as
voyde of faults and escapes in the prynting, as his mynd
was frée frō iustly giuing occasiō of offēce to any. Which
courtesye, if (accordingly) there appeare to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
wythin thee, then (doubtlesse) is his
paynes fully rewarded, and my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
suffycyentlye sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tysfyed.</p>
   <closer>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>