<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERIE WORTHY GENTLE∣man, Mr. Iohn Alleyne, sauing health.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1413_Fr6_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00888</idno>
           <idno type="STC">110.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERIE WORTHY GENTLE∣man, Mr. Iohn Alleyne, sauing health.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The deuills banket : Described in foure sermons. 1. The banket propounded; begunne. 2. The second seruice. 3. The breaking vp of the feast. 4. The shot or reckoning. The sinners passing-bell. Together with Phisicke from heauen. Published by Thomas Adams, preacher of Gods word at Willington in Bedfordshire</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 341, 3, pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="141"/>
   <pb facs="141"/>
   <head>TO THE VERIE WORTHY GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Iohn Alleyne,</hi> sauing health.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I haue endeuoured in this short <hi>Sermon,</hi> to prescribe to these sicke times some <hi>spirituall</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke. The ground I haue receiued from the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God: the methode I submit to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of man. In this I might erre, in the other I could not. The maine and materiall obiects I haue leuelled at, are. <hi>1.</hi> to beget in vs a sense of the sinnes we haue done, of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series whereby we are vndone. <hi>2.</hi> To rebuke our forgetfulnesse of Gods long-since ordained
<pb facs="142"/>
remedie, the true <hi>intrinsique Balme</hi> of his Gospell. In the sauing vse whereof, wee are (like some Countries blessed with the medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall benefits of <hi>Nature,</hi> yet) through nescience or negligence, defectiue to our selues in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. Inward diseases are as frequent as outward; those by disquiet of minde, as these by disdiet of body. It was a rare age, that had no spirituall plague ranging and raging in it. Ours hath manifold and manifest, vile and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ible ones: the <hi>VVorld</hi> growing at once olde and decayed in nature, lustie and actiue in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing sinnes. <hi>VVickednesse</hi> is an aged <hi>Harlot,</hi> yet as pregnant and teeming as euer. It cannot be denied, but that our Iniquities are so palpable, that it is as easie to proue them, as to reproue them. Were our bodies but halfe so diseased, (and yet this yeere hath not fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them) as our soules are, a strange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of mortallitie would ensue. Man is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally very indulgent to himselfe, but mispla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his bountie. Hee giues the body so much libertie, that it becomes licentious: but his soule is so prisoned vp in the bonds of corrupt
<pb facs="142"/>
affections, that she cries of him, as that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>Princesse</hi> of her strict keeper, <hi>from such a Iaylour good Lord deliuer me.</hi> The <hi>Flesh</hi> is made a Gentleman, the <hi>Minde</hi> a Beggar. Sicke wee are, yet consult not the Oracles of <hi>Heauen</hi> for our welfare, nor sollicite the helpe of our great Phisitian <hi>Christ.</hi> He is our Sauiour, and <hi>bare our sicknesses,</hi> saith the <hi>Prophet:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esa. 53.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>tooke on him our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Infirmitates speciei, non indiuidui</hi>:<note place="margin">Aquin.</note> Infirmities commune to the nature of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, not particularly incident to euery singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar person. Those hee tooke on himselfe, that <hi>he might know the better to succour vs in our weaknesse.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. and 4.15.</hi>
      </note> As the Queene sung of her selfe in the <hi>Poet. Non ignara mali miseris succurrere disco.</hi> It is most perfectly true of our <hi>Iesus,</hi> that hee learned by his owne sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes to pitie ours; though all his sufferance was for our sakes. But how should hee helpe vs, if wee make not our moane to him? How should we be restored, when Gods sauing Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke is vnsought, vnbought, vnapplied? To conuince our neglect, and perswade our better
<pb facs="143"/>
vse of the Gospell, tends this weake labour. To your protection it willingly flies; and would rest it selfe vnder your shadow. The God of Peace giue you the <hi>peace of God, which passeth all vnderstanding;</hi> and afford you many ioyes in this life to the end, and in the next his ioy without end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices of loue, THO. ADAMS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>