<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERY VVORTHY GENTLEMAN, Mr. FRANCIS CRAVVLEY: sauing Health.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1413_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00888</idno>
           <idno type="STC">110.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERY VVORTHY GENTLEMAN, Mr. FRANCIS CRAVVLEY: sauing Health.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The deuills banket : Described in foure sermons. 1. The banket propounded; begunne. 2. The second seruice. 3. The breaking vp of the feast. 4. The shot or reckoning. The sinners passing-bell. Together with Phisicke from heauen. Published by Thomas Adams, preacher of Gods word at Willington in Bedfordshire</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 341, 3, pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="75"/>
   <pb facs="75"/>
   <head>TO THE VERY VVORTHY GENTLEMAN, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. FRANCIS CRAVVLEY: sauing Health.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>There are foure sorts of <hi>Bankets,</hi> which I may thus distinguish: <hi>Laetum, letiferum; bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, belluinum.</hi> The first is a ioyfull <hi>Feast</hi>: Such was the <hi>Breake-fast</hi> of the World, in the <hi>Law,</hi> or the <hi>Dinner,</hi> in the <hi>Gospell,</hi> or (yet the future more fully, the <hi>Lambes Supper</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi>: this is a delicate <hi>Feast.</hi> Yet not more, then the next is deadly; the <hi>blacke Banket,</hi> which is prepared for the wicked in <hi>Hell.</hi> Which consists of two Dishes, sayth the <hi>Schoole: Poena damni,</hi> and <hi>poena
<pb facs="76"/>
sensus;</hi> or as the Philosopher distinguisheth all miserie, into <hi>copiam &amp; inopiam: copia tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulationis, inopia consolationis.</hi> Or after some, of three: <hi>amissio coeli, priuatio terrae, positio inferni</hi>: the missing of that they might haue had, the priuation of that they had, the position of that they haue, and would not haue, <hi>torment:</hi> or according to others, of foure: <hi>Mercilesse miserie, extremitie, vniuersallity, eternitie</hi> of anguish. Our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi> abridgeth all into two, or rather one, (for they are <hi>homogenea) weeping and gnashing of teeth.</hi> This is a <hi>bloody Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket,</hi> where (crosse to the festiuall prouerbe, <hi>the more the merrier</hi>) the multitude of guests shall adde to the horror of miseries; so afflicting one another with their ecchoing and reciprocall grones, that it shall be no ease <hi>socios habuisse doloris.</hi> This is a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but the third a laudeable <hi>Feast.</hi> It is that the <hi>Christian</hi> maketh, eyther to man (which is a <hi>Feast</hi> of <hi>Charitie</hi>) or to God, (which is a <hi>Feast</hi> of <hi>Grace.</hi>) Whereunto God hath promised to be a <hi>Guest,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel. 3 20.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>to suppe
<pb facs="76"/>
with him.</hi> The last is a beastiall <hi>Banke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>▪ wherein either man is the <hi>Symposiast,</hi> and the <hi>Deuill</hi> the discumbent; or <hi>Sathan</hi> the <hi>Feastmaker,</hi> and man the Guest. <hi>Sinne</hi> is the food in both. The dye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is not varied, but the <hi>Host. Sathan</hi> feasts the wicked, whiles they feed on his temptations to surfet. The wicked feast <hi>Satan,</hi> whiles their accustomed sinnes nourish his power in their hearts. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Hierome, Daemonum cibus ebrietas, lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uria, fornicatio &amp; vniuersa vitia.</hi> Our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are the very dyet &amp; dainties of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils. With this last onely haue I medled, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring to declare it, to disswade it; (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the dichotomiz'd carriage of all our <hi>Sermons,</hi>) by <hi>explication,</hi> by <hi>application.</hi> Sin is the <hi>white</hi> (or rather the blacke marke) my arrow flies at. I trust, he that gaue ayme to my tongue, will also direct, leuell, and keepe my Penne from swaruing. But since reproofes are as <hi>Goads,</hi> and Beasts will kicke when they are touched to the quicke; and he that speaks in <hi>Thunder,</hi> shall bee answered with <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> by which consequence, I may suspect
<pb facs="77"/>
stormes, that haue menaced stormes: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, behold, it runnes to you for shelter; not to instruct your knowledge, who can giue so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite counsell to others in the Law, to your selfe in the Gospell; being qualified, as that perfect Rhetorician should be, <hi>vir bonus, dicendi peritus</hi>: but that through your <hi>Name,</hi> I might offer (and adde) this poore <hi>Mite</hi> into the <hi>treasurie</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> ascribing the Patronage to your selfe, the vse to the world, the successe to God. Accept then this poore testimonie of my gratitude, who haue vowed my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your VVorships</hi> in all faithfull seruice <hi>THOMAS ADAMS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>