<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1509_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16173</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3093</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1509</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the reformation of a Catholike deformed by Master W. Perkins</title>
                 <author>Bishop, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>214, 2, 30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN READER,</hi> I suppose it shall please thee better, if I doe entertayne thy studious minde with some serious discourse, then if I went about to court it, with the ordinary complements of a curious preamble. Wherefore I purpose (by thy gentle patience) to handle here a matter of merueilous great importance, which <hi>M. PER.</hi> towardes the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of his booke, layeth out against vs in manner of a most grieuous complainte: it is, that we <hi>Catholikes,</hi> among many other capitall crimes by vs (as he fableth) defended, doe bolster and vphold the most haynous sinne of <hi>Atheisme.</hi> The man is not a litle troubled to deuise wherein we doe maintayne any such point of impiety: For compelled by the cleare euidence of truth, he confessed that we doe rightly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the vnity of the God-head in the Trinity of persons: yet that he may seeme to say something therein against vs, he flyeth vnto the threed-bare ragges of their common slanders of mans merits and satisfactions, and such old stuffe: and streatching them on the tenter-hookes, yet one nayle further then his fellowes, striueth to drawe out of them a certayne strange kinde of <hi>Atheisme,</hi> in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>The Roman religion makes the meritte of the workes of men, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the grace of God, therefore it ouerthrowes the grace of God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>vers.</hi> 6.</note> Item, <hi>they acknowledge the infinite justice and mercy of God, but by consequence both are denyed: for how can that be infinite justice, which may any way be appeased by humane satisfaction? And howe shall Gods mercy be infinite, when we by our owne satisfactions must adde a supply to the satisfaction of Christ?</hi> There needes a prety witte (I weene) to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand howe these points appertayne to <hi>Atheisme.</hi> For suppose that we defended, that the meritte of the workes of man concurred with Gods grace, as two distinct agents, which we doe not; for we hold that no workes of man haue any meritte, vnlesse they spring and proceede from the very grace of God: but let that be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what kinde of <hi>Atheisme</hi> or denying of God were this? or howe followeth it thereof, that the grace of God (which is the principall agent, and farre more potent then the other) must thereby needes be cast to the ground and foyled? this is so sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and simple, that I knowe not what to tearme it: for he doth vntruely slander our doctrine, and that to no end and purpose. To his second cauill I answere in a word,
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> that we teach (as he knoweth right well) the infinite justice of God to be appeased no other way, then by the infinite satisfaction of Christes passion: And that our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions are onely to pay for the temporall paynes remayning yet due, after the infinite are paide for by Christ. Nowe whether any such temporall payne remayne or no, after the sinne is remitted, is a question betweene vs: but to say (as <hi>M. PER.</hi> doth) that we be <hi>Atheists,</hi> and doe denie God to be God, for that we hold some tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall punishment of man to be due, after pardon granted of his greater payne, is most apparantly a very sencelesse assertion. As wide from all reason is his third in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: <hi>That Gods mercy cannot be infinite, when by our owne satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions we adde a supply to the satisfaction of Christ.</hi> For if Christs most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and full satisfaction, can well stand with Gods infinite mercy; farre more ease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may mans satisfactions agree with it, which are infinitely lesse then Christes. But the infinite riches of Gods mercy appeareth especially, in that it pleased him freely to giue vnto vs (so meane creatures and wreatched sinners) his owne onely deare Sonne, to be our Redeemer and Sauiour; and both Christes satisfaction &amp; ours are rather to be referred vnto Gods justice, then to his mercy: wherefore very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfully doth <hi>M. PER.</hi> compare them with Gods mercy. Neither is it possible to distill any quintessence of <hi>Atheisme</hi> out of it, more then out of the former; nay, they both vprightly weighed, are so farre of from <hi>Atheisme,</hi> or derogating any thing from Gods glory; that they doe much magnifie and aduance the same. For albeit we hold our good workes to be both meritorious and satisfactory: yet doe we teach the vertue, value, and estimation of them, to proceede wholy from the grace of God in vs, whereby we be enabled and holpen to doe them; and not any part of the dignity and worthynesse of the workes, to issue from the naturall faculty or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry of the man that doth them. So that when we maintayne the meritte or satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of good workes, we extoll not the nature of man, but doe onely defend and vphold the dignity and vertue of Gods grace: which <hi>Protestantes</hi> doe greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>base, extenuate and vilifie, not allowing it to be sufficient to helpe the best minded man in the world, to doe any worke that doth not offend God mortally. Thus much concerning our supposed <hi>Atheisme</hi> against God: nowe of those that be (as he imagineth) against Christ the Sonne of God: First he argueth thus. <hi>He that hath not the Sonne, hath not the Father: and he that hath neither Father nor Sonne, denies God: now the present Roman religion hath not the Sonne, that is</hi> Iesus Christ <hi>God and man: For they in effect abolish his man-hood, by teaching of him to haue two kindes of existing; one natural in heauen, whereby he is visible, touchable, and circumscribed: the other against na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby he is substantially according to his flesh in the handes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery</hi> Priest, <hi>inuisible and vncircumscribed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Answere. <hi>M. PER.</hi> and all <hi>Protestantes</hi> knowe right well, that we beleeue <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> to be perfect God, and perfect man, and therefore we haue both the
<pb n="5" facs="3"/> Sonne and the Father; and his reason against it, is not worth a rush: for we doe not destroy the nature of man, by teaching it to haue two diuers manners of existing or being in a place. When Christ was transfigured before his Apostles, he had another manner of outward forme and appearance, then he had before: yet was not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man in him thereby destroyed, and after his resurrection he was (when it pleased him) visible to his Apostles, and at other times inuisible: and yet was not his man-hood thereby abolished, as <hi>M. PER.</hi> would make vs beleeue: no more is it when his body is in many places at once; or in one place circumscribed, and in the other vncircumscribed. For these externall relations of bodies vnto their places, doe no whit at all destroy their inward and naturall substances, as al Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie testifieth: wherefore hence to gather that we denie both the Father and the Sonne to be God, doth sauour (I will not say of a silly wit) but of a froward will, peeuishly bent to cauill and calumniate. Secondly, <hi>Master PERKINS</hi> chargeth vs with disgrading Christ of his offices: saying, <hi>that for one</hi> Iesus Christ <hi>the onely King, lawe-giuer, and head of the Church, they joyne vnto him the</hi> Pope, <hi>not only as a Vicar, but as a fellowe, in that they giue vnto him power to make lawes binding in conscience: to resolue and determine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly the sence of holy Scripture: properly to pardon sinne: to haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ouer the whole earth, and a part of hell: to depose Kinges, to whome vnder Christ euery soule is subject: to absolue subjects from the oath of alleageance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Answere.</hi> Here is a bed-role of many superfluous speeches: for not one of all these thinges (if we admitte them all to be true) doth conuince vs to haue disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Christ of his offices, which are these: to appease Gods wrath towardes vs: to pay the ransome for our sinnes: to conquer the Diuell: to open the Kingdome of heauen: to be supreme head of both men and Angels, and such like. He may (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any derogation vnto these his soueraigne prerogatiues) giue vnto his seruants; first, <hi>power to make lawes that binde in conscience,</hi> as he hath done to all Princes, which the <hi>Protestantes</hi> themselues dare not denie: then, <hi>to determine vnfallibly of the true sence of holy Scripture,</hi> which the Apostles could doe, as all men confesse; and yet doe not make them Christes fellowes, but his humble seruants: to whome also <hi>he gaue power properly to pardon sinnes:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 24. Ioan. 20. Mar. 16. Matt. 28.</note> Whose sinnes you pardon on earth, sbal be pardoned in heauen: and finally, to them he also gaue authority ouer the whole earth: <hi>goe into the vniuersall world.</hi> Ouer part of hell no <hi>Pope</hi> hath authority; and when he doth good to any soule in Purgatory, it is <hi>per modum suffragij,</hi> as a suppliant and entreater, not as a commander. Whether he hath any authority ouer Princes &amp; their subjects in temporall affaires, it is questioned by some: yet no man (not wilfully blinde) can doubt, but that Christ might haue giuen him that authority, without disgrading himselfe of it; as he hath imparted to him and to others also, faculties of greater authority and vertue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing
<pb n="6" facs="4"/> neuerthelesse the same vnto himselfe, in a much more excellent manner. As a King by substituting a viceroy, or some such like deputie, to whome he giues most large commission, doth not thereby disgrade himselfe of his Kingly authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as all the world knowes: no more did our Sauiour Christ <hi>Iesus</hi> bereaue himselfe of his power or dignity, when he bestowed some part thereof vpon his substitutes. He goes on multiplying a number of idle wordes to small purpose: <hi>as that we for one Christ the only</hi> reall Priest <hi>of the newe Testament, joyne many secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary</hi> Priestes <hi>vnto him, which offer Christ daylie in the Masse.</hi> We in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede hold the Apostles to haue beene made by Christ, not imputatiue or phantasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but <hi>reall</hi> and true <hi>Priestes:</hi> And by Christ his owne order and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to haue offered his body and bloud daylie in the sacrifice of the <hi>Masse;</hi> what of that? see that question. Furthermore he saith, <hi>for one</hi> Iesus <hi>the all sufficient mediatour of intercession, they haue added many fellowes to him, to make request for vs: namely as many Saintes as be in the</hi> Popes <hi>Kalendar:</hi> yea and many more too. For we hold that any of the faithfull yet liuing, may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so requested to pray for vs: neither shall he in hast be able to proue, that Christ on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maketh intercession for vs, though he be the only mediatour that hath redeemed vs. Lastly saith <hi>M. PERKINS, for the only merittes of Christ, in whome alone the Father is well pleased,</hi> (what, was he not well pleased with his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles?) <hi>they haue deuised a treasury of the Churches, contayning besides the merittes of Christ, the ouerplus of the merittes of Saints, to be dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to men at the discretion of the</hi> Pope, <hi>and thus we see that Christ and his merittes be abolished.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Answere.</hi> The good man is somewhat mistaken, for we hold not any ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus of merits in Saints, the which we acknowledge to be by God fully rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in heauen: but we affirme that some Saints and blessed Martirs haue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered more paynes in this life, then the temporall punishment of their owne sinnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eserued:<note place="margin">Iob 6. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Who therefore might truely say with that just man <hi>Iob? would to God my sinnes, whereby I haue deserued wrath, were weighed with the calamitie that I suffer: euen as the sandes of the Sea, this should be the heauyer.</hi> Nowe parte of these sufferinges of Gods Saints (as being needelesse for their owne satisfaction) are reserued in the Churches store-house, and may by the high steward of the Church (to whome the dispensation of her treasure belongeth) he communicated to others, as very reason teacheth vs; for who is fitter to dispose of any mans goodes, then he to whome the charge thereof is giuen by his testament? And thus I hope euery reasonable man doth finde vs <hi>Catholikes</hi> to be farre of from transforming Christ into an Idoll of mans conceite, as <hi>Master PERKINS</hi> dreameth: only we see a misconceited man, labouring in vaine to deface Christes benefites toward vs, to calumniate his chiefe seruantes, and to skirmish more against his owne phantasies, then against any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> of ours. He layeth lastly a third kinde of <hi>Atheisme</hi> against vs, for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of God, not with such respect as is sutable to his nature. <hi>For</hi> (saith he) <hi>our worshippe is meere will worshippe for the most part, without any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance or commandement of God, as</hi> Durand <hi>in his</hi> Rationale <hi>in effect acknowledgeth: it is a carnall seruice standing of innumerable bodylie rites and ceremonies, borrowed partly from the Iewes, and partly from the Heathens: it is deuided betweene God and some of his creatures, in that they are worshipped both with one kinde of worshippe, let them paint it as they can,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Answere. <hi>Ipse dixit: Pythagoras</hi> hath pronounced his sentence; yet you neede not beleeue him, vnlesse you list, because he fableth so formally: doth <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand</hi> acknowledge that all our worship is meere will worship, and that it hath no allowance of God? O egregious and impudent deceiuer! <hi>For that learned deuout Author</hi> Durand, <hi>doth nothing else in all that booke, then set out the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty and declared the meaning of the true worship of God, vsed daylie in our seruice throughout the whole yeare: And therefore doth entitle his booke</hi> Rationale Diuinorum, the reasons of diuine seruice. And as for bodylie rites, we vse but fewe, and those very decent, full of reuerence, and most fit to stirre vp and cherish deuotion. We be not spirits, and therefore must serue God by bodylie ceremonies, although the life and vertue of them proceede from the spirit, employing all partes of the body, in his worshippe and to his honor that made it: neither be they borrowed of Iewes nor of the Heathens; albeit they might perhaps (the one by the commandement of God, the other by the light of nature) vse some such like: but ours were deuised by the inspiration of the holy Ghost (the heauenly guide and directer of the Catholike Church) to moue vs to serue God more deuoutly, and with greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. Now to say that we giue the same worship to any Saint that we giue to God, is a stale jest, that hath long sithence lost all his grace, being found to be nothing else, but a notorious vntruth very often confuted; as by others else where, so by me more then once in this booke: where also these other slanders here cast vpon vs, are more at large in their seuerall places discussed: this therefore may serue in this place for an answere to those imputations of <hi>Atheismes,</hi> which <hi>Master PERKINS</hi> objecteth against vs. And for that this crime of <hi>Atheisme</hi> is the most heynous that can be, as contrariewise, the true opinion of the God-head and the sincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe thereof, is the most sweete and beautifull flower of religion: let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, here (to hold due correspondence with <hi>Master PERKINS</hi>) examine the <hi>Protestantes</hi> doctrine, concerning the nature of God, and their worshippe of him; that the indifferent reader, comparing judiciouslie our two opinions thereof together, may embrace that for most pure and true, that carryeth the most reuerent and holy conceite thereof. For out of all doubt, there can be no greater motiue to any deuout soule, to like of a religion, then to see that it doth deliuer a most sacred doctrine
<pb n="8" facs="5"/> of the Soueraigne Lord of heauen and earth, and doth withall most religiously adore and serue him: Whereas on the other side, there is not a more forcible persuasion to forsake a religion before professed, then to be giuen to vnderstand, that the Masters of that religion, teach many absurde thinges concerning the God-head it selfe, and doe as coldly and as slightly worshippe God almighty; as may be. Marke therefore, I beseech thee <hi>(gentle reader)</hi> for thy owne soules sake, what euidence I shall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in against the <hi>Protestantes,</hi> touching this point of <hi>Atheisme,</hi> and following the same method that <hi>M. PER.</hi> obserueth, I will first touch their errors against the most blessed Trinity and Deity: secondly, such as are against our Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> God and man: lastly, I will speake one word or two about their seruice and worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God: All which shall be performed in a much more temperate manner, then the grauity of such a matter requireth; that it may be lesse offensiue. Concerning the sacred Trinity, it is by the doctrine of certayne principall pillers of their newe Gospell brought into great question.<note place="margin">Lib. 1. In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stit. c. 13. ss. 23. 25. Con. ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones Camp. pag. 152.</note> For <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> in diuers places teacheth, <hi>that the second &amp; third persons of the Trinity, doe not receiue the God-head from the first, but haue it of themselues, euen as the first person hath. And in this he is defended by</hi> M. Whitaker, <hi>and preferred before all the learned Fathers of the first councell of</hi> Nice. Out of which position it followeth, that there is neither Father nor Sonne in the God-head: for according vnto common sence, and the vniforme consent of all the learned; he only is a true naturall Sonne, that by generation doth receiue his nature and substance from his Father. We are called the Sonnes of God, but that is by adoption and grace: but he only is the true naturall Sonne of God, that by eternall generation receiued his substance: that is, the God-head from him. If therefore the second person did not receiue the God-head from the first, but had it of himselfe, as they doe affirme: then certaynelie he is no true Sonne of the first, and consequently the first person is no true Father. For (as all men confesse) Father &amp; Sonne be <hi>correlatiues,</hi> so that the one cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other. Thus their doctrine is found to be faulty in the highest degree of <hi>Atheisme.</hi> For it ouerthroweth both Father and Sonne in the Trinity. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it were true, then doth the holy Ghost proceede neither from the Father, nor from the Sonne: for it receiueth not the God-head from them at all, as they hold; but hath it of himselfe, and so proceedeth no more from them, then they doe from him, &amp; consequently is not the third person: Wherefore finally they doe ouerthrowe the whole Trinity, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost. Secondly, they may be truely stiled <hi>Atheistes,</hi> who thinke any one to be God, that hath not in him all singuler perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ctions, in the most perfect sort that can be, but either wanteth some of them, or else hath them in a meaner degree then any other: they therefore that teach our Sauiour Christ, in his God-head to be inferiour vnto his Father; stand just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged with <hi>Atheisme.</hi> Such a one is<note n="*" place="margin">Epi. ad Polo. pa. 940. &amp; seq.</note>
      <hi>Caluin</hi> who in formall tearmes doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch and say, <hi>that Christ according to his God-head, is lesse then his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
      <pb n="9" facs="5"/> And else where he affirmeth,<note place="margin">In ca. 26, Matt. 64. Cō. Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, ca. de Christo. Cō. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, art. 17. in the confuta. of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists slan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders.</note>
      <hi>the Father to hold the first ranke of honour and power, and the Sonne to obtaine the second,</hi> which he might haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his great master <hi>Melancthon,</hi> who taught <hi>that the Sonne according to his diuinity, is his Fathers subject and minister.</hi> Further, <hi>that in Christ there was something of the nature of God;</hi> some other thing then belike was wanting. Againe, <hi>that the God-head of Christ was obedient vnto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> with whome our country-men <hi>Iewell</hi> and <hi>Fulke</hi> doe jumpe, who affirme <hi>that the diuine nature of Christ offered sacrifice vnto his Father.</hi> Briefly, all <hi>Protestantes</hi> (who hold Christ according to his diuine nature, to haue beene a mediator) <hi>make his God-head inferiour vnto God the Father.</hi> For to be (as a mediator, must needes be) a suppliant vnto another: to pray and offer sacrifice to him, is to acknowledge him to be his better, and that something lyeth in his power to doe, which the other of himselfe cannot doe, but by sute must obtaine of him. Ioyne here vnto that they doe expound most of the textes of holy Scripture, vsed by the auncient Fathers to proue the blessed &amp; sacred Trinity, euen as the old <hi>Arrians</hi> did, reprouing the auncient Fathers exposition; which cannot but argue, that they in their hartes (though they be yet ashamed to confesse it) decline apace from those holy Fathers steps, to fauour <hi>Arrianisme.</hi> This litle therefore may suffice to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate, howe the chiefe pillers of the <hi>Protestantes</hi> religion, doe shake the very foundations of the Christian faith, by their strange glosses and speeches about the sacred Trinity, and by their diuers derogations to Christes diuinity. But this shall appeare yet much more perspiciously, if we doe well weigh what they teach touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very nature of the God-head it selfe. Whosoeuer denies God to be almighty, or presumes to limit the infinite power of God, within the compasse of mans weake vnderstanding, he in effect makes him no God at all, but some meane creature of a limitted strength and power: such be all <hi>Protestantes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">OEcolāp de verbis Domini. Beza in Neoph. simil. cōt. And. pag 15.</note> who affirme <hi>that God can not set a body in the world, without a circumscribed place; nor any one body in many places at once,</hi> with such like: the which (because they cannot, out of the dulnesse of their witte, or will not of frowardnesse, conceiue to be in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture possible) they flatlie deny God to be able to doe: yea, some of them were so blind<note n="*" place="margin">In a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at Paris.</note> and bold, as to auouch God, not to be able to conceiue or vnderstand, how that is possible; which notwithstanding very naturall philosophy teacheth, to haue no repugnance in it selfe, as in his place I haue proued. If they were enemies to Gods omnipotencie alone, it might be somewhat excused, because that might seeme to proceede rather from the weakenesse of their vnderstanding, then out of any ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towardes God: but if they doe further oppose themselues against the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, mercy, and justice of God; that must needes discouer very great impiety to lie festring in their bowels. Who seeth not, that it doth highly attainte the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable goodnesse of God, and his tender loue towardes mankinde, to impute the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of man and his eternall damnation, not vnto mans owne wickednesse and
<pb n="10" facs="6"/> desertes, but vnto the meere will and pleasure of God himselfe? and yet this is too too common an assertion amangst the <hi>Protestantes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">In colloq Monpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. pag. 522.</note> Let <hi>Beza</hi> one of their brauest champions, speake for the rest: <hi>God</hi> (saith he) <hi>in his secret counsel, hath set downe an vnremoueable decree, that he wil not haue the greater part of men saued, nor to beleeue in Christ, and come to the knowledge of truth; but hath created, ordained, and predestinated them to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting damnation.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 336.</note> To whome <hi>M. PER.</hi> in this booke draweth neere, <hi>affirming it to proceede from the very wil of God, that he shewes mercy to some and forsaketh others.</hi> Mercy (indeede) God of his meere goodnes doth powre out vpon vs abundantly: but to imagine that he of his owne will and prime choise, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any foresight of our sinnes, doth forsake vs, and appoint vs to hell fire, is heynous impiety, most contrary vnto the very nature of God; whose goodnesse is so pure and sincere, that it doth good to all thinges, and wisheth euill to none; vnlesse they doe first greatly deserue it. What an vngodly opinion then is it, to hold that he of his owne free choise ordained man (a creature made to his owne Image and likenesse) to most grieuous and endlesse torments, without foresight of any offence of his? As though he should take a singuler pleasure, to see a principall worke of his owne handes, fry in hell fire.</p>
   <p>Another opinion some of them hold, which is yet much more blasphemous then the other, to wit: that God, who hath beene alwaies by good men esteemed the author of all good, and so meerely good in his owne nature and will, that he cannot possibly doe or thinke any euill: that this Ocean (I say) of goodnesse, is become <hi>the author, plotter, promoter, and worker of all the wickednesse and mischiefe, that is, or hath beene committed in the world.</hi> This is the doctrine of <hi>Zwinglius</hi> a great Rabin among the newe Gospellers,<note place="margin">De pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. Dei. pag. 365.</note> who auoucheth that <hi>when we commit either adultery, murder, or any such like crime, that it is the worke of God, he being the authour, mouing and pushing vs on to doe it.</hi> Againe, <hi>that the theefe by Gods motion and perswasion, murthereth, and is often times compelled to sinne.</hi>
      <note place="margin">In cap. 1. ad Rom.</note> With him agreeth <hi>Bucer,</hi> sometimes a professor of diuinity in the vniuersitie of <hi>Cambridge; censuring him to denie God flatly, who doth not firmely beleeue, that God doth worke in man, as well all euill, as all good.</hi> Of the same accursed crue was <hi>Melancthon,</hi> who vpon the <hi>8.</hi> chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> saith: <hi>Euen as we confesse</hi> Paules <hi>vocation to haue bin Gods proper worke: so doe we acknowledge these to be the proper workes of God, which are either indifferent, as is to eate and drinke; or that are euil, as the adultery of</hi> Dauid, <hi>and such like. For it is euident out of the first to the</hi> Romanes, <hi>that God doth al thinges mightely (as</hi> Augustine <hi>speaketh) &amp; not permissiuely: so that the treason of</hi> Iudas <hi>is as properly the worke of God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Li. 1. Inst. c. 18. ss. 1.</note>
      <hi>as the calling of</hi> Paul. But the principall proctor and promoter of this blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy is <hi>Caluin,</hi> who of set purpose bestowes a whole chapter of his Institutions, to
<pb n="11" facs="6"/> hell, to proue and perswade it. There he auoucheth boldly, <hi>that the blinding and madnesse of</hi> Achab, <hi>was the will and decree of God: that</hi> Absolon <hi>indeede defiling his fathers bed with incestuous adultery, committed detestable wickednes; yet this was Gods owne worke:</hi> briefly, <hi>that nothing is more plaine, then that God blindeth the eies of men, striketh them with giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, maketh them drunke, casteth them into madnes, and hardneth their harts.</hi> And whereas the poore <hi>Papists</hi> were wont to interprete such textes of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as seeme to attribute these thinges to God, by saying, that God doth indeede justly <hi>permit,</hi> and <hi>suffer such thinges</hi> to be done, but is not the author of them: this, <hi>Caluin</hi> will not in any wise admitte of, but in the same place confutes it; say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>These thinges many referre to sufferance, as if in forsaking the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, he suffered them to be blinded by</hi> Satan: <hi>but that solution</hi> (saith he) <hi>is too fond,</hi> and so goeth on, prouing that God doth not only suffer, but <hi>actually effect and worke all the euill,</hi> that any man committeth: yea, he addeth that which is more horrible: that God doth worke this euill in man,<note place="margin">Ibidem sess. 17. 2.</note>
      <hi>by</hi> Satans <hi>seruice as a meane; yet so as God is the principall worker of it, and the Diuell but his instrument.</hi> Is not this blasphemy in the highest degree, to make God a more principall author, and worker of all wickednesse, done in the world, then the Diuell himselfe? this is much worse then flat <hi>Atheisme:</hi> for it is the lesser impiety of two to hold that there is no God at all, then to beleeue that God worketh more effectually all mischiefe, then the infernal spirits doe. But some of our <hi>Protestants</hi> wil perhaps say, that they hold not this opinion: be it so, for I thinke better of many of them: yet, be not these men that so teach, as it were the founders of the newe Gospell, and men of chiefest marke among them? Nowe what force such principall authours (as they take <hi>Melancthon, Zwinglius, Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> to be) may haue, to carry the rest away into the same errours, I knowe not. Sure I am, that <hi>Caluins</hi> Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions (wherein this matter is so vehemently vrged) is translated into <hi>English,</hi> and in the Preface commended to all students of Christian diuinity, as one of the most profitable (the holy Scriptures excepted) for the sound declarations of truth in articles of religion.</p>
   <p>But to proceede on with this discourse: the <hi>Protestants</hi> doe not only impugne the power &amp; goodnes of God: but they doe also peruert his justice. For to omit their last position, that God is the worker of al sinne in vs <hi>compelling</hi> (as <hi>Caluin</hi> speaketh) <hi>the reprobate to obedience;</hi> and therefore cannot in justice punish the poore wreatches, for being obedient vnto his owne will and working: and not to vrge their former assertion, that <hi>God of his owne wil &amp; decree, hath predestinated the greater part of men to hell, without any foresight of their euill desertes:</hi> which if it were true, should it not be intolerable wronge, to torment so rigorously innocents, that neuer offended him? To let passe these points (I say) how can they defend the justice of God, who hold that he hath tyed vs to such lawes, as are impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
<pb n="12" facs="7"/> to be kept by any man? For Christ (as he testified himselfe) will condemne men to hell fire for transgressing of these lawes,<note place="margin">Math. 7. vers. 23.</note> by working of iniquity; <hi>depart from me you that worke iniquity:</hi> and what equity should there be in that sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, if it had neuer beene possible for these men to haue done otherwise? For no reasonable Iudge condemneth any man for not doing of that, which he knewe well, lay not any way in his power to be done. So that nothing is more plaine and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, then that the <hi>Protestantes</hi> doctrine trotteth apace towardes open <hi>Atheisme:</hi> by impugning the power of God: by defacing his goodnesse, mercy, and justice, which in our vnderstanding are the chiefe properties of his diuine substance: and by calling into question the blessed Trinity it selfe, which their of-spring and progeny the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi> doe already denie flatly.</p>
   <p>Thus much of their <hi>Atheismes</hi> against God. Nowe to those that be against our Sauiour Christ <hi>Iesus:</hi> I haue before touched their errors concerning his God-head; here I will speake of those that be against his Man-hood, and Mediatorship. First, it must needes argue in them a great want of good affection towardes our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, that they are so backward in his blessed Mother the holy Virgins praises, not hearing with patience, any body that would so much as salute her with the <hi>Haile MARY,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> which notwithstanding is recorded in the Gospell? and are besides so ready vpon euery litle occasion, to speake in her dispraise, that we may with good reason reproue them, as men either wanting judgement (which they will not endure of anything) or else voide of due respect vnto the Sonne, who are such aduersaries to the Mother: whome if they would not reuerence for her owne vertues, which were most rare and singuler; yet for her Sonnes sake (who loued her so tenderly) they should shewe themselues better affected towardes her, and more forward in her praises, if they did indeede loue and honour her Sonne, as they pretend to doe.</p>
   <p>But let vs come to Christes owne person. Whereas the first <hi>Adam</hi> was (at the first instance of his creation) replenished with perfect knowledge: and it is also in holy write said of the second,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1. In cap. 2. Lu. v. 52. Collos. 2. vers. 4.</note>
      <hi>that the word was made flesh, full of grace and truth:</hi> Yet they commonly teach, that <hi>our Sauiours soule was subject to ignorance,</hi> euen as other mens soules are: &amp; <hi>that he was in his youth ignorant of many thinges.</hi> But what and they spare him not <hi>(in whome all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of wisdome and knowledge were hidden)</hi> when he came to ripe yeares, and beganne nowe to preach? let vs for a taste, heare some of <hi>Caluins</hi> sweete ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations vpon the text of the Gospell; because the purer brethren complaine much, that <hi>M. Caluins</hi> workes are in no greater request. <hi>Christ</hi> (saith he)<note n="*" place="margin">Ex Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cismo. li. 7. c. 13. Luc. 16. Math. 7. Ioh. 1.</note>
      <hi>speaketh improperly,</hi> Math. <hi>6.</hi> vers. <hi>18. he vseth harsh and far-fetched si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes: he wresteth the Prophetes wordes into a strange sence: he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth triuiall and vulgar prouerbes, as probable conjectures, not as sound argumentes;</hi> which he willeth vs to beare in minde, as a thing often practised by our Sauiour, <hi>in</hi> Math. ca. <hi>12.</hi> vers. <hi>25.</hi> Luc. <hi>11.</hi> vers. <hi>17. he speaketh after
<pb n="13" facs="7"/> the manner of men, not out of his heauenly cabinette,</hi> Math. <hi>11.</hi> vers. <hi>21.</hi> which is no lesse in plaine <hi>English,</hi> then that he spake vntruly as men doe. And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry sutable to this he noteth else where,<note place="margin">In cap. 7. Lu. v. 29.</note>
      <hi>that Christ could not gette any other to be his Disciples, then some certaine poore fellowes of the refuse and dregges of the people.</hi> Seeme not these execrable notes to issue from the pen of some malicious Iewe, or ranke <hi>Atheist?</hi> yet are they but flea-bitinges in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of those which followe. In his commentary vpon these wordes of our Sauiour: <hi>Father if it be possible, let this chalice or cuppe passe from me.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 26. vers. 39.</note> He obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth first, <hi>that this prayer of Christ was vnaduisedly made:</hi> secondly, <hi>that he ouercome with griefe, had forgotten the heauenly decree, not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring for the time, that he was sent to be the redeemer of mankinde:</hi> thirdly, <hi>that he withstood as much as in him lay, and refused to execute the office of a mediator.</hi> See <hi>Caluin</hi> also vpon these wordes of Christ:<note place="margin">Ioh. 12. vers. 27.</note>
      <hi>Father saue me from this houre:</hi> where he saith, <hi>that Christ was so strooken with feare, and so pinched on euery side with perplexed pensiuenesse, that he was forced through these boisterous waues of temptation, to wauer and fleete too and fro in his prayers and petitions.</hi> Is not this pittifull impiety? Whereas our most louing redeemer, of set purpose tooke that feare vpon him, and most willingly both suffered, and caused that bloudy agony and conflict, by repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting vnto him selfe, both the shame and paine of his dolorous passion, and the causes thereof (which were the innumerable most grieuous sinnes of the world) that he might in euery part both of minde and body, endure what he possibly could, for the time; and spake nothing rashly, but repeated that his prayer ouer three seuerall times, as is set downe in the text it selfe; to shewe vs howe naturally he (as all other men) did abhorre such a cruell and ignominious death: and yet withall to instruct vs, that we should be content with it, and pray to God for strength to beare it, if it were his blessed will to put vs to the like. This holesome doctrine and Godly instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, are by the auncient holy Fathers gathered out of that prayer of Christ: what a venemous spider then was <hi>Caluin,</hi> to sucke such poison out of it? if Christ so wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, where was his constancy? if he were so frighted (as <hi>Caluin</hi> falsly imagineth) where was his fortitude? if he strugled so against his Fathers decree, where was his obedience? if he refused to redeeme vs, what was become of his charity towardes mankinde? if the first motions to euill be deadly sinnes in vs (as the <hi>Protestantes</hi> hold) what will they make of such tumultuous, and vnbridled passions in him, that had a greater command ouer them, then we haue? But we are not yet come vnto the hight of his blasphemies, which he powreth forth more aboundantly vpon those our Sauiours wordes: <hi>My GOD, my GOD, why hast thou forsaken me!</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 27. vers. 46.</note> saying: <hi>when this kinde of temptation was proposed to Christ (as though God being auerted from him, he had beene appointed to vtter destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) he was seised with horror.</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Li. 2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. c. 16. sess. 11.</note> And in his <hi>Institutes</hi> treating of the same
<pb n="14" facs="8"/> subject, saith: <hi>Christ feared to haue beene swallowed vp of death as a sinner: And there can be no more dreadfull bottomelesse gulfe, then for a man to feele himselfe forsaken and estranged from God, &amp; not to be heard, when he calleth vpon him, euen as if God had conspired his destruction: euen thither we see that Christ was throwne downe, so that by enforcement of distresse he was compelled to crie out: my GOD, my GOD, why hast thou forsaken me.</hi> In the Paragraffe before, he speaketh more plainely, <hi>that Christ did hand in hand wrestle with the armies of hel, &amp; the horror of eternal death:</hi> finally, <hi>that in his soule he suffered the torments of the damned, and al those punishments that are due to wicked men in hell:</hi> He then (belike) was the traytor <hi>Iudas</hi> companion: for the while he was in the Diuels handes to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, be <hi>despaired and fared</hi> as men doe in these hellish torments. What greater blasphemy can be inuented, then to condemne the King of heauen, that came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs all from hell, euen to the very pitte of hell it selfe? <hi>Beza</hi> not willing to come behinde his master <hi>Caluin</hi> in this kinde of impiety, whereas <hi>Caluin</hi> craftily admitted only,<note place="margin">In cap. 5. ad Hebr. vers. 7.</note> that Christ then despaired, he affirmeth plainely: <hi>that from Christ (strooken with the horror of Gods curse) escaped the word of desperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And else where, <hi>that Christ was (with the huge heauie burden of Gods wrath, ouerwhelmed and adjudged to the flames of hell: yea, buried and drowned in the bottome of the infernall gulfe:</hi>
      <note place="margin">In ca. 27. Math. &amp; 22. Luc.</note> This man (you see) desires to lodge Christ lowe enough, that would haue him drowned in the very bottome of hell. This their pestilent venime, they might haue sucked out of their good grandsire <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> writinges, who vpon the very same wordes, doth make this goodly commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.<note place="margin">In Psal. 22. ver. 1.</note>
      <hi>What shall we therefore say? Christ to haue bin togither both the most just, and greatest sinner: both the most notorious lier, and truest teacher: at the same instant, both the most highly glorying, &amp; deepely despairing: both happy in the highest degree, &amp; most miserably damned. Vnlesse we say this, I see not</hi> (saith this Oracle of the newe Gospell) <hi>howe Christ was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken of God.</hi> See him also vpon the third chapter to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> where he vttereth yet more detestable speaches of Christ, to wit: <hi>that all the Prophets did in the spirit foresee him to be the greatest theefe, robber, murtherer, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, sacrilegious person and blasphemer, that euer liued.</hi> I could cite you diuers others of the same opinion, but I had rather note their extreame blindnesse, who neglecting the auncient Fathers learned expositions of the holy Scriptures, were ledde away with such horrible extrauagant conceites of our Sauiour, vpon so small occasion. For he at that very time hanging on the Crosse, declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be most farre of from all such hellish torments: yea, he shewed all possible signes of a most quiet and peaceable minde, praying for the saluation euen of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors (he was not then belike in doubt of his owne) promising also to the good theefe that the same day he should be with him in Paradise; wherefore he doubted
<pb n="15" facs="8"/> nothing of being there himselfe: recommending his Mother vnto his beloued Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and him likewise to her; and to fulfill the Scriptures, both saying <hi>I thirst,</hi> and citing euen those very wordes, that they are scandalized at, out of one of the Psalmes of <hi>Dauid:</hi> And finally, aduisedly considering all thinges belonging to his passion, to be accomplished, commended his spirit vnto his Fathers handes; so that there could not possibly be more calme setled judgement, more valiant constancy &amp; resolution, then there was. But what ment he then to say, <hi>my GOD, my GOD, why hast thou forsaken me?</hi> Forsooth nothing else, but to signifie, that in all these torments which he suffered, he had not any comfort or consolation at that time from God, who is wont to giue extraordinary aide and comfort to all those, that suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his names sake: but that Christ might (as he himselfe desired) be put to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all kinde of extremity, all manner of inward consolation was wholely with-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from him; which it pleased him then to expresse by manner of complainte in those most pittifull wordes: <hi>My GOD, my GOD, &amp;c.</hi> the more to moue vs to compassion. Thus much of their impieties against Christes person: nowe to those that they teach against the office of his mediatorshippe.</p>
   <p>They hold first, that whatsoeuer our Sauiour did or suffered before his passion, was of smal value for our redemption. For as a noble <hi>Protestant</hi> said, <hi>the</hi> Monkes,<note place="margin">Moline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia, part. 51.</note> Priestes, <hi>and</hi> Papisticall <hi>Doctors did erre, when they vrged Christes incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and natiuity: for all these thinges profited vs nothing; could doe nothing: but only the death of Christ, which alone was accepted of God for our sinnes.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Caluin</hi> goeth further, and doubteth not to say, <hi>that Christes passion and corporall death would not serue the turne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Li. 2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. ca. 16 sess. 10.</note>
      <hi>and had profited vs nothing at all, had he not in his soule suffered the very paines of the damned in hell.</hi> This doctrine of theirs is not only contrary to an hundreth places of expresse Scripture, that doe assigne our redemption vnto the bloud-shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and passion of Christ: but it also derogateth very much from the dignity of our Mediatour. For not that which he suffered, made the meritte of our redemption: but it was his exceeding charity, with which he suffered it, and principally the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dignity of his diuine person, which gaue that value, price, and estimation to his sufferinges, that the very least thing that euer he suffered in his life, was of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite value; and therefore sufficient to pay the ransome of all mankinde: yea, to haue redeemed a thousand worldes. But let vs proceede on with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes</hi> opinion: did Christes sufferinges of the tormentes of hell deserue of God in justice, the redemption of man? not so, if we may beleeue one of <hi>Foxes</hi> Martirs, <hi>who held</hi> (as he recordeth) <hi>that Christ with all his workes could not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritte heauen for vs.</hi> But for that litle credit is to be giuen to such a <hi>Martir,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Actes &amp; monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. pag. 487</note> and such a <hi>Martir-monger,</hi> let vs heare what some of the learnest amongst them say. <hi>I truly confesse</hi> (saith Caluin) <hi>that if a man will set Christ singly and by himselfe, against the judgements of God, there wil be no roome for merit.</hi>
      <pb n="16" facs="9"/> And after:<note place="margin">L. 2. Insti. c. 17. ss. 1. In abster. calumni. Heshu.</note>
      <hi>Christ could not deserue any thing, but by the good pleasure of God.</hi> Finally, <hi>the deseruinges of Christ depend vpon the only grace of God,</hi> which is defended by his disciple <hi>Beza</hi> against <hi>Heshusius:</hi> so that briefly, all Christes sufferinges in hell and out of hell, in true <hi>Protestant</hi> reckoning, amount to no higher a value, then that by the good pleasure and acceptance of God, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued our redemption; therefore in rigour of justice they were not of sufficient worth to redeeme vs, but were only of grace, by God accepted for such. Is not here a faire reckoning? so might any other man endued with grace, haue redeemed al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde as well as Christ, if it had pleased God to haue so accepted it; seing no equall recompence was to be expected. But to helpe him here by the way, that could not vnderstand howe we were saued by the mercy of God: if Christes merittes did in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice deserue our saluation, it is to be noted that both be true, if they be duely consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. For we are saued by Christes merits in rigour of justice, he satisfying of God as far-forth fully, as we offended him: and yet we be saued freely by the mercy of God too; both, because he hath of his meere mercy without any desert of ours, giuen vs Christ his Sonne to be our Sauiour: and also for that he hath (out of the same his mercy) freely applyed vnto euery one in particuler that is saued, the merits of Christ, through which he is saued.</p>
   <p>To returne to our purpose, and to discouer yet more of the <hi>Protestantes</hi> disgraces offered to our Sauiours mediation. Did Christ suffer his passion for the redemption of all mankinde,<note place="margin">Cō. Hesh pag. 39. Sup. Ioh. pag. 39. In locis fol. 361. 1. Ioh. 2. vers. 2.</note> or did he die only for some fewe of the elect? let <hi>Caluin</hi> answere you. <hi>Christes flesh was not crucified for the vngodly, neither was the bloud of Christ shed to clense their sinnes.</hi> With him agreeth brother <hi>Bucer: Christ by his death did only redeeme the sinnes of the elect.</hi> Musculus wil beare a part in that consort: <hi>Christes death is a satisfaction only for the sinnes of the elect;</hi> all as contrary to the plaine text of Scripture, as can be. <hi>Christ is a propitiation for our sinnes</hi> (where he spake in the person of the elect) <hi>and not for ours only, but also for the whole worldes.</hi> Let vs goe on yet one step further. What effect doth the bloud of Christ worke in the small number of these elected bretheren? Doth it cleanse their soules from al filth of sinne, and powre into them the manifold giftes of the holy Ghost, whereby they may afterward resist sinne,<note place="margin">Pag. 31.</note> and serue God in holynesse of life? nothing lesse. <hi>For in the regenerate</hi> (as <hi>M. PERKINS</hi> with all the rest of them doth teach) <hi>there remaineth originall sinne, which infecteth euery worke of man, and maketh it a mortall sinne.</hi> So that inwardly in their soules these elected <hi>Protestantes,</hi> be voide of justice, and full of all manner of iniquity: marry, they haue created in them the rare instrument of a newe deuised faith, by which they lay hold on Christes justice, and so by reall imputation (to vse <hi>M. PERKINS</hi> wordes) of Christes justice to them, they on the soddaine become exceeding just: therefore Frier <hi>Luther</hi> had some reason to say, that whosoeuer was borne againe of this Euangelicall faith, <hi>was equall in
<pb n="17" facs="9"/> grace vnto both</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul;<note place="margin">Supra 1. Pet. 1. In actis disput. Tigur. Fox Act. fol. 1335. &amp; 1138.</note>
      <hi>and vnto the Virgin MARY Mother of God:</hi> Nay, it seemes that <hi>Luther</hi> came to short, and <hi>Zwinglius</hi> strooke home when he said: <hi>that God the Father did no lesse fauour all the faithfull, then he did Christ his owne Sonne.</hi> And out of the confidence of the same liuely-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling faith, proceeded these speaches of our newe Gospellers in <hi>England. And we haue as much right to heauen, as Christ hath; we cannot be damned, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Christ be damned: neither can Christ be saued, vnlesse we be saued.</hi> Christ (belike) could not liue in blisse without their holy company. What audacious compagnions, and saucy Gospellers were these? yet their reason seemeth sound in the way of their owne religion: for if they were most assured of the benefit of Christs owne justice to be imputed vnto them, they could not be lesse assured of their owne saluation, then they were of Christes owne. To conclude this point, consider (good reader) howe the <hi>Protestantes</hi> (who would be thought to magnifie Christes suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings exceedingly) doe in very deede extreamely debase them. For (as you haue heard) they esteeme very litle of all the rest of his life, besides his passion: secondly, they make his passion without suffering of hell tormentes, not sufficient to redeeme vs: thirdly, that all those sufferings put togither, doe not in justice merit the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of our sinnes, but only that of grace and curtesie, God doth accept them for such: fourthly, that when all is done, they deserue fauour only for a few of the elect, and that not to purge those fewe neither from all their sinnes, but only to purchase them an imputation of justice, to be apprehended by a strong imagination or rather presumption, falsly by them tearmed faith. Is not here a huge great mill-post, faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thwited into a poore pudding pricke (as they say) by them, who after so high ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altations of the all-sufficiency of Christes suffering, doe in fine conclude, that in a very fewe persons it worketh only an imputation or shadowe of justice: but it agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very well and hangeth handsomely together, that by the merits of Christes suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in hell, (which are meere phantasticall) these men should haue created in them a phantasticall faith, neuer heard of before their dayes, to lay-hold vpon a vaine shadowe of an imputatiue and phantasticall justice.</p>
   <p>But to returne vnto Christes mediatorship and merits. Is it not moreouer a great disparagement vnto them, to maintayne (as the <hi>Protestantes</hi> doe) that his best-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued spouse the Church, should continue but a small time, at least in any sight, and should be penned vp in corners: yea, and during that time too, it should not be free from many foule grosse errours, in the very foundation of faith? Furthermore, that he left his holy word (the only rule and square (as they hold) of Christian religion) to be vnderstood of euery man as his owne knowledge and spirit should direct him? and if any doubtfull question did arise there about (as he fore-sawe thousandes should doe) yet he tooke no other order for the deciding and ending of them, but that euery one should repaire vnto the same his word, and doing his diligence to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it, might afterward be his owne judge. As this later opinion would argue our
<pb n="18" facs="10"/> blessed Sauiour, who was the wisedome of God, to be the weakest and most impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident lawe-maker that euer was: so the former doth mightily blemish the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable price of his most pretious bloud, making it not of sufficient value, to purchase vnto him an euerlasting inheritance, free from all errours in matter of faith, and abounding in all good workes.</p>
   <p>To fold vp this part, let me entreate thee <hi>(curteous reader)</hi> to be an vpright judge betweene the <hi>Protestantes</hi> doctrine and ours, in this most weighty matter of Christes dignity, vertues, and mediation; and if thou see most euidently, that ours doth more aduance them, why shouldest thou not giue sentence on our side? They make Christ ignorant many yeares of his life: we hold him from the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant of his conception, to haue beene replenished with most perfect knowledge. They, that he spake and taught nowe and then, as other men did; and was subject to disordinate passions: We, that he was most free from all such, and that he taught alwaies most diuinely. They make his very death not sufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs: we hold that the least thing that euer he suffered in his life, deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the redemption of many worldes. They, that he died only for the elect: we, that he died for all, though many through their owne fault, doe not receiue any benefit by his death. They, that thereby we are not purged from our sinnes, but by imputation: we, that all are by the vertue thereof inwardly cleansed. They, that Christ purchased a Church consisting of fewe, not to continue long, and subject to many errours: we, that he established a Church, that should be spredde ouer all the world, and that should continue to the end of the world visibly, and alwaies free from any errour in any matter of faith. Finally, they hold that Christ left his holy word to the disputation of men, not taking any certaine order for the ending of controuersies, that should arise about it: we teach, that he hath established a most assured meanes, to decide all doubtes in religion, and to hold all obedient Christians in perfect vniformity, of both faith and manners. And because I am entred into these comparisons, giue me leaue to persist yet a litle longer in them. Consider also (I pray you) who goe neerer to <hi>Atheisme,</hi> either we, that thinke and speake of the most sacred Trinity, as the blessed Fathers in the first Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> taught: or they, who directly crosse them, and by the nouelty of their phrases, doe breed newe, or rather reuiue old heresies against it. Againe, who carry a more holy conceit of God, either they, who vpon light occasion doe rashly denie God to be able to doe that, which they doe not conceiue possible: or we, that teach him to be able to doe tenne thousand thinges, that passe our vnderstanding. Whither they, that affirme God of his owne free choise, to cast away the greater part of men: or we, that defend him to desire the saluation of all men, and not to be willing that any one perish, vnlesse it be through his owne default. Either they, that hold him to be the authour of all euill done in the world, and the Diuell to be but his Minister
<pb n="19" facs="10"/> therein: or we, that maintayne him to be so purely good, that he cannot possibly either concurre to any euill, or so much as once to thinke to doe any euill. Finally, whose opinion of him is better, either ours, that hold him to haue beene so reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in framing of his lawes, that he doth by his grace make them easie to a willing minde: or theirs, that auouch him to haue giuen lawes impossible for the best men to keepe? If some <hi>Protestantes</hi> doe say, we doe not maintayne diuers of these positions. I answere that it is, because they doe yet in part hold with vs, and are not so farre gone, as they doe wholy followe their newe masters: For if they did, then should they embrace all the afore-said damnable positions, being so plainely taught by their principall preachers and teachers. These therefore are to warne my deere Country-men, to looke to it in time; and then (no doubt) but that all such as haue a sufficient care of their saluation, considering maturely whither the current and streame of the newe Gospell carrieth them, will speedily disbarke themselues thence, least at length they be driuen by it, into the bottomelesse gulfe of flat <hi>Atheisme.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And is it any great meruaile, that the common sort of the <hi>Protestantes</hi> fall into so many foule absurdities touching religion, when as the very fountaines, out of which they pretend to take their religion, be so pittifully corrupted? I meane the sacred word of God. Master <hi>Gregory Martin</hi> a <hi>Catholike</hi> man, very skilfull in the learned languages, hath discouered about two hundreth of their corruptions of the very text of Gods word: and after him one Master <hi>Brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> a man of their owne (esteemed to be singulerly seene in the <hi>Hebrewe</hi> and <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue) hath aduertised them of more then eight hundreth faultes there in. And the matter is so euident, that the Kinges Majestie, in that publike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference holden at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> in the first of his raigne, confesseth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe not to haue seene one true translation of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>English;</hi> and that of <hi>Geneua,</hi> which they were wont to esteeme most, to be the worst of all others: and therefore commanded them to goe in hand with a newe translation; about which, fifty of the most learned amongst them in both Vniuersities (as it is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported) haue this three yeares trauailed, and cannot yet hitte vpon, or else not agree vpon, a newe sincere and true translation. Here is a large field offered me to exclaime against such corrupters and deprauers of Gods sacred word: but I will leaue that to some other time, because I haue beene to long already. But what a lamentable case is this! they hold for the most assured piller of their faith, that all matters of saluation must be fished out of the Scriptures, and crie vpon all men to search the Scriptures: and yet are the same Scriptures by themselues so peruersly mangled, that their owne pew-fellowes crie out shame vpon them therefore: wherevnto (if it please you) joyne, that the <hi>Protestantes</hi> haue no assured meanes to be resolued of such doubtes and difficulties, as they shall find in the same word of God. For they must neither trust ancient Father,
<pb n="20" facs="11"/> nor relie vpon the determination, either of nationall or generall Councell; but euery faithfull man (by himselfe) examining the circumstances of the text, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring other like places vnto it together, shall finde out the right meaning of all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure sentences, as they most childishly beare their followers in hand. Briefly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point, a great number of them hauing Gods word corrupted, for the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to their feete; and their owne dimme sight, for their best guide: no maruaile, though they stumble at many difficulties in these high misteries, and fall into very absurd opinions, concerning the principall partes of them.</p>
   <p>Nowe to make vp an euen reckoning with <hi>M. PER. Atheisme,</hi> I must come vnto their diuine seruice and worship of God, the third point that I promised to handle; because he spared not to speake his pleasure of ours. First then, whereas a true, reall, and externall sacrifice, is among all externall workes, the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent seruice that can be done to the diuine Majestie, as shall be proued in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of the sacrifice; which also hath euer since the beginning of the world, beene by the best men practised, to acknowledge and testifie, aswell the soueraigne domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that God hath ouer vs, as our dutifull subjection vnto his almighty goodnesse: the <hi>Protestantes</hi> to make knowne vnto the wiser sorte, that they are not Gods true loyall people, will not vouchsafe to performe to him any such speciall seruice, as to sacrifice in his honour: nay they are fallen so farre out with this principall part of Gods true worship, that they doe in despite of it, powre out most vile reproches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the daylie sacrifice of the <hi>Catholike</hi> Church, which contayneth the blessed body and most pretious bloud of our redeemer <hi>IESVS</hi> Christ. Secondly, of seauen Sacraments (instituted by our Sauiour, both to exhibite honour to God, and to san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie our soules) they doe flatly reject fiue of them: And doe further (as much as in them lieth) extinguish the vertue and efficacy of the other two. For they hold Baptisme not to be the true instrumentall cause of remission of our sinnes, and of the infusion of grace into our soules; but only to be the signe and seale thereof. And in steade of Christes sacred body, really giuen to all <hi>Catholikes</hi> in the Sacrament of the Altar, to their exceeding comfort and dignity, the <hi>Protestantes</hi> must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take vp with a bitte of bread, and with a suppe of wine: a most pittifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, for so heauenly a banquet. They doe daylie feele (and I would to God they had grace to vnderstand) what a want they haue of the Sacrament of Confession, which is the most soueraigne salue of the world, to cure all the deadly and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woundes of the soule. Ah howe caresty doe they daylie heape sinne vpon sinne, and suffer them to lie festring in their breastes euen till death, for lacke of launcing them in season by true and due confession! Besides, at the point of death, when the Diuell is most busie to assault vs, labouring then to make vs his owne for euer, there is amongst them no <hi>anointing of the sicke with</hi> holy <hi>oile</hi> in the name of our Lord, (as <hi>S. Iames</hi> prescribeth) <hi>joyned with the</hi> Priestes <hi>prayer,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. 5. vers. 14.</note> which should <hi>saue the sicke,</hi> and by meanes whereof <hi>his sinnes should be forgiuen, and he lifted
<pb n="21" facs="11"/> vp</hi> by our Lord, and inwardly both greatly comforted and strengthned: these hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly helpes (I say) and many others, which our <hi>Catholike</hi> religion afford vnto all persons, &amp; by which rightly administred, God is highly magnified, are quite banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the <hi>Protestant</hi> territories, and consequently their religion for want of them, is mightily maymed. They haue yet remayning some poore short prayers to be said twise a weeke: for fearing (belike) to make their Ministers surfette of ouer much praying, they will not tie them to any daylie prayers: <hi>Mattins, Euensong,</hi> and other set <hi>houres</hi> they leaue to the <hi>Priestes,</hi> sauing that on the Sabbaoth they solemnely meete together at the Church, to say their seruice, which is a certayne mingle-mangle, translated out of the old <hi>portaise</hi> and <hi>Masse</hi> booke, patched vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with some fewe of their owne inuentions. And though it be but short, yet it is (the Lord he knowes) performed by most of them so slightly, that an indifferent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, would rather judge them to come thither to gase one vpon another, or to common of worldly businesse, then reuerently there to serue God. Nowe as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the place where their diuine seruice is said: if goodly stately Churches, had not beene by men of our religion built to their handes, in what simple cotes (trowe you) would their key-cold deuotion haue beene content to serue their Lord? if one Church or great steeple, by any mishap fall into vtter ruine, a collection throughout all <hi>England</hi> for many yeares together, will not serue to build it vp againe: which maketh men of judgement to perceiue, that their religion is exceeding cold in the setting foreward of good workes, and that it rather tendeth to destruction, then to edification. Againe, whereas our Churches are furnished with many goodly Altars, trimmed vp decently, and garnished with sundry faire and religious pictures, to strike into the beholders a reuerent respect of that place, and to drawe them to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly meditations: theirs haue ordinarely bare walles, hanged with cob-webs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept some of the better sort, which are daubed like Ale-houses, with some broken sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Scripture. Besides, the ancient custome of Christians, being to pray with their faces towardes the Sunne rising, to shewe the hope they haue of a good resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and that by tradition receiued euen from the Apostles, as witnesseth Saint <hi>Basil:</hi> their Ministers in their highest misteries,<note place="margin">De Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto. 27.</note> looke ouer their communion table into the South: to signifie (perhaps) that their spirituall estate is now at the highest, and that in their religion there is no hope of rising towardes heauen, but assurance of declining.</p>
   <p>I may not here omitte, that of late yeares they haue caused the Kinges armes to be set vp in the place, where Christes armes the Crucifix was wont to stand: the which I confesse would haue graced their Church better, if it had beene else where placed. But I hope they will giue me leaue to aske them, howe they durst set vp any such Images in their Churches, as be in that armes. For they haue taught hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, that it is expresly against the second commandement, and a kind of Idolatry, not only to worshippe Images; but also to set them vp in Churches: and yet nowe
<pb n="22" facs="12"/> (as it were) cleane forgetting themselues, they fall into that fault themselues, that they haue so much blamed in others. Neither will it helpe them to say, that they reproued only the setting vp of holy pictures, but not of others. For the second commandement (as they expound it) is aswell against the one as the other, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding generally the making of any kind of Image. And is it not a pittifull blindnesse to thinke, that the pictures of Lions and Liberts doe better become the house of God, then the Image of his owne Sonne, and of his faithfull seruants? And may not simple people thinke, when they see Christes armes cast downe, and the Princes set vp in their place, that there dwell men, who make more account of their Princes honour, then they doe of Christes? And that their meeting in that place (cal it what you wil) is rather to serue their Prince, then to serue Christ. But I haue beene longer in their place of prayer then I thought.</p>
   <p>I come nowe to the men that are elected to serue the Lord there. Be not many of them (for the whole corps I will not touch) such as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> was glad to choose, when he made a Schisme in <hi>Israel:</hi> to wit, <hi>de extremis populi, qui non erant de filijs Leui:</hi> not lawfull successors of the true <hi>Priestes,</hi> but others of the baser sort of the people, and them commonly that are notable, either for ignorance or some other odde quality? and must they not also fill their good patrons handes with some feeling commodity, before they can gette a benefice? And so beginning with simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, lincked with perjurie (for the poore fellowes must neuerthelesse sweare, that they come freely to their benefice) are they not like to proceede on holily? As for the vowe of chastity, the daylie seruice and often fasting, which <hi>Catholike Priests</hi> are bound vnto; they by the sweet liberty of the newe Gospell, doe exchange into sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing themselues with their yoke-fellowes: this of the common sort of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. With their preachers I will not meddle for feare of offence: yet if any desire to knowe howe they behaue themselues in other countries, they may read the censure of a zealous learned preacher, one of their owne compagnions; who amongst many other thinges writeth thus of them.<note place="margin">Menno l. de Christ fide. titul. de fide. mulieris Cananeae</note>
      <hi>When you come to preachers, who bragge that they haue the word of God, you shall find certaine of them manifest liars, others drunkers, some vsurers and foule-mouthed slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, some persecutors and betraiers of harmelesse persons. Howe some of them behaue themselues, and by what meanes they gette their wiues, and what kind of wiues they haue, that I leaue to the Lord and them. They liue an jdle, slouthfull and voluptuous life: by fraude and flattery they feed themselues of the spoiles of</hi> Antichrist (he meaneth the benefices taken from the <hi>Papists) and doe preach just as the earthly and carnall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate desireth to heare, and will permitte,</hi> &amp;c. So much, and not a litle more, speaketh one great Master of the late reformation, concerning his Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bretheren. Are not these goodly lampes of the newe Gospell, and likely persons to be chosen by Christ, to giue light to others, and to reforme the world? But perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
<pb n="23" facs="12"/> they haue in some secret corners, certaine deuout religious soules, who in an austere retired life, doe with continuall teares bewaile the sinnes of the rest, and make incessant sute vnto the Almighty, for a generall pardon of the whole. Would to God they had, but I feare me that they be of their inuisible congregation, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none such to be found amongst them. For those religious houses, which our Ancesters had built for such Godly and vertuous people, who (forsaking both fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mother, all their kinne and acquaintance, and flying from all the pleasures and preferments, which this transitorie world could yeeld them) gaue themselues wholy to the holy exercises of humility, chastity, pouerty, and all sortes of mortification: these Monasteries (I say) and all that professed in them a retired religious life, the <hi>Protestantes</hi> haue beaten downe and banished, and haue not in their places erected any other, for the singuler Godly men or women of their religion; Which doth most euidently argue, that there is in them smale zeale, and rare practise, of any such extraordinary piety and deuotion. Surely it must needes be a strange Christian congregation, that holdeth them for no tollerable members of their common weale, whome Christ specially chooseth to serue him day and night; and by whose holy example and most feruent prayers, all other Christians doe find themselues much edified, and mightily protected. So that briefly, whether you consider the persons that serue God; or the place where he is serued; or the manner of his diuine ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion doth in euery point surpasse the <hi>Protestant</hi> by many degrees. Thus much in answere vnto <hi>Master PERKINS</hi> objection of <hi>Atheisme</hi> against vs, the which I esteemed fittest for this Preface, being a matter of so great moment, and therefore most worthy to be examined and considered of a part, with mature judgement. Nowe to the rest of his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, according to his owne order.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>