<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE ACCOM∣PLISHED MIRROR OF TRVE worth, Sr. T. H. the elder, knight, pro∣fessed fauorer and furtherer of all free∣borne studies: continuance of all happinesse.</title>
           <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1516_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16665</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3571</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1516</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE ACCOM∣PLISHED MIRROR OF TRVE worth, Sr. T. H. the elder, knight, pro∣fessed fauorer and furtherer of all free∣borne studies: continuance of all happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Natures embassie: or, the wilde-mans measures : danced naked by twelue satyres, with sundry others continued in the next section</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitaker, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 263, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE ACCOM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLISHED MIRROR OF TRVE worth, <hi>S</hi>
      <seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>T. H.</hi> the elder, knight, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed fauorer and furtherer of all free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne studies: continuance of all happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the natures of men are cleere peruerted, then it is high time for the <hi>Satyrist</hi> to pen som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which may diuert them from their impietie, and direct them in the course and progresse of Vertue; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which consideration, I, (as the meanest <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalchas</hi> that is able to play vpon an oaten pipe) began presently to describe the nature of <hi>Men,</hi> made so farre good by obseruation, as my weake and immature iudgement could attaine vnto; meaning to make the Poets verse an Axiome: <hi>Scribimus indocti, docti{que} poemata passim.</hi> This thus discussed and weyed, I was long in doubt to whom I should dedicate this vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vintage, rather gleanings, or whō I should
<pb facs="3"/>
flie vnto for sanctuarie, if the sinister Reade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> (as who euer wrote without his <hi>Detractour</hi>) should carpe at my labours. Wherefore standing longer in suspence then the matter required, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> picked forth your selfe, most able to weaue an Apologie for your friends defects. Let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the maleuolent censures of such men whose chiefest eye-sores be other mens workes, and whose choisest content is to blemish them with imperfections, receiue the least countenance from you, whose iudgement by giuing these my labours approbation, shal be a greater argument of their merit, then their partiall censures shall argue their want. <hi>Hiparchion</hi> was graced as well as <hi>Musaeus,</hi> though the best of his measures was but piping to the <hi>Muses.</hi> For the paines of well-affected Authors neuer faile of patrons (at least amongst ingenuous men) to protect thē, of fauorites to second them, or guardians du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their minoritie to foster them. And such is your integritie and true loue to learning, that the meanest sheepheard if the flie for refuge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your shelter, shall be accepted aboue the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his deserts, or meanes of his hopes. For without question, if your acceptance did not far exceed the height and weight of my Discourse, <hi>Quid hic nisi vota supersunt?</hi> there would no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remaine for me, but to fall to my prayers,
<pb facs="3"/>
in beseeching the kind &amp; vnkind Reader (like our penurious pamphlet Orator) to commiserate my Treatise, and in stead of a narration, to make a publike supplication: but being protected by the singular care and prouiding eye of your fauours; <hi>—Maior sum quàm cui potuit fortuna nocere.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue penned this short Discourse, interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with history as well as poesie, for two things summarily, and especially for the first thereof. The first is the iniquitie of this present time wherein we liue: so that <hi>Nature</hi> had either time now to send an <hi>Ambassage</hi> or neuer: since</p>
   <q>
      <note n="*" place="margin">At{que} homines prodigia reru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> maxima.</note> Mulier formosa superne desinit in piscem—</q>
   <p>Such is the course of degenerate <hi>Nature,</hi> that in a conceipt of her selfe she thinks she can mend her selfe by being adorned with vnnaturalized ornaments, which <hi>Nature</hi> neuer apparelled her with. The second reason is the motion of a priuate friend of mine, whose pleasure may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my whole meanes, yea my selfe to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost of my abilitie. These reasons haue I alledged, lest my Preface should seeme naked of Reason, which were ridiculous to the reasonable Reader, and to you especially, whose maturitie in arguments of this Qualitie, hath gained you a deserued Opinion, enabled by Iudgement, of power to counteruaile the censures of others lesse
<pb facs="4"/>
iudicious. Thus tendring you the fruites of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Reading compiled, and in manner digested, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> out of selfe-conceit, but aime to publique goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> intended, Irest. From my studie. May 24.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to dispose
Richard Brathwayt.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>