<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>N., Ber.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1523_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16798</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1523</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>N., Ber.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules immortall crowne : consisting of seauen glorious graces. 1. Vertue. 2. Wisedome. 3. Loue. 4. Constancie. 5. Patience. 6. Humilitie. 7. Infinitenes. Deuided into seauen dayes workes. And dedicated to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Burton, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>YOu that haue a heart to lift your eies aboue
your head, and haue not buried your soule
in the sinke of sinne, take a little time to
reade ouer this little Tract, where if ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
may inuite you, wisedome may woe you, loue
may draw you, constancie may content you, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
may perswade you, or humility may entreate
you, you shall not passe without your paiment, and
make a profit of your expence: the villaine can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
taste it, the foole vnderstand it, the hatefull
not loue it, nor the inconstant commend it, the
impatient endure it, nor the proud regard it: but
I hope the best will alow it, and to thē I only leaue
it, who can best iudge of it, will iudiciously peruse
it, and accordingly esteeme it; there is no state
taxed in it, no person abused by it, none that reade
it, but may haue good of it, and for the good of all
men I haue done it. The youthfull may learne,
and the aged consider what is most necessarie for
the soules comfort, the rich may finde treasure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
their wealth, and the poore, reliefe in their
miserie: in sume, to auoid tediousnes, I hope you
shall see Vertue truly honoured, Wisedome truly
praised, Loue truly described, Constancie truly
<pb facs="5"/>
commended, Patience truly proued, and God in
all, truly glorified: to the tuition of whose grace,
in hearty praier for your happines, that you may
seeke it only in his goodnes: I leaue you for this
time, and for euer till I better know you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend as I
finde cause,
BER. N. <hi>Gent.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>