<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Errata]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1536_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20752</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7133</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1536</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Errata]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian vvarfare : Wherein is first generally shewed the malice, power and politike stratagems of the spirituall enemies of our saluation, Sathan and his assistants the world and the flesh; with the meanes also whereby the Christian may vvithstand and defeate them. And afterwards more speciallie their particvlar temptations, against the seuerall causes and meanes of our saluation, whereby on the one side they allure vs to security and presumption, and on the other side, draw vs to doubting and desperation, are expressed and answered. Written especially for their sakes who are exercised in the spirituall conflict of temptations, and are afflicted in conscience in the sight and sense of their sinnes. By I. Dovvname preacher of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Downame, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 272, 271-366, 371-676, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="349"/>
   <p>Christian Reader, because there was some haste required in printing of this booke, part thereof from pag. <hi>371</hi> to pag. <hi>578</hi> was committed to another Printer, who wanting a Corrector suffred these faults to escape which are materiall. As for others which are apparant at the first view, I haue left vnobserued.</p>
   <p>
      <label>THE ERRATA.</label>
   </p>
   <p>Pag. 25. line 14. reade must needes be. pag. 48 l. 13. r. anothers, p. 371. l. 4. r. fleshy. p. 375. l. 6. r. repeateth. p. 378. l. 13 r. thinke ye. p. 391. l. 30. r. selues. p. 396. l. 5. r. all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company. p. 399. l. 29. r. goodly shewes. l. 34. r. health. p. 405. l. 6. r. also haue them. p. 408. l. 23. r. mocke repentance. p. 409. l 3. r. doe not. l. 12. r. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. l. 14. r. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. p. 412. r. he freeth those. p. 418. l. 4. r. Ho euery. l. 18. r. and that he will. l. 24. r. and with all his heart desireth to be. p. 420. l 4, 5. r is properly to God. p. 425. l. 24. r. (as of himself vnwilling) l. 27. r. hainous, no more then. p. 427. l 5. r. mercies. The. l. 27. r. hainous, no more then p 438. l. 29. r and rest. p. 440. l. 18. r. Lord mercie. p. 442. l 22. r. Ho euery p. 446. l 31. r. if when we were p. 449. l. 10. r. that he who for. l. 30. r. of his bountie. p 451 l. 27. r. honour and glorie. p. 455. l. 6. r. and now he. p. 463. l. 30. r. true in thesi, yet false in hypothesi. p. 473. l. 26. r. powerfully. l. 33. ministerie. p. 474. l. 4. r. ministerie. p. 475. l. 22. r. and meere cluill. p. 477. l. 10. r. and though. l. 13. r. entertaine it. p. 479. l 32. r. the hond of this. lin. last r. works of sanctification. p. 481. l. 10. r. so the branches. p. 484. l. 5. r. it seareth. p. 486. l. 4. r. seared l. 29. r. sight and feeling. p. 487. l. 24. r. with an hard. p. 501. l. 29. r. in God at al. p. 507. l. 34. r. may seeme to be. p. 510. l. 30. r. truly sorie. l. 36. r. the case. p. 514. l. 25. r. destruction, but. p. 522. l. 1. r. vanquished. l. 10. r. striuing. p. 526. l. 8. r. similitudes. l. 19. r. moueth and p. 531. l. 20. r. the 5 verse. p. 538. l. 10. r. vp vntill it. l. 19. r. hauing any. p. 540. l. 7. r. more strong. p. 553. l. 29. r. almes aswell as. l. 33. r. strong. Our. p. 557. l. 9. r. seene him? p. 566. l. 13. r. one oblation lin. 21. r. where ho p. 569. l. 7. r. and iudged lin. 8.1. his owne. p. 571. l. 26. r. imaginarie. p. 574. l. 7. r. Apostle. p. 578. l. 19. r. necessarily.</p>
   <pb facs="350"/>
   <pb facs="350"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="351"/>
   <pb facs="351"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="352"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="352"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="353"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="353"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="354"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="354"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="355"/>
   <pb facs="357"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="358"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="358"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="359"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="359"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="360"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="360"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="361"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="361"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="362"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="1" facs="362"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="2" facs="363"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="3" facs="363"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="4" facs="364"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="5" facs="364"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="6" facs="365"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="7" facs="365"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="8" facs="366"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="9" facs="366"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>