<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults in the text.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1550_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18397</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4960</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1550</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults in the text.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the vocation of bishops, and other ecclesiasticall ministers : Prouing the ministers of the pretended reformed churches in generall, to haue no calling; against Monsieur du Plessis, and Mr. Doctour Feild: and in particuler the pretended bishops in England, to be no true bishops. Against Mr. Mason. By Anth. Champ. p. and D. of Sorbonne</title>
                 <author>Champney, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 96, 95-326, 4 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="174"/>
   <p>
      <hi>COurteous Reader, the aùthors absence from the presse hauing caused diuers escapes in the print, be pleased to vse the obseruations following, for the correction of the most and chiefest of them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Page 14. the three first lines are to be read as a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall note, and not as pertayning to the text.</p>
   <p>pag. 217. is the deposition of Abiather by Salomon spoken of, which by errour is repeated againe pag. 238.</p>
   <p>For the rest note, that the fault is not expressed in this table, but the correction onlie, the letter r. signifyng, <hi>Reade,</hi> the letter. e. the number of lines, not from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, but from the end of the page.</p>
   <p>The Ciphers of the pages from 89. vnto 100. are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, and 196. and 266. and 315.</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>Faults in the text.</head>
      <p>PAge 5. lin. from. the end 7. r. we will wittinglie. p. 6. l. 1. put out, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. p. 7. l. 7. e. r. institution. p. 10. l. 3. r. prosecuted, pag. 13. l. 10. r. Ministerie. p. 16. l. 16 e. wanteth a full point. before (we) p 18. l. 1. n. ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were. p. 25. l. 13. e. r. how seuere. p. 32. l. 9. e. put out (no). p. 34. l. 23. r. Roman. p. 35. l. 8. e. r. easilie. p. 38. l. 14. e. r. must needes do, that, p. 39. l. 13. e. r. these. p. 47. l. 5. r. alwaies ioyned. p. 48. l. 6. r. condigne. p. 50. l. 19. r. what. p. 50. l. 3. e. r. true. p. 53. l. 5. r. thrust. p. 53. l. 9. r. then thy. p. 55. l. 6. e. r. ordaine. p. 56. l. 18. e. put out (as). p. 57. l. 5. e. r. now. p. 59 l. 13. r. nor take. p. 67. l. 3. e. r. Arius. p. 73. l. 7. r. hath heard. p. 74. l. 4. r. 1500. yeares. p. 77. l. 15. e. r. or gouernement. p. 86. l. 17. e. r. seeing. p. 93. l. 6. e. r. I wis. l 3. r. doth quite. p. 94. l. 1. r. source. p. 97. l. 7. r. either. p. 97. l. 3. e. r. and. therfore. p. 107. l. 7. r. not interrupted. p. 111. l. 4. r. The reason. p. 115. l. 11. e. r. separated from. p. 116. l. 17. r. M. Mason, and so euer after. p. 116. l. 9. e. r. now are. p. 132. l. 4. r. or brand. p. 156. l. 15. r. the whole. p. 159. l. 5. r. do consist. p. 161. l. 20. r. was euer. p. 161. l. 3. e r. Richard Shilders. p. 162. l. 9. r. teacheth that. p. 165. l. 9. put out (in their doctrine) p. 169. l. 4. r. iudge Dyar. p. 171. l. 10. r. insuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. p. 172. l. 12. e. r. presumptuous law. p. 173. l. 9. r. further. p. 173. l. 13. e. r. and the manner. p. 174. l. 9 e. r. anie quirke. p. 175. l. 14. e. r. th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nke it. p. 176. l. 13. r. against her. p. 177. l. 16. r not leaue. l. 8 e. after (speake) want these words (more by and by, and namelie when we come to speake) p. 183. l. 8. r. began to be. p. 187. l. 7. e. r. Poynet. p. 189. l. 1. r. puritie of the gospell. p. 191. l. 2. e. r. one halfe proofe. p. 196. l. 6. r. he had alreadie. p. 203. l. 11. r. sees. l. 14. r. Coxe. l. 2. e. r. bring one out. p. 207. l. 18. e. r. may not. p. 213. l. 3. e. r. condemned. p. 217. l. 4. e. r. I wil remit the reader to the Chapter following and to the last Chapter. p. 223. l. 11. e, r, he can.
<pb facs="175"/> p. 236. l. 7. e. r. hostes. p. 237. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. being not able. l. 14. r. lawfull vse. p. 24<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> l. 11. r. how farre the power of the keies. p. 253. l. 5. e. r. is also true. p. 26<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. l. 21. r. antithesis. p. 262. l. 10. e. r. law written, but also to the Gentiles in the law of nature. p. 264. l. 17. e. r. and owes. p. 265. l. 4. e. r. doth euidentlie. p. 266, l, 15. r. at last. p. 267. l. 17. r. are like l. 15. e. r. there are. p. 270. l. 15. e. r. a torne coate. p. 271. l. 2. e. r. thother reproued. p. 272. l. 20. r. being thus vnderstood. l. 15. e. put out (conformitie with true reason) l. 2. e. r. his last supper. p. 280. l. 9. r. letter S. l. 11. r. incorrupt antiquitie. p. 283. l. 6. r. ijs qui, l. 15. e. r. 1270. yeares. l. 1. e. r. rogamns te. p. 286. l. 6. r. past. l. 12. r. &amp; diuinitati. p. 290. l. 7. e. r. orantes. p. 292. l. 15. r. tanta fidelium. p. 310. l. 9. r. which waie. p. 311. l. 13. e. r. in the strict, p. 314. l. 16. r. collation, p. 316. l. 9. r. her dominions, l. 19. e. r. to giue vnto her, p. 317. l. 11. r. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles agreed vpon in the conuocation. p. 323. l. 14. r. make mine.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>Faults in the margent.</head>
      <p>PAg. 71. r q. Armenor. ibidem for. g. 9. r. q. 9. p. 78. in the citation of Illiricus r. 730. 731. p. 116. r. Ezechiel. 13. 11. p. 142. r. 81. p. 143. r. act. 1. p. 213. r. orat. ad ciues timore epist. 32. p. 234. r. is from god but what then? will it follow that humane reason. p. 235. r.. 22. p. 248. r. 209. p. 273. wanteth the quotation of Ireneus. l. 4. C. 32. p. 283. r. orat. p. 291. adde the quotation of S. Augustine ser. 32. in verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> apostoli ad Thessalonicenses. p. 293. r. vnanswerable apologie. p. 297. r. ad Hebr. 7, sect. 6.</p>
      <pb facs="175"/>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>