<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all them which are called and sanctified of God the Father, and returned to Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Clifton, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1572_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19033</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5450</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1572</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all them which are called and sanctified of God the Father, and returned to Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Clifton, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The plea for infants and elder people, concerning their baptisme, or, A processe of the passages between M. Iohn Smyth and Richard Clyfton : wherein, first is proved, that the baptising of infants of beleevers, is an ordinance of God, secondly, that the rebaptising of such as have been formerly baptised in the apostate churches of Christians, is utterly unlawful, also, the reasons and objects to the contrarie, answered : divided into two principal heads, I. Of the first position, concerning the baptising of infants, II. Of the second position, concerning the rebaptising of elder people</title>
                 <author>Clyfton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 226 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all them which are called and sanctified of God the Father, and returned to Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et it not seem strange (deare brethren) neyther cause a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to distast the right wayes of the Lord, because from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs some have departed from the fayth, and are turned after errors: For the holy Ghost hath foretold vs▪ that even from amongst our selves, there should mē arise speaking perverse things to draw Disciples after thē, Act. 20. 30. And with such, the primitiue Apostolike Churches were greatly molested, and that whylest the Apostles were living. Iohn doth also witnesse that in his tyme there were many Antichrists. <hi>they went</hi> (sayth he) <hi>out from us. 1. Ioh. 2. 18. 19.</hi> meaning even out of the bosome of the Church. And our Saviour sayth, <hi>many false Prophets shall arise and deceive many. Mat. 24. 11.</hi> And Peter saith, <hi>many shall follow their damnable wayes, 2 Pet. 2. 2.</hi> All which may teach vs not to be offended when the like doth befall to the Churches in our times: Seing it is incident to Gods people, not onely to be persecuted by enemies without, but also greived with false brethren, that under pretence of more sinceritie of religion, will seek to destroy the faith, being the very instruments of Satan, whom he subborneth to deceive the unstable and to corrupt their minds from the simplicitie that is in Christ. 2. Cor. 11. 3. These things being considered, it behoveth us to mind the exhortations and warnings given by the Apostles of Christ, that is, <hi>to stand fast and keep the instructions which we have been taught. 2 Thes. 2. 15. And not to beleeve every spirit, but to trie the spirits whether they be of God or no: for many false Prophets are gone into the world, 1 Ioh. 4. 1.</hi> And the rather it stands vs the more upon to take heed to our selves and be admonished by the word of the Lord, because, as the Divil on the one hand, prevayleth in these our times, by worldly arguments, of profite, pleasure and the like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, to keep many back from walking in the right wayes of God: So on the other hand, (under glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="2"/> shewes of pretended holynes) hath he deceaved many, and drawne them into damnable heresies, labouring to poyson the fountaines of whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some doctrine, reveiled in these last dayes vnto his Church: And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> God in mercie hath preached vnto vs the Gospel (that formerly he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eached to Abraham our father, and by the Apostles vnto both Iewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d Gentiles) that a long time hath bene greatly obscured through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oggy mists of popish doctrines, now seeketh to spoile the church of Christ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ereof altogether, by that detestable heresie of Anabaptisme, which as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hath overspread many places, to the great annoyance of the people of God: So (as a leprosie) hath it at this present infected some of our owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntryemen, who are not onely taynted therewith, but have revolted frō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e faith, and taken vpon them the profession thereof, and published their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reticall opinions in our owne language. For there is lately set forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>rtayne Treatise of theirs, intituled, <hi>The Character of the Beast,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>c. A title as it is most blasphemous (being understood of the baptising <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f infants) so is the book it self ful of many dangerous errours, wherwith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he simple may easily be deceaved. And seing the same book is sent over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>to our own country, and is spread abroad into the hands of many▪ I have thought good also, to give warning to all that loves the Lord Iesus and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e carefull of their own salvation, to take heed therof. And for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd have published this Treatise following, contayning a Processe of the Passages between Mr. Smyth (the author of that book) and me, wherin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l (whose eies it shal please God to open) may see the notable sleights of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>han by this his instrument, who first, sought to disgrace the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures translated, and to cast them out of Gods worship, and now in his <hi>Charcter,</hi> to distroy the covenant of grace (which of old was given to Abraham including the children with the parents,) and to bring in a new Gospel that excludes the children of the faythfull both frō the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and baptism the seale therof. I had no purpose of publishing these my writings, had not the occasion bene offered by Mr. Smyth in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our former private Passages: but so having done, I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>no lesse, then to publish these my labours also, vnles I should have bene iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the truth.
<pb facs="3"/> Seing I had received the copie of Mr Smythes book in written hand, which he purposely sent vnto me, as a reply to my former answer, to his two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptistical Positions, whereunto I had almost finished this my second answer before his book was printed. Otherwise (if I had not bene so far interessed therein) I should haue bene glad if this work had been taken in hand by others more sufficient then my self. But thus God having disposed to imploy me in this part of his service at this present: I shall desire the godly Reader, to accept this my small endeavours, proceeding from an hart, earnestly striving to mainteyne that faith, which was once given unto the Sainsts and to supply my weaknes with his better labours, as there shalbe cause. And withall to take notice, that I have here set downe the whol Passages (touching this controversie) between Mr Smyth and me. First, his Positions with the Reasons annexed. 2. My answer therevnto written in private vnto him, which (without my knowledge) he published together with his reply, committing that against me therein, which he condemneth in Mr Barnard against himself. Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels in the epistle to the Reader. Thirdly, the Summe of his Reply. And lastly, my Answer therevnto. So that the Reader may see how these thinges have (from the beginning) passed between vs. The Lord give vs to discerne the truth from falsehood, to look to our selves that we loose not the things which we have done, but that we may receive a ful reward. And now unto him that is able to keep vs that we fall not, &amp; to present vs faultlesse before the presence of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with ioye: To God onely our Saviour be glorie and Maiestie, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and power, both now and ever.</p>
   <closer>Amen.
<signed>Richard Clifton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>