<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ANSWER TO Mr SMYTHES Epistle to the Reader, which he hath directed,</title>
           <author>Clifton, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1572_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19033</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5450</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1572</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ANSWER TO Mr SMYTHES Epistle to the Reader, which he hath directed,</title>
                 <author>Clifton, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The plea for infants and elder people, concerning their baptisme, or, A processe of the passages between M. Iohn Smyth and Richard Clyfton : wherein, first is proved, that the baptising of infants of beleevers, is an ordinance of God, secondly, that the rebaptising of such as have been formerly baptised in the apostate churches of Christians, is utterly unlawful, also, the reasons and objects to the contrarie, answered : divided into two principal heads, I. Of the first position, concerning the baptising of infants, II. Of the second position, concerning the rebaptising of elder people</title>
                 <author>Clyfton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 226 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="answer_to_Mr_Smythe">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>AN ANSWER TO Mr SMYTHES Epistle to the Reader, which he hath directed,</head>
   <argument>
      <p>To every one that loveth the truth in sincerity.</p>
   </argument>
   <p>BY these wordes, it seemeth Mr Smyth would intimate, that his care is to mainteyne the truth, and that in sinceritie he loveth the same, whereas in deed, he hath destroyed the faith, is become an enemy to the covenant of grace, &amp; a perverter of the right wayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f the Lord: and withall so confident in defence of his heresies, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es to challendge a combate with <hi>all the Separation:</hi> belike to feare men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith great words, and to boast with Rabsake, as if his forces were invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ble: But what they are it wil appeare in this discourse following.</p>
   <p>In the Epistle it self, first Mr Smyth seemeth to excuse their mutabilitie in Religiō, saying: <hi>It may be thought most strange that a man should oft times change <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s religion, and it cannot be accounted a commendable qualitie in any man to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ny alterations, &amp;c. this must needs be true (and we confesse it) if one condition be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>itted, that the Religion which a man changeth be the truth, for otherwise to change <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>lse religion, is commendable, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But Mr Smyth and his company have changed a true Religion for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alse, and therefore that can be no commendable qualitie in them: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uch inconstant persons (as himself saith) <hi>cannot escape the deserved imputation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>folly or weaknes of iudgement therein.</hi> Thus out of his owne mouth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ouncing sentēce against himself: For that alteratiō of him &amp; his cōpany, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s not frō falshood to truth, but the leaving of the truth (which formerly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hey professed) &amp; a taking up of error after error: first calling into question, whether the scriptures being translated into other tongues, were not the writings of men. Differenc. pag. 10. Then casting the reading of them out of the worship of God, affirming that there is <hi>no better warrant to bring tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations of Scripture into the Church, and to read them as parts and helps of worship, then to bring in expositions, paraphrasts and sermons vpon the Scripture, seing all these are equally humane in respect of the worke, equally divine in respect of the matter they handle. Differ: pag.</hi> 10. And for the same cause, separated themselves from other Churches that did read and vse the same in their publike meetings. After this, they dissolved their Church (which before vvas conioyned in the
<pb facs="4"/> fellowship of the Gospel &amp; profession of the true fayth) &amp; Mr. Smyth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pastor thereof, gave over his office, as did also the Deacons, and devised to enter a new communion by renouncing their former baptisme, and taking upon them an other, of mans invention, bringing in an other Gospel, besides that which was preached to Abraham, Gen. 12, 3, &amp; 17. 7. &amp;c. Gal. 3, 8. And now againe, many of this new communion have se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated themselves from the rest, holding the error about the incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f this new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aptised cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>union <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ayning as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is reported <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. persons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l the rest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e runne in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rors.</note> of Christ. An other sort are excommunicate, namely M. Smyth &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers with him, for holding (as it is reported by some that were of them) that their new washed companie is no true church, and that there cannot be in a church the administratiō of baptisme &amp; other ordinances of Christ, without Officers, contrarie to his former judgment, practise &amp; writings, &amp; yet resteth not but is inquiring after a new way of walking, (as the same persons affirme) breeding more errors, as is strongly suspected, and by his manuscripts partly appeares. Whereby it is manifest, that these men can not cleare themselves of instabilitie &amp; changeablenes in Religion, but are guilty of that inconstancie that is worthy reproof and damnable.</p>
   <p>Further he sayth, <hi>For a man of a Turke to become a Jew, of a Iew a Papist, of a Papist a Protestant, are al commendable changes &amp;c. so that not to change religion is evil simplie: &amp; therefore that we should fal from Puritanisme to Brownisme, and from Brownisme to true christian baptisme, is not simply evil in it self, except it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that we have fallen from the true religion, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Here Mr. Smyth would make the world beleeve (as it is the manner of al heretikes) that their alterations were goings forward to further truthes, and therefore commendable. But if their <hi>true Christian baptisme,</hi> (whereof they boast) prove a notable heresie, (as it is indeed, &amp; in this Treatise is proved) then his comparison holds not, but rather their estate is like to those in 1 Tim. 1, 19. <hi>that put away fayth &amp; a good conscience, and as concerning fayth, have made shipwrack.</hi> And that <hi>bring in damnable heresies. 2 Pet. 2. 1. &amp;c.</hi> denying the covenant of grace, and the lawful use of the scriptures, &amp;c. <hi>to bring upon themselves swift damnation,</hi> if God give them not speedy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
   <p>Next M. Smyth setts down the questions controverted, and hereafter answered, affirming that this controversie is between them and the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas he might as well have sayd, betweene them and all christian churches, that have been or are at this day: for it is not we alone that
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ndemne these their heresies, but both the ancient and moderne Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, and vvriters in all ages, (as vvith one consent) have opposed against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>em.</p>
   <p>But where he pretends the publishing of this controversy, to be for <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ay of God the manifesting of the truth to our owne nation, and the destruction of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>man of sinne,</hi> he geveth vs to mynd how Satan hath bewitched his soule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> beleeve that such can be the effects of his heritical opinions. It is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ollicy of the Divil to propound glorious ends, to such as he seduceth, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Evah and others, &amp; teacheth his Ministers to do the like, that by fayre &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>attring speeches, and shewes of good, they might more easily deceave the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mple. And therfore seing we are forwarned that there shalbe false Teachers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mongst vs, which privily shal bring in damnable heresies, it behoveth vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o mynd the counsel of the Apostles, to try the spirits, 1. Ioh. 4. 1. And not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o be caryed about with every wynd of doctrine. Ephe. 4. 14.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now happely,</hi> (sayth Mr. Smyth,) <hi>some man wil wish that the controversy had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> with the Rabbies of the Separation, and not with Mr Clyfton, whome they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>iate to be a weake man, vnable to deale in so great a controversy: wel, let the Reader take notice that though it be Mr Clyftons pen, yet it is not onely Mr Clyftons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>se &amp; def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nce, but his allegatiōs &amp; Reasons are the best plea of the greatest Rabbies thē <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>elves, And if they can say better, they may now speake, for by publishing answere to theire Reasons, we do chalendge al the separation in speciall to the combate.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Challenger would fayne have the world to take notice, that he deales with an adversary that is too weak to try out this controversy with him, &amp; so to forestall mens judgments before ever they come to the reading of my answere. And because he would not be seene to be the Author himselfe of my disgrace, he imputeth this report to the Rabbies of the Separation (as it pleaseth him in his taunting maner to terme them) who (I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded) are guiltles thereof. But if any had so sayd vnto him in private, yet doth he in publishing the same, breake the bounds of love. For myne owne parte, whether any have so spoken or not, it shal not offend me, I knowe the Lord measureth his guiftes to every one as he wil. 1 Cor. 12. 8.—11. I praise God for that I have, and do not envy, but reioyce in the graces that God bestoweth vpon others, and pray that they may vse them to his glory, and to edification. Notwithstanding though Mr Smyth thinke me to weake to incounter with him, yet the Lord assisting me, I meane not for all these his disgraceful speeches, to yeeld him the cause, or
<pb facs="5"/> give back one foot from the defence thereof, knowing that the truth which I contend for: wil discover and convince his damnable errors: the which though he set a glorious shew vpon (as a marchant of false wares) by misapplying of Scriptures: yet wil the falsehood of them appeare, to al such whose eies God shal open, to discerne between the truth and lyes. Moreover if I in my weaknes, make to appeare how vnconscionably &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly Mr Smyth dealeth against the truth: his glorious boasting and Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine valour, will have the more disgrace, then if he had dealt with men of greater guifts: and God shall have the greater glorie, to foyl such a warlike Champion with weak and base meanes.</p>
   <p>As for my allegations and reasons which he saith, <hi>are the best plea of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Rabbies, &amp;c.</hi> herein he both taxeth me and wrongeth them, me, as if I had bene but their pen man in my former answer; them, in saying my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are their best plee, whereas he hath had neither conference with them, by speeches or writing about these matters, save onely with Mr Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binson. And therefore so to speak without triall, bewrayes but the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his spirit against them. Thus Mr Smyth preparing way for his great challendge, by pretending mine insufficiencie, calles forth the Rabbies (as he termes them) to speak, challendging the whol Separation to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: wheras a wise man would haue spared such speaches vntil he had seen the issue of his combate, already attempted: and not thus to provoke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, until he had greater likelihood of victorie. As for those reverend men whom now he calles vpō for better, <hi>if they can say better,</hi> they haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy sayd and written so much against his errors, as I am assured he wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to answer, and when it pleaseth him to reply, (if there be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion) I doubt not but as they have done, so the Lord will inable them to batter downe with spiritual weapons, his greatest forces, that he shalbe able to raise against the truth.</p>
   <p>And whereas Mr Smyth seemeth to insinuate, that by his answering of my reasons, he hath answered theirs, herein he is deceaved: for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in my former answer, (be they what they are,) I acknowledge for mine own, (though written unto him without any purpose of publishing) if ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore weaknes be found in them, let it be imputed vnto me, and neither to our Teachers, (who had no hand in setting downe thereof) nor yet to the truth it self. As for his challenging of the whole Separation, and other his intemperate speaches in his epistle, they bewray in him a malicious hart
<pb facs="5"/> against our poore Church,) and puft vp with too loftie a conceit of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> strength. Did ever any of the Prophets or servants of God thus chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ge a combate with the Lords people? in deed such braving speeches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>eeded from Goliath, 1 Sam. 17. 10. that defied the whol hoast of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>; and from Rabsake. 2. King. 18. 23-25. against the Iewes: But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>as never heard that an Israelite professing the religion of God, vsed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> proud chalendges, as this man doth.</p>
   <p>I pray you Mr. Smyth, wherein hath the separation offended you, or my wise wronged you, that you desyre rather to quarrel with them, then with other Churches holding the same truth in this thing, agaynst you? To the Elders and brethren were you most welcome, and glad they were of you, so long as you walked in the fayth with them. Why is it that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e become their adversary? is it because they have rejected you, and your company for your errors, which you wilfully mayntayne? Alas, they must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o it, vnles they would become vnfaythful to God.</p>
   <p>Next after this Chalendge, Mr. Smyth chargeth the separation with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> constitution, ministery, worship and government, saying.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Be it knowen to all the Separation, that we account them in respect of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>tion, to be as very an harlot, as eyther her mother England, or her grandmother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> is. And although we held her a true church in our ignorance, yet now being better informed &amp;c. we protest agaynst her as wel for her false constitution, as for her false Ministery, worship and goverment &amp;c. the false constitution is of infants baptised.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Concerning the constitutiō of a Church we do not hold that any visible Church can stand onely of infants, neyther that their baptisme doth geve the being thereof 1. Seing there can be no baptising of infants, where there are not first Elder people, with whome they come vnder the covenant of God 2. Baptism is an other thing divers from the Church, Ephe. 4. 4. 5. and it maketh none to be the people of God, onely it sealeth vp to be his people, them that are so formerly by vertue of his covenant. 3. Els Turkes or Indians professing the Popish Religion being baptized, should be a true Church (for Mr. Smyth holdeth the <note n="†" place="margin">Charact. pag. 51.</note> baptism of such to be true bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, if so they confesse their fayth &amp; sinns) 4. Then circumcision should have made the Sichemites a true Church (for that which baptism can doe now in constituting of a Church, circumcisiō could do then) wherfore I say, baptism is an ordinance of Christ geven to his Church to seale vp his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to his people: but is not that whol essential constitutiō therof. And
<pb facs="6"/> therefore our baptizing of infants (if it were admitted to be vnlawful) can not make the constitution of our Church to be false, much les being the commaundement of the Lord, can it so doo. And thus Mr. Smyth fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the first poynt of his charge. As for the other things he chargeth vs withall, shall receave answere in their due place.</p>
   <p>But here further he proceedeth to affirme. <hi>That no man can separate from England, as from a false Church, except he also do separate from the baptisme of Engl. &amp;c.</hi> Wherevnto he may be answered, that it wil not follow, that they which separate from a Church standing in apostasie, or sinne, must se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the baptism therein receaved, or yet from any other of Gods ordinances there retayned. We are commaunded to forsake the whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Babylon, Apoc. 18. 4. but not to seperate from any ordinance of Christ that is found therein, save onely from the polutions thereof. Yea Mr. Smyth cannot deny, that a Church standing in Apostasy, is to be sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from, when the baptism therein received (if it be of such as confesse their fayth and sins) is still to be retayned, for such baptism, (sayth he) <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> true Baptism,</hi> though administred by Antichristians, Character p. 51. 2. Those Israelits that separated from Ieroboams Church (which stood in Apostasy) &amp; went to Ierusalē 2. Cor. 30. 11. did not separate frō their circumcisiō ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in receaved: No more are we from our baptisme, as afterward is proved. As for his Reason.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>That the baptism of England cannot be true and to be reteayned, and the Church of England false and to be rejected &amp;c.</hi> It is but as if he should say, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision of Israell cannot be true and to be reteyned, and the Church of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell false and to be rejected, I speake of Israell being in Apostacy. And therefore thus I answere vnto it, that baptism retayned in Rome and so in all Apostate Churches▪ is baptism, and is not to be repeated, as in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of this Treatise, is proved. And seing Mr. Smyth holdeth there<note place="margin">Character. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ag. 51.</note> may be † true baptism in an Apostate Church if they confesse their fayth, doth not he crosse himself here to say, <hi>neyther can the Church of England possibly be false, except the baptism be false?</hi> Now if true baptism may be in an apostate Church as he affirmeth, then a Church may be false (that is apostate) &amp; not baptism, by his owne reasoning. Yet this man chargeth vs with contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, vz. to say, <hi>England hath a false constitution, Engl. hath a true baptism.</hi> We hold baptism so to be true in an apostate church, as circumcisiō was in the
<pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ate Church of Israel, &amp; otherwise we do not affirm. Now concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ptising of infants, Mr. Sm. thus proceedeth, saying, <hi>It seemeth to vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vnreasonable heresy, of all Antichristianism, for considering what baptism is: An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> is no more capable of baptism then is any vnreasonable, or insensible creature.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d then addeth 3. Reasons agaynst it, 1. from his owne description baptism, saying: <hi>baptism is not the washing with water, but it is the baptism of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>it, the confession of the mouth, and washing with water, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These blasphemous speeches, against the ordinance of Christ bewrayeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f what spirit this man is: Gods ordinance is a <hi>most vnreasonable heresie</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im, yea the <hi>most vnreasonable of all Antichristianisme.</hi> Thus iustifying all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dolatries of the Papists and their detestable heresies in comparison of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tising of infants. Besides his odious and blasphemous comparison, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rming <hi>Infants no more capable of baptisme, then the vnreasonable and insensible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>ures.</hi> So that in his judgement, a horse, yea a block may aswell be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aptised, as the children of the Church, whom the Lord of his free grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ceiveth together with their parents, to be his by an everlasting covenant, Gen. 17. 7. and therefore are holy, and capable of the blessing of Christ, 1 Cor. 7. 14. Ier. 1. 5. Luk. 1. 15. Mark. 10. 16. as hereafter is sufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ved. And therefore to compare these infants with vnreasonable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensible creatures, as touching the participation of Baptisme, argueth the authour of such comparisons, to be void of spiritual sense and reason, and more to follow the corruption of his own hart in hatred against the truth, then to mind what he affirmeth.</p>
   <p>Concerning his description of Baptisme and those Scriptures which he quoteth for proof thereof, see them answered hereafter, pag. 94. where I have shewed, 1. that the baptisme of the Spirit, is no part of that outward Ceremonie of baptisme that is administred by man, but is the inward work of the spirit in the elect of God. 2. That the confession of faith &amp; of sinns, is no part of the Sacrament of Baptisme: seing the confession of sinns, is so often to be repeated, as we transgresse against the Lord, &amp; likewise of faith, as we have occasion administred vnto us. And therefore baptisme, which is given to be the seale of Gods covenant to his Church, is the baptising of the faithful and their seed with water, into the name of the father, and of the sonne and of the holy Ghost. Mat. 3. 11. with Mat. 28. 19. &amp; of this, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are capable.
<pb facs="7"/> neyther is their baptisme <hi>folly,</hi> (as Mr Smyth sayth) but it wil prove his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make mans confession a part of the Sacrament, which oftentymes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hypocrical, (as it was in S. Magus) &amp; to shut out of Gods covenant who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the Lord hath accepted. And it wil prove his folly to denye baptisme to infants, because they cānot performe such actions, as in other respects are required of the elder sort that are to be baptised, who also not having trās<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed in like manner, therefore need not so to confesse. And it wil prove his folly, to deny that an infant can be baptised with the spirit: for so to say, is to deny, that an infant can be saved. But of these things hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
   <p>His 2. Reason is taken from Iohns baptisme, framed thus.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Iohns baptisme was the baptisme of repentance. Infants have not Repentance, and therefore can not have the baptisme of Repentance.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To this Argument I answer thus, 1. That repentance is required of such as have actually transgressed, not as the proper cause of baptisme, but as a necessarie fruit of fayth, &amp; condition of the Gospel required of them, that being of yeares are to be received into the church: whether before or since Christs coming. But of the infants of the faythful, whether of those that are newly received into the church, or of beleevers borne in the church, it is not so. Ergo &amp;c.</p>
   <p>2. Repentance was not required of the infants of the Iewes before they were circumcised: no more is it to be required of our infants before bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, these two Sacraments being the same in use.</p>
   <p>3. If <hi>Baptisme of repentance,</hi> be understood onely of the tyme past, &amp; not of the tyme to come, then is that a false exposition of Iohns baptisme. For as he taught that those that came to be baptised should repent: so also his baptisme did preach a continual dying to sinne, or practise of repentance▪ al our life long, Rom. 6. 4. And therefore though children cannot repent of actual sinne, which they are not to do, they having not committed the same: yet is their baptisme the baptisme of repentance: seeing it preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth continual mortification &amp; repentance to the receivers thereof, which is one true use of baptisme.</p>
   <p>His third reason is from the testimonie of Tertullian &amp; Eusebius. The words of Tertullian, (as Mr, Sm. himself hath englished them) are these.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Therfore to deferre &amp; not to hasten baptisme, is more profitable for the condition dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position &amp; age of every person, but especially as concerning yong children, for what▪
<pb facs="7"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> there to bring sureties into danger for the baptising of Infants, if there be no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> of hastening the baptising of infants. Seing the Sureties are disabled often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> to performe theire promise, both by reason of mortalitie, and of the evil dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e children, when they come to yeares, for whom they promised in baptisme, &amp;c.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> First, concerning Tertullian it is to be noted, that thus he writeth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n he was fallen into the opinions of the Cataphriges or Montanists, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> so held divers errors, as Augustine and others have observed out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> workes. And therefore being thus departed from the fayth; Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Reader judge if this man be a competent witnesse in this case. Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th not this man affirme that infants were not baptised in his tyme, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther the contrary, in that he makes mention of Sureties for infants: say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g, <hi>what necessitie is there to bring Sureties into danger for the baptising of infants,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich words do plainly argue, that the Church then used to baptise in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ts.</p>
   <p>2. Agayne, that which he affirmeth was his owne private judgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d his Reasons are of no weight, as the bringing of <hi>sureties into daunger,</hi> and <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> the suerties are disabled oftentymes to performe theire promise &amp;c.</hi> such sureties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot being appointed of God. 3. P. Mart. Clas. 4. ca. 8. affirmeth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tullian denyed Baptism to yong men and yong widowes; and his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rdes here related, do seeme to intimate some such like thing, in saying, <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>ferre and not to hasten baptism, is more profitable for the condition, disposition and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> of every person,</hi> And this he meaneth of others, then yong children. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er he speaketh of yong children, saying, <hi>especially concerning yong children.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> 4. Crispen, <hi>State of the Church, pag.</hi> 47. 48. witnesseth that Tertullian <hi>brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> extreeme vnction after baptism, the Sygne of the Crosse, offering for the dead, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er the like dreames of the Montanists.</hi> Now if Tertullians judgment be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>and agaynst infants baptism, why not also for extream vnction the sygne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f the Crosse, and the like his errors, seing all these are fruits proceeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>om the same tree?</p>
   <p>But thus this adversary careth not who the witnesse is, so he wil speake in favour of his heresy, let him be Montanist, Papist or what othersoever.</p>
   <p>But let it be further observed, that about Tertullians tyme and after, some deferred theire baptisme, vntil they thought they should dye, and so were not baptised vntil they fell into some great sicknes, as Theodosius &amp; others. And this seemeth to be Tertullians error; as if baptisme was for washing awaye of sinnes past, and not to come.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>Concerning that which Eusebius reporteth of Athanasius his bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> of children in sport, I have answered, pag. 109. and set downe reasons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> prove that those children were not children of the church, but of some o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the heathen, which were instructed in the fayth of Christ by the church, but were not received into the communion of the same. These are the two Auncients that M. Smyth produceth against us, whereof neither of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> affirmeth that the church did not baptise infants in those tymes. Now to these two, I wil oppose other two Auncients amongst many others, that do testifie that infants in their tymes and before, were baptised, viz. Origin, who sayth, <hi>that the church received from the Apostles, to give baptisme to infants. lib. 5. ad Rom.</hi> And Augustine de Bap. contra Donatist. lib. 4. cap. 23. who speaking of the Baptisme of Infants, sayth, <hi>that which the whole church holdeth, neyther is ordeyned by councels, but alwayes hath been holden, we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve to be delivered by Apostolical authoritie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The next corruption that the Separation is charged withal, is, <hi>to have a false ministerie.</hi> Now the Ministers that we have are of Pastors &amp; Teachers, called thereunto by election of the Church, according to these Scriptures, Eph. 4, 9. 11, 12. Rom. 12, 7. 8. 1 Cor. 12, 28. Acts. 13, 1, 2. Revel. 1, 20. Nehem, 8, 1, - 8. Mat. 23, 2. Mal, 2, 7. Act. 14. 23. And practise of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive churches. And of this Ministerie of Pastors and Teachers M. Smyth himself approveth in his Principles, pag. 18. and in his Questions, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, pag. 8. printed this last year, 1609. he describing the officers of the Church, devides them, first into Bishops and Deacons, then the Bishops into Pastors, or Teachers, or Elders, and withal describeth the Pastor, to be a bishop over one particular Church, excelling in the word of wisdome. The Teacher, to be a Bishop over one particular church, excelling in the word of knowledge. The Governour, to be a Bishop of one particular vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Church, excelling in wise government. Thus hath he written: and yet we having no other Ministerie, then he himself approveth, chargeth us to have a false Ministerie, not caring to crosse himself, so he may utter his bitternes against the Church of Christ.</p>
   <p>The 3. corruption this adversarie chargeth us withal, is, <hi>false worship of reading books.</hi> This he sayth, but proves it not. I will breifly set downe our practise, that the Reader may take notice, how unjustly we are charged. 1. For prayer &amp; giving of thanks, that is publiquely performed by our Pastor or Teacher, who invocate the name of God &amp; praise him for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits
<pb facs="8"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s the spirit directs their harts to conceive and giveth utterance, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ithout the use of any book during that action, according to those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ptures, Rom. 8. 26. 27. Eph. 6, 18, 19. Col. 4, 2. Act. 6, 4. Num. 6, 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>4. - 27. Nehem. 9, 3, - 38. Ezra. 9, 5, - 15. &amp; 10. 1. Ioel. 2, 17.</p>
   <p>2. They read the holy scriptures, translated into our owne language, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me two or three chapters or moe, as tyme wil serve, shewing briefly the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eaning thereof. Which is warranted by these Scriptures. Neh. 8, 3,—8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eut. 31, 11. Act. 15, 21. Col. 4, 16. 1 Thes. 5. 27. 1 Tim. 4, 13.</p>
   <p>3. The Pastor or Teacher taketh some Scripture, which they ordinarily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>llow, and after the reading thereof, do expound and apply the same, by doctrine, exhortation, &amp;c. to the further edification of the church: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to these scriptures. Luk. 4. 16. - 21. Act. 8. 35. &amp; 13, 15. and 26. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Tim. 4, 13. 2 Tim. 4, 2. And together with the preaching of the word, the Sacraments are administred after the rules of Christ, with prayer and thankesgiving, according to these Scriptures: Mat. 28, 19. 1 Cor. 11, 23. &amp;c. Act. 20, 7. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>4. Some of the Psalmes of David, before and after the exercise of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ord (the same being first read and opened by the Pastor or Teacher,) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing of the whole church together to the praise of God, and our own edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>cation, according to these Scriptures: Eph. 5, 19. Col. 3, 16. Mat 26, 30. Act. 16, 25. Psal. 95. &amp; 92, 1. &amp; 66. 2. &amp; 89. 1.</p>
   <p>Lastly, each one as he is able, contributeth to the Treasurie, whereby the Officers &amp; poor of the church, are maynteyned: according to these scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. 1 Tim. 5, 17. 18. 1 Cor. 9, 7-14. Gal. 6. 6. 1 Tim. 5. 16. Luk. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. 1. 2 3. 4. Mat. 26, 9. 10. 11. Act. 2, 42. 45, 46. &amp; 4, 34. 35. - 37. 1 Cor. 16. 1, 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Cor. 8, 4, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. And this is that worship and service we publikely practise, which Mr. S. calleth false worship: how truly, let the Reader now judge.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, cōcerning the Govermēt of our church, (which also this adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie taxeth) first, the Governours that we have, are such as Christ hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in his Church, viz. Pastors, Teachers, &amp; Elders, (and such as M. S. <note n="†" place="margin">Principles. pag. 18. Questions &amp; Answers pag. 8.</note> affirmeth the Eldership to consist of) the two former both teaching and ruling, the Elders imployed in the governmēt onely, elected of the church for the overseing, governing &amp; guiding of the same, by the rules of Christ, whose offices and authoritie of Ruling, are warranted by these scriptures. 1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. 5. 17. Rom. 12. 6. 7. 8. 1 Cor. 12. 28. 1 Tim. 3. 5. with Rev. 2. 2. 14. 15. Act. 20. 28. Heb. 13, 8. 24.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>Agayn, as touching the Censures, we proceed therin after Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> private faults vsing private admonitions, and for publike, open reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> cording to these Scriptures. Mat. 18. 15.—17. 1. Tim. 5. 20. 2. Cor. 2. 6. And when the offenders continue obstinate in their sinns after due ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition and conviction by the word of God; the Church being gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, the Pastor, or Teacher or one of the Elders in the name &amp; by the power of our Lord Iesus Christ pronounceth the sentence of excōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication agaynst them, all the brethren consenting, according to these Scriptures. Mat. 18. 17.—19. 1. Cor. 5. 3. 4. &amp;c. 1. Tim. 1. 20. And if the excomunicate do repent, he is with the Churches consent received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne into the cōmunion therof, by some of the Governors according to these Scriptures. 2. Cor. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>7.—11. Mat. 18. 18.—20.</p>
   <p>What Mr. Smyth can fault in this or in any other of our practises, he may at his leasure discover the same, if he be not already satisfied.</p>
   <p>Now besides these false imputations, it pleaseth Mr. Smyth to vtter agaynst this Church many vncharitable and reprochfull speeches: wishing also, <hi>As the Tirant wished concerning the people of Rome, that all theire heades were joyned into one &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To passe by his tart and bitter speeches unbeseeming a professor of the Gospell, concerning his wish, I do certifie him thus much, that if it were granted, that the Separation had but one head, his woodden sword of mans doctrine, wil never be able to smyte it of. Wel may he cary the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants mynd, but for his wish, I trust he shall fynd a like effect therof, as the Tyrant did of his, who contrary to his expectation, found the people of Rome not to have one head, but many hands to smyte of his head: So this wisher shall, fynd that the Separation hath many hands to convince his abominable errors.</p>
   <p>And whereas he desyreth <hi>the Separation that they wil not in craftines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe from the combate, as hetherto they have done in the matter of the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nslati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Worship, and Presbyterie,</hi> &amp;c. He himselfe now knoweth that he hath answere to all these things, and if any delay hath bene herein, it was not any withdrawing through craftines, as he falsely chargeth vs, but we saw him so mutable and inconstant, and his latter writings to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw his former, that his owne workes would be a sufficient confutation thereof: And now that there was so great occasion of answere, and that he so insulted vpon the differring therof, he hath his answere geven him. For
<pb facs="9"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> his speeches, of charging and challendging vs to the defence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rors, I hope he wil stay his penne henceforth from such vanitie, seing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e not ashamed, or yet neglect to vndertake the defence of that truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> professe, and to manifest that he is a defender of errors and not we, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e scanderously reporteth of vs.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, Mr Smyth requires of the Separation, and of all men, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> impute vnto them, <hi>The denying of the old Testament, the Lords day, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>stracy, and humanity of Christ.</hi> Why this request should be made, I know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot, vnles they would beare the world in hand, that they are not taynted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith these errors, which other anabaptists doo hold. Concerning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st of them, Mr. Sm. affirmeth that the Lord made with his people vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e old Testament, a carnal covenant, denying that everlasting covenant in Christ to be geven vnto them, or circumcision to be the seale thereof: He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>so denyeth the seede of the faythfull to be within the covenant of grace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yther before or since Christs comming, contrary to Gen. 17. 7. Act. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>9. And therefore I cannot see, but that the denying both of the old and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ew Testament, in this respect, may justly be imputed unto him, as in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reatise following it will appeare.</p>
   <p>For their denying of the Lords day, as yet we have litle to say, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>anding it is reported that some of their company, makes question ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
   <p>But concerning the Magistracy, Mr. Smyth bewrayeth his vnsoundnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> these words, <hi>But of Magistrates converted to the faith and admitted into the Church by baptism, there may questions be made, which to answere we cannot if we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ld, when such things fall out, the Lord we doubt not will direct vs into the truth concerrning that matter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Here let the Reader observe how they plead ignorance in the matter of the Christian Magistrate, if so they thought of his Authoritie, that he being of the Church, was to beare the sword, and them of the Church to obey him, as having civill power over them, and whome he might commaund in defence of Religion, &amp; of his country to take vp armes; then needed not he thus to speake. For by his words they geve vs to conjecture, that they think more may be yeelded to an heathen Ruler, then to a Christian Magistrate. If they be cleare in this pointe, they may so explane their myndes. Also in this pleading ignorance of the Magistracy, they seeme to tax the new Testament, not to be so playne, as Mr Smyth affirmeth, where
<pb facs="10"/> he sayth, <hi>All the ordinances of the new Testament are plainely taught by C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> his disciples.</hi> Character, pag. 34. Now if all things be taught in the new Testament, why then can he not answere those many questions that may be made about the Christian Magistrate, or why looks he for new direction? wel: this I perceave, that eyther he must deny the authority of the Christian Magistrate, or be driven to confesse that the writings of the Apostles are not playne enough to discribe his office and Authoritie, without the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the old Testament, from which if it be lawfull to reason concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter of the Magistracy, then I hope it cannot be denyed, but so it is lawfull to do, for other ordinances also.</p>
   <p>Touching the error of the Incarnation of Christ, which also Mr. Smyth desyreth may not be imputed vnto them. It is wel knowne that many of theire company holding that error about the incarnation, are separated from the rest. And Mr. Smyth him selfe (as some amongst them have reported) maketh a question about the first matter of Christs humane nature as if it were not a poynt of fayth to beleeve that it was of the virgin, though it be to be beleeved that the second matter was nourished in her womb. Whether his hearers do wrong him in such reports, or how he resteth satisfied, it is best knowen to himselfe. And be it, that he stand cleere of this error, yet is be taynted with the errors of general redemption and free wil, els why hath he given forth these Positions? 1. <hi>Christs Redemption strecheth to all men. 2. Man hath not lost the facultie of willing any good thing that is shewed him.</hi> And with all added therevnto his Reasons in defence thereof.</p>
   <p>Now let the Reader judge what cause he had to desire, that these things should not be imputed vnto them.</p>
   <p>Lastly, Mr. Smyth taketh upon him to advertise our Church, saying: <hi>Let the Separation be advertised, that whereas they do so cōfidently through theire▪ selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, &amp; self conceat, fil their mouthes with heresie and hereticks, as therby they would feare Babes, that therein they tread in the steps of all the Antichristians their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For this his advertisment, if any have spoken otherwise then is meete, I am no Patrone of any such speeches, but if it was lawful for Iohn to call the Phariseis <hi>Generatiō of vipers,</hi> And Paul to say to Elimas, <hi>Oh ful of subtilty &amp; all mischeiffe &amp;c.</hi> then is it not simply vnlawfull, to vse such speeches, so it be for reproofe, and not for reproche. Therefore to call them hereticks and
<pb facs="10"/> their opinions heresies, (it being true and spoken in detestation of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, not of their persons;) I see no evil in so saying, see these places. Io. 8. 44. 2. Pet. 2. 1. 2. 1. Io. 2. 18. Act. 13. 10. Gal. 3. 1. Rev. 2. 6. 15. And if this be a fault in vs, why doth Mr. Smyth fil his mouth with Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an errors, so calling those truthes which we hold? Hath he a dispensati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so to speake agaynst the truth, and yet to blame vs for calling their false doctrynes, heresy? I should rather have thought, that he ought to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertised himselfe for these reprochful &amp; sclanderous speaches that he hath vttered agaynst our Church, &amp; the Teachers thereof, calling them <note n="†" place="margin">Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Epistle the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>Rabbies of the Separation. The greatest Rabbies.</hi> And thus speaking to the Church. <hi>Be it knowen to the Separation, that we account them in respect of their constitution as very an harlot as eyther her mother England or her Grandmother Rome. We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test agaynst her, as wel for her false constitution, as for her false Ministery, worship, and Goverment. I could wish as the Tyrant wished, Concerning the people of Rome, that all their heads were joyned into one. We desire the Separation they wil not in crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes withdrawe from the Combate. We require them, nay we charge them, yea we chalendg them to the defence of their errors. We protest agaynst them to be a false Church. They treade in the steps of all the Antichristians their Predecessors. Let them take heed, that notwithstanding their Syrenes songs, they prove not Cages full of most vgly and deformed Antichristian Hereticks.</hi> All these reprochfull speeches, if not more, hath he published in lesse then a sheete of paper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydes, what are contayned in his Book. And yet notwithstanding all these speaches have thus passed from him, he takes vpon him to advertise vs, for that we can justifie against his doctrines &amp; against themselves, for their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate defending of their errors. But where he chargeth vs to call them He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, &amp; their doctrines heresie, <hi>through self love and self conceatednes &amp;c.</hi> If he had applyed self love and conceipt to him self, I take it he might more just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have done it, if we may judge by his words. As for selfe love and selfe cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, we condemne in whomsoever. And howsoever we have our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I trust he shalnot be able to tax any of vs iustly, of these imputations.</p>
   <p>And as Mr. Smyth wisheth us not to be wyse in our owne eies, through pryde, &amp;c. we hope the Lord wil so teach vs. And we pray the Lord to geve him a sight of his damnable heresies whereinto he is fallen, openly sinning in the publishing thereof, to the great dishonor of God, and greiffe of al the godly: and that the almighty may preserve all that are his chosen, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poysoned with the same.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Richard Clyfton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>