<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1596_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08327</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1596</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The guide of faith. Or, A third part of the Antidote against the pestiferous writings of all English sectaries : And in particuler, agaynst D. Bilson, D. Fulke, D. Reynoldes, D. Whitaker, D. Field, D. Sparkes, D. White, and M. Mason, the chiefe vpholders, some of Protestancy, and some of Puritanisme. VVherein the truth, and perpetuall visible succession of the catholique Roman Church, is cleerly demonstrated by S.N. Doctour of Diuinity</title>
                 <author>S. N. (Sylvester Norris)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 229, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue often heard this principle recorded by <hi>Aristotle</hi> much cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated amongst Deuines, <hi>Quier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat ad pauca respicit,</hi> He that erreth looketh into few thinges. Which <note place="margin">A princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Protestāts</note> learned axiome of so graue a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher the temerity of Protestants teacheth to be true. For they with partiall eye haue regard to few thinges when in matters of fayth abandoning al au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenticall proofes and argumentes of credibility, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing so many approued miracles, historyes, prescriptions, so many infallible traditions &amp; testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes of truth, they betake thēselues to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alone, to the maine Ocean of Propheticall and Apostolical writings, without carde to direct them, or pilot to guide them in that sea of difficulties. They looke into few thinges, when rowing there, they passe ouer innumerable euident texts which make
<pb facs="6"/>
against them, and take hold of some one which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth a little shew and semblance of countenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their fancyes. For example, they once read in S. Matthew, <hi>The Lord thy God shalt thou adore, and</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> c. 4. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</note>
      <hi>him only shalt thou serue.</hi> And without further consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of what homage he speaketh, they peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily condemne all religious worship and adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Angells, of Saints, of their tombes &amp; reliques so often intimated in other places. They once read in S. Iohn: <hi>It is the spirit that quickneth, the flesh profiteth nothing,</hi> and thereupon they depriue their owne soules of the inestimable profit of Christs vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uificall <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 63.</note> and reall flesh in the sacrament of the Altar, notwithstanding it be constantly auouched by the Apostle, by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> &amp; all the rest of the Euangelists. They once read: <hi>That Christ is the propitiation for our sinnes,</hi> That he paid for vs a full and perfect ransom, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> and they deny all Canonicall or voluntary satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all workes of pennance or expiations of sinne, to which the Holy Ghost very often most earnestl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> exhorteth vs. The like vnaduised and precipitate rashnes I might note in all other articles in which they swarue from vs, but it shallbe inough to speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy it further in their chiefest article of iustification, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hosius l.</hi> 1. <hi>de haeresi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nostri temporis: citatur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teolum verb. lusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatorij. Gen.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5. <hi>ad Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 19.</note> wherein they are so headlong as no sooner do they find any one word sounding to their purpose, but they obstinatly cleaue &amp; sticke fast vnto it. For one Protestant readeth (as <hi>Hosius</hi> diligently pursueth this matter) <hi>Abraham belieued, and it was reputed vnto him for iustice.</hi> And thence he gathereth his imputatiue iustice, by only faith. Another readeth: <hi>we are iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his blood,</hi> &amp; he inferreth that the pretious bloud of Christe is our iustice. Another readeth: <hi>As by the</hi>
      <pb n="3" facs="6"/>
      <hi>disobedience of one man many were made sinners: so also by the obedience of one many shallbe made iust,</hi> &amp; he faineth Christs obedience to be the garment of our iustice. Another readeth: <hi>he rose for our iustification,</hi> and he <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> accounteth Christs resurrection our heauenly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture. Another readeth: <hi>The holy Ghost shall argue the world of iustice, because I goe vnto my Father,</hi> and he <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.</note> straight way affirmeth Christs passage to his Father to be our robe of righteousnes. Thus they deuise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <note place="margin">Prateolus in elencho verbo lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stificatorij-</note> twenty seuerall opinions, of that one substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall point of Iustification alone.</p>
   <p>Againe they looke into few thinges not only in adhering, but chiefly in expounding such parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer passages as they first light vpon: for neglecting the publique spirit &amp; voyce of God which speaketh in his Church, neglecting the generall tribunall and consistory of the world, they hearken only to the outward letter, and to the priuate spirit which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideth in themselues, by them only they interprete and by them only they willbe tryed whether their interpretatiō be good or no. As if a theefe accused of felony would deliuer his owne tale as he frameth it, <note place="margin">Protestāts are fitly compared to the guilty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son who admitteth no triall but his owne.</note> and admit no examination of witnesses, no tryall of iury, or sentence of iudge, no former presidents or decisions of like case, but his owne information &amp; voyce of his Soueraigne diuulged in his law, which he maketh to sound as himselfe liketh best; were not this to stop his eares against all testimonies but his owne, to refuse all triall or iudgment which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe being guilty doth not pronounce, and yet such is our aduersaryes dealing. They expound Scripturs as their secret spirit in wardly perswadeth them, and they will trye their spirit by no other touchstone,
<pb facs="7"/>
then by the publique word of God interpreted by themselues. We appeale to the iudgment of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Catholik Church, they contemne her sentence; we ascend to our Ancestours that haue gone before vs, they cut off at one clappe the vsage, practise, and prescription of a thousand yeares space; we repaire to the Doctors, &amp; Fathers of the primitiue Church, to the generall Councels, and their authenticall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, to the very sentences of Scripture explayned by them, they regard them not any further then they agree <hi>in their opinion</hi> with the word of God. At last we sommon them to their owne Court, we presse them with the authority of Protestant writers, they answere, <hi>they were men, they might erre, no man is bound</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>D. VVhit. defens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note>
      <hi>to follow them any further then they follow the truth.</hi> And so these new Reformers will iudge alone what is truth and who are followers and imbracers of it. <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon shift of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants in answering their own writers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thē.</note>
   </p>
   <p>They looke into few things when challenging at least in outward shew one or two, they despise all other Sacraments of God &amp; ancient ceremonyes of the Church. When pleading for fayth alone, they gayne say the valew of workes, and supernaturall dignity of infinite vertues. When scandalized at the licentiousnes of some dissolute liuers in the Catholik Church, they admire not the heriocall acts and res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plendent sanctity of so many zealous Prelates, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Priestes, Religious Friers, Monkes, Nunnes, and whole armies of Saints, which flourish therein. When dismayed with the faygned impossibility of keeping Gods Commandements, they lift not vp their eyes to his Euangelicall Counsels and workes of supererogation. When dazeled with the Sunne of Christs glorious morits, they see not the beames
<pb facs="7"/>
of light and aboundant merits he deriueth vnto vs. They see not the efficacy of his sacraments, the dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of his grace, the full indulgence and remission of our sinnes, the inherent beauty and splendour of iustice by which he garnisheth vpon earth the soules of his seruants.</p>
   <p>They looke into few thinges in perusing the ancient Fathers. When reading in <hi>S. Augustine</hi> for example, <hi>That he is a miracle, who seeketh for miracles</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>August, l.</hi> 22. <hi>de c uit. Dei cap.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>to belieue,</hi> they conclude thereupon that all miracles haue ceased, not weighing the occasion of S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> wordes, not attending to the miracles which in the same Chapter he mentioneth to haue beene <note place="margin">
         <hi>S. Ciprian serm de lapsis post medium. S. Gregor. Nazian. in laudem Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priani. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monum profligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsionem, futuram rerum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiam, quae qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem omniū vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ineres ipsi Cypria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, modò fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des adsit, efficiunt. Vide etiam illum in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris. Chrysost. l. cont. Gentiles. Quotidiana <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Martiribus miracula eduntur. Hieron. Ep:</hi> 22. <hi>ad Eustoch. vide miracula diuersa ad Sanctorum monumenta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita. Reade him also de muliere septies icta, &amp; in vita Hilarionis.</hi>
      </note> supernaturally wrought by the Reliques of S. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi> Not hearkning to the miracles which S. <hi>Cypriā</hi> S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> S. <hi>Chysostome,</hi> S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> a thousand historiographers very plentifully recount &amp; the powerfull hand of God in sundry Countryes dayly atchieueth.</p>
   <p>They looke into few things when angled with the conterfet bayte, and vayne promise of truth cast forth by their Ghospellers, they diue not into the manifold absurdityes, and open repugnancyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in their doctrine. They consider not their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, falsifications, detorting of Scripture, and racking of the Fathers which they commonly vse to writh them to their purpose. Thus they skimme of in Luther, in Caluin &amp; other their predecessours, the froth of their noweltyes, and ouerslip diuers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious barbarismes, diuers atheisticall and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="6" facs="8"/>
speaches couched in their writinges, which haue beene often layd open by the learned of our side. Yet to approue the vigilancy and wisedome of our soueraigne King IAMES, who hath prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inhibited the reading of such new brued and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned workes, to the noble students of his two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Vniuersityes, I will briefly insinuate some few of Caluin, the chiefe late Nouelist, his Atheismes, wherin he appeacheth the diuine goodnes it selfe of iniustice, impotency, &amp; dissimulation, his beloued sonne Christ Iesus of ignorance, incongruity in his speach, superfluons inferences, rashnes, timidity &amp; desperation. The immaculate Virgin his dearest Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of sinnefull enclosing the omnipotency of God within the boundes of Nature. For first he often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcateth, <hi>that God is chiefe author of his own iust ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and Satan is but only a minister therof. That God</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Calu. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>inflit. c.</hi> 18. §. 1. 2. 3. <hi>&amp;c &amp; l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. §. 2. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1. <hi>Ibid. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23. §. 8.</note>
      <hi>purposeth, willeth, moueth, loueth, and commandeth the wickednes of sinners, their obstinate blindnes and hardnes of hart. Then, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> will of God is a necessity of things.</hi> From whence it ensueth that the reprobate necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily sinne by the appointement of God, which they cannot auoyd, and that God is vniust for punishing them without cause. Likewise it followeth that sinne it selfe is no sinne, but an vpright action con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant vnto reason. For the wil of God (saith <hi>Caluin)</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Calu l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23. §. 2.</note>
      <hi>is so the highest rule of righteousnes, that whatsoeuer he willeth, euen for this that he willeth it, it ought to be takē for righteous</hi> But God (according to him) willeth sinne, therefore sinne is righteous, good, &amp; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to rule.</p>
   <p>Secondly it followeth, that Good decreeth those <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid. l.</hi> 1. <hi>inflit. c.</hi> 18. §. 13.</note> thinges <hi>with his secret purpose, which he hath openly</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>forbidden by his lawe,</hi> and so he both willeth and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not the same thing, which without dissimulatiō or contrariety cannot be conceaued. Besides he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth Gods absolute power of effecting all thinges. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23. §. 2.</note>
      <hi>We trust not</hi> (quoth he) <hi>in the feygned deuise of abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power, which as it is prophane so worthily ought it to be abhorred of vs.</hi> No lesse impious is he against God, then malepart and audacious against our Sauiour Christ in accusing him of ignorance: That he <hi>knew</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>In c.</hi> 24. <hi>Matt.</hi> 36. <hi>Matt.</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>In cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Matt. v.</hi> 2. Quod quidam existimāt Christum diuinitùs conscium fuisseipso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um fidei quae oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultantiùs lat ebat. mihi coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur. <hi>Matt.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Calu. in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um locum,</hi> Superua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua est il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio. <hi>Calu. l.</hi> 2. <hi>instit. cap.</hi> 16. §. 12. <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 10. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>not as man the day of iudgment, nor of what kinde the figge tree was that grew by the way side,</hi> nor the inward thoughts of the hart saying, <hi>That which some think that Christ was acquainted from aboue with their saith which lay hild within, seemeth to me aforced &amp; astrayned thing:</hi> he accuseth him likewise of incōgruity in his speach to wit, That <hi>Christ promiseth from God reward to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting is an improper speach:</hi> of superfluous inferēce, for when Christ inferred, <hi>All thinges therfore whatsoeuer you will</hi> &amp;c. Caluin giueth it this glose, <hi>It is a vaine or superfluous illation</hi> Of timiditye and searefulnes in these wordes; <hi>Theeues and other euill doers doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately hast to death, many doe with hauty courage des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pise, some other doe mildly suffer it. But what constancy or stout courage were it for the some of God to be astonished, and in a manner stricken dead which feare of it &amp;c. howe shamefull a tendernes (as I sayd) should this haue beene to be so far tormented with feare of comon death as to melte in bloudy sweate, and not to be able to be comforted but by sight of Angells.</hi> Wherupon he brayeth forth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sacrilege, that our Sauiour besides his corporall death suffered the death of his soule: <hi>he suffered that death wherwith God in his wrathstriketh wicked doers. He felte the rigour of Gods vengeance in his soule, he suffered</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>the terrible tormentes of a damned and forsakes man</hi> His <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. <hi>Calu. in harm. super eum locum v.</hi> 38. <hi>Calu. in harm. in c.</hi> 27. <hi>Matt. v.</hi> 46. Sed absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè videtur Christo elapsam desperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis vocē: solutio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilis est, quamuis enim sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus carnis exitum apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit, fixa tamen ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit sides in corde. <hi>Calu. in harm. in. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Luc. v.</hi> 34. Videtur Sancta virgo non minus malignè Dei prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiam restringe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quàm priùs <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> &amp;c. nec magnopere laborandum est vt eam purgemus ab omni vitio. <hi>Calu. l.</hi> 3. <hi>insti. c.</hi> 20. §. 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27. <hi>&amp; l. de rat. reforma. Ecclesiae,</hi> sanctos vocat laruas, carni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, vmbras, bestias.</note> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nome is not yet spent. He traduceth also the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Wisedome as rash and inconsiderate in those wordes which he vttered: <hi>Father, if it be possible let this cupp passe from me This prayer</hi> (saith Caluin) <hi>of Christ was not premeditate but the force and extremity of grief wringed from him this hasty speach. To which a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection or recalling was presently added; The same vehemē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy drewe from him the presente memory of the heauenly decree;</hi> At length he concludeth, that Christ was so amazed with feare at the iudgements of God as he was drouen to despaire, at least in outward wordes. For obiecting to himself how <hi>absurde it should seeme that a speach of desperation should fall from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hrist,</hi> he answereth: <hi>The solution is easye, for although the sense of fleshe did apprehend destruction, yet faith remayned stable in his harte:</hi> as though he should say his tongue vttered wordes of despaire although his hart were still fixed in God. Where the sonne of God is thus blasphemed can the Mother of God be free from dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace? the venomous wretch very seldome discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of that heauenly Queene, but by a word which he vttereth you may throghly ghesseat his malicious spirit. Vpon that question of our Ladies to the Angel Gabriell, <hi>how shall this be done</hi> &amp;c. he maketh this comment: <hi>The holy virgin seemeth no lesse spitefully to restraine the power of God then before Zacharias did</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Neither ought wee to labour much to free her frō all vice.</hi> I omit how he termeth many other Saintes, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blins, or Night-ghostes, shaddowes, Butchers and beasts. The filthines I haue already discouered is
<pb facs="9"/>
more then inough to iustifye our Maiesties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aegidius Hunnius in libro cui titulus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribitur Caluinus iudaizans, &amp;c. Illiricus in defens. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess. Aug. c.</hi> 7. <hi>Osian. in Enchirid. cont. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. c.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 198.</note> of such diuelish workes, and to terrifie all Christians from reading of them, which men of his owne sect (if Protestantes combine in one secte) haue already detested &amp; proscribed as full of Iudais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, Arianisme, and other most execrable heresies: whereof <hi>Aegidius Hunnius</hi> a Lutheran doctour and professour of diuinity in the vniuersity of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> hath printed a booke, whose title beginneth thus <hi>Caluinus Iudaizans &amp;c. Caluin Iudaizing, or playing the Iewe,</hi> and <hi>Illiricus</hi> a prime sectary of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession giueth testimony that <hi>Caluins</hi> liturgie is defiled not with one only sacriledge, &amp; that it hath carried innumerable soules into eternall perdition. <hi>Luke Osiander</hi> another Protestant confuting certaine assertions of the <hi>Caluinists</hi> calleth them <hi>a gulfe, whir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepoole, or hell of Caluinian doctrine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Besides these Lutherans <hi>Castalio</hi> a Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <note place="margin">
         <hi>Humfred. de rat. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret. l.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</note> much commended by M. Doctour <hi>Humfrey,</hi> so farre abhorreth the opinion of Caluin in feigning God to be the authour of sinne, &amp; damnation in the reprobate, as he distinguisheth that supposed God of <note place="margin">Castal. in l. ad Calu. de praedestin.</note>
      <hi>Caluin</hi> from the true God described in the scripture: his wordes are these: <hi>The false God</hi> (that is the God which Caluin frameth to himself) <hi>is slowe to mercy,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See the iudgment of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Caluins holding God to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of sinne, and dānation.</note>
      <hi>prone to anger, who hath created the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atest parte of the world to destruction, and hath predestinate them not only to damnation but also to the cause of damnatiō. Therefore he hath decreed from all eternity, and he will haue it so, &amp; he doth bring it to passe that they necessarily</hi> sinne; <hi>so that neither theftes, nor murders, nor adulteries are comitted but by his constraint &amp; impulsion. For he suggesteth vnto men euill &amp; dishonest affections, not only by permission but</hi>
      <pb n="10" facs="10"/>
      <hi>effectually (that is by drawing them to such affections) &amp; doth harden them in such sorte that when they perpetrate euill they doe rather the worke of God then their owne: he maketh the deuill a lier, so that nowe not the deuill but the God of Caluin is the Father of lies. But that God which the holy scriptures teach is altogeather contrary to this God of Caluin &amp;c.</hi> Imediatly after, <hi>for the true God came to destroy the worke of that Caluinian God: &amp; these two Gods as they are by nature contrary one to another, so they beget and bring forth children of contrary disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to wit, that God of Caluin children without mercy proud &amp;c.</hi> Hither to <hi>Castalio.</hi> To whom I add the like censure of <hi>Stancarus</hi> a Protestāt also of no smal fame who writing to <hi>Caluin</hi> saluteth him thus: <hi>VVhat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Stancarus cont. Calu. K.</hi> 4. <hi>Vide etiam lib. de Tri. K.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>O Caluin, hath seduced thee to speake with</hi> Arius <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the sonne of God, that thou mightst proclaime him to be depriued of his glory, &amp; now to intreate to haue it giuen him, as though he had not alwayes had it? That Antichrist of the North whome thou doest impudently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi> Melancthon <hi>the Grammarian hath done this.</hi> At length he concludeth with this earnest admonitiō: <hi>Beware (O Christian Reader, &amp; especially all you Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters) beware of the books of Caluin, and principally in the articles of the Trinity, Incarnation, Mediatour, the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptisme, &amp; predestination: For they containe wicked doctrine &amp; Arian blasphemyes: In so much as the spirit or soule of burned Seruetus may seem according to the Platonists to haue entred into Caluin.</hi> So he. Whose caueat, or serious admonition, togeather with the prohibition of our Soueraigne, &amp; censures of Gods Church, willbe a warning I hope to my dearest Countrymen, to abhorre the writtings of that <hi>Ariā, Seruetian, Iudaicall, Simonian, Manichean</hi> Sectary,
<pb n="11" facs="10"/>
whome Heauen and Earth, God and Man, <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> and <hi>Protestants, Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Sacramentaryes,</hi> iustly condemne of such hatefull impietyes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>