<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHARITABLE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1631_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07362</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17746</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1631</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHARITABLE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The patterne of all pious prayer, and the epitomie of all Christian Catholique beliefe : being a patheticall and paraphrastical meeter vpon the Pater Noster, Ave Maria, and Credo in Deum, &amp;c. : together with a divine dittie made vpon St. Patricks Day last past in honour of the Christian crosse, with wholsome preparatives for death and judgment : also a short panigyre on Mary-land in America</title>
                 <author>Mayerne, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>47 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>TO THE CHARITABLE READER.</head>
   <p>GReat cause I had (Christian Reader) to invite thee by this Epistle (Charitable,) for this poore Babe of my braine begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in charity, desires to have charitable nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, charitable Censure, and chiefely Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptation; For the tender weakeling by reason of its Parents weaknesse, (should it bee rigidly dealt withall) would even perish in the very blast of an over-curious or fastidious ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict; Therefore let Charity cover what indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
<pb facs="14"/>hath left naked, and let a loving heart excuse Defects of Art; What I have heere published was done at the (powerfull) solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a very good Friend of mine, or else this rude worke had onely beene for the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans owne vse: And as it was written to anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate worse employment; so as a Whetstone to his devotion, It might have (and I trust will) set a sharper edge vpon the same, And conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently produce more keene and piercing ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Charity, Feare of GOD, Obedience to his immaculate Spouse the Holy Catholique and Apostolique CHURCH; Reverence to his Saints, Zeale of his Honour, Fervor in true Religion, and in all pious and laudable Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises that a CHRISTIAN ought to practice. Among which, nothing can bee more vsefull and necessary at all times, And especially in
<pb facs="14"/>this heauy time of Mortalitie, Then the thought of DEATH and IVDGEMENT: Although it bee a Subject that hath beene written vpon by divers Angelicall quils, (To whose Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I humbly prostrate mine;) yet I know that a single Penny or a halfe-penny is as good silver and as Currant coyne as a Shilling: To conclude, if any Fruit spring from this simple Seed, to him bee the honor who first inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>