<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Amiot to the Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1644_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09802</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20066</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1644</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Amiot to the Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lives of the noble Grecians and Romanes : compared together by that graue learned philosopher and historiographer, Plutarke of Chæronea: translated out of Greeke into French by Iames Amyot, abbot of Bellozane, bishop of Auxerre, one of the kings priuy counsel, and great amner of Fraunce, and out of French into Englishe, by Thomas North</title>
                 <author>Plutarch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wight (Wyght, Wayght, Whyte?), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 1175, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_of_French_version_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Amiot to the Readers.</head>
   <p>THe reading of bookes vvhich bring but a vaine and vnprofitable pleasure to the Reader, is iustly misliked of vvise and grauemen. Againe, the reading of such as doe but onely bring profit, and make the Reader to be in loue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith, and doe not ease the payne of the reading by some pleasauntnes in the same: doe seeme somevvhat harshe to diuers delicate vvits, that can not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long vpon them. But such bookes as yeeld pleasure and profit, and doe both delight and teache, haue all that a man can desire vvhy they should be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersally liked and allovved of all sortes of men, according to the common say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Poet Horace:
<q>
         <l>That he which matcheth profit with delight,</l>
         <l>Doth winne the price in euery poynt aright.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Eyther of these yeeld his effect the better, be reason the one runneth vvith the other, profiting the more bicause of the delight, and deliting the more bicause of the profit. This commendation (in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion) is most proper to the reading of stories, to haue pleasure and profit matched together, vvhich kind of delight and teaching, meeting in this vvise arme in arme, hath more allovvance then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of vvriting or inuention of man. In respect vvhereof it may be reasonably auovved, that men are more beholding to such good vvits, as by their graue and vvise vvriting haue deserued the name of Historiographers, then they are to any other kind of vvriters: bicause an historie is an order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly register of notable things said, done, or happened in time past, to mainteyne the continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, and to serue for the instruction of them to come.</p>
   <p>And like as memorie is as a storehouse of mens conceits and deuises, vvithout the vvhich the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the other tvvo parts should be vnperfect, and vvelneare vnprofitable: So may it also be sayd, that an historie is the very treasury of mans life, vvhereby the notable doings and sayings of men, and the vvonderfull aduentures &amp; straunge cases (vvhich the long continuance of time bringeth forth) are preserued from the death of forgetfulnes. Hereuppon it riseth, that Plato the vvise sayth, that the name of historie vvas giuen to this recording of matters, to stay the fleting of our memorie, vvhich othervvise vvould be soone lost, and retaine litle. And vve may vvell perceiue hovv greatly vve be beholding vnto it, if vve doe no more but consider in hovv horrible darkenes, and in hovv beastly and pestilent a quamyre of ignorance vve should be plunged: if the remembrance of all the thinges that haue bene done, and haue happened before vve vvere borne, vvere vtterly drovvned and forgotten. Novv therefore I vvill ouerpasse the excellencie and vvorthines of the thing it selfe, forasmuch as it is not onely of more antiquitie then any other kind of vvriting that euer vvas in the vvorlde, but also vvas vsed among men, before there vvas any vse of letters at all: bicause that men in those daies deliuered in their lifetimes the remembrance of things past to their successors, in songes, vvhich they caused their children to learne by hart, from hand to hand, as is to be seene yet in our dayes, by thexam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the barbarous people that inhabite the nevvfound landes in the VVest, vvho vvithout any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of vvritings, haue had the knovvledge of thinges past, vvelneare eight hundred yeares afore. Likevvise I leaue to discourse, that it is the surest, safest, and durablest monument that men can leaue of their doings in this vvorld, to consecrate their names to immortality. For there is nether picture, nor i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of marble, nor arche of triumph, nor piller, nor sumptuous sepulchre, that can match the durablenes of aneloquēt history, furnished vvith the properties vvhich it ought to haue. Again, I mind not to stand much vpon this, that it hath a certaine troth in it, in that it alvvayes professeth to speake truth, &amp; for that the proper groūd therof is to treate of the greatest &amp; highest things that are done in the vvorld: insomuch that (to my seeming) the great profit thereof is as Horace sayth, that it is commonly called the mother of trothe &amp; vprightnes, vvhich commendeth it so greatly, as it nedeth not elsvvhere to seeke any authoritye, or ornament of dignitie, but of her very selfe. For it is a certaine rule and instruction, vvhich by examples past, teacheth vs to iudge of things present, &amp; to foresee things to come: so as vve may knovve vvhat to like of, &amp; vvhat to follovv, vvhat to mislike, and vvhat to eschevv. It is a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, vvhich (as it vvere in a table) setteth before our eyes the things vvorthy of remembrance that
<pb facs="4"/>
haue bene done in olde time by mighty nations, noble kings &amp; Princes, vvise gouernors, valliant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines, &amp; persons renovvmed for some notable quality, representing vnto vs the maners of stran̄ge na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, tha lavves &amp; customes of old time, the particular affaires of men, their consultations &amp; enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, the meanes that they haue vsed to compasse thē vvithall, &amp; their demeaning of them selues vvhen they vvere comen to the highest, or throvven dovvne to the lovvest degree of state. So as it is not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for any case to rise either in peace or vvarre, in publike or priuate affaires, but that the person vvhich shall haue diligently red, vvell conceiued, &amp; throughly remembred histories, shall find matter in them vvhereat to take light, &amp; counsell vvherby to resolue himselfe to take a part, or to geue aduice vnto others, hovv to choose in doutfull &amp; daungerous cases that, vvhich may be for their most proffit, and in time to find out to vvhat poynt the matter vvill come if it be vvell handled: and hovv to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate him selfe in prosperitie, and hovv to cheere vp and beare him selfe in aduersitie. These things it doth vvith much greater grace, efficacy, and speede, than the bookes of morall Philosophie doe: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as examples are of more force to moue and instruct, than are the arguments and proofes of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or their precise precepts, bicause examples be the very formes of our deedes, &amp; accompanied vvith all circumstances. VVhereas reasons and demonstrations are generall, and tend to the proofe of things, and to the beating of them into vnderstanding: and examples tende to the shovving of them in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise and execution, bicause they doe not only declare vvhat is to be done, but also vvorke a desire to do it, as vvell in respect of a certaine naturall inclination vvhich all men haue to follovv examples, as also for the beavvtie of vertue, vvhich is of such povver, that vvheresoeuer she is seene, she ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her selfe to be loued and liked. Againe, it doth things vvith greater vveight and grauitie, than the inuentions &amp; deuices of the Poets: bicause it helpeth not it selfe vvith any other thing than vvith the plaine truth, vvher as Poetry doth commonly inrich things by commending them aboue the starres and their deseruing, bicause the chiefe intent thereof is to delight. Moreover, it doth thinges vvith more grace and modestie than the ciuill lavves and ordinances doe: bicause it is more grace for a man to teach and instruct, than to chastise or punish. And yet for all this, an historie also hath his maner of punishing the vvicked, by the reproch of euerlasting infamie, vvherevvith it defaceth their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, vvhich is a great meane to vvithdravv them from vice, vvho othervvise vvould be levvd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vvickedly disposed. Likevvise on the contrarie parte, the immortall praise and glorie vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith it revvardeth vvelldoers, is a very liuely &amp; sharpe spurre for men of noble corage and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manlike nature, to cause them to aduenture vpon all maner of noble and great things. For bookes are full of examples of men of high corage and vvisedom, vvho for desire to continue the remembraunce of their name, by the sure and certaine recorde of histories, haue vvillingly yeelded their liues to the seruice of the common vveale, spent their goods, susteined infinite peines both of bodie and minde in defence of the oppressed, in making common buildings, in stablishing of lavves and gouernments, and in the finding out of artes and sciences necessarie for the maintenance and ornament of mans life: for the faithfull registring vvhereof, the thanke is due to histories. And although true vertue seeke no revvard of her commendable doings like a hireling, but contenteth her selfe vvith the conscience of her vvell doing: yet notvvithstanding I am of opinion, that it is good and meete to dravv men by all meanes to good doing, and good men ought not to be forbidden to hope for the honor of their vertuous deedes, seeing that honor doth naturally accompanie vertue, as the shadovv doth the bodie. For vve commonly see, not to feele the sparkes of desire of honor, is an infallible signe of a base, vile and cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish nature: and that such as account it an vnnecessarie, needelesse, or vnseemely thing to be praised, are likevvise no doers of any things vvorthy of praise, but are commonly men of faint corage, vvhose thoughtes extend no further than to their liues, vvhereof also they haue no further remembranuce, than is before their eyes. But if the counsell of olde men be to be greatlie esteemed, bicause they must needes haue seene much by reason of their long life: and if they that haue trauelled long in straunge countries, and haue had the managing of many affaires, and haue gotten great experience of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this vvorld, are reputed for sage, and vvorthie to haue the reynes of great gouernmentes put into their handes; hovv greatly is the reading of histories to be esteemed, vvhich is able to furnishe vs vvith mo examples in one day, than the vvhole course of the longest life of any man is able to doe? Insomuch that they vvhich exercise them selues in reading as they ought to doe, although they be but young, become such in respect of vnderstanding of the affaires of this vvorld, as if they vvere old and
<pb facs="5"/>
grayheaded, and of long experience. Yea though they neuer haue remoued out of their houses, yet are they aduertised, informed, and satisfied of all things in the vvorld, as vvell as they that haue shortned their liues by innumerable trauells and infinite daungers, in ronning ouer the vvhole earth that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited: vvhereas on the contrary part, they that are ignorant of the things that vvere done &amp; come to passe before they vvere borne, continue stil as children, though they be neuer so aged, and are but as straungers in their ovvne natiue contries. To be short, it may be truely sayd, that the reading of histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is the schole of vvisedom, to facion mens vnderstanding, by considering aduisedly the state of the vvorld that is past, and by marking diligently by vvhat lavves, maners, and discipline, Empires, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and dominions, haue in old time bene stablished, and aftervvard mainteyned and increased: or contrarivvise chaunged, diminished, and ouerthrovven. Also vve reade, that vvhensoeuer the right sage and vertuous Emperour of Rome, Alexander Seuerus, vvas to consult of any matter of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, vvhether it concerned vvarres or gouernment: he alvvayes called such to counsell, as vvere reported to be vvell seene in histories. Notvvithstanding, I knovv there are that vvill stand against me in this poynt, and vphold that the reading of histories can serue to small purpose, or none at all, tovvards the getting of skill: bicause skill consisteth in action, &amp; is ingendred by the very experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; practise of things, vvhē a man doth vvel marke &amp; throughly beare avvay the things that he hath seene vvith his eyes, &amp; found true by proofe, according to the saying of the aūcient Poet Afranius.</p>
   <q>
      <l>My name is skill, my Syre Experience hyght,</l>
      <l>And memorie bred and brought me forth to lyght.</l>
   </q>
   <p>VVhich thing vvas ment likevvise by the Philosopher that sayd, that the hand is the instrument of skill. By reason vvhereof it comes to passe (say they) that such as speake of matters of gouernment and state, but specially of matters of vvarre by the booke, speake but as booke knights, as the Frenche prouerbe termeth them, after the manner of the Graecians, vvho call him a booke Pilot, vvhich hath not the sure and certaine knovvledge of the things that he speakes of: meaning thereby, that it is not for a man to trust to the vnderstanding vvhich he hath gotten by reading, in things that consist in the deede doing, vvhere the hand is to be set to the vvorke: no more then the often hearing of men talke and reason of paynting, or the disputing vppon colors, vvithout taking of the pensill in hand, can stand a man in any stead at all to make him a good paynter. But on the contrary part, many haue proued vvise men and good Captaines, vvhich could neither vvrite nor reade. Besides this, they alleage further, that in matters of vvarre, all things alter from yeare to yeare: by meanes vvhereof the slights and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that are to be learned out of bookes, vvill serue the turne no more than mynes that are blovven vp. According vvhereunto Cambyses telleth his sonne Cyrus in Xenophon, that like as in Musicke the nevvest songs are commonly best liked of for once, bicause they vvere neuer heard afore: So in the vvarres, those policies that neuer vvere practised afore, are those that take best successe, &amp; commonly haue the best effect, bicause the enemies doe least doubt of them. Neuerthelesse I am not he that vvill mainteyne that a vvise gouernor of a common vveale, or a great Captaine can be made of such a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, as hath neuer trauelled out of his study, and from his bookes: hovvbeit that vvhich Cicero vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Lucius Lucullus, is true, that vvhen he departed out of Rome as Captaine generall and Lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Romanes, to make vvarre against kinge Mithridates, he had no experience at all of the vvarres, and yet aftervvard he bestovved so great diligence in the reading of histories, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring vppon euery poynt vvith the olde Captaines and men of longe experience, vvhome he caried vvith him, that by the tyme of his comming into Asia, vvhere he vvas in deede to put his matters in execution, he vvas found to be a very sufficient Captaine, as appeared by his deedes: insomuch that by those vvayes, cleane contrary to the common order of vvarre, he discomfited tvvo of the most purs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, and greatest Princes that vvere at that time in the East. For his vnderstanding vvas so quicke, his care so vigilant, and his courage so greate, that he needed no longe trayning, nor grosse instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by experience. And although I graunt there haue beene diuerse Gouernors and Captaynes, vvhich by the onely force of nature (furthered by longe continevved experience) haue done good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and greate exploytes: yet can it not be denyed me, but that if they had matched the giftes of nature vvith the knovvledge of learning, and the reading of histories, they might haue done much greater thinges, and they might haue becomen much perfect. For like as in euery other cunning &amp; skill vvherein a man intendeth to excell: so also to become a perfect &amp; sufficient person to gouerne
<pb facs="5"/>
in peace and vvarre, there are three thinges of necessitie required,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Three things necessary for a Magistrate, or Captaine.</hi>
      </note> namely, nature, art, and practise. Nature (in the safe that vve treate of) must furnishe vs vvith a good moother vvit, vvith a bodie vvell disposed to indure all maner of trauell, and vvith a good vvill to aduaunce our selues: Art must geue vs iudgement and knovvledge, gotten by the examples and vvise discourses that vve haue read and double read in good histories: and practise vvill get vs readinesse, assurednesse, and the ease hovv to put thinges in execution. For though skill be the ruler of doing the deede, yet it is a vertue of the minde vvhich teacheth a man the meane poynt, betvvene the tvvo faultie extremities of too much and too little, vvherein the commendation of all doinges consisteth. And vvhosoever he is that goeth about to attaine to it by the onely triall of experience, and had leuer to learne it at his ovvne cost, than at an other mans: he may vvell be of the number of those that are touched by this auncient prouerbe, vvhich sayth, Experience is the schoole mistresse of fooles: bicause mans life is so short,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prouerbe.</hi>
      </note> and experience is hard and daungerous, specially in matters of vvarre, vvherein (according to the saying of Tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus the Athenian Captaine) a man can not fault tvvice, bicause the faultes are so great, that most commonly they bring vvith them the ouerthrovv of the state, or the losse of the liues of those that do them. Therefore vve must not tary for this vvit that is vvon by experience, vvhich costeth so deere, and is so long a comming, that a man is ofttimes dead in the seeking of it before he haue attained it, so as he had neede of a seconde life to imploy it in, bicause of the ouerlate comming by it. But vve must make speede by our diligent and continuall reading of histories both old and nevv, that vve may enjoy this happinesse vvhich the Poet speaketh of:
<q>
         <l>A happie wight is he that by mishappes</l>
         <l>Of others, doth beware of afterchappes.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>By the vvay, as concerning those that say that paper vvill beare all things: if there be any that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthily take vpon them the name of historiographers, and deface the dignity of the story for hatred or fauor, by mingling any vntrueth vvith it: that is not the fault of the historie, but of the men that are partiall, vvho abuse that name vnvvorthily, to couer and cloke their ovvne passions vvithall, vvhich thing shall neuer come to passe, if the vvriter of the storie haue the properties that are neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily required in a storie vvriter, as these: That he set aside all affection, be voyde of enuy, hatred, and flattery: that he be a man experienced in the affaires of the vvorld, of good vtterance, and good iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to discerne vvhat is to be sayd, and vvhat to be left vnsayd; &amp; vvhat vvould do more harme to haue it declared, than do good to haue it reproued or condemned: forasmuch as his chiefe drift ought to be to serue the common vveale, and that he is but as a register to set dovvne the iudgements and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue sentences of Gods Court, vvhereof some are geuen according to the ordinarie course and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of our vveake naturall reason, and other some goe according to Gods infinite povver and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible vvisedom, aboue and against all discourse of mans vnderstanding, vvho being vnable to reach to the bottome of his iudgements, and to finde out the first motions and groundes thereof, do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the cause of them to acertaine fortune, vvhich is nought else but a fained deuice of mans vvit, dazeled at the beholding of such brightnesse, and confounded at the gaging of so bottomlesse a deepe, hovvbeit nothing commeth to passe nor is done vvithout the leaue of him that is the verie right and trueth it selfe, vvith vvhom nothing is past or to come, and vvho knovveth and vnderstandeth the very originall causes of all necessitie. The consideration vvhereof teacheth men to humble them selues vnder his mightie hande by acknovvledging that there is one first cause vvhich ouerruleth nature, vvhereof it commeth, that neither hardinesse is alvvaies happie, nor vvisedom alvvaies sure of good successe. These so notable commodities are euery vvhere accompanied vvith singular delight, vvhich proceedeth chiefly of diuersitie and nouelty vvherein our nature delighteth and is greatly desirous of: bicause vve hauing an earnest inclination tovvards our best prosperity and aduauncement, it goeth on still, seeking it in euery thing vvhich it taketh to be goodly, or good in this vvorld. But forasmuch as it findeth not vvherevvith to content it selfe vnder the cope of heauen, it is soone vveary of the things that it had earnestly desired affore, &amp; so goeth on vvādring in the vnskilfulness of her likings vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of she neuer ceasseth to make a continuall chaunging vntill she haue fully satisfied her desires, by attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the last end, vvhich is to be knit to her chiefe felicity, vvhere is the full perfection of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and goodnes. This liking of varietie can not be better releeued, than by that vvhich is the finder out and the preseruer of time, the father of all noueltie, and messenger of antiquitie. For if vve finde
<pb facs="6"/>
a certaine singular pleasure, in hearkening to such as be returned from some long voyage, and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port things vvhich they haue seene in straunge contries, as the maners of people, the natures of places, and the fashions of liues, differing from ours: and if vve be sometime so rauished vvith delight and pleasure at the hearing of the talke of some vvise, discreete, and vvell spoken old man, from vvhose mouth there flovveth a streame of speech svveeter than honnie, in rehearsing the aduentures vvhich he hath had in his greene and youthfull yeares, the paines that he hath indured, and the perills that he hath ouerpassed, so as vve perceiue not hovv the time goeth avvay: hovv much more ought vve be rauished vvith delight and vvondring, to behold the state of mankind, and the true successe of things, vvhich antiquitie hath and doth bring forth from the beginning of the vvorld, as the setting vp of Empires, the ouerthrovv of Monarchies, the rising and falling of Kingdoms, and all things else vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie admiration, and the same liuely set forth in the faire, rich, and true table of eloquence? And that so liuely, as in the very reading of them vve feele our mindes to be so touched by them, not as though the thinges vvere alreadie done and past, but as though they vvere euen then presently in doing, and vve finde our selues caried avvay vvith gladnesse and griefe through feare or hope, vvell neere as though vve vvere then at the doing of them vvhere as notwithstanding vve be not in any paine or daunger, but only conceiue in our mindes the aduersities that other folkes haue indured, our selues sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting safe vvith our contentation and ease, according to these verses of the Poet Lucretius:
<q>
         <l>It is a pleasure for to sit at ease</l>
         <l>Vpon the land, and safely thence to see</l>
         <l>How other folkes are toffed on the seaes,</l>
         <l>That with the blustring windes turmoyled be.</l>
         <l>Not that the sight of others miseries</l>
         <l>Doth any way the honest hart delight,</l>
         <l>But for bicause it liketh well our eyes,</l>
         <l>To see harmes free that on our selues might light.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Also it is seene that the reading of histories doth so holde and allure good vvits, that diuers times it not only maketh them to forget all other pleasures, but also serueth very fittely to turne avvay their griefes, and somtimes also to remedie their diseases. As for example, vve find it vvritten of Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus King of Naples, that Prince so greatly renovvmed in Chronicles for his vvisedom and goodnesse, that being sore sicke in the citie of Capua, vvhen his Phisitions had spent all the cunning that they had to recouer him his health, and he savv that nothing preuailed: he determined vvith him selfe to take no mo medicines, but for his recreacion caused the storie of Quintus Curtius, concerning the deedes of Alexander the great, to be red before him: at the hearing vvhereof he tooke so vvonderfull pleasure, that nature gathered strength by it, and ouercame the vvayvvardnes of his disease. VVhereupon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing soone recouered his helth, he discharged his Phisitions vvith such vvords as these: Feast me no more vvith your Hippocrates and Galene, sith they can no skill to helpe me to recouer my helth: but vvell fare Quintus Curtius that could so good skill to helpe me to recouer my helth. Novv if the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and knovvledge of histories be delightfull and profitable to all other kind of folke: I say it is much more for great Princes and Kings, bicause they haue to do vvith charges of greatest vveight and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie, to be best stored vvith giftes and knovvledge for the discharge of their dueties: seeing the ground of stories is, to treate of all maner of high matters of state, as vvarres, battells, cities, contries, treaties of peace and alliances, and therefore it seemeth more fit for them, than for any other kinde of degrees of men: bicause they being bred and brought vp tenderly, and at their ease, by reason of the great regard and care that is had of their persons, (as meete is for so great states to haue) they take not so great paines in their youth for the learning of things as behoueth those to take vvhich vvill learne the noble auncient languages, and the painfull doctrine comprehended in Philosophie. Againe, vvhen they come to mans state, their charge calleth them to deale in great affaires, so as there remaineth no exercise of vvit more conuenient for thē, than the reading of histories in their ovvne tunge, vvhich vvithout paine is able to teache them euen vvith great pleasure and ease, vvhatsoeuer the painfull vvorkes of the Philosophers concerning the gouernment of common vveales can shevve them, to make them skilful in the vvell ruling and gouerning of the people and contries that God hath put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their subiection. But the vvorst is, that they euer (or for the most part) haue such maner of persons
<pb facs="6"/>
about them as seeke nothing els but to please them by all the vvayes they can, and there are very few that dare tell them the truth freely in all things: vvhere as on the contrary part, an history flattereth with them not, but layeth open before their eyes the faults and vices of such as vvere like them in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of degree. And therefore Demetrius Phalereus (a man renovvmed as vvell for his skill in the good gouernment of a common vveale, as for his excellent knovvledge othervvise) counselled Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, first king of AEgypt after the death of Alexander the great, that he should often and diligently reade the bookes that treated of the gouernment of kingdomes, bicause (sayd he) thou shalt finde many things there, vvhich thy seruaunts and familiar friendes dare not tell thee. Moreouer, this is another thinge, that suche great personages can not easily trauell out of the bounds of their dominions, to goe vievv straunge contries as priuate persons doe: bicause the ielousie of their estate, and the regarde of their dignitie, requires that they should neuer be in place vvhere another man might cōmaund them. And often times for vvant of hauing seene the contries, and knovven the people and Princes that are their neighbours, they haue aduentured vppon attempts vvithout good ground: to anoyde the vvhich, the instruction they may haue by the reading of histories, is one of the easiest and fittest remedies that can be found. And though there vvere none other cause then onely this last, surely it ought to induce Princes to the often and diligent reading of histories, vvherein are vvritten the heroicall deedes of vvise and valiant men, specially of kings that haue bene before them, the considering vvhereof may cause them to be desirous to become like them, specially vvhich vvere of stately and noble courage: bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the seedes of Princely vertues that are bred vvith them selues, doe then quicken them vp vvith an emulacion tovvards those that haue bene or are equall in degree vvith them, asvvell in respect of noblenes of bloud, as of greatnes of state, so as they be loth to giue place to any person, and much lesse can find in their harts to be outgone in glory of vertuous doinges. VVhereof innumerable examples might be alleaged, if the thing vvere not so vvelknovven of it self, that it vvere much more against reason to doubt of it, than needefull to proue it. Therefore a man may truely conclude, that an historie is the scholemistresse of Princes, at vvhose hand they may vvithout payne, in vvay of pastyme, &amp; vvith singular pleasure learne the most part of the things that belonge to their office. Novv, according to the diuersitie of the matter that it treateth of, or the order and manner of vvriting that it vseth, it hath sondry names giuen vnto it: But yet among the rest there are tvvo chiefe kinds. The one vvhich set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth dovvne mens doings and aduentures at length, is called by the common name of an historie: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvhich declareth their natures, sayings, and maners, is properly named their liues. And although the ground of them both doe cloze very neare in one, yet doth the one respect more the things, and the other the persons: the one is more common, and the other more priuate: the one concerneth more the things that are vvithout the man, and the other the things that proceede from vvithin: the one the euents, the other the consultacions: betvvene the vvhich there is oftentymes great oddes, according to this aunsvver of the Persian Siramnes, to such as maruelled hovv it came to passe, that his deuises being so politike had so vnhappy sucesse: It is (quod he) bicause my deuises are vvholly from my ovvn inuention, but the effects of them are in the disposition of fortune and the king. And surely amonge all those that euer haue taken vppon them to vvrite the liues of famous men, the chiefe prerogatiue, by the iudgement of such as are clearest sighted, is iustly giuen to the Greeke Philosopher Plutarke, borne in the citie of Chaeronea in the contry of Baeotia, a noble man, perfect in all rare knovvledge, as his vvorkes may vvell put men out of doubt, if they lyst to read them through, vvho all his life long euen to his old age, had to deale in affayres of the common vveale, as he him selfe vvitnesseth in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, specially in the treatise vvhich he intitled, <hi>VVhether and olde man ought to meddle with the gouernment of a common weale or not:</hi> and vvho had the hap &amp; honor to be schoolemaster to the Emprour Traian, as is commonly beleeued, and as is expressely pretended by a certaine Epistle se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Latin translation of his matters of state, vvhich (to say the truth) seemeth in my iudgement to be somevvhat suspicious, bicause I find it not among his vvorkes in Greeke, besides that is speaketh as though the booke vvere dedicated to Traian, vvhich thinge is manifestly disproued by the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the booke, and by diuers other reasons. Yet not vvithstanding, bicause me thinkes it sagely &amp; grauely vvritten, and vvell be seeming him: I haue set it dovvne here in this place.
<q>Plutarke vnto Traeian sendeth greeting. I knovv vvell that the modestie of your nature vvas not desirous of Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reintie, though you haue alvvayes indeuored to deserue it by your honorable conuersation by reason
<pb facs="7"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="7"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="8"/>
vvhereof you have bene thought so much the vvorthier of it, as you have bene founde the further of from all ambition. And therefore I do novv reioice in your vertue &amp; my fortune, if it be so great as to cause you to administer that thing vvith iustice, vvhich you haue obtained by desert. For othervvise I am sure you haue put your selfe in hazard of great daungers, and me in perill of slaunderous tongues, bicause Rome can not avvay vvith a vvicked Emperour, and the common voyce of the people is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies vvont to cast the faultes of the schollers in the teeth of their schoolemaisters: as for example: Seneca is railed vpon by slaunderous tonges, for the faultes of his scholler Nero: the scapes of Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians young schollers are imputed to Quintilian him selfe: and Socrates is blamed, for being too myld to his bearers. But as for you, there is hope you shall doe all things vvell enough, so you keepe you as you are. If you first set your selfe in order, and then dispose all other things according to vertue, all things shall fall out according to your desire. I haue set you dovvne the meanes in vvriting, vvhich you must observe for the vvell gouerning of your common vveale, and haue shevved you of hovv great force your behauiour may be in that behalfe. If you thinke good to follovv those thinges, you haue Plutarke for the directer and guider of your life: if not, I protest vnto you by this Epistle, that your falling into daunger to the ouerthrovv of the Empire, is not by the doctrine of Plutarke.</q>
This Epistle vvitnesseth plainly that he vvas the schoolemaister of Traian, vvhich thing seemeth so be auovved by this vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Suidas: Plutarke being borne in the citie of Chaeronea in Boeotia, vvas in the time of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Traian, and somvvhat affore. But Traian honored him vvith the dignitie of Consulship, and commaunded the officers and Magistrates that vvere throughout all the contrie of Illyria, that they should not do any thing vvithout his counsell and authoritie. So doth Suidas vvrite of him. And I am of opinion, that Traian being so vvise an Emperour, vvould neuer haue done him so great honor, if he had not thought him selfe greatly beholding to him for some speciall cause. But the thing that maketh me most to beleue it true, is, that the same goodnesse and iustice appeared to be naturally imprinted in most of Traians sayings and doings, vvhereof the paterne and movvld (as a man might terme it) is cast and set dovvne in Plutarkes Moralls, so as men may perceiue expressely, that the one could vvell skill to performe rightly, that vvhich the other had taught vvisely. For Dion vvriteth, that among other honors vvhich the Senate of Rome gaue by decree vnto Traian, they gaue him the title of the Good Emperour. And Eutropius reporteth that euen vnto his time, vvhen a nevv Emperour came to be receiued of the Senate, among the cries of good hansell, and the vvishes of good lucke that vvere made vnto him, one vvas: happier be thou than Augustus, and better than Traian. Hovvsoeuer the case stoode, it is very certaine that Plutarke dedicated the collection of his Apothegmes vnto him. But vvhen he had liued a long time at Rome, and vvas come home againe to his ovvne house, he fell to vvriting of this excellent vvorke of Liues, vvhich he calleth Parallelon, as much to say, as a cupling or matching together, bicause he matcheth a Grecian vvith a Romane, setting dovvne their liues ech after other, and comparing them together, as he founde any likenesse of nature, condicions, or aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures betvvext them, and examining vvhat the one of them had better or vvorser, greater or lesser than the other: vvhich things he doth vvith so goodly and graue discourse euery vvhere, taken out of the deepest &amp; most hidden secrets of morall and naturall Philosophie, vvith so sage precepts and frute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full instructions, vvith so effectuall commendation of vertue, and detestation of vice, vvith so many goodly allegacions of other authors, vvith so many fit comparisons, &amp; vvith so many high inuentions: that the booke may better be called by the name of the Treasorie of all rare and perfect learning, than by any other name. Also it is sayd, that Theadorus Gaza, a Grecian of singular learning, and a vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the auncient Greece, being asked on a time by his familiar frendes (vvhich savv him so ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly giuen to his studie, that he forgate all other things) vvhat author he had leuerest to thoose, if he vvere at that poynt that he must needes choose some one to holde him to alone, did aunsvvere that he vvould choose Plutarke: bicause that if they vvere all put together, there vvas no one both so profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and so pleasaunt to read, as be. Sofuss Senecio to vvhom he dedicateth his vvorke, vvas a Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Rome, as vvitnesseth Dion, vvho vvriteth that the three persons vvhom Traian most loued and honored, vvere Sosius, Parma, and Celsus, insomuch that he caused images of them to be set vp. True it is that he vvrote the liues of many other men, vvhich the spitefulnes of time hath bereft vs of, among vvhich he himselfe maketh mention of the liues of Scipio Africanus, &amp; Metellus Namedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. And I haue red a litle Epistle of a sonne of his, vvhose name is not expressed, copied out of an olde
<pb facs="8"/>
copie in the Librarie of S. Marke in White, vvherein he vvriteth to a frende of his, a register of all the bookes that his father made: and there among the cupples of liues, he setteth dovvne liues of Scipio and Epaminondas, and lastly the liues of Augustus Caesar, of Tiberius; of Caligula, of Clandius, of Nero, of Galba, of Vitellius, and of Otho. But hauing vsed all the diligence that I could in serching the chiefe Libraries of Venice, and Rome, I could neuer find them out. Onely I drevv out certaine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersities of readinges, and many corrections by conferring the old vvritten copies vvith the printed bookes: vvhich haue stoode are in great stead to the vnderstanding of many hardplaces: and there are a great number of them vvhich I haue resto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed by coniecture, by the iudgement &amp; helpe of such men of this age, as are of greatest knovvledge in humane learning. Yet for all this, there remaine some places vnamended, hovvbeit very fevve, bicause some likes vvere vvanting in the originall copies, vvhereof (to my seeming) it vvas better for me to vvitnesse the vvant by marking it vvith some starre: than to gesse at it vvith all aduenture, or to adde any thing to it. Novv finally, if I haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot my selfe in any thing, as it is verie easie to do in so hard and long a vvorke, specially to a man of so small abilitie as I am: I beseeche the Readers to vvouchsafe for my discharge, to admit the excuse vvhich the Poet Horace giueth me, vvhere he sayth:
<q>
         <l>A man may well be ouerseene</l>
         <l>In workes that long and tedious bene.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Specially sith that of so many good men &amp; men of skill as haue heretofore set hand to the translating of it, there vvas neuer yet any one found that vvent through vvith it in any language, at least vvise that I haue seene or heard of: and that such as haue enterprised to translate it, specially into Latin, haue euidently vvitnessed the hardnesse thereof, as they may easely perceiue vvhich list to conserve their translations vvith mine. Neuerthelesse if also fortune that men find not the speech of this translation so flovving, as they haue found some other of mine, that are abroad in mens hands: I beseech the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to consider, that the office of a fit translater, consisteth not onely in the faithfull expressing of his authors meaning, but also in a certaine resembling and shadovving out of the forme of his style and the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap> of his speaking: vnlesse he vvill commit the errour of some painters, vvho hauing taken vpon them to dravv a man lively, do paint him long vvhere he should be short, and grosse vvhere he should be slender, and yet set out the resemblance of his countenance naturally. For hovv harsh or rude soeuer my speech be, yet am I sure that my translation vvill be much easier to my contriemen, than the Greeke copie is, euen to such as are best practised in the Greeke tonge, by reason of Plutarkes peculiar maner of inditing, vvhich is rather sharpe, learned, and short, than plaine, polished, and easie. At the hardest, although I haue not compassed my matters so happily as ye coulde haue vvished and desired: yet do I hope that your Lordships in reading it vvill hold the parties good vvill excused, vvhich hath taken such paines in doing of it to profit you. And if my labor be so happie, as to content you: God be praised for it, vvhich hath giuen me the grace to finish it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>