<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faultes escaped in the printing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1664_Ba1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15418</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20485</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faultes escaped in the printing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations vppon the mysteries of our holy faith : with the practise of mental praier touching the same, composed in Spanish by the R.F. Luys de la Puente of the Societie of Iesus, natiue of Valladolid. And translated into English by F. Rich. Gibbons of the same Societie. The first part. The contents of this woorke are to bee seene in the page folowing</title>
                 <author>Puente, Luis de la</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 94, 97-359, 19, 306, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="191"/>
   <head>Faultes escaped in the printing.</head>
   <p>Pag. 52. contended, reade contented p. 53. then, them. p. 51. him, hir. p. 172. the, thee. p. 194, wich, with. p. 195. rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, recaled. ibid. vould, would. ibid. out, our. p. 196. perfocre, perforce. ibid. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumsemee, accuse mee. ibid. the, them. p. 202. whosoeuet, whosoeuer. ibid. mother, mother. ibid. haut, haue. p. 203. peruersc, peruerse. p. 204. thee, the. p. 206. haut, haue. p. 207. danmed, damned. ibid. neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, neighbour. ibid. hec, her. p. 210. might, night. ibid. on wicked, on the wicked. p. 212. his, this. ibid. Cod, God. p. 213. fuffer, suffer. ibid se, so. p. 215. deliuee, deliuer. p. 220. vs, as. ibid. man, many. p. 122. which the damned, which the exteriour senses of the damned. p. 224. ane, and. p. 225. and, and. p. 227. from all, from all this. p. 234. these, there. p. 235. shall, shalt. p. 296. puritie, purifie. ibid. bening, being. ibid, fillowing, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. p. 297. in good, in the good. p. 299. thee, the p. 230. thee, there.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Good Reader, if thou finde any other which I haue ommitted, I pray thee of thy curtesie to correct them.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="191"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>