<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR, TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1683_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19434</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5861.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1683</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR, TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Anti-Coton, or, A Refutation of Cottons letter declaratorie : lately directed to the Queene Regent, for the apologizing of the Iesuites doctrine, touching the killing of kings : a booke, in which it is proued that the Iesuites are guiltie, and were the authors of the late execrable parricide, committed vpon the person of the French King, Henry the Fourth, of happie memorie : to which is added, a Supplication of the Vniuersitie of Paris, for the preuenting of the Iesuites opening their schooles among them, in which their king-killing doctrine is also notably discouered, and confuted / both translated out of the French, by G.H. ; together with the translators animaduersions vpon Cottons letter</title>
                 <author>Du Coignet, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Boyle, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 76, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="44"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR, TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat thou be not ignorant of the occasion
of <hi>Anti-coton,</hi> bepleased to be informed,
that since the last execrable parricide in
France, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Doctors of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> met
together in solemne Conuocation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
a booke written by <hi>Iohn Mariana</hi> a Spanish Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suite,
maintaining the murthering of Kings, and before
that, was it adiudged by the presidents of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Paris, that the said booke should publikely be
burnt by the common executioner before the great gate
of the Pallace, and withall as well the buying as selling
of it was by them straitly forbidden; hereupon a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
spread it selfe, that the Iesuites generally main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
the same opinion: and consequently their writings
to that purpose were as lyable to censure and fire as that
of <hi>Mariana</hi> Whereupon <hi>Cotton</hi> newly returned from
the Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erals of the Kings heart at <hi>la Flesche,</hi> and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
to be much appaled with this unexpected noyse,
was in a manner co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>strained (for the making up of this
sodaine breach) presently to put pen to paper to disclaime
what <hi>Mariana</hi> had affirmed, to produce the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
of his associates, who seemed to defend the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie;
and lastly, to set downe those articles in this point,
<pb facs="45"/>
which his societie (as he pretended) would stand vnto;
upon this <hi>Declaratorie Letter</hi> of <hi>Cottons</hi> (as himselfe
termes it) dedicated to the <hi>Queene Regent,</hi> comes forth
within a very short space this <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> (written a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
it seemes by one of the same Religion, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but carrie the greater shew of truth,) which labours
to proue against <hi>Cotton,</hi> that the doctrine and practise
of the Iesuites made a ready way vnto, if not acted, the
late horrible blow in Fraunce: which booke (as I am cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly
informed by a friend of good intelligence and credit,
<hi>being greedily deuoured of all sorts of the French,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Auidissime l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ab omnibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sque adeo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssit Cottonum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini exciuerit lachrymas prae dolore &amp; iudig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione.</note>
      <hi>So
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ung</hi> Cotton, <hi>that it wrung teares from him for very
griefe and indignation,</hi> and personall imputations (as
you know) the truer they are, the deeper impressions they
usually worke. Now because I suppose some may be desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
more particularly to understand of the quality of
this <hi>Cotton</hi> (who is so often named thorow this worke,)
for the further content of such, I can assure them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
France he carries the name rather of a good Orator, then
a deepe Clark, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> better what belongs to points
of Courtiership, then Schollership, notwithstanding a man
he is, much magnified by his owne Societie, for hauing so
thorowly understood, and fully possessed the affections of
the last King, as if he had inchanted him; to whom hee
was both Confessor and Preacher: and was besides that
both at meales and at Masse continually in his eare, no
man more; insomuch that in Fraunce it grew to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
iest upon any repulse from the King, or deniall of
acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him; <hi>Les oreills du Roy sont buschees de</hi>
Cotton: <hi>The Kings eares are stopt with</hi> Cotton. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
about three yeares since this Pasquill flew abroad
in Paris.</p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="45"/>
      <lg>
         <l>Le Roy ne scauroit faire vn pas,</l>
         <l>Que le Pere <hi>Cotton</hi> l'accompagne:</l>
         <l>Mais le bon Sire ne scait pas,</l>
         <l>Que le fin<note place="margin">
               <hi>Fin</hi> in the French signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies as vvel craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as fine.</note> Cotton vient d'Espagne.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>The King no where can step a foote,</l>
         <l>But Father <hi>Cotton</hi> findes him out:</l>
         <l>But the good King is not aware,</l>
         <l>That fine Cotton is Spanish ware.</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
   <p>But I leaue his person, and returne againe to his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
in the scanning of which I have somewhat to say to
him, which the Author of <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> passeth by, which
is this; that whereas he vndertakes to proue that the
other Iesuites accord not with <hi>Mariana,</hi> in the doctrine
of making away Princes, and to that end produceth the
testimonie of <hi>Becanus,</hi> one of their chiefe pillars: tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to the passage he quotes, I finde that <hi>Becanus</hi> in
that very place approues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> in expresse
termes, and withall holds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> common tenent of
the Iesuites, his words are these▪ <hi>In respons▪ ad Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rism.
9. At{que} haecest expressa sententia</hi> Iohannis Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae
<hi>loco citato, &amp; aliorum Iesuitarum qui ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> de re
scripserunt, in qua non video quid Caluinistae possint
meritò reprehendere:</hi> And this is expresly the opinion
of <hi>Iohn Mariana</hi> in the place alledged, as also of the other
Iesuites who haue written touching this subiect, in which
I see not what it is which the Caluinists ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> iustly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue.
That which I now affirme is a matter of fact, and
therefore needes no more adoe then the opening of the
Booke, and the reading of the text.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="46"/>Againe in producing <hi>Gregorie de Valentia</hi> his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie
of him,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 2 2. disp. 5. quest. 8. punct. 3.</note> he affirmes, <hi>determine qu'il n'est nulle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
permis d'attenter sur la vie du Prince, iaçoit
qu'il abuse deson authorite:</hi> he concludes, that it is in
no case lawfull to make a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> assault upon the person of the
Prince, howbeit be abuse his authoritie▪ Whereas the said
<hi>Valentian</hi> in the same place by him alledged, first distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing
of a tyrant by adminis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ration and usurpation,
plainely affirmeth, <hi>de primo eadem estratio, ac de alijs
malefactoribus▪ qui solum per publicam pote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>atem
puniri possint:</hi> of a tyrant taken in the first sense (that is
by administration) there is the same reason as of other
malefactors, who cannot be punished but by publike au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie.
In which words he seemes to me to range un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly
Princes (though they pretend neuer so iust a title to
their Crownes) in the Catalogue of common murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
and theeues, and to make them as abnoxious to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
censure, whereas <hi>Cotton</hi> would make us beleeue
that he holds their persons altogether inuiolable.</p>
   <p>Lastly, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> to say at this time against
<hi>Cotton,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> he alledgeth is this; against
himselfe, that he prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eth, the opinion in this case of all
the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>suites in common, and euery of them in pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ticular,
no way to dissent or vary from that of the uniuersall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique
Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rch, which assertion of his to be meerely u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true,
shall hereafter (God willing) be fully demonstrated,
by making it cleerely appeare what the Catholique
Church hath euer taught and practised in this point from
age to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> downe to thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> very present times, and by
comparing it with that which the Iesuites now adayes
generally both teach and practis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. Against the Authors
he alledgeth this I say, that whereas they impute the
<pb facs="46"/>
occasion of the Canon of the Councell of <hi>Constance</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
tyrannicides,<note place="margin">Azorius Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, alij{que}.</note> to the doctrine of the Hussites, it
must needs arise either from their ignorance, or their
malice, or both; for had they but read the Canon it selfe
as it is laid down in the body of the Councel, or Iohn <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
In his proposition on the behalfe of the French
King:</hi> or lastly, <hi>The French Historie</hi> in the life of
<hi>Charles</hi> the sixt, they might easily haue perceiued that
the occasion thereof grew from a doctrine which <hi>Iohn Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit,</hi>
a Doctor of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> set a foote in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aris on the
behalfe of <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of Burgundie, who tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>herously
shew <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of Orleance, as the author of this prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
Booke hath rightly obserued, in the very first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
thereof, and surely I make no doubt but the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
part of those Fathers who met at that Councell, if
they now liued and saw how matters are carryed in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m,
would as willingly subscribe to the censuring
of that opinion which the Iesuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> maintain tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
to making away of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> did to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation
of that of <hi>Iohn</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> very deed and
truth is little or nothing differing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rom that of the Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites,
sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e onely they are growne more cunning to east a
fairer glasse &amp; varnish vpon it. Thus much haue I added,
not that I take any pleasure in ripping vp and discouering
other mens imperfections, which with my heart I rather
wish were not; or in exagitating that Sect among whom
reside many excellent wits, but which dwell ill, and as he
said, <hi>in malum publicum,</hi> but only that I migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a little
farther search into that wound which I find cannot be
cured without much launcing: in the meane time my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
is, and daily prayer vnto God shall be, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
wee differ in some points of our Religion, yet
<pb facs="47"/>
we may all agree in our obedience to our Soueraigne, and
striue on each side to gaine credit to our Religion by the
fruits of our obedience, as assuring o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r selu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s (because
Truth it selfe hath deliuered it) that <hi>Obedience is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then Sacrifice:</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 22. Ita a plebibus Principes, &amp; a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is domini fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>di sunt, vt sub <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rcitati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>leranti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Iconclude with S. <hi>Augustine: So are
Subiects to beare with their Soueraignes, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
with their Lords, that through the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
of our patience, things transitorie
may be endured, and eternall
hoped for.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="47"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>