<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1715_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11802</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22097a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1715</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vox Dei</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 86, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER</head>
   <p>IT may be thought (<hi>perhaps</hi>) by some, which shall vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe
to reade this following discourse, that my generall
aymes in this publication, are, to exasperate the humor of
the tyme (too tart (as some thinke)▪ already) against the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Adversary,</hi> and withall, to flatter my selfe into favour, by
needles repetitions of notable <hi>by-past</hi> actions.</p>
   <p>For the <hi>first,</hi> let such know, that neither my minde, nor
my booke, looke higher then the <hi>middle Region,</hi> being both
bred, and conversing continually in the <hi>inferiour,</hi> where, they
haue no force to raise stormes of action, but to participate
in passion, with such gufts as fall from aboue. I am not so
vaine-gloriously apprehensiue, as to thinke my selfe able, to
raise the least dust, with any feete but mine owne; or to work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
vpon the judgement of any man, with my weake oratory, to
moue him to a violent course, beyond his naturall inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
Yet thus much I say for my selfe, and my cause, that if
I should avme at what they object, and should accomplish
my aymes, I did no more, then the greatest, wisest, devoutest,
amongst them, <hi>professe</hi> to doe, and <hi>practise</hi> continually, against
vs, &amp; <hi>praise</hi> in others, so following their footesteps. Witnesse
that treatise (amongst divers the like) which <hi>Scioppius,</hi> (a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Counsellor for the house of <hi>Austria</hi>) hath made against
the protestants, and intituled, <hi>Classicum Belli sacri▪ Siue s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>asoria ad
Imperatorem de Christiani Caesaris, erga Principes Ecclesiae rebelles offici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,
&amp; veris Haereticorum compescendorum rationibis. Fdito. 1619. A Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet
of the holy warre;</hi> wherem by authority of <hi>Scripture,</hi> pitifully
wrested, and misapplied, by reasons of state, and policy, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently
vrged, and wrung to force out blood, he moues, and
excites, nay, as it were, inforceth, the house of <hi>Austria</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,
and in particular the <hi>Emperour</hi> (&amp; so by consequence
the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi>) to a merciles massacre, of their subjects, &amp;
neigbours, round about, against whome they may any way
<pb facs="4"/>
pick a quarrell, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for point of <hi>Religion.</hi> And what needes the
blood of <hi>Austria</hi> be heated to this end?</p>
   <p>I am to be blamed (with others) therfore, if my zeale for
truth be any whit colder, then his for falsehood; and I am to
be pardoned, and excused, even by such as are of his opinion,
if I pursue as eagerly (as he doth) the side, and cause I affect;
and resist vnto blood, where he bloodely assaults my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,
or the innocent truth in me, and in others. Nay, let
this worke of his, moue all Counsellors, and others, that haue
place about Princes, and Power with them, to doe their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes
in a contrary course, and whet the edge of authority,
with all the arguments of their art, to shew it selfe sharpe
for <hi>Christ,</hi> and his cause, against <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and his adherents.
And let not their goodly discretion, and moderation, delude
the world any longer, with vaine expectations, and promises,
as if they were (like <hi>Iobs</hi> faint freindes) <hi>lob 12. 2. the only people,</hi>
and <hi>that all wisedome lived in them, and should dye with them;</hi> least if
they dally any longer, <hi>the axe be layd to the roote of the tree, Mat.</hi> 3.
and they for their fruitles <hi>fearnes,</hi> without sap of sincerity
or piety, (only with a smoake or, shadowing of hypocrisy) be
cast into the vnquenchable fyre of <hi>Gods</hi> just judgement. <hi>Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly,
Necessity calls vpon vs, to do something in time, for our cause,</hi>
and our freindes, or to prepare our selves <hi>to suffer</hi> all
thinges from our Enemyes. <hi>Spaine</hi> can easely charme <hi>France,</hi>
by the helpe of the <hi>Iesuites,</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> to sit still, and giue ayme,
till his foote be vpon the neck of the <hi>Vnited Provinces;</hi> for it
wilbe made a warre of religion, which <hi>France,</hi> (as the eldest
sonne of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church) is by all meanes to advance. If
then they can keepe <hi>vs</hi> back, but a while longer, either by
pretences, or promises, or gifts, or presents, or pensions, or
<hi>East-Indian</hi> quarrells, or treatyes, or marriages, or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
or by any other meanes, the goale is gotten, and wee
must be forced to take the law from them, and to admit, not
only. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lleration,</hi> but also <hi>Alteration</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and perhaps
<pb facs="4"/>
the <hi>Inquisition</hi> also, into our land, in spite of our hearts
though wee, &amp; our King with vs, say <hi>NOE</hi> never so loud; ther
will neither heare vs, nor beleeue vs, nor then admit of our
negatiue voyce. And I am perswaded all that are not of this
minde, &amp; so ready to take all occasiōs, vse all meanes, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
it; are of their minde, and wills take all occasions; &amp; vse
all meanes (though closely, and by degrees) to advance it.</p>
   <p>For the second objection, made by such, as thinke I am
out of favour, &amp; intend hereby to flatter my selfe into grace
againe; I let such know, that as I account the favour of my
superiours, to be a great blessing, so (beleeving I never lost it,
at least by desert) I professe sincerely not to seeke it, with
any corrupt or ambitious thought. If what I write offend not,
it is the yttermost extent, yea crowne of my happinesse here;
being for the rest contented, and holding it a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
to liue in any ayre, and to be buryed in any soyle; Since
<hi>I liue by faith,</hi> and expect the <hi>resurrection of the just.</hi> But the truth
is, that as those who looke on, doe often see, what the Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
over-see; And as those who stand in a direct lyne against
the mouth of the Cannon, cannot discerne the danger co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meing
swifftly vpon them, soe well as those that stād a-loofe
off, and obliquely: soe wee that stand removed from the
steeple, heare the noyse of the bells distinctly, and where
they jangle, and where they ring round, and where they vary
with musicall, and delightfull changes; which such as stand
vnder, cannot so perfectly judge.</p>
   <p>And wee thinke wee saw the danger coming, and were
more sensible of it, then many seemed to bee, that stood with
in the dint: And now (hoping the greatest storme is over) wee
behold the deliverance with more admiration, then many
seeme to haue done, which stood neerer the danger. And to
this end wee write, that you may read, and see, and applaud
your owne felicity with ours, giving glory to <hi>God,</hi> and due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
to the instruments, he hath beene pleased to vse in this
<pb facs="5"/>
great▪ and miraculous worke of his mercy.</p>
   <p>For to this end the Lord doth all his workes of wonder, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting
well of their service, who set forth his <hi>praise with the
best instruments that they haue;</hi> denyeing only to be gratious to
such, as neglect his workes, or passe them by, without obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
and threatning to punish such severely, who rob him
of his glory, either arrogating it to themselves, or imputing
it vnworthily to others.</p>
   <p>Herein, therefore, I do but, with <hi>Moses,</hi> salute <hi>God</hi> with a
songe, having past the red sea, looking back vpon it with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration,
and beholding <hi>Pharoh Exod.</hi> 15.and his Hoast in it,
with pitty and astonishment: I doe but, with <hi>Deborah,</hi> call vp
<hi>Barak, Iud.</hi> 5. to the triumph: And, with the <hi>Virgins,</hi> meete <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. after his victory, with timbells &amp; dances.</p>
   <p>This is the true end of writing this treatise, wherein if I
erre in any point of Divinity, History, or Pollicy, either in
relation, or application, I referre my self most humbly to
the favorable censure of the Church and State, not being
willing to commit a fault against either, or having done it, to
defend it with obstinacy. Yet before wee part, giue me leaue
to say, that whilst I hope wee are past the danger, I would be
so vnderstood as a man that partly feared, wee were not.
Warre must be proclaimed with <hi>Spaine,</hi> before wee can be
fully resolued; othevwise our <hi>offensiue warres</hi> against the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
Bavaris,</hi> or any other, &amp; our <hi>defensiue,</hi> and <hi>divertiue</hi> warres
by assisting the <hi>States Generall,</hi> will proue vndertakings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
our selues, and we (running our selves out of breath)
will soone learne to repent our forwardnes, &amp; call for peace,
faster then wee haue done for warre. Our comings in, must
be answerable to our expences, if wee meane to holde out:
for though the horse be fat &amp; strong, yet if wee ride him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
without provender, he will waxe weake, and leane,
and trye vnder vs. To warre with the <hi>Emperour</hi> &amp;, hold peace
with <hi>Spaine,</hi> is to fight with one of our hands, against the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="5"/>
body of the Catholique league, assisted with both their
armes of the <hi>East,</hi> and <hi>West-Indyes,</hi> whose force is sufficient, to
buy <hi>Briareus,</hi> to side with them, against <hi>God,</hi> and his truth, and
from whence, all the arrowes they shoote against <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ome,</hi>
at this present, are both headed, and feathered; pluck
off these, and they hurt not. And the way to pluck off these,
and so to make peace, is to send out our <hi>Navie</hi> (as wee had
wont) to fish for gould in their seas. For our <hi>Navie</hi> is the <hi>right
hand</hi> of our State, of whole advantageous vse, wee depriue our
selves, when wee warre in a cold and lame manner, only with
the <hi>left hand</hi> by <hi>defence,</hi> by <hi>divertion,</hi> and that by <hi>land,</hi> where the
enemyes strength lyes. This is, to fight, and let him <hi>choose</hi> the
weapon, and to spend our blowes, where wee see him best
<hi>armed.</hi> It is the <hi>Navie</hi> that weakens the Enemy, by taking
from him, and spoiling, what he gets to spoile others. It is the
<hi>Navie,</hi> that causeth his <hi>West-Indian Fleetes</hi> to be wasted home
with such a guard, as eat's out the gaine of that <hi>voyage;</hi> though
they returne safe, but vndoes him, if they miscarry. It is the
<hi>Navie</hi> that payes the troopes by land, &amp; fills the Ercheaquer
faster, then all the customes, &amp; projects, vnprofitable peace
can invent, though it would study to exact still from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious
Marchant, even to his vndoeing. Witnesse our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
warres <hi>in Yreland,</hi> where there was no boote for the soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diar,
as in other parts may be found, (if at least wee serue
them, and theirs, as they did vs, and ours, in the <hi>Paltz.</hi>) but all
the Army was to liue (as wee say) vpon the <hi>penny.</hi> And yet for
all that expence in <hi>Yreland, Scotland, Sweden, Denmarke, France,</hi> in
the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and all other partes, where <hi>Antichrist</hi> advanced
his counterfeit <hi>crosse,</hi> against the crosse of <hi>Christ,</hi> how rich was
the subject? how plentifull all provisions? how quick all
trades, &amp; trading? how well stored was the Ercheaquer with
Coyne, the mint with Bullion, the Tower, and all other places
with ordinance, ammunition, plate, hangings, jewells? The
expence, and waste, of treasure since, meerely vpon the old
<pb facs="6"/>
stock, without any equall, annuall, and certaine supply, the
raysing and allaying of golde and silver, without curing our
generall wāt (which <hi>Spaine</hi> withall the Enemyes, &amp; warres our
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> had, could not make her do as her <hi>Epitaph</hi> tells you)
is a witnesse of this truth beyond contradiction. If therefore
wee haue warres with the <hi>Emperour,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bavaria,</hi> (heare my folly
and pardon it; <hi>wisemen</hi> may proffit by the prating of fooles)
let vs haue it with <hi>Spaine;</hi> If wee defend the <hi>States,</hi> and <hi>our
selves,</hi> with the <hi>lef hand,</hi> let vs fight with the <hi>right hand</hi> also,
and put <hi>Spaine</hi> to his fence; let vs vse both hands, or neither;
let vs (to conclude) fight in good earnest, or lay downe the
bucklers, and submit our selves to their mercy, who will,
without question, cut our throates in kindnes with the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
expedition, as they haue done our freindes, vpon the
same tearmes.</p>
   <p>Consider I beseech thee, advised <hi>Reader,</hi> how the <hi>Navy</hi>
(which I spake of) lyes now idle; a great &amp; continuall charge
to the state, the <hi>Marriners,</hi> the <hi>Officers,</hi> the <hi>Seamen</hi> of all
sorts, waste away, are vnprofitable, forget their professions,
when, if these were imployed (as I haue spoken) they would
recover our reputation, be a security to our selves, a terror
to our enemyes, make vs againe Masters, not only of the
narrow seas, but of the Ocean, beare their owne charges, &amp;
helpe to defray others. In which regard (giue me leaue to
proceede in playing the foole) I suppose if the <hi>East-Indian
Fleete,</hi> and stock, were thus imployed, we would soone finde
the odds of the adventure, &amp; neither the state, nor the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
would repent them of the change, although wee
bought spice at the second hand, or spent lesse then wee doe
(as other Countryes vse,) or permitted voluntaryes to trade
in those seas.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the <hi>Hollander</hi> who findes how hard, or booteles it
is to sayle against the sunne, sees his owne fault, and begins
to steere a contrary course, and though he still hold his
<pb facs="6"/>
ground, and trade in the East, yet finding it a drayne for the
treasure of <hi>Christendome,</hi> it is probable he will lessen his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
there,and seeke out Westward for gould and silver, to
feede that couetous Easterne climate, as wee may doe also, if
wee be not <hi>too wise</hi> to learne, and <hi>too proud</hi> to follow, when
they goe before.</p>
   <p>But some object, that what wee had wont to get alone in
the West &amp; South-sea, the <hi>Hollander</hi> now meete's withall, and
takes vp, by fore-stalling the market; so that there will not
bee sufficient, to beare the charges of both Nations. As if
the <hi>Hollander</hi> tooke all, and no fish past his net: Nay assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
if both of vs went out vpon this errand, both should haue
more, whilst one helped the other. Besides the <hi>Hollander</hi> is
more numerous in shipping, and those commonly of better
sayle then ours, and so fit for scouts, to beate the water; ours,
are better built, better man'd, better armed, fitter for fight,
and so like to speede better, if there should be fraude in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship.</p>
   <p>Thus much I thought good to add, not as a Counsellour,
but as an Intelligencer, for my King, and Country; and if any
say it suites me not, to stirre vp warre, being by <hi>profession</hi> a
<hi>Peace-maker:</hi> I answer, though I feare I shall haue no such
force to moue that heavy Engine, yet the <hi>necessity</hi> of the case
makes me attempt it, and put my hand, to a multitude of
others, who wynne hearts, and hands to this end: And the
same <hi>Necessity</hi> pleades my excuse, whilst I seeme to transgresse
the lawes of my Commission; since there is no other sure
way to make peace, or to saue the effusion of Christian blood
(so much sought after, and so sweete in the tast of those wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish
<hi>Antichristians)</hi> then thus to take this <hi>fire-brand,</hi> this <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netainer
of quarrells</hi> (Gould) out of the hands of the common
<hi>Quarreller.</hi> If any thinke otherwise, I feare he shall finde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
deceaved, when it wilbe a shame for a wiseman to say,
<hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n putaram.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
For my selfe, let men thinke of me as they please; It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
good in my opinion, <hi>to play the foole</hi> (as wisemen say) <hi>in print <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
selfe,</hi> since it must needes be done, as to suffer <hi>see many others</hi> to
doe it in <hi>my name,</hi> or to looke on, and hold my peace till my
King, Couutry, and Religion, be betrayed. Now though it
be not in my private power to remedy these evills, yet the
world shall witnesse for me, I am free from the blood of all
men, and no way accessary, or priuie, to those mynes which
are ready to springe, to the hazard, not only of our state, but
of the liberty of all <hi>Christendome</hi> besides. From which conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,
they can no way cleere themselves, who having place
to speake (bee it <hi>purdue, Sentinell, or Corps du gard,</hi> high or low)
hold their peace whilst the Enemy approcheth. <hi>Canes latr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
pro Dominis suis, &amp; non vis me latrare pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Christo? Mori possum, tacen
non possum. Hierom. Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l. 3. adversus Ruffin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> Dogs bar ke for
their Masters, and will not thou haue me open my mouth for
<hi>Christ?</hi> I can dye, I cannot hold my tongue. <hi>God hath not give
vs the spirit of feare, but of power, and loue, &amp; of a sound minde, 2 Tim.</hi>
1. 7. Therefore after <hi>vox Dei,</hi> expect <hi>vox Regis,</hi> to follow with
the vtmost speede; when the King hath heard <hi>Gods voyce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi>
wee shall heare the Kinges <hi>voyce ecchoing.</hi> Pray for this
houre, and in the meane time, pardon what errors thou m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>test withall, whether of myne, or the <hi>Printers,</hi> be it in matter,
in wordes, or letters, or in pointes, the greatest I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
observed to thy hand, it is like there may be more, since I
could not be neere the Presse, and the <hi>Printer</hi> vnderstands
no English, therefore before thou reade, be entreated i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
reforme such as thou findest in the <hi>Catalogue.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>