<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADIOYNDER OF SVNDRY OTHER PARTICV∣LAR WICKED PLOTS AND Cruell, Inhumane, Perfidious; yea, Vnnaturall practises of the Spaniards.</title>
           <author>O., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1714_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11787</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22078.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADIOYNDER OF SVNDRY OTHER PARTICV∣LAR WICKED PLOTS AND Cruell, Inhumane, Perfidious; yea, Vnnaturall practises of the Spaniards.</title>
                 <author>O., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A second part of Spanish practises. Or, A relation of more particular wicked plots, and cruell, in humane [sic], perfidious, and vnnaturall practises of the Spaniards : With, more excellent reasons of greater consequence, deliuered to the Kings Maiesty to dissolue the two treaties both of the match and the Pallatinate, and enter into warre with the Spaniards. Whereunto is adioyned a worthy oration appropriated, vnto the most mighty and illustrious princes of Christendome, wherein the right and lawfulnesse of the Netherlandish warre against Phillip King of Spayne is approued and demonstrated</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>AN ADIOYNDER OF SVNDRY OTHER PARTICV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAR WICKED PLOTS AND Cruell, Inhumane, Perfidious; yea, Vnnaturall practises of the Spaniards.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>To the well-affected indifferent</hi> READER.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, there being so much spoken, as thou maist perceiue, by the fore-going first Part of the Spanish practises, touching the cruell, inhumane, trecherous, perfidious; yea, vnnaturall practises of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in most parts of the World, which may suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently delineate him in his deserued colours, that whosoeuer beholds him may mourne to see this <hi>Hazael</hi> so to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize ouer the innocent, and that the Lord should permit, and the earth beare such an vnheard of monster; yet notwithstanding, much more might be added in sundry other particulars, as the Dutch Chronicles mention, and other Writers haue well set out: amongst which, although I my selfe be a stranger by Nation to them; yet since the time of my abode here, hauing attained some vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in the Language, I haue thought fit to adde some further particulars, which in my reading I haue obserued, and could adde many more; but my purpose being onely to annex a few things, I will not enlarge, lest I adde another Treatise. But before I come to what I intend, I haue thought fit hauing some ouersight in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of this Treatise aforegoing, to note by the way,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The Dutch word</hi> Ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sante <hi>signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadour or Messenger.</hi>
      </note> the ill tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating of one word, in the 21 folio, it is touching the Princesse of <hi>Parma,</hi> the Translator termes her <hi>a crafty Queane,</hi> wheras the word beares no such sence in the Dutch, but signifies one that hath a sharp wit to deceiue, as is said of the serpent that beguiled <hi>Eue.</hi> Beside, that that is translated <hi>Embassadour,</hi> speaking of such as were sent
<pb facs="17"/>
from the States to the King, I conceiue to be more fittingly rendred <hi>Messenger.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>First, thou art to vnderstand, gentle Reader, that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> was louingly receiued here in the 17 Prouinces, and a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne oath was taken on both parts; the King for his part swore to maintaine all their Lawes and Priuiledges, and they to him all due homage and allgeance: Hee presently demanded of them a summe of money, whereupon the States did assemble, and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected for him 40. millions of Florines, of <hi>Brabants</hi> money, to be paid in nine yeares, and paid it into his Exchequer; and although it was more then they had paid before to his predecessours, yet vpon this he did take great displeasure against them; and, as they write, he for this did hate them to death.</p>
   <p>But he pretended this to be the cause of his wroth, because he saw that there were some among them, that did defie the Pope and all his Religion: but that could not be, for the Citie of <hi>Aelst</hi> was as superstitious in that Religion as <hi>Rome</hi> it selfe; for they did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute the Reformed Religion euen vnto death: and yet for all that both they, and 170 faire Villages that belonged vnto them, were by them plundered and spoyled of all their goods, and many of them wounded and tormented for to confesse where their mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney was, and many were killed. Thus much by the way.</p>
   <p>My scope and chiefe intent, is to shew the first and iust cause of the warres in the <hi>Netherlands</hi>; whereby the diligent Reader (not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally affected) may clearely vnderstand, that the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> did not rebelliously take vp Armes against a lawfull Prince, (as some ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly thinke and speake) but iustly and religiously defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues against a perfidious Tyrant who sought their ruine, by all pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible meanes he could, and the subuersion of the whole State. A long while they patiently vnder-went his cruell oppressions, and intollerable vexations, as the Histories clearely manifest; till there was no hope, but either they must become slaues in soule and body, worse then that of <hi>Israel</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they and theirs for euer, or else be butchered by mercilesse executioners of a cruell Tyrant.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap> was there</hi> 4. <hi>yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
      </note> This Tyrant hauing a purpose to innouate all things, to root out the ancient inhabitants, and to frustrate all the Lawes, Customes and Priuiledges which himselfe had sworne to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, knew not how better to effect his euill ends, then by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a bloudy Inquisition to set ouer them for their gouernment;
<pb facs="17"/>
which said Inquisition (raised in <hi>Spaine</hi>) concluded and pronounced certaine Articles, the tenth of February 1568, which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the King, the 26. following. Now because it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare I doe them no wrong in this charge, I will lay downe the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles themselues verbatim.</p>
   <p>The most sacred Office of Inquisition so often attempted in the Netherlands by his Maiestie, and hindered vntill this time, shall be instituted and aduanced in this manner, which is most expedient.</p>
   <p n="1">1 They must perswade the Emperour, being gone astray, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly confederated with heretikes, that hee resigne his Kingdomes vnto his Sonne, with the whole administration of the Neither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</p>
   <p n="2">2 That the Emperour with his two sisters, hauing giuen ouer all affaires, leauing the Netherlands, shall retire into Spaine vnto Vs, being assured that they shall neuer returne more to doe any harme.</p>
   <p n="3">3 These being dispatcht, we must also draw the king to vs, and keepe him for euer that he part not, and not suffer any Flemmings to haue accesse or conference with him.</p>
   <p n="4">4 That the King write vnto, and command the Clergie of the Netherlands that with the Inquisition they should accept of 15 new Bishops, the which should be free from all secular iurisdiction, yea in cases of treason.</p>
   <p n="5">5 The subiects of the Netherlands through their malice and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, will reuolt and moue seditions and tumults, pleasing to all but to our companie.</p>
   <p n="6">6 The Princes and Noblemen, heads and authours of those fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, with the subiects, must be taken away, and the others redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnto reason.</p>
   <p n="7">7 They shall hire at our charge theeues and spoilers of Churches and Images, whose offences shall be by all the world imputed to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, by some subtill meanes, and so we shall vanquish them.</p>
   <p n="8">8 That all Comerce, Negotiation, Liberties and Priuiledges, shall be rooted out, and that all be reduced to extreame pouertie, whereby the realme shall be permanent for Vs.</p>
   <p n="9">9 No man of all those Countries (except he be of our faction) shall be held worthy to liue; and finally all to be rooted out: and all Goods, Possessions, Arts, and Trades, and all Orders to bee
<pb facs="18"/>
taken away, vntill there may bee a new Realme, and a new people.</p>
   <p n="10">10 In this action the wise and valiant Duke <hi>Alva</hi> shal be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in person; whereas any other, were he of the bloud Royall, or a Prince, shall be of no esteeme: so as being suspect, yea in the smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest matters, they must be dispatcht.</p>
   <p n="11">11 No Contracts, Rights, Promises, Donations, Oathes, Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and solemne Assertions of the Netherlands, shall be of any force for the Inhabitants, as being guilty of high treason.</p>
   <p n="12">12 But aboue al we must haue an especiall care that in these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of so great weight and moment, wee proceed not violently, but by meanes, by degrees, and that discreetly, to the end the Princes, Nobilitie, and inferiour subiects may mutinie amongst themselues, so that one may persecute, yea execute the other vntill at last the hangman be executed himselfe. For in all Christendome is there not a Nation more foolish and indiscreet, and whose levitie and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy may sooner be deceiued then these Netherlanders and God punisheth them accordingly.</p>
   <p>There were other Articles found in President <hi>Vergaes</hi> chamber at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and there Printed; and those are more cruell then these.</p>
   <p>By these articles and vnlimited power of these lawlesse Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, no man had any assurance of life or goods for a day, but were in danger continually to be called into question, either for the law of their God, or for some work of mercie, which either religion, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall equitie, or the bond of nature called for: or else if they had co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for none of these, they would impose such vnreasonable taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which if the Cormorants had not their gorges crambed full, they would make prey of all, whether by right or wrong it mattered not. But my purpose being to auoid prolixitie, and to passe by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies and needlesse repetitions, I will come to that I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In the yeare 1565, a match was concluded for the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> and the nuptials were solemnized at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> whither all the Nobilitie and Gentry of the Countrey were inuited, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyt, here met of them about foure hundred, who like faithfull <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> being grieued to see the daily oppression of their brethren by the hard task-masters of the Inquisition, who not onely robbed them of
<pb facs="18"/>
their goods, but also by inhumane crueltie, and vnnaturall butchery, depriued them of their liues, who daily led them as sheepe vnto the slaughter: The consideration hereof they ioyntly layd to heart, and hereupon (being met vpon this occasion) they resolued to present a petition to the Princesse of <hi>Parma,</hi> which they did the fifth of April next following. The Earle of Breedrod deliuering the petition, humbly requested a fauourable answer. Three dayes after they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued this answer, <hi>viz.</hi> they should send two of their Noblemen to the king, by whom she would write in their behalfe. The Lord of Barlaymont being present, after their departure said (<hi>like a flattering Courtier</hi>) they were a company of Rascals and Beggars.</p>
   <p>It was concluded that the Marquesse of Bargen, and the Lord of Mountigny should goe into Spaine, who humbly presented their suit to the King, but could get no answer in 16 Moneths after.</p>
   <p>The 26 of August <hi>anno</hi> 1566, the Princesse of <hi>Parma</hi> sent for the Gentrie, telling them she had receiued letters from the King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining promise that all should be well, and that the Inquisition should cease. And for the Proclamations they should not be of force, but his Maiestie would take such order as they and the State should well like of. The Princesse also gaue them toleration for their Religion, on condition, they should not deface, nor breake downe the ornaments of the Churches: for, there had beene before this time vilde and lewde persons that frequented the meetings of the Reformed; these went into the Papists Churches, stole their siluer and what was worth carrying away, and brake down their Images: but the Reformed suspected that this was done by the appointment of the Princesse; neither was their suspition without good ground, for it is to be seene in the Kings letters, <hi>Art.</hi> 7. that she had order to hire this raskall company to doe this villany,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Emanuel de Miter saith, that in Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders they tooke</hi> 50. <hi>of them at one time, and hanged</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>and whipped the rest.</hi>
      </note> which fact was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the Protestants, to the end that they might not only be odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous there, but also seeme guilty, euen in the iudgement of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; howbeit the offenders were punished with imprisonment, yea, with death, euen by the Reformed themselues, who iointly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed the action vnlawfull, and were so farre from hauing occasion of offence in this nature, that Papist Burgers themselues offered good securitie that no such thing should be attempted by them. Who then can make any doubt that they were free from giuing any hand in those outrages laid to them, the very opposites in Religion
<pb facs="19"/>
being Iudges, who as appeares were willing to undertake for them; now as their faithfulnesse brought so good effect for their persons, so did the Lord worke that the truth of Religion found many friends likewise, the Lord wondrously prospering the course of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in so much that in short space they had in <hi>Flanders</hi> 60 Assemblies, some Churches themselues builded, but were by Duke <hi>d' Alva</hi> soone cast downe, who erected gallowses of them, and hanged them vpon them.</p>
   <p>The Princesse of <hi>Parma</hi> also began to entertaine souldiers with pretence to apprehend the Church-robbers, but intended indeed to take away the ancient Liberties and Priuiledges of the <hi>Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> wherefore sending certaine companies to <hi>Valencyn,</hi> the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants denied them entertainment, who for that were proclaimed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels the 14 of December, soone after they were besieged, sacked, and many of them put to death.</p>
   <p>But before they of <hi>Valencyn</hi> denied entertainment to the souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Let pretended it for religion, but his aime was to get their lands and goods.</hi>
      </note> the Nobility had receiued letters out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> from the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse of <hi>Bargen,</hi> shewing, that the King was exceedingly incensed against the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> that he had in the presence of many vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be fully reuenged of them, though it were with the hazard of all his Countries; that hee would make them an example to all the world, and would inuite the Pope and Emperour to assist him in this quarrell. Vpon the receit of the letters the Nobility assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Dortmond</hi> to consult what were best to be done, but conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not any thing, some iudging it safest to ioyne, and make head to resist his tyrannicall furie, other seeking rather to escape by flight.</p>
   <p>Now was the Inquisition againe brought in contrary to the Lawes and Liberties of the Country, which the King was sworne to maintaine, for execution whereof there were appointed 12. Inquisitors, commaunding them to receiue the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> these were called, <hi>The bloudy Councell,</hi> and so they were indeede, which <hi>Rome</hi> well knew, refusing it, <hi>anno</hi> 1559. when as they fell vpon the Inquisitors house, set it on fire, wounded the chiefe of them, brake open the prison, and set at liberty the captiues, and would haue burned a Cloyster that belonged vnto them, had they not beene by faire meanes disswaded by two Lords in the Citie, <hi>viz. Marc▪ Antonio Colunus, Iuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Caesar.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="19"/>Likewise <hi>Venice, Naples</hi> and <hi>Millaine,</hi> though they be Papists, would not suffer it; the Marchants of <hi>Lisbon</hi> who are as superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Romish Religion as any in the world, yet they did offer the King two millions and a halfe, that they might not haue it in their parts.</p>
   <p>Yet the cruelty of this Inquisition did here encrease, and many souldiers came into the Countrey, that some of the Countrey for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooke their houses, and resorted towards Freezland, and some did stay at home, and went to meete Duke <hi>Alva,</hi> and welcomed him into the Countrey, and shewed him all the kindnesse they could,<note place="margin">
         <hi>As the Grais of Egmond, &amp; the Grais of Horn, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Gentry at Brussels,</hi> 1568.</note> but hee very shortly tooke off most of their heads, so that hee did so terrifie the inhabitants, that there fled out of the Countries more then an hundred thousand housholders, besides many that were taken in flying, were taken and hanged, and all these had their goods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscated to the King.</p>
   <p>The Prince of Orange, and the Earle of Bredrod, and fine Earles, eight Lords, and fifty Gentlemen, and they had some fine thousand of Souldiers being in Freesland, but were most ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> his forces; so that they were driuen to Embden land, and there prepared themselues to the sea.</p>
   <p>Now the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> did commaund all the inhabitants to pay the hundreth peny of all their goods, and of all that was bought and sold▪ the which some of the States did yeeld vnto: And then hee commaunded them to pay the twentith peny: and then hee commaunded the tenth peny of all things that were bought and sold, so often as they should be sold. Some of the States did make their humble petition to the Duke, and to the Princes, shewing them that it would driue all trading out of the land. The Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> told them that hee would haue it, though it did ruinate all the land; but if hee saw them to doe their best to pay it, hee would deale fauourably with them.<note place="margin">
         <hi>All the prisons were filled, in so much as they were forced to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare more, and filled them also.</hi>
      </note> But hee said that it was against the Kings honour if they should not pay it, seeing it was his pleasure to require it. And now did the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition imprison and execute many of the richer sort, as well Papists as of the reformed Church: and if they were rich, there was no escaping for them. And whosoeuer was found to haue any hand in way of suit and petition to haue the tenth
<pb facs="20"/>
peny to be remitted, they were adiudged to haue committed high treason against God and the King; and all these must forfeit life and goods to the king, and not any of their children to enioy one peny worth of the same: but (poore Orphanes) they must begge their bread. And some that had beene buried certaine months, they cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them to be digged vp, and hanged on the gallowes, and some to be burned, because they had not the sacrament, and confessed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their death; but it was because he would confiscate their goods to the king: yea when these insatiable gold-thirsty and bloud-thirsty wretches wanted colour to couer their iniustice and cruelty, they had their officious imps (false-witnesses) suborned by <hi>Jesabel,</hi> to get <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> vineyard; witnesse <hi>Marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Hutton,</hi> who was one of the Inquisitors Clarkes, and (being committed to Prison) did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that hee had made many false testimonies against sundry rich persons, some whereof were of the reformed Church. Here might fitly be brought in the hundred Marchants of <hi>Granado,</hi> who were of the Romane Religion, and were neuer other; what pretence had hee to cause them to bee murthered all in one night, and then presently to command all their goods to be brought to his treasurie of Exchequer, whose estate was worth more then 28 hundred thousand pounds sterling? Now as this tyrant was a deuourer and destroyer of the liues of men, so did hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to vsurpe further, not only vpon ciuill ordinances, but vpon the things of God; so that those that were married in the reformed Church, he forced to be married againe: and if they were rich, hee tooke them from their husbands, and gaue them to his souldiers to make prize of them. Those that were baptized in the reformed Church, he compelled to be baptized againe, contrary to Gods word, and to the decree of the ancient counsels, so that intolerable were the burthens this cruell <hi>Pharoh</hi> layd, so excessiue was his cruelty, that he filled all places with blood, <hi>bloud touching bloud,</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet speakes. For in small townes hee executed 50, and in great townes 200, and 300 or 400. And in places as men trauelled from one towne to another, they might see many that his souldiers had hung up in trees to death, and some were worth 80 thousand gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and some lesse: yea, this tyrant did confiscate so much lands and goods, as by his account sent into Spain, did amount yearly to 8 tun of mony sterling, besides the many thousands that he &amp; his souldiers had.
<pb facs="20"/>
All the money that he did exact out of this land in 6. yeares, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to more then 50. millions of gold. And if any were knowne to haue any thing that did belong to any that were put to death, and had not brought it to the knowledge of the Inquisition, they did loose both life and goods: yea the 16. of February 1566. hee gaue sentence in his Court at <hi>Madrill,</hi> that they were all traytors against God and himselfe. At Vtrecht he beheaded a widow that was 84. yeares old, because shee had before lodged a Preacher one night, whose liuing was worth foure thousand guldens yearely. And at Mastricht a father for lodging his son that he had not seene in a long time, that was fled for religion, was put to death. And at that place there was one put to death for giuing a widow a peck of corn for an almes, whose husband this bloudy Court had put to death. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny women were put to death, because they receiued their husbands in the night that were fled for religion; yea, they haue killed women great with child, and ripped vp their bellies, and taken out the child and killed it: and some they haue fleyed aliue, and couered drummes heads with their skies, and some they haue tyed to a post, and made a small fire round about them, and so rosted them to death.</p>
   <p>At Naerden they receiued the Spaniards friendly into the towne,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The like cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty they did at Ondwater.</hi>
      </note> who promised them both their liues and goods; and as soone as they came in, they commanded them to come to the State-house without their Armes, the which they did, and the Spaniards gaue fire vpon them, and murthered them all: and then they ran about in the towne, and rauished the women, and after killed them and fired the towne. The yong children that lay in the cradle, they quartered them, and tooke them vpon their pikes, and so went vp and downe the towne, reioycing in their cruelty.</p>
   <p>Such sauage cruelty is scarcely to be found in any History, what Christian heart can heare it, and not be affected with deepe sorrow, yet behold some monsters herein haue been found, that haue beene so farre from humanity herein, (for hee that hath humanity in him will commiserate others calamities) that they haue applauded it, as if he had in all these outrages done God good seruice. Amongst the rest, I shall content my selfe at present, but to name the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, and one of his chiefe sonnes in this businesse. The Pope sends his Legate to commend these so rare exployts, and cals this cruell Duke <hi>Alua</hi> his beloued sonne, sends him a costly
<pb facs="21"/>
sword, the hilts whereof were of Gold, and a hat wrought with gold, and be-set with rich and costly stones, thanking him for his good seruice in maintaining the Romish Religion, and subuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of heretikes. Howbeit that his chiefe son I mentioned (excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this man of sin, in the sin of cruelty, as if he would verifie himselfe to be ten-fold more the child of Satan, then his father the Pope) thinkes not so well of it, his name is <hi>Vergas,</hi> the President of this bloudy Inquisition; for going shortly after into <hi>Spaine,</hi> he told the King, that he and Duke <hi>d' Alua,</hi> did marre all in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> by shewing so much mercy to those people.</p>
   <p>Concerning this Duke <hi>d' Alua,</hi> of whose outrage and cruelty so many haue felt, and perfidious dealing which many haue found by lamentable experience, whereby may easily appeare of what stamp his excessiue mercies are, euen such as the Wiseman speakes of <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.10, <hi>the tender-mercies of the wicked are cruell.</hi> In which he prids himselfe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>These words he spake at a banquet, as he sate at the Table, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing he had done the King so good seruice.</hi>
      </note> boasting he had slaughtered eighteen thousand and sixe hundred, in form of iustice, in six yeares times, and ten times so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he and his Souldiers murthered otherwaies. And many more would he doubtlesse haue murthered, had not the Lord restrayned and limited him, for his desire herein was as hell, that cannot be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied: Witnesse the purpose of his proceeding against the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> because they did not collect the tenth peny so as he desired. He sware that he would haue it, and before he would let it fall or remit it, the Sunne and Moone should leaue their shining: so he went to Brussels, and commanded the executioner to prepare ladders and ropes to hang vp that night in their doores 70 of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Anno</hi> 573 1 <hi>April.</hi> 1. <hi>I haue instan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced but</hi> 4 <hi>or</hi> 5 <hi>towns, but there were scarce any town escaped their cruell pillaging, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they had bribed their Commanders with exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> and gaue them his warrant in writing what they should be: But God in his prouidence preuented this his cruell purpose, in that there came newes that the Graue of Mark had taken in the Brill, so the tyrant did not goe forward with his bloudy enterprises.</p>
   <p>Thus hauing giuen you a taste of some of those many things I haue obserued concerning the intolerable oppression, and worse then sauage cruelty of the Spaniards, exercised vpon the people, which they endured and laboured vnder the space of sixteene yeares; I wil now leaue these cruell tyrants to the Lord for iudgement, and address my selfe to speak somewhat further concerning this Earle of Mark, who had those Gentlemen with him that fled. Before this hee had laine with his shipping in England, but the King of Spaine sending
<pb facs="21"/>
his Embassadour to our Queen (who was then in peace with him) to desire her that she would not suffer his subiects to haue their harbour in her land, and that she would not giue them or suffer them to haue any reliefe whereby they should make head against him: and hereupon the Queene sent and commanded them out of her har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and she commanded that they should not be suffered to haue any prouision in her coasts, so that now they had no other meanes but onely God, who did in his mercie prouide for them better then they expected. For they were purposed to haue gone for the Tassel, and to haue taken some towne about that part; but when they came neere that part, they had the wind contrary that they could not come there, so they went for the Malse, and came with their ships before the Brill, and there they went presently and tooke it; yet the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> had his forces in the towne, neere so many as they were, whom they presently killed and chased out of the towne, and out of the Iland. The Prince of Orange being in France, and hearing what had happened, he sent them souldiers with as much speede as could be out of France. And within one moneth after Duke <hi>Alua</hi> sent cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine companies to Vlishing to keepe that place strong for himselfe, and many of the Commanders were come into the towne: So the Magistrates commanded the citizens to come presently vpon the Statehouse, so they told them they must lodge the Spaniards in their houses, and they knowing how they had vsed the Citizens in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they came, they told the magistrates they would not haue the Spaniards in their towne. The Magistrates asked them which of them it was that did refuse to receiue them. They said, All of them. So the Magistrates seeing them so earnest against the Spaniards, they ioyntly tooke their Armes, and killed and tooke prisoners all them that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the town,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hee had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed those to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted because they were they were the chiefe that stood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the payment of the tenth peny.</hi>
      </note> &amp; with their Ordnance they shot at his ships where the Spaniards were, and they made away. And of those that were taken, there were the names of about 80 that they had in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from Duke <hi>Alua</hi> that dwelt in the Iland, that they should put to death. So those of the Bril sent their souldiers with speed to help thē. And shortly the Prince of Orange came with forces and defended them; and some other townes, seeing the crueltie of the Spaniards, forsooke the Spaniard, and ioyned with them, and took the Prince of Orange to be their Protector, yet the States notwithstanding did remaine in obedience to the King some seuen yeares after.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="22"/>Againe, it is further worthy to be noted, that these Prouinces did three times send to the King their Noblemen, but could obtaine no mercy, and many more times they went to the Princesse of <hi>Parma,</hi> and made their humble petition for redresse of their oppression, but could not obtaine any fauour, then they made friends to the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Queene of England, and to the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and to the Emperour, who did earnestly entreat by their Embassadours for them. The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> answered their Embassadours with these words; he bad them tell their Masters, <hi>That they should meddle with their owne subiects, and not with his, for he knew well enough how to rule his subiects without their counsell.</hi> Now when our Queenes Maiestie found his vnreasonablenesse and cruelty, then and not before, she as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted them with Armes.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ann.</hi> 1575.</note>
   </p>
   <p>His owne sonne Prince <hi>Charles</hi> did intreat for them, that it would please him to let them haue their Lawes and Priuiledges, and that they might not be so oppressed;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Marplam in his Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle an.</hi> 1567.</note> and withall hee told his father that those Countries did belong to him, and that they were giuen him at his Baptisme, for the which his father sent him to prison, and he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came out againe. If the Lord would not haue forgot what <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek</hi> did long after, for smiting the weakest &amp; hindmost of his people, how may we in equity forget the infinite murthers, and spoiles, this cruell Tyrant hath executed where-euer hee hath preuailed? And who can forget in speciall that bloudy attempt against our selues, in the yeare 1588.</p>
   <p>If I should trace this Tyrant from place to place, I should runne in infinitum, hauing made the name of Christianity hatefull, by his cruelty, amongst the Heathens that know not God further then the light of nature: for it is confessed by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themselues, that some of the chiefe of the <hi>Jndians,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>They were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by a Popish Priest to minde, that after this life, there was one place for ioy, and an other of torment.</hi>
      </note> who were to be burne to death, being told of heauen and hell, they asked whether the <hi>Spaniards</hi> went when they died? It was answered to heauen, <hi>Oh then said they, we will neuer come there, for we will neuer come where the Spaniards are.</hi> But not to run so far, I wil rest content to keep me within the bounds I chiefly intended concerning these Countries. When the Citizens of <hi>Leyden</hi> were in great extremity, by reason of a long siege, the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> proffering conditions of peace, if so be they would yeeld vp the Citie and themselues to them, they returned answer; <hi>Not while they had a right hand to hold the sword, or a left to eate</hi>; but if they should
<pb facs="22"/>
be driuen to fall into their hands, they would rather burne the Citie and drown themselues, then to submit to them, of whose perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse they had had so lamentable experience: and when some of the Citizens pressed a yeelding, in respect of the extremitie of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, a Burgermaster, called <hi>Peter Adrianson</hi> said; <hi>Louing friends, I confesse the famine is great, and that some doe die for want of food: yet rather let vs agree to eate vp one another, as it shall fall by lot, begin with me first, and deuide me amongst you.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>At <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> by the appointment of their Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour did come into the Citie in battell order, and marched vp and down their streets, and shot into their houses, and made a tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous noise, as if they had beene so many deuils, for one day and two nights, and tooke the keyes from the Magistrates,<note place="margin">
         <hi>They did this as wel to the Spiritualty▪ as to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralty no sort e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>cepted.</hi>
      </note> and set watch at the Ports; whereby they put the Citizens in so great feare, that many women with childe fell in trauell, and some dyed with feare: and they went by 12 or 20, into the best houses, and commanded them to prepare them the best cheere, as boyled and rost, and other dainty dishes, as they list to call for; and besides beere,<note place="margin">
         <hi>They did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them two parts in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and the third <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>cloth, but they cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</hi>
      </note> they would haue at least two sorts of wine. And all the chiefest Citizens houses had at least tenne of these guests. And they all cryed out for money, and said that they would haue 15 moneths pay, before they went out of the Citie, of them; and the Magistrates told them that they would procure them in cloth, and apparell, and money the summe; but they all cryed out for mony, and that mony they would haue before they went away; so at the last, the Magistrates got the mony, which did amount to 400 thousand Guldens. And the charge they were at,<note place="margin">
         <hi>I doe make but a short relation of some of the cruelties they did against this Citie yet there stands in the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>cle, one qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of paper of their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cruelty▪</hi>
      </note> which these companions did cost the Citizens, was 600 pound sterling the day, and thus they were oppressed with them 28 daies, in which time they had made them all rich suites, some of sattin and veluet, and some of cloth of gold: and one of them had a cushi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of veluet, with these words in letters of gold. <hi>I am the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Bride-well Master.</hi> And thus they got r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d of them for the present. And about two yeares after they came againe, and then they vsed the Citizens much more cruelly, for these deuils did bring straw, and set on fire, and put it into the houses, whereby they set nine rich streets on fire, and burnt them with many rich and costly goods, and rifled the Citizens of all their rich and costly iewels, and siluer-workes, with their money, and three dayes did they tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="23"/>
the inhabitants for money:<note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>That they are now and haue been this</hi> 30. <hi>yeares more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>▪ I easily yeeld it. But why? not that they haue changed their former na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for they still hold the former princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Councell of Trent, but being more subtill, and finding their Kingdome is more weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they dare not so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>In the yeare</hi> 1580. <hi>the States pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed King Phill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p to haue l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st his right, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son he viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his oath. A Spaniards kindnesse to his friends.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> and in this time there was murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Citizens aboue foure thousand. The money they tooke at that time, is reckoned for more then 40 tun of gold, beside the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels and the losse they had by fire, was as much as the rest. And thus was the best Citie of Marchants in Europe ruinated.</p>
   <p>At <hi>Risell</hi> there was a Spaniard would force a rich woman to haue the vse of her body, and the woman cried out for helpe, and her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band came, and two of his neighbours to helpe his wife, and they thrust the Spaniard away, and hee ranne into the street and cried <hi>Spaynea, Spaynea,</hi> and there came many Spanish Souldiers about him, and they rushed into the house, and tooke the man and his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and carried them before the Magistrates on the Towne-house where they were assembled, and there before them he complained of them to be rebels, and stirrers vp of vp-ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, and told the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates that if they did not presently put them to death, they would burne their Towne, and execute them themselues, whereupon they durst doe no otherwise, but hanged two, and whipped the other.</p>
   <p>Diuers things being manifested of the Spaniards cruelty, I wil adde one instance of their trechery, and that of a famous person to his nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest familiars; yea, when he pretended sweetest familiarity &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6. a Spaniard by birth, inuited diuers No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles &amp; Cardinals to a banket, with a purpose to poyson them all. The meetest instrument he made choyse of to effect this, was a Spaniard, one <hi>Caesar Burgia,</hi> his sworn seruant. The Pope shewed himself won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull pleasant to auoyd suspition, and drank a carouse to them all; willing that his trusty seruant to fill from such a bottel he knew well: which hee did very effectually to the Pope himselfe as well as to the rest. After the company was departed, the Pope perceiuing by an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in himselfe, what was done, and that he must die now also, said to <hi>Burgio, This is a right Spanish trick.</hi> It is written of them that they are so expert in these exploits, that if <hi>Iudas</hi> himselfe were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, he might goe to them to Schoole.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>J doe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>seech the Lord to shew mercy to my natiue Country, that they may neuer come vnder the gouernment of the Spaniards, and giue them hearts to repent of their transgressions, and that they may sincerely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Gospell of Iesus Christ, to their endlesse comfort. Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to command in all seruices, for the aduancement of the truth of Iesus Christ. <hi>S. O.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>