<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Errata]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1715_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11802</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22097a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1715</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Errata]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vox Dei</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 86, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <p>VVHere faults appeare in Letters,<note place="margin">To the Reader.</note> Points, or Words,
The Printers ignorance excuse affords:
And where the Matter or the Forme doth hault,
The Author may hope pardon for his fault,
Since as the One, knowes of the tongue no part▪
The other, knowes as little of the heart.</p>
   <p>PAge 1,<note place="margin">Errors in the Preface.</note> line 25, reade rationibus. Edito. page 2, line 19, reade s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arnes,
page 3, line 2, reade <hi>they</hi> page ib. line 3, reade <hi>our</hi> page ib. line 6,
reade <hi>will</hi> page 4, line 14, reade <hi>Timbrels</hi> page ib. line 24, reade
<hi>otherwise</hi> page ib. line 30, reade <hi>expences,</hi> pa. ib. line 33, reade <hi>tyre</hi>
ib. reade Emperour, <hi>and hold</hi> page 5, line 16, reade <hi>wafted</hi> page ib.
lines 19, &amp; 31, reade <hi>Exchequer</hi> page 7, line 25, reade <hi>ioyne</hi> page 8,
line 16, reade <hi>wilt.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>PAge 2.<note place="margin">Errors in the Booke.</note> line 6. reade principally p. 3. l. 2. r. <hi>part,</hi> p. ib. l. 13. r. <hi>eldest</hi>
p. 4. l. vlt. r. <hi>the</hi> p. 6. l. 9. r. <hi>him such, so</hi> p. ib. l. 32. r. <hi>the</hi> p. 8.
l. 10. r. <hi>brothers person, how</hi> p. ib. l. 28. r. <hi>sent</hi> p. 9. l. 1. r. <hi>being</hi>
p. ib. l. 20. r. <hi>is it</hi> p. 10. l. 8. r. <hi>his</hi> p. 12. l. 12. r. on p. ib. l. 18. r. your
p. ib. l. 29. r. amongst p. 13. l. 9. r. <hi>expostulate</hi> p. ib. l. 24. r. <hi>iniuries</hi>
p. 17. l. 15. r. <hi>idollatrous</hi> p. 18. l. 20. r. <hi>vndertaking. For, these
words,</hi> Is there not a cause, <hi>haue</hi> p. 20. l. 13. r. <hi>high, excellent,
and eminent</hi> p. ib. l. 26. r. <hi>same.</hi> p. ib. l. 28. r. <hi>or</hi> p. 21. l. 4. r. <hi>the</hi>
p. 24. l. 4. r. <hi>thee</hi> p. ib. l. 8. r. <hi>thy</hi> p. ib. l. 9. r. Hypocrits p. ib. l. 12. r. Lou
p. 25. 26. r. <hi>for the way,</hi> p. 26. l. 3. r. <hi>imagination</hi> p. 29. l. 20. 21
r. <hi>fact, Behold,</hi> Abraham <hi>stands forth, like</hi> p. ib. l. vlt. r. <hi>flye,</hi> p. 31
l. 11. r. <hi>laying</hi> p. 32. l. 10. r. <hi>restores</hi> p. 33. l. 10. 11. r. <hi>tyrannous</hi>
p. 36. l. 13. r. <hi>the Shipwrackt</hi> p. 37. l. 16. r. <hi>seruilitie,</hi> p. 38. l. 21.
r. <hi>his</hi> p. 39. l. 15. r. Bulling br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>okes p. ib. l. 28. r. <hi>become me▪</hi> p. 41.
l. 32. r. <hi>one</hi> p. 43. l. 19. r. <hi>and</hi> p. 44. l. vlt. r. <hi>Such only, seeme</hi> p. 45
l. 24. r. <hi>professe,</hi> p. 46. l. 21. r. <hi>know</hi> p. 47. l. 5. r. <hi>seeme</hi> p. ib. l. 32
r. VVho is he being p. 48. l. 29. r. thee, p. 52. l. 17. r. <hi>these</hi> p. 54. l. vlt.
r. <hi>profane</hi> p. 55. l. 6. r. and the malice p. 56. l. 25. r. <hi>Noble blood
ran not then in Ignoble vaines.</hi> p. ib. l. vlt. r. <hi>saith a man</hi> p. 57
l. 2. r. <hi>Superiour.</hi> p. 62. l. 19. r. <hi>vseing</hi> p. 65. l. 26. r. <hi>an exchange</hi>
p. 67. l. 29. r. <hi>and tyde them fast in</hi> p. 69. l. 27. r. <hi>most</hi> p. ib. l. 30.
r. <hi>tended</hi> p. ib. l. vlt. r. <hi>a most</hi> p. 70. l. 15. r. but ioy p. ib. l. 23 r. <hi>rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blement</hi>
p. 71. l. 12. r. <hi>preceded.</hi> p. ib. l. 13. r. <hi>is</hi> p. 72. l. 22. r.
<hi>proffered</hi> p. 73. l. 5. r. <hi>that do worship</hi> p. ib. l. 13. r. <hi>wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> p. 77
l. 21. r. <hi>layd in before,</hi> p. 83. l. 13. r. <hi>Natiues</hi> p. ib. l. 24. r. <hi>those</hi>
p. vlt. l. 23. r. thorough p. ib. l. 27. r. Be.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>