<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO HIS  Scholler, VVilliam  wisheth  felici∣tie 1581.</title>
           <author>Salter, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1788_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09380</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1968.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO HIS  Scholler, VVilliam  wisheth  felici∣tie 1581.</title>
                 <author>Salter, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A contention betwene three bretheren, that is to say, the vvhoremonger, the dronkarde, and the diceplayer : to approue which of them three is the worste, by reason that their deceased father had giuen his succession from the worste of them three : a worke no lesse profitable then pleasurable to read, for so much as the vilenesse of those three vices, is herein sette oute at large / compiled by Thomas Salter</title>
                 <author>Beroaldo, Filippo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Gosson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48, that is 96 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶TO HIS <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> Scholler, VVilliam <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> wisheth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie 1581.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the giuing of a gift vnto any one (my good Scholler) on hope to receiue for it a greater gift, is a kinde of vsurie: So to giue none at al for feare of losing reward, is a degree of auarice.</p>
   <p>Againe, as to repent the giuing of a gift after it is giuen, is a testemonie of imprudencie: So to giue one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force without receiuing satisfaction for it from thē that receiue it is an vnwise bargaine. But who so cōside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in his giuing of any gift, what he giueth, when he giueth, to whom he giueth &amp; how much he giueth, may not onely be thought a true, but also a liberall and discreet friend.</p>
   <p>Now I thy Tutor, louing thee faithfully, doe giue vnto thee with a most hartie &amp; Zealous good will, this
<pb facs="3"/>
little Pamdhilet, intituled: A strange Contentiō betweene three brethren &amp;c. And therfore euē as the right gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of a gift, is an act of liberalitie, so a little remuneration is a manifest token of a thankful minde. Now the recompēce that I request (for this) at thy hāds, is no other, thē first to haue thee courteously to accept it, next willingly to read it, &amp; lastly, wisely &amp; discretely to cōsider of it. And so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, although it beareth outwardlye the badge of brauling betwene bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrē, yet by meanes of the same, thou shalt see theree execrable vices so pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily deciphered &amp; set foorth, that is to say, Whoordome, Dronkenness, &amp; Diceplaying, as I haue no doubt, but it shal both turne to thy pleasure, and others Profite. For what greater Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure may be presented vnto the, or what sweeter profit vnto other, then to see, (by sundry exampls, valeable reasōs, &amp; inuincible argumēts) those dangerous shelues, &amp; Perilous rocks laid open (thereby the better to shun &amp; auoid them) on which many earst
<pb facs="3"/>
haue made, &amp; diuers yet dayly doe make most shamefull and grieuous shipwrake. Well as I saide, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this my gift, my request once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine is, that you first courteously ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, &amp; thē that you request others vprightly to iudge of it. By dooing wheroff they whom you request shal do wisely to themselues, &amp; thākfully to you, &amp; you curteously vnto them, &amp; thankfully vnto me, &amp; I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly, liberally, &amp; curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously vnto you all, which am yours in all I may to do you good.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Salter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>