<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The Prayer Of oure Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1782_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06743</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1719.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1782</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The Prayer Of oure Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The flour of godly praiers : most worthy to be vsed in these our daies for the sauegard, health, and comforte of all degrees, and estates. Newlie made by Thomas Becon</title>
                 <author>Becon, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, xcvi, xcix-xcxvi, xcxv-clii, cli-cliiii, 7 l, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <head>¶The Prayer Of oure Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD God our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē, we thi mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serable chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drene vppon earth, besech thee mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to loke vppon vs, and sende vs thy grace, that thy name maye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e sanctifyed amonge vs, and in all the worlde throughe the pure preachynge of thy woorde▪ and trewe knoweledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge of thee same, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe earneste charytye in oure dayelye conuersacyon and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge. Seclude thou gracyously
<pb facs="15"/>
frome vs all false doctryne and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll lyuynge, whereby thy worthy name myghte be blasphemed and slaūdered. Oh let thy kyngedome come and bee greate to all synfull and blynde people, and such as be houlden captyue of the deuyll and his kingdome, brynge thou Lorde to repentaunce and to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the trewe faith in Iesus Christ thy sonne. Strengthen vs Lord with thy grace, to do thy wyl in life and deathe, in well and in woo, that our wil may be alwaies broken offered vp, and mortified. Geue vs our daily bread preserue vs from all couetousnes▪ and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate carefulnes of the belly, that of the we maye be assured to haue aboundaunce of all good thinges necessary for vs. Forgeue vs oure trespasses▪ that we maye haue a glad and a quiet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> conscy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="16"/>
in the, in that we receiue for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geuenes of our synnes, as we be wyllyng to forgeue all them that trespasse againste vs. And leade vs not into tēptacion, but strēgth then vs Lord wyth thy spirite, to subdue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesh to dispise y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde wyth the vanities thereof, &amp; to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome the deuell wyth all hys crafty assaultes, And finally deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from al euil, both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely and ghostlye tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternal, for thine is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye for euer. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>