<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶THE ARGVMENT OF this present Boke, Intituled: A Con∣tention betweene three Bretheren: that is to say, the Dronkard, the VVhoore∣monger, and the Dice∣player.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1788_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09380</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1968.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶THE ARGVMENT OF this present Boke, Intituled: A Con∣tention betweene three Bretheren: that is to say, the Dronkard, the VVhoore∣monger, and the Dice∣player.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A contention betwene three bretheren, that is to say, the vvhoremonger, the dronkarde, and the diceplayer : to approue which of them three is the worste, by reason that their deceased father had giuen his succession from the worste of them three : a worke no lesse profitable then pleasurable to read, for so much as the vilenesse of those three vices, is herein sette oute at large / compiled by Thomas Salter</title>
                 <author>Beroaldo, Filippo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Gosson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48, that is 96 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶THE ARGVMENT OF this present Boke, Intituled: <hi>A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention betweene three Bretheren:</hi> that is to say, the Dronkard, the VVhoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, and the Dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>player.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Certain Father dravving nere vnto his ende, (hauing three levvd disposed sonnes, the one a VVhooremonger, the other a Dronkarde, and the thyrde a Diceplayer, ordained by his last VVill and Testamente, that the most vvicked and vicious of them three shoulde bee depriued of his succession. He being deceased, by reason of the strife risen through this bequest betvveene the sayd Bretheren, they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their cause themselues before Iudges, for the same purpose appoynted. To the intent that by reciprocall, and mutual accusations, personally declaimed, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might more clearely, and vvith greater Vehemency be deciphered and vnderstoode, then if it vvere sette foorth and debated by the voice and Organe of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate. The Dronkard first, (as appertaining vnto him for some cause) beginneth the Alarum against his tvvo Bretheren, seuerally, and by sundry assaultes: to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that he might agayne at one time, receiue from both of them, by one only assault the like. Vpon this the parties being amplie heard, there is sentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Certifying you right courteous and gentle Readers (for it is to you, and to no enuious or malignaunt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, that I addresse this present) that if it please you to beholde the same, it shall not bee vvithoute some pleasure, and as I hope lesse vvithout profite. For the
<pb facs="5"/>
principall end thereof tendeth vnto the teaching of all men, cheefely and first of all to be carefull of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and not to thinke or imagine any thing preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall or hurtfull to their neighbour, neither to search (as Socrates alleaged in xenophon) the imperfections of others, leauing to enquire afte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> their ovvn fault, by examining of themselues. Beeing counselled by this vvise aduertisement, to take heede rather (as the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teatheth vs) vnto the great beame that restes in our ovvne eyes, then vnto the little more that hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the sight of others, that is to say, to consider, make clere, correct and a mend our ovvne great faultes, and offences, before vve intermeddle vvith those litle ones of our neighboures. For to doe the contrary, and to stumble on this errour no lesse daungerous then common, is the right pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie and nature, saith Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero in his Tosculanes of folly and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>