<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1830_Bo1_1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16984</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3867.9</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1830</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holy genealogie of Iesus Christ : both his naturall line of fathers, which S. Luke followeth, chap. 3, and his kingly line, which S. Matthew followeth, chap. I, with fit notation of their names / by H. Br</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head type="sub">To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy <hi>Genealogie</hi> of <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> (may not be reckoned in the number of those prophane ones, which <hi>S. Paul</hi> condemneth in 1. Tim. 1.4. for it) doth not consist in a vaine repetition of Names, (as many doe thinke) neither is the knowledge thereof superfluous, (as some doe affirme;) But verily (if it be rightly vnderstood) it is of exceeding great vse and consequence; not onely to prooue <hi>Christ</hi> to be the promised Seede, (which is a weightie poynt;) But also it serueth as a speciall guide, to direct vs in the true vnderstanding of all the <hi>Holy Storie:</hi> For the natiue iudgement of all men teacheth, that Histories cannot be learned rightly, without knowledge of the Persons vpon whom the Narrations goe. That beeing so, all that looke for Saluation by Scripture, which calleth vs vnto our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> should haue a special care to know our <hi>Lords Line</hi>: for vpon it, all the Stories go principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; either in open phrase of words, or else with some close relation: as hee that will take but a serious view of our <hi>Lords line of Fathers,</hi> shall soone see, how all the <hi>Holy storie</hi> dependeth vpon it, and from it, as from a Fountaine, doth branch it selfe into a most pleasant varietie of all Gods holy proceedinges, in the wonderfull preseruation of his Church, and in the fearefull ouerthrow of all the enemies thereof.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Ebrew</hi> hath kept a perfect Register of all their Names vnto <hi>Dauid;</hi> but
<pb facs="2"/>
after that <hi>Dauid</hi> had the promise of the <hi>Celestiall Throne,</hi> (2. Sam. 7. Then our <hi>Lords</hi> kindred was kept in priuate Recordes, all sauing foure: As <hi>Nathan</hi> for the first, and three others of him, that inherited <hi>Salomons</hi> right: And yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the God of Wisedome, hath not suffered those Names (which the <hi>Ebrew</hi> hath omitted in the old Test.) to perish in obliuion; But the Holy Ghost hath been excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding carefull, to set downe (in Greeke) a perfect Register of them all, in the very fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, (euen like a most stately <hi>Vlam</hi> or <hi>Porch,</hi>) before the Temple of the New Testament.</p>
   <p>And yet, it is a most lamentable thing to consider, how many men doe peruert and obscure this glorious entrance of the blessed <hi>Gospel,</hi> to the great hurt of all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie, &amp; to the great hardoning of the poore blind <hi>Iewes</hi> in their obstinate resisting of all our <hi>Gospel:</hi> For say they, If so many grosse errours (as many Christians haue broched for currant truth) be set in the very forefrunt of all the N. Testament; then <hi>Christ</hi> is not come in the flesh, neither is our N.T. from God. Which assertion cannot be denied, if it be true, as many doe affirme: First, That <hi>Salomons</hi> house did end in <hi>Achazias.</hi> Secondly, That King <hi>Ioas</hi> in Mat. 1. and <hi>Simeon</hi> in Luk. 3. are all one man. Thirdly, That <hi>Ioachaz</hi> a younger Brother, was made Father to <hi>Ioakim</hi> two yeares his elder. Fourthly, That <hi>Salathiel</hi> was the naturall Sonne of <hi>Iechonias,</hi> notwithstanding Gods Oath, that he should die childlesse. Ier. 22.</p>
   <p>But to cleare the holy <hi>Genealogie</hi> of <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> from these, and many other grosse errours, it will not be amisse, first to lay downe a briefe Table, to reconsile <hi>S. Matthew</hi> and <hi>S. Luke:</hi> which shall begin no higher then <hi>Dauid;</hi> because the maine errours, are chiefly found in his posteritie. And after this, shall follow a more large Table of all our <hi>Lords Fathers,</hi> with briefe obseruations vpon their Names; which shall be layde downe in their true distinctions, and with notations agreeable to the <hi>Ebrew,</hi> and to occasions, holden fitte to giue them names at their birth times: And herein we may consider the wonderfull prouidence of God, closely disposing their Names, to that which in Storie should be most famous: For it is euident, that the Names of our <hi>Lords line,</hi> were sagely giuen by the guidance of Gods spirit, and in more wise sort, then euer any fieigner could thinke vpon; as the discreete Reader may easily discerne, by the correspondance of their Names, which abridge the Holy Story. The <hi>Syria{que}</hi> or <hi>Chaldy, Arabi{que}</hi> and <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> are as <hi>Ebrew.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. Broughton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>