<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE Wherein, First, are discouered the seuerall sleights vsed by Protestants, to charge the Church of Rome with Dissentions in doctrine. Secondly, it is proued, that the Necessity of Vnity in Fayth, ought to be in the Church of Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1838_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4263.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1838</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE Wherein, First, are discouered the seuerall sleights vsed by Protestants, to charge the Church of Rome with Dissentions in doctrine. Secondly, it is proued, that the Necessity of Vnity in Fayth, ought to be in the Church of Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Adelphomachia, or The warrs of Protestancy· : Being a treatise, wherein are layd open the wonderfull, and almost incredible dissentions of the Protestants among themselues, in most (if not all) articles of Protesta [n] cy: and this proued from their owne wordes &amp; writinges. VVritten by a Cath. priest. Whereunto is adioyned a briefe appendix, in which is proued; first, that the ancient fathers, by the acknowledgments of the learned Protestants, taught our Cath. and Roman fayth. Secondly, that the said fathers haue diuers aduantages about the Protestant writers, for finding out the true sense of the Scripture</title>
                 <author>B. C., Catholic priest</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>189, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="17" facs="10"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE</hi> Wherein, <hi>First,</hi> are discouered the seuerall sleights vsed by Protestants, to charge the Church of Rome with Dissentions in doctrine. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is proued, that the Necessity of Vnity in Fayth, ought to be in the Church of Christ.</head>
   <p>— <hi>HORRENTIA Martis Arma Virum{que} cano.</hi> — Vndertaking to record the vnnaturall, and blouddy Wars, which the Protestant wageth against the Protestant in matter of Fayth; And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending in this Ensuing discourse, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantle, and lay open to the view of all, the naked state of Protestancy, so far forth, as it concernes its want of <hi>Ʋnity,</hi> and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall <hi>Dissentions</hi> among the Professours thereof; and further well remembring, that our Aduersaries (through their Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine calumny of some among them) are euer ready pressed (by way of Recrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to obtrude, though most wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the like dissentions vpon vs Catholiks:
<pb n="18" facs="11"/> Therefore I haue thought good in the front hereof, to remoue such Replies, and surprize all Obiections, by preuention, as may seeme to fix vpon the Catholiks that blemish or Scar, wherewith Protestancy lyes here iustly chargeable. I herein imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the proceeding of a carefull Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in the Wars, who first labours to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and forestall the Enemy of all Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages and Wayes, whereby the approach of his forces might endanger him; and then drawes out his owne Troupes for the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulting of his said Enemy. Well then, to the point.</p>
   <p n="1">1. First we are to obserue (which the yawning and heedles Reader perhaps will not espye) that in doctrines, there are to be considered two things (as <hi>Beza</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">Beza <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n Epist. Theolog. Epist. 18. sayth:</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum sempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nisi sobriè &amp; prudenter attingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um.</note> well noteth,) to wit, The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, signifying a <hi>Categoricall</hi> or Positiue assertion, that such a thing is true in doctrine, hath euer reference to the <hi>Conclusion:</hi> As for example, <hi>That Saintes in Heauen do heare vs.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, hath res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect only to the <hi>Manner,</hi> or some other Circumstance of the <hi>Conclusion; As whether the Saintes do heare vs, by behoulding all things intuitiuely in God, in whom they see all things: Or that they heare our Prayers, through their ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerity and incredible speedines of the Motion of their soules, who in the smallest tyme are able to descend, and ascend from Heauen to earth.</hi> This <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or <hi>Conclusion</hi> in Fayth, is that, in which all Catholikes (continuing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks) do vnanimously agree. But tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or <hi>manner</hi> of such a point or <hi>Conclusion,</hi> they dissent sometymes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="19" facs="11"/> themselues: Because the <hi>manner</hi> of a point in doctrine is (for the most part) of that <hi>Adiaphorous,</hi> and indifferent Nature, as that seuerall learned Men may teach se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally touching the said <hi>Manner,</hi> without any breach of Fayth. And we are thus war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from being ouercurious and searching into the <hi>Manner</hi> of the Conclusion by an ancient Father, who sayth:<note n="(b)" place="margin">Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Orat <hi>1.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And thus accordingly hereto, all Men are obliged to belieue all decreed Articles of Fayth; yet not euer to belieue the particular <hi>Manner,</hi> or Reason thereof: Which manner being a Point but of Indifferency, is often reduced for triall, to some Scholasticall subtilty or apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
   <p n="2">2. I am to aduertize the Reader, that whereas there is <hi>Questio Juris,</hi> and <hi>Questio Facti;</hi> we are heere to obserue, that matter of <hi>Fact</hi> (but not matter of <hi>Fayth</hi>) may be controuerted among Deuines, without any want of <hi>Vnity</hi> in doctrine; because the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences &amp; determinations passed vpon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Fact,</hi> may and ought to be altered, vpon later and better Informations, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matter of <hi>Fact.</hi> And in this sense and vpon this Occasion, were alterable the Decrees (obiected against vs by some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants) of <hi>Pope Formosas,</hi> by <hi>Pope Steuen</hi> the 6. and <hi>Pope Sergius</hi> the 3. Which decrees were after confirmed againe by <hi>Pope Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus, Theodorus</hi> 2. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. Now the reason of altering the said decrees ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally proceeded from matter of <hi>Fact;</hi> to wit, whether <hi>Formosus</hi> was truly and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically elected Pope (and consequently had
<pb n="20" facs="12"/> full power to make those decrees) or was but only a schismaticall Pope. And thus these other Popes maintayned seuerall O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, touching his Election, being but matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> and according to their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iudgments therein, did abrogate or confirme the decrees of the said <hi>Formosus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">3. A Third Obseruation may heere be taken from the authority of <hi>S. Austin,</hi> thus writing: <hi>Sometimes</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin, l. de Baptismo Contra Iulian. Telag. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the most learned and best defenders of the Catholik Rule, do without breaking the Frame of Fayth, not accord.</hi> And more: <hi>Diuers</hi>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. de Baptism. contra Donat l. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>men be of diuers iudgments without breach of Peace, vntill a Generall Councell allow some one part for cleare &amp; pure.</hi> Thus according hereto we are instructed, that if any doubt of Points concerning Fayth and Religion, do occur and rise (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before determined by the Authority of Gods Church) Christians may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne different Opinions, touching the same Points, vntill the Voyce of Gods Church hath definitiuely and sententional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decreed the said Points one only way. And according to this Caution, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersy houlden betweene the <hi>Thomists</hi> and <hi>Scotists,</hi> concerning the <hi>Conception of our Blessed Lady</hi> (much insisted vpon against vs by our Aduersaries) may be houlden without any violence to Vnity in Fayth; seing this Controuersy is not yet determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and defined by the Church. Of which Controuersy <hi>D. Field</hi> thus sayth: <hi>Touching</hi>
      <note n="(e)" place="margin">D. Field. <hi>l.</hi> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f the Church. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 9. <hi>pag.</hi> 58.</note>
      <hi>Contradictory Opinions, some were named Thomists, other Scotists in Controuersyes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, not yet determined by consent of the Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersall Church:</hi> So idly and impertinently
<pb n="21" facs="12"/> do the Protestants diuerberate the ayre, in vpbrayding the Catholikes with this Controuersy, touching the <hi>Conception of our B. Lady.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">4. Another Obseruation, of which I thinke good to aduertise the Reader, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes certaine forlorne and broken Men (yet competently learned) who once were Catholiks, but after did apostate from the Catholike Church, by entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning some one or other Opinion of Noue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lism, condemned by the said Church; With euery one of which we may well expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in the Dialect of <hi>Josue: Noster</hi>
      <note n="(f)" place="margin">Iosu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> c. <hi>5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>es an Aduersariorum?</hi> yet before their deaths, most of them abandoned, their said Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, and so by their finall submission they dyed Members of our Catholike Church: Such were these few following, <hi>Erasmus, Berengarius Aeneas Siluius, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor Ʋirgil, Laurentius Ʋalla; Wicelius, Cassan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and one or two o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her Pseudo-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks; out of all which Doctour <hi>Morton</hi>
      <note n="(g)" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>olog. Catho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> is not ashamed to vrge that they (being Papists) are deuided in doctrine among themselues. Now to this I answere. This Obiection is of no force, because the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Men did maintayne but some one or other Point against the Church, compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and interleaging in all the rest with the Catholiks: But after, the most part of them relinquishing their former Errours, dyed Catholiks; and in regard of their submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion before their deaths to the Church of Rome (and not otherwise) they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Catholiks. Secondly, I say, that whiles these former Men did persist in their
<pb n="22" facs="13"/> Nouelismes, during all that tyme, they were condemned by the Church of Rome for Heretiks; and therefore it cannot be vrged, that these Men were Papists, at that tyme of their dissenting from the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall Church; for by such their Schisme, they were cut off from the Catholike Church, and wholy reiected for members thereof. And I freely grant, that a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or Papist (as we are opprobriously called) may become an Heretike, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayning some Innouations; But then (I say) he ceaseth to be a Catholike, or Papist.</p>
   <p>But the Case is far otherwise with the Protestants vrged in this following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise. For first the Protestants heere produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (being incomparably far greater in number, then the former named Sectaries) do not disagree in one, or two, or three Points only of Protestancy among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; but they are distracted almost in all points of Protestancy. Againe, I say, the Protestants by me vrged, though recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally crossing one another (contrary to the state of <hi>Berengarius Erasmus,</hi> and the rest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue specified) yet during he same time of maintayning their cōtradictory Opinions, do still remayne Protestants; &amp; accordingly they are all promiscuously acknowledged, as good Members of the Protestāt Church: So great is the disparity betweene the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vrged Authours by <hi>D. Morton,</hi> and the Protestants hereafter by me alledged. That these Protestants, whether they be <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> or <hi>Swinglians</hi> (vnder whom are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended <hi>Caluinists</hi>) which I am to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce,
<pb n="23" facs="13"/> notwithstanding their great discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pancy and dissentions in Fayth, do remayne still Members of the Protestant Church, appeareth from the iudgmēt of <hi>D. Whitaker,</hi> who thus writeth to his Aduersary <hi>Father Campian</hi> (happy Man, who pledged his bloud for the fayth of Christ:) <hi>Quod</hi>
      <note n="(h)" place="margin">In respons. ad rationes Campiani rat. <hi>8.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>autem Lutheranos cum Swingliants coniungis &amp;c. In that thou dost conioyne, and vnite the Lutherans and the Swinglians together, thou dost not offend vs; For we willingly honour Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as our Father, and all them</hi> (meaning, the <hi>Lutherans, Swinglians,</hi> and <hi>Caluinists) as our most deare brethren in Christ.</hi> And according to this tenour <hi>D. Iewell</hi> affirmeth, saying: <hi>The</hi>
      <note n="(i)" place="margin">In his Apolog. of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. <hi>pag.</hi> 101.</note>
      <hi>Swinglians and Lutherans are good friends; they vary not among themselues, vpon the Principles and foundation of our Religion, but vpon only one Question, which is neither weighty nor great.</hi> And thus far of the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parency of the former Obiection, touching <hi>Berengarius, Erasmus &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Hitherto may be adioyned, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Protestants are hereafter charged with great dissentions &amp; inconstancy, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their often altering their <hi>Common Booke of Prayer; D. Doue</hi> acknowledging so much, seekes to auoyd this blemish, by say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The</hi>
      <note n="(k)" place="margin">D. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ne in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion to English Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</note>
      <hi>Papists haue done the like &amp;c. How many tymes haue their Breuiaryes beene altered?</hi> But good <hi>Reader,</hi> see the great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence herein. The Protestants altering their <hi>Communion Booke,</hi> do withall alter some points of Beliefe and doctrine; seing the change of their <hi>Communion Booke</hi> resteth only in change of doctrine; the later <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Booke</hi> euer reiecting certaine Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="24" facs="14"/> of Fayth, which the former did allow off. Now the altering of the <hi>Breuiaries</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists only in inserting certaine prayers in the later, which were not in the former, throgh occasion of Canonization of Saints, or some other vrgent Cause: But there is not any alteration, or change or Articles of Fayth in their different Breuiaries, which is the point only here to be insisted vpon.</p>
   <p>Now these Premonitions being afore acknowledged for true, whereby are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented some weake Obiections, of which diuers of our Aduersaries haue made vse, to seeke to proue the Catholiks disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in matter of Fayth; it is lesse strange that some of them haue not forborne (such is the scarsity and want of them) to alledge<note n="(l)" place="margin">This obiection of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Church of Rome, is vrged by <hi>D. Fulke</hi> in his ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were <hi>to a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyte Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike p.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5. By <hi>D. Iewell</hi> in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. <hi>pag.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. and by others.</note> for matter of Controuersyes, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Papists,</hi> some are called <hi>Francis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, some Benedictines, others Augustines &amp;c. These do sometymes eate flesh, those other feede only vpon fish,</hi> most idly and ignorantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted vpon. For what do these differences concerne matter of Fayth and Religion? Do not all these seuerall Orders of Gods Church belieue all the Articles of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and Roman Fayth? They only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer among themselues in liuing in a more strict, or remisse course of life. And this Answere is giuen by <hi>D. Field</hi> in these Words: <hi>We must</hi>
      <note n="(m)" place="margin">Of the Church. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>pag.</hi> 58.</note>
      <hi>obserue, that they, who professe the Fayth of Christ haue beene sometimes in these later Ages of the Church, called after the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall names of such Men, as were the Authours, Beginners, and Deuisers of such courses of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasticall Profession as they made choyce to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; as Benedictins, &amp; such like.</hi> Thus <hi>D. Field.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb n="25" facs="14"/>
   <p>Therefore I conclude, that in regard of want of true Arguments in proofe of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions amōg Catholiks, touching meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters of Religion, I cannot but much approue the ingenuous and playne Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of some of our Aduersaries heere, in our be halfe. And fortably hereto we fynd <hi>D. Whitaker</hi> thus to confesse of this Point: <hi>The dissentions</hi>
      <note n="(n)" place="margin">De Eccles. contra Bellarm. controuer. <hi>2.</hi> q <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>327.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>among the Papists, are but</hi> futiles, <hi>concerning things of small importance.</hi> And <hi>D. Fulke</hi> agreeth with him, saying: <hi>As for the</hi>
      <note n="(o)" place="margin">A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Hes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp;c. pag. 295.</note>
      <hi>consent, and peace of the Popish Church, it proueth nothing, but that the Diuell had all things at his Will, and therefore might sleepe:</hi> thus truly acknowledging Vnity in Fayth in the Roman Church, but most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciously transferring the Cause therof to him, who is the chiefe Enemy to <hi>Vnity.</hi> But <hi>Syr Edwin Sands</hi> (a most remarkable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant) doth not only acknowledge all war of dissention in our Catholike Church; but also giueth his reason thereof in these Words: <hi>The Papists</hi>
      <note n="(p)" place="margin">In his Relation. <hi>fol.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>haue the Pope, as a common Father, Aduiser, and Conductour to reconcile their iarres, to decide their differences, to draw their Religion, by consent of Councells, to Ʋnity &amp;c.</hi> To whose Iudgment herein subscribeth <hi>Andraeas Duditius</hi> the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant aboue mentioned, in the Epistle De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory) who thus writeth: <hi>The Roman</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">
         <hi>Beza</hi> reporteth these words of <hi>Duditius,</hi> in his Epist. Theolog. <hi>Epist. ad Duditium.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Church is not deuided with so many Diss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but it hath the plausible apparence of Ʋe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Antiquity, Ordinary Succession, and Perpetuall Consent.</hi> Thus <hi>Duditius.</hi> And thus farre by way of Preuention of all such Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guments, as the Protestant Wryters may seeme to vrge, thereby to make their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="26" facs="15"/> followers belieue, that the Catholiks do labour with one and the same disease with themselues, touching disagreements in points of Fayth, and Religion.</p>
   <p>Only before I passe further, I thinke good to relate that ordinary and common refuge, and tergiuersation, which diuers Protestants of England being vpbrayded with disagreements in Fayth among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, are accustomed to fly vnto, who thus reason: <hi>I am an English Protestant, I litle regard, how forraine Protestants disagree among themselues; I am content to range my selfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our English learned Protestants; who I am assured, maintayne the Truth of Fayth without any contradiction, or dissention among themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</hi> Now because this point requyreth a large and full Answere, therefore as willing to contract this <hi>Preface</hi> in as few words, as conueniently I may, I refer the Reader for his full satisfaction herein to the latter end of this ensuing Treatise, viz. at 22. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, where he shall see the Vanity of this silly euasion, fully layed open and answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Before I come to any other Passages of this <hi>Preface,</hi> I hould it not amisse to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late (for the benefit of others) what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened touching these former Points to my selfe. In my being in Spayne, a <hi>Chaplayne</hi> of the <hi>English Embassadours</hi> there resyding, (being my former familiar acquaintance in <hi>England</hi>) oftentimes came to the place where I there studied; and did much soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and diswade me, from entring into <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders</hi> (for then I was not <hi>Priest.</hi>) His chiefest argument by him alledged, was taken out of <hi>D. Mortons Apologia Catholica,</hi>
      <pb n="27" facs="15"/> (which booke it seemes, he had studyed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>igently) touching the dissentions in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of some few broken Catholiks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue alledged, as, <hi>Erasmus▪ Nilus, Cassander &amp;c.</hi> as also from the dissention of the <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists</hi> and <hi>Scotists,</hi> touching the <hi>Conception of our B. Lady;</hi> the <hi>Chaplaine</hi> much vrging and inferring, that our Catholike Religion, as wanting <hi>Vnity in doctrine</hi> in the Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours thereof, could not be true. This his Argument for a tyme (I grant) seemed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry strong to me (I then being but yong, and not conuersant in the Protestants owne bookes, thereby to discerne their dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in doctrine) and did cause me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer my taking of <hi>Priesthood,</hi> a yeare or more longer, then afore I was determined to haue done.</p>
   <p>But after acquainting others of my daily familiars (much read in the Protestants Writings) with this my doubt; they fully resolued, and satisfyed me touching those <hi>Pseudo. Catholiks;</hi> to wit, what kind of Men they were, &amp; how, &amp; vpon what grounds they for the tyme, dissented from the then Common doctrine of the <hi>Catholike Church:</hi> As also I was then informed how the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of the <hi>immaculate Conception of the B. Ʋirgin,</hi> was not defined on either syde by the Church; and that therefore it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (without any breach of <hi>Vnity</hi>) to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne either part. Vpon whose learned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution all my former doubt instantly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished away. And indeed this Accident first be got a desire in me, to looke into the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants Works more fully, to see, whether they had thy disagreements in Fayth amōg
<pb n="28" facs="16"/> them: So forcible (we see) the Argument drawne from wāt of <hi>Vnity</hi> in Fayth (though but indirectly, and with mistaking, vrged) seemes to proue that Religion, which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Ʋnity</hi> in Fayth and doctrine, cannot be the true Religion, instituted by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi> But to recall my selfe, and to proceed further.</p>
   <p>In the next place of this my <hi>Preface,</hi> I will demonstrate the absolute necessity of <hi>Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> touching Matters of Fayth in the Church of God; it being an acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and inseparable Marke thereof:) and how incompatible, dissentions, and Errours in Fayth, are with the said true Church: <hi>Adulterari</hi>
      <note n="(r)" place="margin">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. lib. de Vnitate Ecclesia.</note>
      <hi>non potest sponsa Christi; Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupta est, &amp; pudica.</hi> This I will euict both from humane and diuine Authorities: and will begin with humane proofes, and so ascend in weight of proofes, to the diuine Scriptures.</p>
   <p>And first I will alledge some testimonies of Protestants themselues: For do we not fynd <hi>Luther</hi> thus to teach? <hi>A Kingdome</hi>
      <note n="(s)" place="margin">Luther. tom. <hi>3.</hi> Witten. berg. in Psalm. <hi>5.</hi> fol. <hi>166.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>deuided in it selfe shall not stand; Neither haue any Heretiks at any tyme beene ouercome by force or Subtilty, but by mutuall dissention: Neither doth Christ fight with them otherwise, then with a spirit of giddinesse and disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And more, <hi>The Authours</hi>
      <note n="(t)" place="margin">Luth. tom. <hi>5.</hi> Witten. berg. in Galat. c. <hi>5.</hi> fol. <hi>416.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>of Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes are disagreeing among themselues &amp;c. They byte and deuours one another &amp;c. till at the last they perish &amp;c.</hi> O see, how truly his owne Words do recoyle vpon himselfe.</p>
   <p>The Like want of this <hi>Vnity</hi> in doctrine, do the Deuines of <hi>Manifold</hi> vrge (as a Marke of a false Church) against the <hi>Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi>
      <pb n="29" facs="16"/> to impugne their doctrine; those deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes thus writing: <hi>We haue</hi>
      <note n="(u)" place="margin">Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldenses in Confessio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldica Latina. fol. <hi>110.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>iust reason to hold in suspition the doctrine of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, in that they are not concordant in one, and the same sentence, or iudgment; but are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themselues deuided: so as some of them are called Carolostadians, others Swinglians, Occo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampadians, Caluinists &amp;c.</hi> And the same kind of argument is vsed by the Deuines of <hi>Heidelberge</hi> (all Protestants) against the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> thus vrging. <hi>Si</hi>
      <note n="(x)" place="margin">Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ocollo Frankal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talensi n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Praefat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptistas.</note>
      <hi>vobis Ecclesiae titulum concedere vellemus &amp;c. Yf we would grant to you the name of a Church, what Sect among you, should be reputed the Church of God, seing you are deuided into so many Sects?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To come, in this next place, to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriries of the ancient Fathers; Whose Pens were euer imployed against euery then new arising Doctrine, not bearing <hi>Ʋnity</hi> to the Fayth of Gods Vniuersall Church; we fynd <hi>S. Athanasius</hi> thus to Wryte: <hi>Jllud</hi>
      <note n="(y)" place="margin">Orat. <hi>1.</hi> contra Arianos.</note>
      <hi>quoque prorsus admirabile &amp;c. This also is very wonderfull, that all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resyes, in coyning diuers things, do differ in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and do iointly agree in defence of fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. S. Chrysostome</hi> sharpeneth his penne in this sort, against the Enemyes of <hi>Ʋnity</hi> in Fayth: <hi>Omnes Infideles</hi>
      <note n="(z)" place="margin">Opera imperfect. in Math. hom. <hi>20.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>qui sub diabolo sunt &amp;c. All such Infidells, or Misbelieuers, which are in the power of the Diuell, are not vnited, but are deuided through diuersity of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: And such is the want of Fayth among Hereticks, who neuer agree in one consent of Things; but maintayne as seuerall Opinions, as themselues are seuerall in number.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Chrysostome.</hi> S. <hi>Hilarius</hi> in this sort pensilleth out the face, and countenance of disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing
<pb n="30" facs="17"/> Heretiks:<note n="(a)" place="margin">L. <hi>7.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Trinitate.</note>
      <hi>Haeretici omnes contra Ecclesiam veniunt &amp;c. All Heretiks do assault the Church; But whiles Heretiks do mutually ouercome one another, they ouercome nothing therin; since their Ʋictory, when one Heresy doth euen fight against another, is finally become the Triūph of the Church. Tertullian</hi>
      <note n="(b)" place="margin">L. de Praescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersus Haeres. <hi>41.</hi>
      </note> writes of this point in this manner: <hi>Inspectae Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses omnes &amp;c. All Heresyes (being truly looked into) are deprehended to dissent in many things, euen with thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> owne Authours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I will conclude with Irenaeus: <hi>Videmus</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> in initio.</note>
      <hi>nunc &amp; corum inconstantem sententiam &amp;c. We now see their inconstant iudgment, who, if they be but two or three in number, how diuersly they teach the same things.</hi> And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the said Father: <hi>Durum</hi>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">Vbi supra. c. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>est omnium describere sententias &amp;c. Jt is a difficult thing, to set downe the different Sentences of all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> For greater breuity of this point, I refer the Reader to the testimonies of <hi>S. Ierome</hi>
      <note n="(e)" place="margin">In Math. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>4.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>S. Austin</hi>
      <note n="(f)" place="margin">Contra Epist Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>S. Ambrose</hi>
      <note n="(g)" place="margin">L. de fide, ad Gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>, and the <hi>Councell of</hi>
      <note n="(h)" place="margin">In de cretis Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e nae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note>
      <hi>Nyce.</hi> And thus far tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Fathers herein.</p>
   <p>Now, in this last place, to ascend to the sacred Authorities of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> which are the stamps, sealing vp the Truth of all the former Humane Authorities; which testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies I reserue hitherto, wherewith to close yp the Iudgment of the Reader here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And first to shew the Vglines of <hi>Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> we read:<note n="(i)" place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 11.</note>
      <hi>Euery Kingdome deuided in it selfe, shall perish.</hi> And vpon this ground the Prophet thus prayeth. <hi>Destroy,</hi>
      <note n="(k)" place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5.</note>
      <hi>O Lord, and deuide their Tongues;</hi> implying hereby, that their deuided Tongues in iudgment, shall occasion their destruction.
<pb n="31" facs="17"/> And another <hi>Prophet</hi> in further proofe of this point, thus hath left recorded: <hi>Their</hi>
      <note n="(l)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ose.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0.</note>
      <hi>Hart is deuided, they shall now perish.</hi> And the <hi>Wiseman</hi> instructeth vs in these Words: <hi>God</hi>
      <note n="(m)" place="margin">
         <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb.</hi> 6.</note>
      <hi>hateth him, that raiseth vp Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among Brethren.</hi> All which Scripturall Authorities as they shew the malice &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of <hi>Disunion</hi> and <hi>Dissention</hi> in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; so they implicitly, and potentially proue, that Want of <hi>Vnity</hi> in Doctrine, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not stand with true Fayth. Therefore the more reason had the Apostle <hi>S. Paul</hi> to vse this his feruerous admonition to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians of his tyme, saying: <hi>I beseech</hi>
      <note n="(n)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>you Brethren, that there be no dissentions among you: Not forsaking</hi>
      <note n="(o)" place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.</note>
      <hi>the fellowship, which we haue among our selues.</hi> Neither is the Apostle lesse slow in recommending the <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Vnity</hi> in expresse words (though this be coincident with the former;) for thus he instructeth his followers: <hi>I beseech</hi>
      <note n="(p)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>you, that you all speake one thing; be you knit togeather in one mind, and one iudgment:</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>Endeuoring to keep the Ʋnity of spirit in the band of peace. God is the God,</hi>
      <note n="(r)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note>
      <hi>not of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision, but of Peace.</hi> And according hereto we read, that our <hi>Sauiour</hi> prayed for the Members of his Church, that they may be <hi>One</hi>
      <note n="(s)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 17.</note>. And to conclude according to this his prayer, it is recorded, that the Multitude of them, which belieued, <hi>were</hi>
      <note n="(t)" place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>of One Hart, and One Soule;</hi> so luxuriant &amp; aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we fynd the sacred Scriptures to be, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or the extirpation of all <hi>Dissention</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ision</hi> out of the society of Christians, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or the entertayning of <hi>Vnity</hi> among them, in all Matters of Religion.</p>
   <pb n="32" facs="18"/>
   <p>Now then hauing thus demonstrated the Necessity of <hi>Vnion</hi> in matters of Fayth, both from diuine and humane Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and withall hauing in the beginning aboue (as it were) beset all wayes &amp; pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, by which our Aduersaries might in a vulgar iudgment, seeme to assault vs, by their pretence of some weake and feeble Reasons,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Sze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedin. <hi>(the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant)</hi> in loc. om. pag. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>4. thus saith:</hi> Vnity, one of the Notes of the Church.</note> for proofe of <hi>Diuision</hi> in Fayth to be in our Catholike Church: it remayneth, that we hasten to shew, whether <hi>Vnity</hi> in Fayth (as being a Marke of the true Church, euen by the iudgment of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants themselues) can be found in <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy;</hi> Or in place thereof implacable and irreconcileable <hi>Disagreements</hi> and Warres: A most foule scarre or moale, to remayne vpon the Fayth of the supposed Chiefe Professours of the <hi>Ghospell:</hi> So indisputably true it is, that <hi>Protestancy</hi> lyes exposed, or rather becomes thrall to all Fluctuation &amp; Inconstancy in doctrine. And with this (I say) I will hasten to present to the sight of the Reader, that face, which is ingendred of so many <hi>Contradictions in Fayth;</hi> and I will be content (for the tyme) to become the <hi>Protestants Herauld,</hi> in blasing the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of their Contentions. So shall the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> withall discerne, that the <hi>Protestants</hi> Pens are euer prest, and ready to discharge vpon their owne Brethren (for matter of Fayth and Religion) euen whole Volleys of shot, of most reproachfull Words, and intemperate Language.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>