<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Clavell, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1866_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5369.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1866</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Clavell, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A recantation of an ill led life. Or A discouerie of the high-way law : With vehement disswasions to all (in that kind) offenders. As also many cautelous admonitions and full instructions, how to know, shun, and apprehend a theefe. Most necessarie for all honest trauellers to per'use, obserue and practise. Written by Iohn Clauell, gent. Approued by the Kings most Excellent Maiestie, and published by his expresse commaund</title>
                 <author>Clavell, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clavell, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THe liueliest and best Monuments of men
are their actions, and in those, their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories
either die before them in infamy,
or suruiue them vnto the farthest extent of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie
in the fullest and fairest Registers of time,
and glorie; both of these retaine their subsisten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
not in the brazen leaues of Sepulchres, nor
in the tongue-failing relation of succession, but in
those Paper Records, which seldome forfeite
them to losse, although assaulted by neuer so
many alterations, as the Stories from the first
World, as well prophane, as diuine, may
wonderfully witnesse to all Obseruers, This
truth may question my discretion, that haue
made mine owne hand the Character of such
actions as Posteritie will blush at, whose me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
might easily haue lost the thoughts of men
in lesse then halfe an age. If thus I had not giuen
<pb facs="10"/>
it continuance as lasting as the World; It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
in respect of my selfe the answere is difficult,
but in respect of God, the World, and mine
owne conscience, I could contriue no fairer or
more reall satisfaction. The sinnes of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest
children of God haue had their like pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments,
<hi>Dauid's</hi> Murther and Adulterie must
haue <hi>Dauid's</hi> written Confession and Contrition,
<hi>Salomons</hi> Lasciuiousnesse must haue his owne
acknowledgement and recantation, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
he that is ashamed to confesse the ills hee
hath beene conscious of, argues too palpably
that he is a great many leagues from repentance,
and is more in loue with his sinne, then his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment.
Belieue in Charitie, this is my resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that mine owne free detection of this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
and common vice, might not only kill the
feare of my impossible relapses, but be a iust de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrer
of all the worshippers of this course. Nor
can I feare, that such Idolatry of theirs can rise
in Iudgement against this truth of mine, which
hath so honestly condemned them, and their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
or that their reuenges, which they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie
proclaymed against the innocence of my
Recantation, can reach farther then the counsels
of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> Whose effect extended to selfe
ruine, whilst I shall be happie, to be either censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="10"/>
or forgotten by them; for whose amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
I owe my Prayers, and will Religiously
inuoke; that they may, either become new
men like me, or else, that they may know my
resolution hath built me beyond the aspersion
of their poysons Nor can I feare the ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struing
of this worke of mine, they that loue
truth, and reconciliation of wild youth (to
that perfection the first Creation intended)
will loue my expression, more then my
Verse; and hugge my intended innocence,
more then they can in goodnesse condemne
my detected Offences; The rest, that are
Gald, or preuented by this Discouerie must
not dare to Iudge, because all indifferencie is
denied them. Nor can they whose hatreds
against my Person, or Actions, haue drawne,
into a resolued opposing, of my fairest cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
clayme any Language in the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of my Booke, or profession of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
since their splenatiue Soules will draw
them into a worse extremitie of censure, then
euer my most prouoking needes could mee,
into the high way of this kind of sinning.
How so euer it is taken, it is honestly meant,
and will prooue (questionlesse) a wholesome
<pb facs="11"/>
preuention for the honest traueller, whose sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
I couet, that my ills may finde some
redemption that way, which is the fullest am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
and hope of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your well wisher,
Iohn Clauell.</signed>
      <dateline>From my louely sad, and
vnfrequented Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi>
         <date>October, 1627.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>