<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1869_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12150</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5554</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1869</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Breefe collection concerning the love of God tovvards mankinde, &amp; hovv for diuers causes vve are iustlie bounde to loue &amp; serue him : with preparation to prayer, and certaine necessarie prayers and thankesgeuing to God for his benefites, daylie to be vsed : also a deuote meditation to procure contrition, and excite deuotion with other vertuous prayers</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--East Ham</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62, that is 72, 4 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>BEing desirerous (good Reader) to haue published some short Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of most necessairie praiers, but hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by diuers vrgēt occatiōs: I thought good, in respect of my duty to God, and necessity of the time presēt, rather vvith the poore vvidovve, to offer vnto him this simple Mite, for the increase of his honour in helping of the godly, then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to geue ouer my purpose. And vvheras true vertue, cōsisteth principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in the loue of God: vvithout vvhieh our praiers are of no force. I haue here prepared a litle Treatise concerning that matter, and in vvhat respect vvee are bounde to serue him: In vvhich, as in a glasse vve may clerelie behold our ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itude,
<pb facs="3"/> tovvardes so louing a Lord. And because manie rather of custome then true deuotion, so rashlie goe about that holie vvoorke of prayer: I haue set doūe a preparation thereunto, vvith necessarie prayers, Meditations, and thankesge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, to be vsed daylie. Farevvell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>