<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>D., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1885_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20150</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6584.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1885</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>D., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians care for the soules safety, or, The wofull losse of the soule compared with the vaine gaine of the world in a sermon lately preached by Iohn Denison</title>
                 <author>Denison, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 61 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of some worthy friends, hauing preuailed with mee for copies of this Sermon, their iudgements for the use of it haue made it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique. The subiect indeede is large, but my time alot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for deliuery was short
<pb facs="3"/>according to which J was to contriue and contract my Meditations. For what is the allowance of an howre, to speake of whatsoeuer is vnder the Sunne?</p>
   <p>Yet as a few clusters of <hi>grapes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Num. 13.25.28.</note> were sufficient to shew by implication the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate condition of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse and to demonstrate the riches of Canaan: so these fewe <hi>Lines</hi> may in some measure discouer the vanitie of this present life, and manifest the excellency
<pb facs="3"/>of the soule; and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what great care is to bee had and what good courses to be taken for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the same. This is that <hi>Vnum necessarium,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luke 10.42</note> that one thing which is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; Which if a man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect,
<note place="margin">Sap. 2.8.</note> though Hee crowne himselfe with Roses, &amp; inioy the confluence of all earthly contents, yet is he misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and his case lamentable. Jt were good for him if hee had neuer bene borne: Or,
<note place="margin">Matt. 26.24</note> like the contemptible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="4"/>had a Life onely in stead of salt to preuent pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction.
<note place="margin">Animum pro sale datum. Cicer <hi>of the Hogg.</hi> de finib. bon. lib. 5.</note> If these briefe meditations shal adde some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to thy Christian care, it is what I desire of God, to whose good blessing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending both them and thy selfe, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> I. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>