<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull sir Frauncis Iobson knight, Lieutenant of the Toure, Iohn Drout wisheth long lyfe, with continuall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Drout, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1906_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20864</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7241.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull sir Frauncis Iobson knight, Lieutenant of the Toure, Iohn Drout wisheth long lyfe, with continuall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Drout, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pityfull histori [e] of two louing Italians, Gaulfrido and Barnardo le vayne : which ariued in the countrey of Grece, in the time of the noble Emperoure Vaspasian. And translated out of Italian into Englishe meeter by John Drout, of Thauis Inne Gentleman. Anno. 1570</title>
                 <author>Drout, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull sir Frauncis Iobson knight, Lieutenant of the Toure, Iohn Drout wisheth long lyfe, with continuall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN AS I had perused and diligētly red ouer this pitiful historie, and sundry times gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē my vvhole indeuor to the vvell markyng of the same (right vvorshipful sir) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered vvith my selfe, first hovve profitable it vvold be to those, vvhich be desirous to learn the <hi>Italian</hi> speeche: ageyne pondring in my mynde, hovv pleasant a thing it is for to reade this hidden historie, (vvhich not vvithout lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paine) I haue translated out of <hi>Italian</hi> into English verse, very plainly, for those vvhiche shall meane to giue their vvhole indeuor and industry to the attaining of so pleasant a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. VVherefore being vvholly bent and purposed to haue this my simple translation of so notable a tragedie published: I thought it good for diuers considerations to bestovve this the first frutes of my trauell, vpon youre vvorship, rather than vppon any other man, first bicause of the great affection, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall good vvill, vvhich your vvorship and my good Lady your bedfelovv (vvhich lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased
<pb facs="7"/>
(haue borne to my deare parents, vvhō I pray God long to continue, and for many more benefites, the vvhich (for breuities sake) I do pretermitte: for consideration vvhereof I haue the more boldlyer attempted to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this my little and simple volume to your vvorship, hauing a good hope and trust that you vvill haue me excused for my rude bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and accept my good vvill herein signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Thus leauing you, and all yours to the tuition of almightie God, vvho increase you vvith continuall vvorship, graunt you long life, vvith eternall feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, I bidde you fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships to commaunde, Iohn Drout.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>