<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull and his especiall good friend, Maister Iohn Kemp∣horne Esquier, R. W. wisheth in this life prosperous successe in all affaires, and in the life to come a crowne of glorie.</title>
           <author>Wolcombe, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2155_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04501</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14630.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2155</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull and his especiall good friend, Maister Iohn Kemp∣horne Esquier, R. W. wisheth in this life prosperous successe in all affaires, and in the life to come a crowne of glorie.</title>
                 <author>Wolcombe, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent treatise touching the restoring againe of him that is fallen written by the woorthy man Saint Iohn Chrysostome ... ; turned and put into English, out of an ancient Latine translation, written in velume, by R.W</title>
                 <author>John Chrysostom, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Winnington, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 143 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull and his especiall good <hi>friend, Maister Iohn</hi> Kemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>horne Esquier, R. W. wisheth in <hi>this life prosperous successe in all</hi> affaires, and in the life to <hi>come a crowne of</hi> glorie.</head>
   <p>SEeing alwaies it hath been accounted a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous worke, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her to commende in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ollo wisedome, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ol in Hercules puissance, or to praise in Minerua knowledge: it may bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hought no lesse needlesse or me, to praise in fined words and garnished stile if so I were able to do) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>our ardent zeal in Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ruth, and maruellous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ection towards the true
<pb facs="3"/> professors thereof. And bicause among those that know you, it shineth so o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riently, as in words to set it foorth, were rather to imbeazle than illustrate it; and among those tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> know you not, by com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mending it abundantly may feare the censure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> smoothing, I thinke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> better, at this time (as Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lust saith of Carthage) to speake nothing at all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it than a little. Yet surely (though the enuious hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily mislike it) this I af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firme, when I bethough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to find a meete protecto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for this pamphlet, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> might loue it, as Antoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us the Emperor was won<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to loue books, as Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus
<pb facs="3"/> was accustomed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme the works of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, that might reade it diligently as Erasmus did Terence, as bishop Iewell did Horace, as Ladie Iane Graie did Platoes Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: none came to my minde before your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, vnder the wings of whose tuition, these my slender labors might safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be shadowed, from all the malice of spitefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouers and taunting carpers. Now concerning the worke, some I knowe will finde fault with my presumption, that being a tender suckling and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in good letters, I would dare to put foorth ought in print, especially
<pb facs="4"/> in such a plentifull time of bookes. Let these take this answere; that I did it not voluntarily but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, and that by the request, not of one or two but of many, whose good will I haue often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, whose friendship in the Lorde I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (for a small cause) violate, whose authoritie I may not despise. For lighting by chance on this treatise of Chrysostome, reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it at the first sight more for antiquitie than ought else, assoone as I had read it ouer, I did it faithfully for my priuate vtilitie into English, neuer thinking it should come to this passe. But hauing
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent it vnto some of my Friends, desirous of such a peece of matter, they fell suddenly into that liking and louing of it, that they neuer ceased exhorting, begging, compelling (I may say) vntill (maugre my head) I granted, it should go foorth for the benefit of many. Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ow being newly borne and come into the world, I beseech your courtesie to receiue into your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage: and as it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from a willing mind, so to take it with a glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some countenance. And notwithstanding this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie of a gratefull mind, do not any waye counterpoise the weight
<pb facs="5"/> of your demerits, yet I beseech you to accept of the poore widowes mites, and of the cheerfull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers mind. Thus surcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing any longer to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt your Worships seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affaires, I suppliantly craue of the Almightie, daily to augment his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in you and the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentlewoman your wife, that after your rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ran in this dale of misery, you may for euer enioi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the sight of Christ Iesus in heauen. From Chud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh, Anno. 1587.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships daily and humble Orator,</hi> ROB. WOLCOM<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>