<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull, and his lo∣uing kinde Father, maister Iohn Banester, Chirurgian, and Licenti∣ate in Physicke: health, and his harts desire intirely wished.</title>
           <author>Tyrer, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2211_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72769</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16644.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2211</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull, and his lo∣uing kinde Father, maister Iohn Banester, Chirurgian, and Licenti∣ate in Physicke: health, and his harts desire intirely wished.</title>
                 <author>Tyrer, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exercise of a Christian life, written by G.L. Being the first ground and foundaion [sic], whence the two treatises appertaining to resolution, were made and framed, by R.P</title>
                 <author>Loarte, Gaspar de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Leake, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 112, 4 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Worshipfull, and his</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kinde Father, maister <hi>Iohn</hi> Banester, <hi>Chirurgian, and Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi> in Physicke: health, and his <hi>harts desire intirely wished.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emembring how many kind fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, I haue from time to time receiued at your handes (louing friend &amp; father) yet on my part no moitie of answereable courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie returned, whereby you might either finde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of your gentlenesse, or note my thankefull mind: Now at last, as neerely touched with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of mine owne slothfulnesse, I presume to dedicate this small Treatise to you, therein to require fauour for all former wants, and in your woonted affable nature, to bury all defects on my behalfe. For the excellencie of the worke, I dare commit it to your iudgement, after reading, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I knowe you can both reade and censure: And for my selfe, I likewise with the booke, stand readie at your seruice, and to bee commaunded to the vttermost power while I liue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>