<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2211_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72769</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16644.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2211</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exercise of a Christian life, written by G.L. Being the first ground and foundaion [sic], whence the two treatises appertaining to resolution, were made and framed, by R.P</title>
                 <author>Loarte, Gaspar de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Leake, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 112, 4 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS learned Treatise of the exercise of a christian life (Gentle Reader) was first written in the Italian tounge, by a certayne Iesuit Frier whoe was named <hi>Gasper Loarte,</hi> and afterwarde more at large wrought vppon, and handled in more plentifull discourse, by <hi>Robert Persons</hi> Englishman, yet a Iesuite likewise, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beyond the Seaes, which he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>A Christian exercise, appertaining to Resolution,</hi> two partes whereof are extant in English, and many haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Christian profit from them, I doe not doubt. Nowe this treatise, beeing the firste frame and ground-woorke,
<pb facs="4"/> where these two seuerall bookes were deriued, and containing very muche good matter left vnhandled in them: is likewise published for thy further benefite if with like minde and spirite thou giue it entertainement, as it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. Diuers learned men haue had the perusing of it, and haue left no matter in it to vrge thy dislike: then thankfully accept of their paines that would gladly do any thing for thy profit.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>