<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER, Concerning the tvvo Catalogues ensuing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2249_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08325</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18658.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2249</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER, Concerning the tvvo Catalogues ensuing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An appendix to the Antidote· : Conteyning a catalogue of the visible and perpetuall succession of the Catholique professours of the Roman Church, by whom the doctrine now taught vnder Pope Gregory the XV. hath beene in all ages, and countreyes, since Christ, constantly &amp; vniformely maintayned. Togeather with a counter-catalogue discouering the interruption of hereticall sectes, amongst whome the chiefe Protestant articles, and their authours, haue beene in diuers ages, vpon sundry occasions, contradicted, and condemned, by the watchmen of the true Church. By S.N. Doctour of Diuinity</title>
                 <author>S. N. (Sylvester Norris)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>107, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER, <hi>Concerning the tvvo Catalogues ensuing.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR as much as the visible suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of lawfull Pastors, &amp; the perpetual pedigre of zealous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuers, is an infallible marke of Christes chosen Spouse; I haue heere (Gentle Reader) presented to thy view: First, the supreame Heads &amp; Gouernours of the Roman Church. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the cheife Professours by which it hath still continued, and such as for the most part in all ages haue bene generally knowne, or publiquely canonized Saints. Thirdly, diuers substātiall points of our Catholique Faith, which they most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly taught &amp; belieued: I quote the places only,
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
but seldome relate their wordes, because I haue ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them at large, for the first fiue hundred yeares in the Controuersies themselues. Fourthly, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels lawfully called, and assembled by them. Fiftly, the Conuersions of Countries, which they haue performed by authority &amp; commission from Christ his Vicar on earth. Sixtly, sundry au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall and approued miracles by which God himself vouchsafed to testify either the sanctity of the men, or verity of their doctrines: for as with miracles the Church was first plāted by Christ, as with miracles it was after spread &amp; propagated by the Apostles, who <hi>going forth preached euery where</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Marc.</hi> 10. 20.</note>
      <hi>our Lord, working with all, &amp; confirming the word with signes that followed:</hi> So with the glory of miracles it hath still flourished according to our Sauiour his <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14. 12.</note> Prediction: <hi>He that belieueth in me, the workes that I doe he also shall do; and greater then these he shall do.</hi> Likewise, <hi>These signes shall followe such as belieue: in</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.</note>
      <hi>my name they shall cast out Diuels</hi> &amp;c. For this cause <note place="margin">
         <hi>Tertul. in lib. de Praescript. Epiphan. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de hares haer.</hi> 30.</note> Tertullian challengeth the Heretikes of his time, to produce their miracles, as we do now our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Sectaries. Epiphanius conuinceth Ebion of false beliefe, because neither he, nor any one of his faction had the gift of working miracles, speaking thus vnto him. <hi>Raise thou, O Ebion, some dead man, cleanse the leprous, restore sight to the blinde, or heale a man sicke of the palsey if thou canst; but thou canst not, because through incredulity thou docst the contrary, clogged with the chaines of flesh: but if thou canst not performe these thinges, as indeed thou canst not by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy naughty faith, yea if thou inuocate the name</hi>
      <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
      <hi>of Christ, thou shalt no way preuaile &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ambros. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>ser.</hi> 91. <hi>de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. corp. SS Gerua. &amp; Protas.</hi>
      </note> discardeth the Arrians from being of the same beliefe with the glorious martirs of Christ, for not acknowledging the famous miracles wrought by their merits, <hi>which the very diuels confessed. S. Augustin</hi> among other markes, by the fame of miracles, <hi>was held in the bosome of the Church:</hi> and saith of them. <note place="margin">
         <hi>August. cont. epist. Manich. c.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>Now also at this present miracles are wrought in Christs name, what by his sacraments what by the praiers or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of Saints.</hi> And thē rebuking the infidelity of our aduersaries, <hi>They belieue not (quoth he) these la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r, which also do not belieue that our Lord Iesus was</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 22. <hi>de ciuit. c.</hi> 8. <hi>ibid cap.</hi> 8. 9. 10.</note>
      <hi>borne of his mother without impayring her virginity, &amp; that he entred in to his disciples the dores being shut.</hi> Hitherto <hi>S. Augustin.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>On the other side I haue also set downe the dismembred rowe, or scattered rankes of such he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall Innouatours, as from Christ his daies euen vntill ours, haue newly sprung vp, &amp; vented forth their strange deuises; which according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of lies &amp; falsities, haue bene neuer the same: but diuers, monstrous, and allwaies changeable, cōcurring in nothing but in maine oppositiō to the Roman Church, &amp; her professours, she still remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning inuiolable, &amp; constant without any addition, change, or alteration of her first receiued Faith; the speciall note, by which <hi>Thcodorct</hi> discerneth verity from falshood, saying: <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that is in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish: <hi>Alcasing is diuers and various, but one or single</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Theod. orat.</hi> 1. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>id.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>is the beauty of truth.</hi> How beit I do not specify all their infamous blasphemies: but only such as beere
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
and there are licked vp by the Protestants of our time.</p>
   <p>Then I shew how the Pastours of the true Church haue particulerly checked and repressed them: by which, my deare Countreymen may see that the braue shew, or whol band of their new assertions, is nothing els but a fresh muster of old accursed heresies; that the predecessors and forerū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of whome they vaunt, were Rebells to the Church, Enemies to God, and blasphemers of his holy name. Yet because want of others forceth our Ghospellers, to entaile their profession vpon them, I declare briefly how they imbraced some grosse errours, or fundamentall articles of Catholique religion impugned by Protestants, both which cut them off frō their confederacy. Neither is their claime of any force to linke thē with Christ, set case they had not varied in opinions: for the faithfull of his flocke must be a knowne generation of Pastours and People, Parentes and Children, Heades and Members, successiuely propagated, &amp; iointly vnited without interruption one from the other: they must still perseuere constant and impregnable, what opposition soeuer be made against them. But these heretikes started vp at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers times, in diuers countries, heere one, there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, without head, without parentage, without knowledge, dependance, or communication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge themselues, haue often retracted, often changed their hideous fancies, were all conquered, subdued, and put to silence by the Romane Church; and therefore could not be that happy
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
seed which our Lord hath blessed, but base and vnkind slipps, grafted by Sathan; of whome the <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sap</hi> 4. <hi>vers.</hi> 3. 4.</note> Wiseman saith: <hi>Bastard plantes shall not take deepe roote, nor lay sure foundation. And if in the boughes for a tyme they shall spring being weakely set, they shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be moued of the wind; and by the vehemency of the windes, they shalbe rooted out.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>