<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2278_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09499</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19781.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2278</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An Earnest perswasion vnto the pastours of Christes churche, whersoeuer thei be dispersed, but especially vnto his Churche of Englande : that as thei haue thruste the plough share into the grounde, so zelously and watchfully to walke forth right, not leanyng to the left hande, neither tournyng to the right, for who so laieth hold of the plough and looketh backe, is not apte for the kingdome of heauen</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et no man that shall reade, or heare this reade, or any thing within this booke conteined, thinke or imagine the writer hereof is perswaded, or goeth about to perswade, by any woorde, within this booke, that it were meete or conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for any Preacher or Minister, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinct vnto hymself, either cappe or other garmente: but that thei are all bounde by the duetie of their alleagance, to weare and doe, all suche orders as the Prince shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinct them, to imitate and followe: or els with sainct Peter, by the worde of God, to confuce the same, as neither lawfull nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie. And not by their euill example, suffer the truthe to be shadowed and darc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, the forwarde fathers to bee by the Papistes, condempned as rashe and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised doers. But either to proue them so, or els to defende their quarell, and be content to bowe their sholders to the bearyng of the crosse, the whiche who so refuse to doe
<pb facs="3"/>shalbe founde loyterers, and not true la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers. To whom these fewe woordes are dedicated and directed, I truste none other thyng then by the sincere truthe, maie bee sufficiently supported and defended. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you not to esteme this to bee dooen of arrogancie, neither to haue any ill mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, but onely to craue at your handes; some shorte pitthie woorke to satisfie all men. For a great nomber of the laite will in no wise now goe backe to their old lessons, [beyng now further and muche better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed] then to defile theim selues with the giltines of this crime: to the condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of all those reuerende fathers, whiche haue followed the Apostles; in the puritie of perfecte religion, receiued from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue churche. But desire rather to steppe forwarde still, vntill it shall please God to banishe al supersticion clene out of this churche, whiche he sone bring to passe for his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes sake. Amen, AMEN.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>