<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Noble, and vertuous Gentlemen, Sir Iohn Sheaf∣field, Knight; and M. Oliuer S. John: Sonnes and Heires to the Right Honourable Edmond Lord Sheaffield, Lord President of the North, and Oliuer Lord S. Iohn, Baron of Bletsho: grace, and peace.</title>
           <author>Pierson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2273_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09376</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19677.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2273</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Noble, and vertuous Gentlemen, Sir Iohn Sheaf∣field, Knight; and M. Oliuer S. John: Sonnes and Heires to the Right Honourable Edmond Lord Sheaffield, Lord President of the North, and Oliuer Lord S. Iohn, Baron of Bletsho: grace, and peace.</title>
                 <author>Pierson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A clovd of faithfvll witnesses, leading to the heavenly Canaan: or A commentarie vpon the 11. chapter to the Hebrewes, preached in Cambridge by that godly, and iudicious divine, M. William Perkins : Long expected and desired; and therefore published at the request of his executours, by Will. Crashawe, and Tho. Pierson, Preachers of Gods Word: who heard him preach it, and wrote it from his mouth</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Greene, Leonard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Cotton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 592 pages, 4° in 8's</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Noble, and vertuous Gentlemen, Sir <hi>Iohn Sheaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, Knight</hi>; and M. <hi>Oliuer S. John:</hi> Sonnes and Heires to the Right Honourable <hi>Edmond</hi> Lord <hi>Sheaffield,</hi> Lord President of the North, and <hi>Oliuer</hi> Lord <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> Baron of Bletsho: grace, and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He gracious promises of God (Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and most worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) made to the holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, touching the Land of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, were singular comfort to the belieuing Israelites, in their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Egypt. And the renuing of the same by the hand of <hi>Moses</hi> (whose words God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by so many miracles) must needes augment their ioy aboundantly, although their bonds at that time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased. But, the pledge of Gods presence in the cloudie pillar, whereby he led them in the wildernesse both night and day, did so farre exceede all his promises for matter of consolation, that euen <hi>Moses</hi> himselfe desired rather
<pb facs="3"/>
to be detained from the promised Land, than depriued of the comfort of that his presence in the waie:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod. 33.15. 1. Cor. 10.6</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>If thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi> (sayth hee) <hi>goe not before vs, bid vs not depart hence.</hi> Now, these things being <hi>ensamples</hi> vnto vs, and euident types of our estate who liue vnder the Gospel, shew apparantly, that howsoeuer Beleeuers bee greatly cheered in their spirituall trauell, by the gratious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises which God in Christ hath made vnto them; yet, this their ioy is much increased, by the viewe of those that haue gone before them in the waie of faith; who are vnto them as a <hi>Cloude of Witnesses, or a cloudie Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</hi> For, howsoeuer the truth of God be the only ground of sound consolation: yet, because we are a-kin to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> and will not beleeue vnlesse wee see, and feele; therfore it is, that by the example of Beleeuers (wherin is some sensible euidence of the comfort of Gods truth) we are farre more cheered, than by the promise it selfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
   <p>Heere then beholde what great cause wee haue to cast our eyes vpon this <hi>Cloude of Witnesses;</hi> which the ho-Ghost hath erected as a pledge of his presence, &amp; a direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all those that shall followe their steps in the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of faith, til the worlds end. Shall <hi>Moses</hi> affect that Cloude so much, which led them only the waie to a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inheritance: and shall not we much more be rauished with delight in <hi>this Cloude,</hi> which leades vs to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb. 10.38 2. Cor. 5.7</hi>
      </note> In al estates <hi>the Iust must liue by faith:</hi> For, <hi>We walk by faith, and not by sight.</hi> And what is the hope &amp; happinesse of a Christian man, but to receiue at last <hi>the saluation of our soules,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Pet. 1.9</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>which is the end of our faith,</hi> and period of this walke. But any faith will
<pb facs="3"/>
not support vs herein: some begin in the <hi>Spirit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal. 3.3</hi>
      </note> who end in the <hi>Flesh,</hi> going out with <hi>Paul</hi> for a while; but at length returne with <hi>Demas</hi> to the world,<note place="margin">
         <hi>2. Tim. 4.10</hi>
      </note> neither can they doe otherwise: for, <hi>Apostasie is the Catastrophe of Hypocrisie.</hi> He that would deceiue in his profession is vsually deceiued of his saluation.</p>
   <p>Wherfore this shal be our wisedom, to see to our soules that our faith (as the <hi>beloued Apostle</hi> sayde of loue) <hi>be not in word, and tongue; but in deed, and in truth.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Ioh. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </note> And for our better direction in trying the truth of our faith, we haue here many notable precedents in this <hi>Cloud of Witnesses,</hi> consisting of most worthy Beleeuers in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges before <hi>CHRIST'S</hi> incarnation: all which shewed the life of faith by their workes; and we in them may see how to put our faith in practice. Now, the rather must we attende hereunto, because in all estates we must prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice faith. For, <hi>Without faith it is impossible to please God.</hi> And what estate of life cā possible befall vs,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb. 6.</hi>
      </note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue not a liuely patterne and forerunner leading vs the way to Heauen, within the compasse of this Cloud? Art thou a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Magistrate?</hi> beholde <hi>DAVID, HEZECHIAS,</hi> and the <hi>Iudges:</hi> art thou a <hi>Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>? Looke on <hi>MOSES</hi>: art thou a <hi>Martiall-man</hi>? Beholde <hi>SAMSON, DAVID, IOSVAH.</hi> Heere is <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOCH, NOE,</hi> and the Prophets for <hi>Ministers</hi>: the <hi>Patriarches</hi> for Fathers: <hi>SARA</hi> and the <hi>Shunamite</hi> for mothers: <hi>ISAAC</hi> and <hi>IOSEPH</hi> for children: Heer is <hi>ABEL</hi> for Shepheards, and <hi>RAHAB</hi> for victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: Heere are some that liued in honour, in peace, and plenty, some in want, &amp; some in sicknesse: but most of all in persecution; because therein is the greatest <hi>tryall
<pb facs="4"/>
of faith.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Pet. 1.7</hi>
      </note> So that, which way soeuer we turne vs, if wee walke by faith, we haue heere some faithfull witnesse to goe before vs. And to cleare their steps the better to our sight, that so we may <hi>follow hard towards the mark</hi> without wandring,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil. 5.14.</hi>
      </note> we haue heere a notable light in this learned Commentarie; which, we must confesse, is much obscured, for lacke of the refining hand of the godly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himselfe: but now, seeing that shining light is quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, vse this our Lampe; it is fed with such oyle as wee receiued in the Lords Sanctuarie, from that Oliue Tree, whence many a one did fill his vessell. And, being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned to expose the same for the Common good, wee haue presumed to place it vnder the shelter of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable names; beseeching God it may helpe <hi>to guide your feete in the way of peace.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke 1.79.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>The religious precedents of your Honourable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (Right Noble and hopefull Gentlemen) must per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade you much to be sound, and constant in the faith: for, declining in religion brings <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Ier. 22.15 &amp;c. to the end.</hi>
      </note> staine of honour, and decay <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>1. King. 11.11</hi>
      </note> euen of temporall portion. But, labour you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease in grace, and trust the Lord with your outward greatnesse. Honour him, and hee will honour you: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Sam. 2.30. Psal. 37.4.</hi>
      </note> and hee will giue you your holy hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire; his faithfulnesse will bee your shielde, to the griefe of those that enuie your happinesse. But, beware of bad example, and euill counsell, which are the bane and poyson of younger yeares. Walk with God like <hi>Enoch:</hi> vse the world as <hi>Abraham</hi> did,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb. 11.5.</hi>
      </note> and followe <hi>Moses</hi> in the matters of delight,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse 10.</hi>
      </note> forsaking them when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the pleasures of sinne.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Verse 24. &amp;c.</hi>
      </note> So shall you <hi>obtaine
<pb facs="4"/>
good reporte,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb. 12.39</hi>
      </note> and your memories shalbe blessed with your Posterities, like these faithfull Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses. <hi>NOVEMBER. 10. 1607.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the LORD to be commanded, WILLIAM CRASHAVV, THO. PIERSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>