<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROPOSITION
of this first Worke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2289_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10252</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20534</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2289</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROPOSITION
of this first Worke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Divine poems : containing the history of Ionah. Ester. Iob. Sampson. Sions sonets. Elegies. Written and newly augmented, by Fra: Quarles</title>
                 <author>Quarles, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marriot, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marriot, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 266, 6, 267-502, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="proposition">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PROPOSITION
of this first Worke.</head>
   <l>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>TIs not the Record of great <hi>Hectors</hi> glory,</l>
   <l>Whose matchlesse <hi>Valour</hi> makes the <hi>World</hi> a Story;</l>
   <l>Nor yet the swelling of that <hi>Romans</hi> name,</l>
   <l>That onely <hi>Came,</hi> and <hi>Look'd,</hi> and <hi>Overcame;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Nor <hi>One,</hi> nor <hi>All,</hi> of those brave <hi>Worthies</hi> nine,</l>
   <l>(Whose Might was great, and Acts almost divine,</l>
   <l>That live'd like <hi>Gods,</hi> but dy'd like <hi>Men,</hi> and gone)</l>
   <l>Shall give my <hi>Pen</hi> a Taske to treat upon:</l>
   <l>I sing the praises of the <hi>KING</hi> of Kings.</l>
   <l>Out of whose mouth a <hi>two-edg'd Smiter</hi> springs,</l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Words</hi> are <hi>Mystery,</hi> whose <hi>Works</hi> are <hi>Wonder,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Eyes</hi> are <hi>Lightning,</hi> and whose <hi>Voice</hi> is <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Who like a <hi>Curtaine</hi> spreads the <hi>Heavens</hi> out,</l>
   <l>Spangled with <hi>Starres,</hi> in Glory round about:</l>
   <l>'Tis <hi>He,</hi> that cleft the furious waves in twaine,</l>
   <l>Making a <hi>High-way passage</hi> through the <hi>Maine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>'Tis <hi>He,</hi> that turn'd the waters into <hi>Blood,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And smote the <hi>Rocky stone,</hi> and caus'd a <hi>Flood;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>'Tis <hi>He,</hi> that's justly armed in his <hi>Ire,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Behinde with <hi>Plagues,</hi> before with <hi>flaming Fire,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>More bright than mid-day <hi>Phoebus,</hi> are his <hi>Eyes,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And whosoever sees his <hi>Visage, dyes.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I sing the Praises of <hi>Great Iudahs Lyon,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The fragrant <hi>Flowre</hi> of <hi>Iesse,</hi> the <hi>Lambe</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Head</hi> is whiter than the driven <hi>Snow,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose <hi>visage</hi> doth like flames of <hi>Fier</hi> glow:</l>
   <l>His <hi>Loynes</hi> begirt with golden <hi>Belt,</hi> his <hi>Eyne</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Like <hi>Titan,</hi> ridinst in his Southerne <hi>Shine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>His <hi>Feet</hi> like burning <hi>Brasse,</hi> and as the noise</l>
   <l>Of surgie <hi>Neptunes</hi> roaring in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Voice,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>This is that <hi>Paschall Lambe</hi> whose dearest <hi>Blood</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Is soveraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>Drinke,</hi> whose <hi>Flesh</hi> is saving <hi>Food:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>His precious <hi>Blood,</hi> the Worthies of the <hi>Earth</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Did drinke, which (though but borne of <hi>mortall</hi> birth)</l>
   <l>Return'd them <hi>Deities:</hi> For who drinkes <hi>This,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Shall be receiv'd into <hi>Eternall Blisse;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Himselfe's the <hi>Gift,</hi> which <hi>He</hi> himselfe did give,</l>
   <l>His <hi>Stripes</hi> heale us, and by <hi>His Death</hi> we live;</l>
   <l>
      <hi>He</hi> acting <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> in double Nature,</l>
   <l>Did reconcile <hi>Mankinde,</hi> and <hi>Mans Creator.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I, heere's a <hi>Taske</hi> indeed; If <hi>Mortalls</hi> could</l>
   <l>Not make a Verse, yet <hi>Rockes</hi> and <hi>Mountaines</hi> would:</l>
   <l>The <hi>Hills</hi> shall dance, the <hi>Sunne</hi> shall stop his Course,</l>
   <l>Hearing the <hi>subiect</hi> of this <hi>high</hi> Discourse:</l>
   <l>The <hi>Horse,</hi> and <hi>Gryphin,</hi> shall together <hi>sleepe,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The <hi>Wolfe</hi> shall fawne upon the silly <hi>Sheepe,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The crafty <hi>Serpent,</hi> and the fearfull <hi>Hart,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Shall joyne in <hi>Consort,</hi> and each beare a part,</l>
   <l>And leape for <hi>Ioy;</hi> when my <hi>Vrania</hi> sings,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>She</hi> sings the praises of the <hi>King of Kings.</hi>
   </l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>