<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE COVRTEOVSE READER.</title>
           <author>Weston, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2385_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14981</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25290.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2385</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE COVRTEOVSE READER.</title>
                 <author>Weston, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triall of Christian truht [sic] by the rules of the vertues, namelie these principall, faith, hope, charitie and religion, seruing for the discouerie of heresie, and antichrist, in his forerunners and misteries of iniquitie. The second parte, entreating of hope : wherein is made manifest, that the pretended hope of the Protestant, empeaching the merits of Christ, his holy grace, and man his vertuouse life, destroyeth all true confidence in allmightie God, either exceding in presumption, or wanting in desperation / by Edward Weston</title>
                 <author>Weston, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Marguerite</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--East Ham</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 260 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE COVRTEOVSE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is nothing so sacred, which is not in some sorte infested by impietie, or so pure and vndefiled, that man his malice endeuoreth not vpon occasion to pollute &amp; corrupte. But for that suche practises are in their oune proper shapes and natures passing vglie and detestable, therupon wilie witt in them playeth conning pranckes, and laboreth earnestlie to make that seeme holie, which is plotted against all sanctitie, that to appeare shining bright, which is ordained to oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se and extinguish the verie beames of the sunne with an infernall vampe of error and foule transgression. Which manner of craftie maliciouse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendemēt is in no one kinde, as more ruefull to feele, so nether more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable to beholde, then in the progresse of heresie &amp; heretickes againest faith and children of the Ghospell: whose endeuors either are so couert lie couched in the treanche of deepe dissimulation, or so gorgiouslie sett oute vpon the stage in the fained coulors of hipocrisie, that none shall be able to discrie the treacherouse conceilement of the one, and the false varnished splendour of the other, vnlesse his watchefull Prudence be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lased beloe with humilitie, and his humble obedience be reared vp oboue to the height and light of discreete vigilancie.</p>
   <p>When Abrahams seruantes had by digging founde oute sundrie foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n. 26.</note> for the commoditie of cleare water in the soile of <hi>Palestina,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitans of the Countrie enuying his successe as it seemed, with violence dammed them vp by quantitie of earth cast into their discouered Sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: the which notwithstanding after by the industrie of his sonne Isaac were cleansed, and in them the liquor was brought againe to wholesome vse, and natiue perfection. Wherupon did then arise a new manner of opposition betwixt the homebred shepheardes of <hi>Gerara,</hi> and those of his owne retineue: whenas his prophane enimies did not now as before in Abrahams dayse, by strength of arme glutt and stopp them vp, but maintained claime vnder a false title vnto them: &amp; so by sclaunder and emnitie sought to impatronise themselues with proprietie of such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouse
<pb facs="3"/> treasures, which before God his people helde in lawfull possessiō.<note place="margin">Orig▪ Homil 13. in c. 26. Ge.</note> In like sorte what aunci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>taines of deuine doctrine we haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed vs from the labors of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>arckes, and Prophets; or of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inuention discouered vnto vs by our Sauiour Christ, and his Apostles, some bende their force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> with the Iewe and Gentill by earthlie and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall interpretations, or els by might of perseq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ution, vtt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>lie to abolish, and so to drie vp the water of them euen to the darkenes of obliuion. Others not professing their totall extermination, to wit h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> kes, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence suict. againest their trewe owners by clamorouse comba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ments, ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>full inst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntes of furie, to entitle themselues Lordes ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, to which equitie affordeth not them an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e allowable interest, or i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>le pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. Notwithstanding in ishue of effecte, heretickes as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inest vs Catholickes to be commaunders of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, so not contente with the lordeshipp of them, moreouer seeke by their vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tion to defile them: with the Pagan and Iewe accorde in this fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, that they, as monumentes and headspringes of faith, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vp with clods and rubbish of infidelitie and idolatrie.</p>
   <p>It h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>he beene auerred in the precedent Treatise, that our assured as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent<note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ust in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ill and vnderstanding s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rendred to saith, as vpon rocke and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher doeth depende vpon some outeward auctoritie, through poyes of remar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>keable grauitie pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>t with such, who prudentlie are to iudge what is to be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>leued, &amp; what to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>schewed fals<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly recommended vnto<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> them as matter of that heauenlie qualitie. In regard wherof the Apostle S. Paule pronounced, faith to be engendered by hearing, and hearing employed aboute the same, to be directed to the worde of God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that faith may be attained by hearing, not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lie is to be attended a soun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing Voice of the Preacher, but all so the propertie of him as cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chist is to be considered: in that from him onelie are wee dutifullie to heare in this important affaire, who according to a iudiciouse calculatiō is founde to be a deuine messenger of the holie Ghoste: for otherwise emong manie Doctors and maisters in contrariety, our attentiue hearing should be vncertaine, distractiue, and so liable to the decciptes of forging dissemblers and false Relligionars. Wherefore when we haue by a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent examine once founde oute the waight and moment of aucthoritie, then in vertue of the same may wee maturelie esteeme the Preachers wordes as the verie wordes of allmightie God, deliuered vnto vs from the mouthe of man, as from his oracle of approued seruice and designed ministerie. For by the worde of God the Apostle in that place did not meane the whritten worde, but rather the worde of the churche in her preaching tradition: in that the worde of the Ghospell was not then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistred
<pb facs="3"/> by letters when he vttered that doctrine: and allso for that, many<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en lib. 1. c. 5.</note> barbarouse Nations conuerted to the faith of Christ, not knouing any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde of scripture, neuerthelesse in their first conuersions, and originall matriculations in the societie of God his people, as they conceiued faith b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hearing, so allso d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ubtlesse did they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen heare the worde of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing. Therefore the most assured, breife and substantiall method how to stick to tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uth when the ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, instrument of faith and discipline, is as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailed by fals<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ie, is exactlie to discusse, which contradictorie partie is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched by gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter and better aucthoritie, as through more ample num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of beleuers, elder professiō, orderlie mission, more eminent sanctitie, more famouse explo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tes in the processe of veritie and vertue: then heru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon respectiuely it will be approuable by reason, relying on the one, to censure as lighte, weake, not worthie our admirtance suche pretended auctoritie, which in balāce of triall shall appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> deuoide of all those pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues of deuine grauitie and maiestie. According to which manner of proceding S. Augustin by waye of ponderou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e aucthoritie doeth not onely excellently well prescribe in generall against all heresie banded in armes to infest the Catholick faith, but moreouer still disputing in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular against the <hi>Manichies,</hi> the <hi>Donatistes,</hi> the Pelagians, applieth this capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Prescription from outward aucthoritie to the present controuerlie: and therby not onelie Theologicallie, but allso prudently, as eache intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent persone may in like Case, concludeth for the Catholick faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainest their heresies. And vpon this grounde, comperatiuely valeuing the presumptuouse aucthoritie of Protestants with that of Catholickes, it hath beene by me demonstrated, that naturall prudence doth geue sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for vs againest them: and most euidently haue we made it good, that Protestantes for w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nte of this outeward competent aucthoritie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently haue no meanes to setle and ancher themselues in substance, in constancie, in vnitie of beleefe, to conuerte Pagans, to reclaime heretic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or to condemne their errors as iustely reproueable.</p>
   <p>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> what semeth in this poincte to me most considerable, is this: that<note place="margin">Cir. in exposit Symb. Nicen.</note> wereas the Protestante clearelie perceiueth, that outewarde aucthoritie of grace and worthe stanneth not for him, but rather for vs, and in fronte of hostilitie against his faction, therupon turneth he his batterie to demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish and beate doune this grande outeward aucthoritie diuersely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching the same: &amp; so in effecte manifesteth himselfe an auoued soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of Antichrist. For yf once his impiouse and rebelliouse pride should preuaile against auctoritie in the affaire of faith: yf he shall dismantle faith of the safegard &amp; state of aucthoritie, forthwith must faith perish, as a tree despoiled of the barcke, as a plante depriued of heauens influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<pb facs="4"/> as the conducte wanting the pipe: then must there be no pregnant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes lefte to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>concile the infidell or misbeleuer, no supporte rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante to a certaine wauering Christians, no preseruatiue extant againest the infection of heresies and seduction: and then herupon must all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian pietie and beleefe, as the Protestant formindeth, breath oute their vitall spiritt into atheisme &amp; paganrie. In this respect deseruedly Aetius, as whriteth Socrates, was suruamed the Atheist, for that disdainefully he misprised the aucthoritie of commentaries endighted by the learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, relying whollie in resolution vpon his owne priuate expositions<note place="margin">Socrat l 2. Hist. c. 28.</note> deuising this or that pretenddely, as sense deducted frō the sacred Texte. Allso for this selfe same consideration S. <hi>Athanasius</hi> calleth <hi>Arius</hi> an<note place="margin">Athanasius. orat 2. cont. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ian.</note> Atheist, all thoughe in counterfeict resemblance he vrged scriptures to fortifie his heresie, in the meane season contemning aucthoritie, and boasting of himselfe as peculiarly illuminated by allmightie God. And as concerning the Protestant, yf we once thincke with him, that the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, from which in perplexitie we are to receiue assurance, in strife to gaigne repose, to be inuisible, shrouded and buried in the bouells of darc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes, what purpose is it for vs in searche to make repaire to her mansion place or tribunall of iudgement? Yf we conceipte, as Protestants doe, that the teaching aucthoritie of the churche may erre, and hath often times made lapse into falsitie, whie shoulde we now for the present creditt her definitions, peremptorely auouching, these whriringes to be the very worde of God Ghostly from him inspired: allmightie God to be one in substance, and triple in personalitie: the second persone in the B. Trinitie to be incarnated for the worldes redemptiō, seing that in these, as well as in others matters by her indifferently recommended vnto vs, she may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from veritie, and all conformite with the prime &amp; eternall truthe? Whereupon abandoning churchlie aucthoritie, we must remaine lefte to our owne tiring deuises, and so flitt and wander, as shall please poore reason frō her weake vigour changeably to geue vs information. Then at the the first brandeling steppe into a labarinth, shall we entertaine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niō with the Arians, that it smallie importeth our saluation of what secte be our faith in sundrie particular poinctes, so after owne deuised fashion we beleue in God &amp; Christe: who as recordeth <hi>Athanasius, thought to be an</hi>
      <note place="margin">Athana. orat. 2 con Arian. Epist ad. stud v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>indifferent thing</hi> the asse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tiō of <hi>Arins, &amp; thereupō equallie stiled them good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, who followed the same.</hi> In like manner shall we consorte with Donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, who as witnesseth S. Augustin accounted it a matter meerely disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the practice of rebaptising. Allso shall we ioyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shue with Pelagians<note place="margin">Aug <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>▪ cont. Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>con. c. 4. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>g c 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> denying the necessitie of grace to good life: <hi>In whiche thing, sayed they,</hi> as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiseth vs the same S. Augustin, <hi>yf we be conninced to haue erred, yet our errour will
<pb facs="4"/> not appeare otherwise a faulte, then against ciuilitie.</hi> After beeing possessed with this caruing conceipte in matter and obiecte of deuine faith, crying oute with the strumpet <hi>Diuidatur,</hi> lert variances in beelefe haue free pasportes<note place="margin">3. Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> to trauaile withoute losse throughe damnation, our priuate deuises in mutiny phantasying this or that, not geuing vs full cōtentment, doubting of all shall we rushe vpon atheisme, and losing sense and spiritt of heauen, finally die in the hidiouse gulfe therof. And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s staked the dismall and blacke period of Protestancie auiling and neglecting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeable<note place="margin">Aug. epi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> aucthoritie of the Catholick churche. <hi>Que est enim peior mors animae, quàm libertas erroris? what death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f the soule worse, then fredome to erre?</hi> For as hathe bene declared againest the Protestante, his misprisall of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tewarde aucthoritie concerning i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>efragable iudicature in questions controuersed, importing assured deliuerie of the cathechisme to all desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse of instruction, openeth the gappe to distrus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, to dissentions, to all heresies, and at lenght to rennegacie of faith and infidelitie purposed by Antichrist, and his vnuersall bande of enroled complices. Then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader, I doubte not, but that thou haste vnderstoode by the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denr parte, firste, that by vertue of naturall prudence, yf for thy direction in the affaire of faith thou resoluest to folloue any teaching auctoritie, thow atte absolutely to followe that, which stanneth for the Catholik Romane beleefe: that of the protestant, in veue and verdicte therof, not beeing equall, or in any sorte comparable. Secondly haste thow learned, how that the Protestā<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> by diuerse his positions, purposely applied to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace all outewarde aucthoritie of the churche, as denouncing, or rather renouncing it as inuisible, as pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>able to error, as subiect to the examine &amp; censure of euerie priuate spirit, as for many hundreds of yeares in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Antichrist to haue displaied his banner of crueltie, of falsitie, of impietie: in defiance of Christe and Christian veritie to haue ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted sundrie Canons and decrees, laboreth hereby to destroy the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie instrument of the Holie Ghoste for the persuading of faith, and nurrishing the same; &amp; so maketh entrance for rude, blouddie, cruell, sauage atheisme, with barbarouse neglecte of all diuinitie.</p>
   <p>Moreouer for that the totall office of a Christian is not abridged in the<note place="margin">Lactant lib. 1. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o. Homil. quod Nemo laedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> sole worke of faith, but allso is enlarged to a vertuouse life: and in this respected most eminently, for that our sauiour Christ, guider therunto, in regarde of the deitie of his persone, puritie of his doctrine, and price of his deserte, is most highe, souerane, and efficaciouse, therfore suruay is now to be made, to what p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tche of excellencie in this kinde is leuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Catholik beleefe; then vpon what border burteth the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>siguised credulitie of the protestant. In discussion of which matters are to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb facs="5"/> the ensuing controuersies apertaining to Hope, Charitie, &amp; Rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
   <p>There is no heresie, the which doeth not, as affirmeth of Arianisme <hi>S.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Athan. ora▪ 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. c 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pist 166. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> in Iob <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n. ca <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> C. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Ep Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> Ho. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>aur▪ Greg N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ss <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. l de Chara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cter Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Christian.</note>
      <hi>Athanasius</hi> playe the parte of the subtle serpent, inuesting it selfe in the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> holy Scriptures, therby in secrecie to make entrie into the paradice of Christ his Catholick churche, and in that place in agencie for Antichrist to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ade Christ, intending to diminish his excellencie, ether in his person, in his meritt, or in his graciouse beneuolence imparted to man kinde. And for that this highe degre of imparted goodnes is espe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tially aimed at by our sauiour Christ, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ruicte and ende of all, to witt that his faithfull children be in worcke and action of life excellently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, ritchely abundant, and so, as in a prime sorte conformable to right reason, so allso moste agreable to allmightie God, aucthor and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the same: herupō Heretickes vnder a pretended title of holy writt, and of magnifying Christ, haue s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ily endeuoured to empare in man this perfection of vertue throughe Christ, yea contrariewise, to entice him to impure and dissolute liberty by a priuilege of a fained Ghospell: at laste to force him to the thralldome of Antichristiā seruility through sinne and wickednes. Wherefore the Fathers wrighting againest Pagans, emong<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> cent. Iul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>an. Aug Epist. 3. 5.</note> other argumentes to proue vnto them our Christian beleefe to bee pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently credible, &amp; to be entertained iudiciously by all, haue vrged this as most pregnant and forcible, that our holy faith aboue whatsomeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther institutions of humane Philosophy, or coulorable inuentions of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inted Poetrie, is most persuasiue and vigorouse for vertue: namely to to combine man with God in pietie, man with man in charitie, and in all integritie of conuersation. <hi>Marcke I pray the,</hi> writeth S. Augustin to his<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 202. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. quest. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. &amp; N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. Test. c. 7.</note> Freinde <hi>Nectarius, with what prayses in the Catholick Churche are recommended frugalitie, continencie, and in regarde of wedlock fidelitie, and to conclude, all other honest and good manners. In which when anie Cittie dothe excell, it may be truly sayed, that it florisheth.</hi> And when as some made argument against the Catholick faith, as preiudiciall to the estates of Princes, and common wealthes, the same Doctor thus discouereth their humor, and preposte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse intended pollicie: <hi>Therfore they thinck, or seeme so to doe, that the Christiā doctrine is contrarie to the common vtilitie, because they will not, that the common</hi>
      <note place="margin">Augu. Epist. 3.</note>
      <hi>waalth doe stande by the power of vertue, but rather by the impuritie of vice. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t then suche as auouche the Christian doctrine to be repugnant to the commonwealth, geue me such an armie of men, accordinglie as the Christian doctrine enformeth soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, let them geue me such gouerners, suche husbandes, suche wiues, suche parentes, suche children, suche Lordes, suche seruantes, such kinges, suche Iudges: to conclude suche payers of debtes, and exacters of princes rentes, as are appoincted by the Christian
<pb facs="5"/> doctrine, and then lett them dare affirme the same to be hurtefull to commonweal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, or doubte to confesse, the same, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> followed, to be most commod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>se vnto commonwealthes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And allthough vertue, in regard that it is a qualitie agreable vnto a reasonable soule, is in a degree most eminently pleasant therunto, and as it were the liquor of hunnie flowing aboute the sense of tast, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twithstanding for that the intellectuall inuention of that medioc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, which is the marke aimed at by mans will, in the obiecte therof, is not all Waise easiely discried by euerie minde, and much more harde is it, to holde on that action bente by resolution towardes the same, when sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall perturbations are a floote, and stande furiously in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes for the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite vice, therfore it semeth, that it is accompanied with contrarieties, as being light and darcke to the intelligence, deliciouse and harshe, facill and troublesome vnto the affection. <hi>Euerie man</hi> as speaketh the Prince<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>st <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a Moral. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> of the Philosophers, <hi>can drawe forthe a circle, but to po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ncte oute the center therof, is a thinge very difficulte. Wherfore allthough it be an easie matter to discerne in iudgement what is the mediocritie of euerie perturbation, yet to keepe in action this mediocritie, wherby we are made praysworthy, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> a busin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sse passing d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ll. And therfore it is a reare thing to be an honest man.</hi> It falleth ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e often times, that the amiable hewe of vertue is shadowed with suche outeward represen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations, as doe not onlie hide the trew luster therof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>om the vulgar eye, but allso vnto the same make it contemptible and dispriseable. <hi>What sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>more loathsome,</hi> sayeth S. Augustin, <hi>then martirdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f a man aske the question of his carnall eyse? yet what thing more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aire, yf he enquire of the eyse of the haerte?</hi> Whoe can easelie perceiue the splendor of patience shining in holy Iob sitting vpon the dunghill, the carbuncle of zeale in Daniell bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the lions denne, in S. Peter, and S. Paule emprisoned, tyed in chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, banished, in wante and indigence, dying violent deathes▪ or whoe can with Abraham in expedition of a decreed purpose holde vp an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me made cruell with a sworde, to kill his best &amp; onely deare Isaac emong all his wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dlie delightes and contentements! wherfore in that Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie and Heathenish Poeterie were insufficient to geue vs this direction<note place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>l lib. 10. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esaur. ca 3.</note> of minde to finde oute vertue, to entertai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e this courage of wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue the same, the sonne of God became man, intelligible by his doctrine, and imitable by his ensample, to the ende we might know vertue, and consequentlie be enamoured with the beautie therof. <hi>The Pagans</hi> as wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth<note place="margin">Ioseph. in Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>at. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Iosephus, <hi>imputed to their Gods shamefull factes, and hereupon encreased the malice of euill disposed persons for the accomplishment of all wickednes.</hi> And as vpō reuew of histories wee may easely proue, that the ciuil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st and sue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>est sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of people, liuing euer vpon the earth, to haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Christians, so may
<pb facs="6"/> we know, that oure profession beefore all other hath ariued therunto, in reconing that it hath beene addicted to vertue in all excellencie, which intelligenceth the minde, and ridding the will of all harshenes, sweteneth it in amitie, pietie, charitie; and so draweth the whole man from the leese of sensualitie, That, as speaketh S. Augustin, <hi>As the beautie of the bodie</hi>
      <note place="margin">Augu T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. 32. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 7. c. Iohan. 2. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t. 1.</note>
      <hi>is the soule, so the beautie of the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ule be allmightie God.</hi> Happie and desired lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer, expected by the sacred Apostle S. Peter, to arise in the haertes of all trew beleeuers! No glittering masse of goulde or siluer, no riche Iuell<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of pearl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s and precio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se stones yea as speaketh Aristotle, no princelie empire, by which mortall men doe much r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>semble allmightie God, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth<note place="margin">Arist. l. 1. Mag Mor. c. 4. &amp; 6.</note> man to that top a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d tipe of dignitie, to that degre of honor and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill respecte, to which vertue causeth him to mounte and aspire. Vpon which consideration, Courteouse Reade, in regard of Ciuilitie, thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e diligentli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to marke and ponder, which faith stanneth more effectuallie for documentes to enforme the vnderstanding, for restraincte, and inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements allso of the will, to inure the same in all vertuouse actions: for hereupon dependeth thy coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ctiue conclusion, to censure which faith and relligion are truly ciuill and politicke, and which balefull thereunto. And withoute all doubte, the ende and drifte of nature drauing men to vnitie and combination of Cittie, and common wealth, was not only by reciprocall commerce to enriche the inhabitants, to make them abounde in pleasure, but espetially that they should be hereby vertuouse, &amp; that in a better manner, then they coulde be liuing sauadgely in distraction and vagrancie: for otherwise vertue set a side, greater calamitie, and sharp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> miserie, will accompanie Citizens, Rulers, and subiectes, then yf they liued in sequestration vpon mountaines, in wodes or dennes: for that the malice and luste of man are then moste potent, when they be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with dissimulation, with crafte, where the partie assailing may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue what he liste: which trickes of vnnaturall pollicie haue commonly for schoole the cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e where vertue is wanting, for feelde and theater the common wealthe, for vpsho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> barbaritie, and hatefull disunion. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore yf in this affaire, not relying on reasons discourse, we will sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholde the pole st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r of heauen the prouidence of allmightie God, we shall euen by experience know, that only vertue is ciuill and politick; in that vertue only is mother of loue, of honor of prosperitie, with oute which no tricking descant, or odiouse coosenage of a barbarouse politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, can make any common wealth truly ciuill, or for wisdome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. What braue and greate exploites, I pray you, are brought to passe by this new glosse, by this forged coyne, by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ascar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e altering nature in false viso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, by these clokes, which strike no thing but that
<pb facs="6"/> which is not? where are at home their aboundance, their contented and vnited mindes, their trustefull repo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s in each others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>iance? where are abrode their trophies of armes, and letters, of redoubted puisance &amp; renoume, of faithfull leauge and amitie? where is their same, which maugre death, and the whole heape of its funeralls, glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th the name against lenghte of time, or enuie of the wicked? what is then the summe? A litel time to be dissolute, by litel and litel in time to dissolue all: and after time to be eternally and miserably tormented. Heare the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Iosephus, a sage Historiographer emong tha leues. <hi>We may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioseph. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>at An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iq.</note>
      <hi>tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> such commun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ties as are obedient to the will of allmightie God, and are afraied to violate lawes well decreed, to be prosperouse in all suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esse aboue humane c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ipte: to whom allmightie God for reward proposeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>elicitie. But contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise yf the departe from the obseruance of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m, their deuis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s finally come to no good ende: moreouer their endeuors, which vnto them seeme good, expire in most remedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lesse calamities.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherupon in dewe consequence doeth it follow, that as the Christian<note place="margin">Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ de Repub A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. ca. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> de leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ophon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>o Arist. in Magnis Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> beleefe is wonderfully auayleable vnto vertue, as to iustice, to charitie, relligion, continencie, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ude, and temperance, so is it most effectually profitable to ciuilitie, and humane commercement in societie. No fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouse Philosopher endoued o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ely with the light of reason, as commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to posteritie, hathe hetherto written of ciuill institution, who hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> laied dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n as grounde of such discipline vertue, and that good abea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance betwixt man and man, which is conform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ble to right reason, and by meanes therof auaileable to the communitie: allso supposing fell bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baritie, opposite to ciuilitie, to be no thing els but a frouard distraction of man from man through vice and wickednes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ewarely brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into furie, or closely conceiled vnder the resemblance of probiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, infestingst artifically all honest decencie of life and comportement: for as well (to geue an example) stanneth in oppositiō against iustice the ingene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Burglar, attempting his enterprice in the dearckenes of the night,<note place="margin">Dissimilite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> nocent sed non dissimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>piunt Aug P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aef. in Psal. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> as the open theefe attending his booty on the highe way side. Most apparant is it then, the new founde kinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of pollicie, attributed by some to theese our dayese, as to a sager age, vaunted and vented forth frō the pen of Nicholas <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>uill,</hi> to be naught els but an artificall intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of barbarisme, the nourcery in deede of all vice, the torment of of mens soules and bodies, the impeachement of the communitie, bicau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se it beareth strong heade against vertue, the pillar and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>combe of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill life &amp; conuersation. Yf the Rulers securitie must be founded vpon the deboshementes of the bodies and soules of his subiectes, as vpō their lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xurie, their incontinencie, their roietousnes, their prodigalitie: Yf his
<pb facs="7"/> assured staye must arise from their disagremente, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uspitions, tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acherise, riualitise, hostilitise, in recknoning of diuersitie in relligions or otherwise emong them: yf his wealth is to be purchased from their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuries, their bondage, frō their base couardely &amp; ignorant dispositions: as that Florentine Scribe aduer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>seth Princes, iust according to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>enor of Barbarisme, excellentlie described and politickly reiected by Aristotle,<note place="margin">Ari l 5. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>it. cap 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> then suppose wee, that freinde and freinde, mayster and seruant, lauwer and client, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sition and patient, souldior and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ustick, marchant and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, husband and wise, be thus likewise aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cted correspondently to the <hi>Idaea</hi> of a Prince towardes his subiectes, and theese towards him, (as one will certainly ensue of the other) and then tell me in this mutiny of vice, in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nisprision of vertue, in this anxietie of feare and dreade, in this egar pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>uicte ofter priuate luste o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lukar, what ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>litie will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in a common wealth, what bonde in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olablye combining citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens▪ or rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> be confessed, that sauagenes will make her trophey, as vpō the spo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les of vertue, so vpon the ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rthroe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rew sounde and solid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. In which respecte, cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eouse Reader, thou shalt vnderstāde, of what importe is it, to entertaine &amp; embrace the Catholick Romane faith, euen ciuill state of humane societie meerly considered, it recommeding vnto the so eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ctually vertue, the sole instrument of good pollicie, and repressing so pouerably iniquity, the proper engine of cruell and disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>Withoute all doubte yf we shall in seuerall by ioincte and member ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>se he belefe of Protestants, we shall beholde it according to the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> therof, to haue progenie, as mightely biased with carnalitie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, from these three Heades: to witt for the vnderstanding, that it be freed from commaunding aucthoritie of menn: that the will be licenced in liberty from conscionable subiection to Princes: and that sensuall concupiscence beare sway as not controble by remorse of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, or opinion of spirituall hurte from any sinfull transgression: all which are so many elementes and letters, which spell barbaritie. Of the former hath beene made a su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>icient remonstrance in the precedent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: the other to we are easely strained frō the pregnancie of their doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. In generall it is the humor of an Heretick, to be barbarouse in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouse and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bidinouse outerage, resembled by those horses in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calips, whose hurtfull mighte was <hi>In their mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>thes, and in their tailes:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupō very elegantly thus S. Gregorie: <hi>Theese horses, that is naughty Preachers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc 9. Greg l 33 in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ob. cap 29.</note>
      <hi>running euerie where by the instincte of carnalitie, haue power in ther mouthes, and in their tailes: for that preaching peruerse thinges, and beeing borne oute by the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall magistrate, they exalte them selues by ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>kward and wordly meanes.</hi> Were
<pb facs="7"/> not Luther and Calmn in this respecte barbed horses of Antichrist, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce barbarisme, whose rebelliouse mouthes breathed out a relligion contrarie to the whol churche then beeing regnante? whas not their tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les allso pouerable, when promising men securitie in all lustefull liberty, drew many to the carion of their dunghill? wicklefth, that disgraciouse monster of ōur nation, did he not poyson the aire, bane the bodies and soules of millions with incitementes to turpitude of life, auouching that God is aucthor and ordainer of sinne? and yet to Caluin, and Luther, to<note place="margin">Luther lib de l. arb. Calum. l. 1. Inst cap. 3.</note> all Protestantes he seemeth in this an Euangelister! Doe not theese infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall harpies teache no sinne in vilany, in barbaritie, to endamage an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending Protestanter, no good worcke of vertue to be puetly good, or good in puritie, no obseruance of the lawe to be possible or nedefull? and whie? but that men loyter, flying from labor in vertuouse endeuors, and lull themselues a sleepe in securitie, where all sinnes abounde, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the wormes of wicked factes breake oute of the liuing bowelles of pampered panches? where is emong them the christall fountaine of profounde speculation? where is any curbing restrainte to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the will from sensuall disportes? wher is any forcible inuitement to liue a vertu onse life, which be the three principall instrumentes of ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie? Suerly that eye, which can not clearly take a veue of theese wantes emong Protestants, liueth in Egypte, and knoweth no darckenes: he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Chelidonian stoone to restore dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ied nature, beeing far from any accidentall endoument, or excellency in this respecte: he that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth not theese de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ectes to be occasioned througe the very genius and drifte of Protestancie, well may he be proude, but not for excesse in science, but rather for extremity of follie and ignorance.</p>
   <p>Wee are then for the present, to proue to we thinges against the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant: first that the whole purpose of his doctrine tendeth to the disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Christ his metitt, empareth such meanes of his bountie, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the beene by the same purchased for vs to attaine vnto perfection of life, and diuine beatitude: as it were damming vp the flude of God his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies through our Sauiour Christ, by which is conuayed to the paradice of his churche the liquor of heauenly dewe, the force of Christian grace, to fertilise our soules, to clense vs from impuritie, to carie vs along in good action contrarie to the maine current and streame of our decaied and depraued natures: so that his steps forewarde of his pretended hope appeare nothing els, but so many proude presumptuouse passages ish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from his folly, and determining in his oune ruin, his moste misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lamentable destruction. Secondly shall wee make a most cleare remonstrance, that his doctrine in the affaire of Christian hope doth so▪
<pb facs="8"/> blemish and defile with the excrements of hell, disgorged from the mouthes of olde infamouse heretickes, of Antichrist that man of sinne, the beautie of vertue, that men crediting him, shall haue no iust cause to be inamoured therwith, to make any espetiall regard therof, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> trouble them selues much as atcheue the same: and that contrariewise endeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by sundrie Positions to maske and excuse the deformitie of vice, to lessen the greuouse and hatefull harme encurred therby, doth conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently encourage mortall menn to accomplish their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll course in all iniquitie, and barbaritie, the doughter of loose disportefull carriage. Lett them glose or the will, guilde as the like, the ordu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of defiled conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whilest they seeme to repose on Christ alone for recouery and recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: lett them flatter them selues in the meane season with the inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of a deuised libertie, of a refined Ghospell, and of a spatiouse place to daunce the currant of their recom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ts: lett them glorie, that in their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den they gather nothing but roses withoute thornes, the course there aboute the allies and mazes withoute restraincte: the rest and sleepe on the verdure of their late inuented pleasant Phancies: yett this is, and shall bee the vpshott, and I hope Epitaphte read by the world of their doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and endeuors, <hi>That men cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mne vertue, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eade no vice.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Contrariewise as our Catholick hope is passing stronge, so is it allso excedinglie pure and vertuouse: the former is caused by this, that we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe throughe deuine grace, the which is most potent and firme: the other procedeth from sych meanes as Christian hope vseth to attaine her ende and purpose. <hi>Let man his hope</hi> sayeth S. Augustin, <hi>so be setled on God, that he</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug Ena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ a in Psalm. 90.</note>
      <hi>nether be allured from him by pleasure, nor broken throughe feare.</hi> There be towe principall affections, against which vertue is to striue: that is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and vaine loue, and allso drouping dreade. By loue we trespasse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vertue, preferring before it the opposite and forbidden delight: by feare of losse we leaue our station, &amp; performe not that, which is apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted<note place="margin">Arist. in mag. Mor. ca 8. Apoc. 16.</note> by vertue. Wherupon thus concludeth Aristotle: <hi>wherfore vertue is employed aboute pleasures, and dolors.</hi> Therefore that is a preposterouse ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, yea an inhumane and deformed expectation, which loketh for beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude without all dependance of vertue and trew ciuilitie: as yf one might through Christ ariue to eternall blisse, and yet permit his loue to yelde to concupiscence, suffer his feare to worcke the omission of that good offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, which is prescribed by vertue: and in deede suche a hope as this is, founde in the Protestant, is no thing els, butt the witch Circes her cupp to transforme mē into beastes, and in deede that goble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, which the Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian strumpet, daughter to Antichrist, and mothermistresse of all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes, tendreth to all, whose liquor droncke by thē turneth their estates to that
<pb facs="8"/> condicion, which is proper to the bratts and slaues of the beast, that man of sinne Antichrist. Our Christian hope then ought to be puisant and resolute; yet pure and honest; and in that respecte more pure and honest, because it is not Philosophicall, but Christian, not humane, but deuine. Consider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, I beseeche the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntle Reader, first, what reliance hath the Catholick hope on vertue, whose ancher taketh holde on the goodnes of allmighty God, and allso vpon the goodnes of life &amp; action, allthough in a diuerse qualitie: not presuming with an vncleane repose, as sinfull touche, to lay holde on puritie it selfe. On the other side seriouslie way with thy selfe, how a Protestant by eficacie of his pretended hope is not onely defiled, but likewise emboldened by sacrilegiouse conceipt, as yf from heauen he were assured that his hope diuorced from vertue were sufficiently auaileable to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cheue his finall ende of happines. wherupon must thou nedest conclude, that faithe to be accepted of the, which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth a vertuouse Hope: and such auouched faith to be reiected, which boldly lanceth in to the debth of all iniquitie: which acertaineth men of their saluation, when suarming with vices they looke in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptiō for that croune, which is ende &amp; period of all mans endeauors.</p>
   <p>In what pittifull plight must then be plunged that common wealth, in which, with <hi>Machiauilian</hi> pollicie concurreth and accordeth Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Theologie? The Machiauilian will aduertise the Prince, that his as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of estate dependeth on the sinnes and basenes of his subiectes, as vpon their disagrementes, vpon their voluptuouse riott and effemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, vpon their si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>plicitie, slauerie and ignorance: then the Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish minister will preach▪ bothe to Prince, and subiecte, that no wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mputed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nto a beleuer, that the law of God and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is impossible, that vertue is nether commendable, nor priseable, that ciuill l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wes oblige not the conscience, that sinnes by abolishment are neuer assoiled, that the Rule of faith is eache mans priuate spiritt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the worde, that allmost no heresie is damnable: That the splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and substance of outeward Relligion is superstition or idolatry: &amp; so when all are possessed with theese principles of courte, and Pulpit, the hearers and crediters as they will be lauish for vice, and disdainefull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards verue and heauen, so finallie their manners, besides offence against God, &amp; trespasse against Nature, besides mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>prisall of the crosse of Christ, will be resolued into barbarisme: for as nothing is truly ciuill but lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and vertue, so nothing balefully barbarouse but ignorance, and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie. Alas, what la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dable maiestry is it in waye of pollicie, to induce the rude popularitie into a relligion, &amp; to confirme them in the same, which is gratefull to sense, proportionable to the inclination of flesh &amp; bloode
<pb facs="9"/> in their distempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atures. The Turchishe discipline of gouernemēt depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth principally vpon these thre apoinct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ments: first that the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bee not troubled with any difficultie in matter of faith: then that sensualitie be gratified by free acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se, with all indemnitie, of carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures: lastely, that presentement of horrible penalties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nforce bodies &amp; soules into slauerie and vtter dastardie: all which serue as instrumentes to retaine in office and dutie that base generation. Contrariewise a thing prayesable is it, and worthy a ciuill gouernour so to dispose the haertes of subiectes, that willingly they submitt their mindes to obiectes of beleefe, which exceede naturall reach, and as it were trauerse the course therof: then to encline their affections to such obseruances, as be austere, irckso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and afflicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to concupiscence: finallie to make vertue so powerable with them, that terror do not so much moue them to good abearance, as a cordiall loue of vertue, and espe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ially, an inflamed charitie towardes God and man. This, This was the course of pollicie, which our auncient and renoumed fore fathers haue held, so gloriouse vnto them, &amp; auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable to vs, enioying now the fruictes of their ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e wisdome &amp; constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
   <p>It shall suffice then, gentle Reader, that I a farr of crie thee aime, and geue thee intelligence by the dutie of a faithfull Sentinell, and a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Patriott, in that prefession most assuredly pleadged, and stronglie obliged euer to remaine thyne for thy chefest good and abletterance in what he may</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>EDWARD WESTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>