<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE UNKNOWN PATRON.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2396_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09098</idno>
           <idno type="STC">194</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2396</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE UNKNOWN PATRON.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The repertorie of records : remaining in the 4. treasuries on the receipt side at Westminster, the two remembrancers of the Exchequer. With a briefe introductive index of the records of the Chancery and Tovver. Whereby to give the better direction to the records abovesaid. As also, a most exact calender of all those records of the Tovver: in which, are contained and comprised whatsoever may give satisfaction to the searcher, for tenure or tytle of any thing</title>
                 <author>Agard, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 141, 144-217, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE UNKNOWN PATRON.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His work I did intend to <hi>Mercury,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Before his wings were sick, and he could fly:</l>
      <l>But now the Gods incensed, all together</l>
      <l>Have layd diseases upon every feather:</l>
      <l>(Alas) he cannot raise himselfe nor carry</l>
      <l>His plumes, as does the rest of all the Ayrie:</l>
      <l>But is retired to some shady Grove,</l>
      <l>To hide him from the great incensed <hi>Iove.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And where to find my Patron to deliver</l>
      <l>This little worke of mine; I know not, neither</l>
      <l>If he were found (and no discretion lost)</l>
      <l>This title might offend him, or me most.</l>
      <l>Now all ye Gods beare witnesse, I intend</l>
      <l>Onely to shew a bounded thankfull mind</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
Unto this <hi>Mercurie,</hi> by whose quicke fire</l>
      <l>My Muse being lately wounded did respire.</l>
      <l>And whether sinne of these two be the lesse?</l>
      <l>A feare in Conscience, or unthankfulnesse,)</l>
      <l>Judge Heavens; And vouchsafe me onely this,</l>
      <l>What's well intended be not tooke amisse.</l>
      <l>And now goe on my Booke, and seeke about,</l>
      <l>Till thou hast found this unknown Patron out:</l>
      <l>And tell him thou cam'st from an unknowne friend,</l>
      <l>Whose Love's a Circle, round, without an end.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>Ante leves ergo, &amp;c.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>