<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S244_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01653</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11791</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S244</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The invasions of Germanie : With all the civill, and bloody warres therein, since the first beginning of them in anno. 1618. and continued to this present yeare 1638. Wherein are described the severall battles, encounters, conflicts, and assaults, of cities, townes, and castles, at severall times, and in severall places, with a new and exact map of Germany, wherein the cities, and townes are figured with the same figures which are expressed over the heads of the particulars in the booke, so that the reader may behold at one view the places, time, yeere, and event of every battle, skirmish, and assault. Together with the progresse of every army, marked with severall markes or lines, with the pictures of the chiefe commanders on both sides. Faithfully collected out of good, and credible originalls. By a Gentleman well deserving that hath suffered much in those warres</title>
                 <author>Gentleman well deserving that hath suffered much in those warres</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136, 12 pages, 1 folded plates, map, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THe Civill Warres of this (sometime) flourishing Country might be rather desired to be buried in silence, then bee recalled and perpetuated to memory, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut that the Lord will have his <hi>great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orkes to be had in remembrance,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>hers might see, and feare him that <hi>doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hat ever he pleaseth in Heaven, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Earth.</hi> How great the misery of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>any</hi> hath beene, no tongue can expresse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> heart can beleeve, except those that have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ene, and felt the bitternesse of it, they have <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>runken the wine of Astonishment,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hough they would not beleeve their misery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> have beene so neere, nor so dreadfull, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or these last twenty yeares have beene mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rably destroyed, that I may say of it, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rophet <hi>Esay</hi> saith of Ierusalem: <hi>Your</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Country is desolate, your Cities burnt with fire, your land strangers devoure in your presence.</hi> Shee is now left so poore, that she can call nothing her owne, she that relieved others is now in need of others reliefe. She that of late was as a Princesse <hi>among the Nations,</hi> with her sumptuous Palaces, is now with the <hi>Daughter of Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a Cottage in a Vine-yard, or as a desert Wildernesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We all this while continue as the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the Lord, fenced about by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and sheltred under his protection, wee onely heare what others feele. God strikes some that others might take warning. <hi>Goe to my place which was in Shiloh, where I set my Name at first, and see what I did to it, saith the Lord. Esay. 7. 12.</hi> We are admired (by all the world) for our peace, it will be our wisdome to labour to be as famous for Piety, peace should bee the Nurse of Piety, if we improve this our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity
<pb facs="3"/>
to Gods Glory, it may be a lengthning of our tranquillity.</p>
   <p>If you shall meete with any harsh phrase, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> unusuall expression in the insuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, you will be easily inclined to a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble construction, when you shall consider that he is a <hi>German</hi> borne. A Gentleman sometimes of good worth in his own Country, able to deliver himselfe elegantly in his owne Language, in Latine, or in those other Languages in which he hath been longer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised, than in our English tongue. You shall find it worthy your reading, wherein you shall suddenly behold the state of the wars, the severall Battles, Encounters, Conflicts, and Assaults of Cities, Townes, and Castles, with a new, and exact Map, with figures both on Map, and Book, referring you to each other, wherin you may perceive the time, the yeere, and day, with the successe, and event of every Battle, Skirmish, and Assault, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of the best <hi>German</hi> Histories. Read, and consider. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>