<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his Ingenuous, and much lou'd Friend,
the Author.</title>
           <author>Chapman, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S250_Fr1_5_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16936</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3830.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S250</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his Ingenuous, and much lou'd Friend,
the Author.</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ghost of Richard the Third : expressing himselfe in these three parts, [brace] 1. His character, 2. His legend, 3. His tragedie : containing more of him then hath been heretofore shewed, either in chronicles, playes, or poems</title>
                 <author>Brooke, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 6, 76 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb n="1" facs="6"/>
   <head>To his Ingenuous, and much lou'd Friend,
the Author.</head>
   <l>YOu now amids our Muses Smithfield are</l>
   <l>To sell your <hi>Pegasus,</hi> where Hackney ware</l>
   <l>(Rid by the swish swash Rippiers of the Time,</l>
   <l>Pamper'd and fronted with a Ribband Ryme)</l>
   <l>Though but some halfe Houre soundly try'd, they tyre,</l>
   <l>Yet sell, as quickned with Eternall Fire.</l>
   <l>All things are made for sale; sell man and all</l>
   <l>For sale, to Hell: There is no Soule, to sale.</l>
   <l>Your flippant sence-delighter, smooth, and fine,</l>
   <l>Fyr'd with his Bush Muse, and his sharpe Hedge Wine,</l>
   <l>Will sell like good old Gascoine. What does then</l>
   <l>Thy Purple in graine, with these Red-Oker men?</l>
   <l>Swarth Chimney sweepe, that to his Horne doth sing,</l>
   <l>More Custome gets; then in the <hi>Thespian</hi> Spring,</l>
   <l>The thrice bath'd Singer to the <hi>Delphia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> Lyre,</l>
   <l>Though all must needs be rid heere; yet t' aspire</l>
   <l>To common sale, with all turne-seruing Iades,</l>
   <l>Fits Pandars, and the strong voic't Fish-wife Trades.</l>
   <l>Affect not that then, and come welcome forth,</l>
   <l>Though to some few, whose welcom's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omthing worth</l>
   <l>Not one, not one (sayes <hi>Perseus</hi>) will reade mine;</l>
   <l>Or two, or none; 'Tis Pageant Orsadine</l>
   <l>That goes for gold in your Barbarian Rate,</l>
   <l>You must be pleas'd then to change gold for that.</l>
   <l>Might I be Patterne to the meauest few</l>
   <l>Euen now when hayres of Women-hated-hew</l>
   <l>Are wither'd on me; I delight to see</l>
   <l>My Lines thus desolately liue like me,</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="2" facs="7"/>Not any thing I doe, but is like Nuts</l>
   <l>At th' ends of Meales left; when each Appetite gluts.</l>
   <l>Some Poet yet can leuell you a Verse</l>
   <l>At the Receipt of Custome; that shall Pierce</l>
   <l>A sale Assister; as if with one Eye</l>
   <l>He went a Burding; strikes Fowles as they fly,</l>
   <l>And has the very Art of Foulerie.</l>
   <l>Which Art you must not enuie; be you pleas'd</l>
   <l>To hit Desert; fly others, as diseas'd,</l>
   <l>Whose being pierst, is but to be infected;</l>
   <l>And as bold Puritans (esteem'd elected)</l>
   <l>Keep from no common Plague, which so encreases;</l>
   <l>So these feed all Poeticall Diseases.</l>
   <l>Best Ayre, lest dwellers hath; yet thinke not I</l>
   <l>Fore-speake the sale of thy sound Poesie;</l>
   <l>But would in one so worth encouragement</l>
   <l>The care of what is counted worst, preuent;</l>
   <l>And with thy cheerefull going forth with this;</l>
   <l>Thy Muse in first Ranke of our Muses is.</l>
   <epigraph>
      <q xml:lang="lat">Non datur ad Musas currere lata via.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <closer>
      <signed>GEOR: CHAPMAN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>