<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The authors preface to his learned ad∣uersaries.</title>
           <author>Brereley, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2531_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16708</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3608</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2531</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The authors preface to his learned ad∣uersaries.</title>
                 <author>Brereley, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sainct Austines religion : Collected from his owne writinges, &amp; from the confessio [n] s of the learned Protestants: whereby is sufficiently proued and made knowen, the like answearable doctrine of the other more auncient fathers of the primitiue church. Written by Iohn Brereley</title>
                 <author>Anderton, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Birchley Hall Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>31, 1, 375, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="18" facs="10"/>
   <head>The authors preface to his learned ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries.</head>
   <p>THough not from any great hope to perswade, where the whol frame of our religion appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth as al declining, or rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate vnder the burden of disgrace, nor as confident in my owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, whereby to oppose my selfe against so great a multitude of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, yet if for no other accasion, but that posterity may know we haue (according to the measure of our knowledge) not beene wanting in our better offices towardes our dearest country, from which not perils, at home, or exile abroad can euer estrange our Christian affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as also to make ful supply in liew of my owne cōfessed vnablnes in that behalfe, I haue (as no lesse then zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the one, and al conscious to my selfe of the other) vndertaken to offer vnto your graue considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, a breefe suruey of the many
<pb n="19" facs="10"/> collected particulars of <hi>S. Austines</hi> professed religion, a father whose ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dying memory is by your<note n="(a)" place="margin">See hereafter, c. 1. h.</note> selues yet hitherto not vnworthily celebrated.</p>
   <p>In which course howsoeuer I haue not made strange to communicate with the commendable labours of our other learned writers, with whom I am ioyned in one commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of faith, I haue yet neuerthelesse performed it with such addition and further alteration of manner &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, as I may perhaps be thought to haue written, though not <hi>noua,</hi> yet <hi>noué,</hi> as hauing accomplished the same (to vse <hi>S. Austines</hi>
      <note n="(b)" place="margin">Tom. 3. de Trinitate. l. r. c. 3. ante med.</note> wordes) <hi>diuerso stilo non diuersa fide:</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the nouelty of this argument in our language, and my particular cyting (not from others collections, but from mine owne eyes perusing the originals at large) of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>tome</hi> of<note n="(c)" place="margin">The edition of S. Austines workes vsually followed in this treatise, is that which is in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio. printed Lugduni. An. 1586.</note>
      <hi>S. Austines</hi> workes, the <hi>booke,</hi> the <hi>chapter,</hi> and <hi>very part</hi> of the chapter (where it is capable of partition) in which <hi>S. Austines</hi>
      <pb n="20" facs="11"/> alledged sayinges are extant, to be found; I haue yet further added a general<note n="(d)" place="margin">See hereafter c. 19.</note> preuention to such other his more obscure sayinges as are by our aduersaries vulgarly obiected; and haue also in more ful and euident explication of his religion yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explained the same frō the like answearable consenting doctrine of the other auncient Fathers that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued next<note n="(e)" place="margin">See hereafter, c. 20. sect. 13.</note>
      <hi>before</hi> his age, in<note n="(f)" place="margin">See hereafter, c. 20.</note>
      <hi>his age,</hi> and<note n="(g)" place="margin">See herafter. c. 2. sec. 13.</note>
      <hi>after</hi> his age, from al whom it is incredible that he should dissent, him selfe saying of the Fathers,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Tom. 7. l. 1. contra Iulian. Pelag. c. 5. prope fin. and see c. 7. ante med. &amp; l. 2. versus finem.</note>
      <hi>what they beleeue I beleeue, what they hold I hold, what they teach I teach what they preach I preach &amp;c.</hi> And lastly I haue made most of al this (concerning both <hi>S. Austine</hi> and the foresaid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fathers) euident, not from my owne priuate inforcing or applying of their produced sayinges, but from the frequent abounding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of our learned and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing aduersaries them selues, of whom I must yet say (as did<note n="(i)" place="margin">Tom. 7. ad Donatistas post. collatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. c. 34. fin.</note>
      <hi>S.
<pb n="21" facs="11"/> Austine</hi> in like case of the <hi>Donatistes) we must rather for this thanke God then them, for that in our behalfe they should publish and lay open al those thinges ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word or reading, it was the truth that enforced them, not charity that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now as concerning your alledged writers whom I thus produce, as confessing for vs and against both you and them selues, they are not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, vulgar, or of meane esteeme, but men eminent and of cheife ranke in your Churches, as namely and cheifly for forraine authors, the <hi>Century writers of Magdeburge, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Suinglius, Caluin, Beza, Bucer, Bullinger, Melancthon, Musculus, Zanchius, Peter Martir &amp;c.</hi> And for domesticke writers, <hi>Iewel, Humfrey, Whitguift, Bilson, Whitaker, Willet, Fulke, Perkins, Brightman, Carth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, &amp;c.</hi> Now of what account haith euer beene the argument thus taken from the learned aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>confessing against them selues,</hi> is in it selfe most cleare, and haith beene
<pb n="22" facs="12"/> by<note n="(k)" place="margin">See Protest. Apol. p. 671. And D. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, ep. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic.</note> others largely confirmed from Protestant writers; wherefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the hereafter ensuing further force thereof, you can haue no other remedy then (as did<note n="(l)" place="margin">Theodoret. hist. Tripart. l. 6. c. 17.</note>
      <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apostata in the like case) to forbid &amp; bar vs Catholickes for the time to come from the reading of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant authors; for me to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the particular sayinges of <hi>S. Austin,</hi> and the other auncient fathers without improbable vrging the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage resulting from the wordes and circumstance of the place, would haue beene, though perhaps not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer difficult, yet to some tedious, &amp; stil subiect to question and reply; whereas to alledge them in the very same confessed sense, wherein they are by your owne learned brethren vnderstoode, and for such therupon by them selues reiected, as making directly against both you and them, is that which as to the point of <hi>S. Austines</hi> now controuerted religion geueth end to al question or further doubt thereof, &amp; enableth me your
<pb n="23" facs="12"/> humble aduersary bouldly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke your grauer iudgements vnto the consideration of this treatise fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
   <p>Now as touching <hi>S. Austines</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges alledged in this ensuing trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise most of them are vndoubted, knowen, and confessed, as being specially named &amp; cyted by <hi>S. Austin</hi> him selfe in his cōfessed bookes of <hi>Retractations:</hi> And as for those other few alledged bookes, that are by some affirmed not to be <hi>S. Austines,</hi> as namely the bookes entituled, <hi>Hipognosticon, de Ecclesiasticis dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, de visitatione infirmorum, Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiones veteris et noui Testamenti, de verbis Apostoli, de vera et falsa paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensia &amp;c.</hi> Besides that these are by<note n="(m)" place="margin">In iustitut. printed, 1602. in the Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berical table vnder the word Augustinus, most of these bookes are ran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked and alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as in the Catalogue of S. Austines owne bookes.</note>
      <hi>Caluin,</hi> and the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Cent. 5. c. 10. col. 1127. 1128. 1129.</note>
      <hi>Centuristes,</hi> acknowledged to be <hi>S. Austines</hi> proper workes, and are the vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted writinges, if not of <hi>S. Austine,</hi> at the least yet of some other aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers that liued in, or neare his time, they be also in this treatise purposly forbonre as being but very
<pb n="24" facs="13"/> seldome or sparingly alledged or if at al alledged, yet commonly not without some other saying annexed thereto, taken from <hi>S. Austines</hi> owne vndoubted writinges, or from some other auncient Father of his age.</p>
   <p>But yet to speake somwhat in profe of these bookes, and first concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Hipognosticon,</hi> the same being professedly written <hi>contra Pelagianos, et Celestianos,</hi> against whom likewise <hi>S. Austin</hi> wrote, argueth the booke to be written by him, or some other father of those times: In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect <hi>M.</hi>
      <note n="(o)" place="margin">In Problem. p. 29.</note>
      <hi>Perkins</hi> seuereth it from the <hi>spuria scripta Augustini,</hi> and placeth it vnder the other title of <hi>Dubij tractatus.</hi> And it is yet further alledged almost 500. yeares since by <hi>Peter</hi>
      <note n="(p)" place="margin">Lib. 4. dist. 21.</note>
      <hi>Lambard,</hi> vnder S. <hi>Austines</hi> name; and is by <hi>D.</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">Defence of the reformed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, p. 91.</note>
      <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot,</hi> for such acknowledged and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
   <p>Concerning the booke <hi>de Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticis dogmatibus,</hi> it is cyted 800. yeares since, vnder the name of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadius</hi>
      <pb n="25" facs="13"/> (who liued in <hi>S. Austines</hi> age) by <hi>Walfridus</hi>
      <note n="(r)" place="margin">De rebus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. c. 20.</note>
      <hi>Strabo,</hi> by<note n="(s)" place="margin">Lib. 1. de corp. et sang. Dom. c. 22.</note>
      <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerus,</hi> and by<note n="(t)" place="margin">In Symacho. fin.</note>
      <hi>Platina.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Concerning the booke, <hi>de visita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione infirmorum,</hi> it is likewise by <hi>M.</hi>
      <note n="(u)" place="margin">In Problem. p. 30.</note>
      <hi>Perkins</hi> seuered from the <hi>spuria scripta Augustini,</hi> and by him placed vnder the title of <hi>Tractatus dubij,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so reputed the worke of some auncient Father.</p>
   <p>As touching <hi>Quaestiones veteris et noui Testamenti,</hi> it is alledged vnder <hi>Austines</hi> name, almost 500. yeares since, by<note n="(x)" place="margin">Caus. 32. quaest. 2. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag. Moyses tradidit.</note>
      <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi>
      <note n="(y)" place="margin">Lib. 4. dist. 31. 32.</note>
      <hi>Lombard;</hi> In so much as <hi>M.</hi>
      <note n="(z)" place="margin">2. part of his answeare, p. 19. 4.</note>
      <hi>Hutton</hi> professeth <hi>to thinke the author of this booke somwhat auncienter then Austin.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And as for the booke <hi>de vera et falsa paenitentia,</hi> it is alledged vnder <hi>S. Austines</hi> name almost 500. yeares since frequētly by<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lib. 4. dist. 15. 17. 19. 20.</note>
      <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> and for such acknowledged and vrged by <hi>D.</hi>
      <note n="(b)" place="margin">2. part. of his defence. p. 289.</note>
      <hi>Abbot.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly as concerning the booke <hi>de verbis Apostols,</hi> it is alledged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>S. Austines</hi> name by <hi>Peter</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">Lib. 2. dist. 30. l. 4. dist. 21.</note>
      <pb n="26" facs="14"/>
      <hi>Lombard,</hi> &amp; about 900. yeares since by <hi>S. Bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> (as appeareth next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of euery seueral sermon of that booke, according to the edition of <hi>S. Austines</hi> workes printed <hi>Lugduni.</hi> 1586.) and is for such alledged and acknowledged by<note n="(d)" place="margin">Vbi supra. p. 192. 252. 296. 399.</note>
      <hi>M. Abbot:</hi> whom I the rather here alledge, for that of al the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant writers yet come to my han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, he sheweth him selfe most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersant and frequent in the reading and alledging of <hi>S. Austin.</hi> As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise I do the rather here alledge <hi>Gratian,</hi> and <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> for that the Protestant writer<note n="(e)" place="margin">In Method. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquot locorum &amp;c. fol. 12.</note>
      <hi>Simon Pauli,</hi> making a Catologue of the <hi>Doctors and restorers of the heauenly doctrine,</hi> therein ranketh <hi>Gratian,</hi> and <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> together with <hi>Husse, Luther,</hi> and <hi>Melancthon,</hi> and so also doth<note n="(f)" place="margin">Method. theol. in pref. p. 1. 2.</note>
      <hi>Hiperius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But to returne to the learned ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries; this careful preparation being by me thus made, I can but here request leaue to admonish you with the Apostle,<note n="(g)" place="margin">lac. 2. 1,</note>
      <hi>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o hold the
<pb n="27" facs="14"/> faith of Christ in the acceptation of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> reguard not I pray you who it is that writeth, but what is written, and howsoeuer you thinke of me as perhaps (&amp; not iniustly) but weake and despicable in the presence of your owne very learned iudgemēts, for beare not yet I pray you, your due respect vnto <hi>S. Austin</hi> him selfe, and to so great a troupe of your owne learned writers, who in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of their so many alledged sayinges digested into this breefe treatise, are the primarie authors, and my selfe but as it were the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour or reporter thereof.</p>
   <p>And let me also request further leaue without offence to premonish, that in answeare hereto you would not (as some of you whom I spare to name haue heretofore done in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare to other treatises) seeke to euade, or to obscure the matter thus euidently proued, either by prolixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of discourse (as thereby to seduce or diuert the vnwary reader from the point properly issuable, which
<pb n="28" facs="15"/> in case of supposed truth might with shorter tearmes receiue direct and ful answeare vpon your confessing, denying, or distinguishing) or by passing ouer with silence without al answeare thereto such proofes as are of greatest importance, for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer this kind of omission may be houlden excusable by the preceptes of Rhetoricke, yet is it in diuinity grosse and vnworthy; or otherwise by vsual tergiuersation of obiecting (in steede of answering) certaine old obiected and often answeared ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurer sayinges of <hi>S. Austin,</hi>
      <note n="(h)" place="margin">See hereafter. c. 19.</note> (hereafter purposly in part preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) or other of the Fathers, wherin their contrary meaning is euident and for such by learned Protestants them selues<note n="(i)" place="margin">See hereafter. c. 20.</note>
      <hi>confessed:</hi> or els by digressing into allegation of certaine schoolemen dissenting somtimes frō the more common receiued doctrine concerning not the conclusions of faith, but the manner of some such conclusion, or some other like point not then by the Church determined.
<pb n="29" facs="15"/> Which how litle it forceth, is by <hi>S. Austin</hi> him selfe in sundry<note n="(k)" place="margin">Tom. 7. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iulian. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. l. 1. c. 6. post init. And de Baptismo, contra Donat. l. 1. c. 18. i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Aud l. 2. c. 4. prope init.</note> places declared and taught: Or otherwise in alledging certaine <hi>Noualistes,</hi> as<note n="(l)" place="margin">See the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisement set be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. Apol.</note>
      <hi>Erasmus, Valla, Wicelius, Cassander Agrippa, Polidore, Virgil, Iacobus Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and some few more such like, who not confessed against them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, but as parties affirmed directly for them selues in behalfe of some one or other of your nouel opinions by them for the time defended; which yet they al or most of them afterwardes<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
      <hi>retracted</hi> by their final submission to our Catholicke Church. For al this whatsoeuer, howsoeuer countinanced with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of reading, or other probability and ornament of discourse, (as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore it haith beene, and in such e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laborate sort as I haue seldome kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, so il a tale so wel told) yet what was it then as to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by vs obiected, and by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries confessed iudgements in the conclusions of faith? Or what can it be now as to the point of <hi>S.
<pb n="30" facs="16"/> Austines</hi> controuerted religion, and so many of your learned bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren confessing thereof against both you and them selues? If any shal vndertake to publish such further answeare of this kind, as I nothing doubt but that the studious Reader thus premonished wil of him selfe be able easily to discerne the same to be no other then wast of time and paper, so I for my part in steede of reply therto (which in case of more direct &amp; ful desired answeare would not be wanting) shal rather choose to spend part of my good houres in ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nest prayer for the party which shal so abuse his better leasure, that not depending too much vpon humane<note n="(n)" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.1.</note>
      <hi>knowledge</hi> which but <hi>puffeth vp,</hi> and which at this present distracteth the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Besides com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, see the Protest. Apol. tract. 2. c. 3. sec. 5. sub. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note>
      <hi>Lutherans, Caluinistes, Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, Anabaptistes, Brounistes, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>trinitaries,</hi> into no lesse great diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of opinions, then singular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt each of other, he may from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of these, learne to become so humble wife, and wisely humble, as
<pb n="31" facs="16"/> forbearing to be his owne iudge) according to the direction and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise of sundry Protestant<note n="(p)" place="margin">Acontius in stratagem. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. l. 4. p. 203. Hooker in Eccles. pol. in praef. sec. 6. p. 28. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon, l. 1. epist. ep. ad Regē Angliae. p. 49. The harmony of confessions in English. p. 319. Field of the Church. epist. dedic. Bancroft in his sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the 8. of Feb. pag. 42.</note> writers, <hi>to rest in others iudgement,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to<note n="(q)" place="margin">Deut. 32.7. Iob. 8.8. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. 8.9.</note>
      <hi>remember the auncient dayes</hi> of the Primitiue Church, <hi>to consider the yeares of so many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and<note n="(r)" place="margin">Hierem. 18.15.</note>
      <hi>auoyding</hi> as dangerous <hi>the wayes not tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dden, to</hi>
      <note n="(s)" place="margin">Ierem. 6.16.</note>
      <hi>enquire for the old way which is the good way,</hi> and <hi>to walke therein,</hi> that so keeping the Churches<note n="(t)" place="margin">Isay. 35.8.</note>
      <hi>beatē path wherin</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen very) <hi>fooles cānot erre,</hi> &amp; resigning vp him selfe (according to <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="(u)" place="margin">Tom. 7. cont. Crescon. l. 1. c. 33. init.</note>
      <hi>Austines</hi> aduise in case of doubt or question) to the iudgement of her who<note n="(x)" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15.</note>
      <hi>is the piller &amp; ground of truth,</hi> and whom<note n="(y)" place="margin">Math. 18.18.</note>
      <hi>not to heare, is to be as a Hathen or Publican,</hi> he may so at last yealde, not verbally but really to<note n="(z)" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note>
      <hi>captinate his vnderstanding to the obedience of Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN BRERELEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>