<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOS HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, IAMES by the grace of God, King of great Bri∣taine, France, &amp; Ireland, defender of the faith; my most gracious &amp; dread Soueraigne.</title>
           <author>Brereley, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2531_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16708</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3608</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2531</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOS HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, IAMES by the grace of God, King of great Bri∣taine, France, &amp; Ireland, defender of the faith; my most gracious &amp; dread Soueraigne.</title>
                 <author>Brereley, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sainct Austines religion : Collected from his owne writinges, &amp; from the confessio [n] s of the learned Protestants: whereby is sufficiently proued and made knowen, the like answearable doctrine of the other more auncient fathers of the primitiue church. Written by Iohn Brereley</title>
                 <author>Anderton, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Birchley Hall Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>31, 1, 375, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOS HIGH <hi>AND MIGHTY PRINCE, IAMES</hi> by the grace of God, King of great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France, &amp; Ireland, defender of the faith; my most gracious &amp; dread Soueraigne.</head>
   <p>THe much obserued and no lesse commended care, wherwith your highnes endeauoreth to enrich your Princely vnderstanding, not forbearing so much as at the time of your bodily repast, to haue for the then like feeding of your intellectual part your highnes table surrounded with the attendance &amp; conference of your graue and learned diuines (in which respect you may not vnaptly be tearmed in the very wordes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>napius, a liuing liberary, &amp; walking stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi>) addeth a more then ordinary lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre of ornament to your royal estate, and encorageth my otherwise fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; humble thoughtes, more bould<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to approch and salute your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with this saying of <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">Lib. 8. indict. 3. ep. 37. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentio. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe sin.</note>
      <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> Si delicioso copitis pabulo saginari beati Augustini opuscula legite:</hi> And although the viandes hereby thus prepared may, in reguard of the Cookes plaine or rather vnskilful workmanship in confection, seeme vnworthy of your royal presēce; for so much yet as they be of them selue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> soueraigne Antidotes whereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the dispersed contagiō of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous infection, and are now placed on the table before your highnes by the attendance and seruice of men to your Maiesty not vngrateful or su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected, euen the learnedst Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes them selues, from whose fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent abounding confessiō the many hereafter ensuing particulars of <hi>S. Austines</hi> professed religion are col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; I am not without hope that your highnes wil in such respect vouchsaife to esteeme them as not vnworthy either of your owne taist, or the view and further tryal of your attending learned diuines.</p>
   <p>And pardon great Saueraigne your meanest (yet wel meaning) subiect,
<pb n="5" facs="3"/> but to put your Maiesty in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that seeing our knowledge in this life is but <hi>in</hi>
      <note n="(b)" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9.</note>
      <hi>part, euen by a</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note>
      <hi>glasse in a darke sort,</hi> and that the Sciptures a lone are prescribed by your learnedst diuines for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying &amp; quieting of our knowlege in al doubts of religiō whatsoeuer; that your Maiesty would plese to take notice that the said sacred Scriptures are not able to afford vs so much as certaine &amp; infallible proofe &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them selues; for as the titles of the said bookes can be no certaine proofe of their diuine authority, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that many writinges of like title were forged vnder the<note n="(d)" place="margin">See Eusebius hist. l. 3. c. 19. et lib. 6. c. 10. S. Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra aduers. leg. et Proph. l. 1. c. 20. Zozom. hist. l. 7. c. 19. Hmmelman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de tradit. Apost. part. 1. l. 1. col. 251. et part. 3. l. 3. col. 841. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d see 2. Thes. 2.2.</note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles names, and neuer receiued by the Church for Canonical: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise Protestant writers expresly teach, &amp;<note n="(e)" place="margin">Hooker in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. pol. l. 1. sec. 14. p. 86.</note> conclude resolutly, that <hi>of thinges necessary the very cheifest is to know what bookes we are to esteeme holy, which point is confessed impossible for the Scripture it selfe to teach: And</hi>
      <note n="(f)" place="margin">Ibid. l. 2. see. 4. p. 102. 146. Couel in his defēce of Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, art. 4. p. 31.</note>
      <hi>it is not the word of God which doth, or possibly can assure vs that we do wel to
<pb n="6" facs="4"/> thinke it is his word.</hi> From whence it is that yet to this present, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes so importantly differ in the very Canon of the Scriptures, for it is wel knowen that the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Adamus Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisci in Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita Theol. p. 448. Chemnit. in exam. part. 1. p. 55. 56. 57. and in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid. p. 63. Hafenref. in loc. Theol. loc. 7. p. 292. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siand. Cent. 4. l. 3. c. 38. p. 399. The Centuristes, cent. 1. l. 2. c. 4. col. 54.</note>
      <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi> Churches do stil reiect as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal <hi>the Epistle to the Hebrewes, the Epistle of S. Iames, the second and third of</hi> S. <hi>Iohn, the latter of S. Peter, the Epistle of</hi> S. <hi>Iudas, and the Apocalips of</hi> S. <hi>Iohn:</hi> with whom agreeth<note n="(h)" place="margin">Loc. com. c. de iustific. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag. 5. p. 250.</note>
      <hi>Wolphangus Musculus a Caluinist,</hi> in reiecting the Epistle of S. <hi>Iames</hi> as erroneous in <hi>iustification by workes.</hi> Now if the Scriptures be cōfessedly thus vnable to afford vs but so much as certaine proofe of them selues, then in al true consequence of reasō much lesse are they able to direct &amp; exempt vs in case of al doubt or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion infallibly from error.</p>
   <p>And the rather cosidering that in such case (as <hi>D.</hi>
      <note n="(i)" place="margin">Conference c. 2. diuis. 2. p. 68.</note>
      <hi>Raynoldes</hi> confesseth) <hi>It is not the shew but the sense of the wordes</hi> (of Scripture) that must <hi>decide controuersies;</hi> and that touching this questionable sense, the
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> Scripture howsoeuer infaliible and sufficient in it selfe which none deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yet it is not (which is the onely point now pertinent and questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable) infallibly sufficient as to vs in her instruction therof, as not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soluing and instructing vs therein infallibly, because not immediatly of it selfe but onely by certaine meanes<note n="(k)" place="margin">Whitaker de Scriptura, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouer. 1. q. 5. c. 9. p. 251.</note> on our behalfe required, as<note n="(l)" place="margin">Whitaker, ib. p. 521. 522. 523. Reynoldes in his cōfer. c. 2. p. 83. 84. 92.</note> namely, <hi>Our skil in the tongues, our waighing the circumstances of the text, our conferring of places, our praier, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence &amp;c.</hi> Al which though endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored by vs with al possible care, are yet (as being actions on our part) most clearly not infallible but hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and subiect to<note n="(m)" place="margin">Lubbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tus de princip. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. dog. l. 6. c. 13. p. 442. Whitaker. de Eccles. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouer. 2. q. 4. p. 221.</note> error: And such as the same notwithstanding, <hi>Luther,</hi> and many other his followers haue (euen according to our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries censures) no lesse confessedly then greeuously<note n="(n)" place="margin">Whitguift in defence. p. pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nult. Bridges in def. of the gouernment. p. 559. Hospin. hist. sacram. part. 2. fol. 14. 44. 55. 49. 57.</note> erred, and therin persisted,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Luther de caen a Domini. tom. 2. Germ. fol. 174.</note> euenconcerning such
<pb n="8" facs="5"/> pointes of doctrine as they from their owne careful obseruation of these foresaid meanes held for most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, vndoubted, &amp; cleare. And the like might be exemplifyed in the<note n="(p)" place="margin">In their Apol. p. 103.</note>
      <hi>Broumstes,</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Eccles. pol. in pref. sec. 8. p. 38.</note>
      <hi>Anabaptistes,</hi>
      <note n="(r)" place="margin">Carrh▪ wright in his second reply. part. 1. p. 18. 509.</note>
      <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes,</hi>
      <note n="(s)" place="margin">Caluin, Tract. theol. p. 533. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Libertines, and</hi>
      <note n="(t)" place="margin">Colloq. Ratisbone.</note>
      <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranes,</hi> whoal of them in like manner haue no lesse carefully conferred, and seriously pretended the Scriptures in defence of their so many different er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, which each of them seuerally apprehended for vndoubted &amp; true, and yet the same notwithstanding al of thē confessedly erred.</p>
   <p>Vpon due consideratiō therefore had of these premises so necessarily inferring our owne incertanty, al foresaid pretence of Scripture to the contrary notwithstanding, and like further obseruation that the cheife question of the Canonical Scriptures thē selues, is determined to vs not by Scripture it selfe, as haith<note n="(*)" place="margin">See here before at e. f.</note> beene shewed, nor<note n="(u)" place="margin">Whitaker. aduersus Stap. l. 2. c. 6. p. 370. l. 2. c. 6. p. 357.</note>
      <hi>by priuate testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the spirit,</hi> but according to the learnedst<note n="(x)" place="margin">The author of the treatise of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the Church. c. 16. fol. 75. Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. cont. Staplet. l. 2. c. 4. p. 298. 300. Chemnit. in examen. part. 1. p. 69. Lubbertus de princip. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. dog. l. 1. c. 4. p. 18.</note> Protestants <hi>by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="5"/> of the Church,</hi> which confessedly<note n="(y)" place="margin">Fulke his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare to a count. Cath. p. 5. Iewel in def. of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. part. 2. p. 242. Witaker contra Stap. l. 1. c. 5. p. 69.</note> had <hi>the assistance of the holy Ghost,</hi> in her infallible discerning to vs which bookes of Scripture were sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and which not; wherby also is further argued or rather conuinced her no lesse needful assistance of the same spirit in her like discerning to vs the sense<note n="(z)" place="margin">Chemnit. in ex am. part. 1. p. 74. Sar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ia in defen. tract. cont. Bezam. p. 8.</note> of the said Scripture, for what auaileth it vs to be made certaine of the bookes, and left in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine of the sense. What reason can our aduersaries allegde wherby to acknowledge the Churches priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the one &amp; deny it (where it is no lesse needful) in the other?</p>
   <p>It cannot therfore I hope (in these times of so great doubt &amp; question) seeme either vnfitting or vnsafe, that for our owne more certaine instruction in the doctrine of the Primitiue Church, (which both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties acknowledge for the true Church) we should make humble recourse vnto the receiued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed writinges of S. <hi>Austin</hi> (a principal member of the said church)
<pb n="10" facs="6"/> who liuing so long before these our times, and being in such respect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to our late since vprisen controuersies, is by our learned ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries professedly reuerenced, as the vndoubted<note n="(a)" place="margin">See hereafter c. 1. h. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>best witnes since the Apostles times of Apostolicke doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neither can the perswasion which is oftentimes setled and growen strong in vs by education, afford any infallible certanty to your greatest Maiesty, or your learned diuines, whereby to secure your selues from error, as might be made plaine (without al further needful di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourse) by example, not onely of sundry auncient Kinges and<note n="(b)" place="margin">See the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. Apol. tract. 2. c. 3. sec. 6. parag. 2. p. 513. ats.</note> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, who brought vp in <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme,</hi> did thereupon imbrace and by their lawes establish the error therof as a truth most consonant to the Scriptures; but also of diuerse mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne <hi>Lutheran</hi> Princes, as of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke. Saxony, Brunswicke &amp;c.</hi> who vpon their like education in <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranisme,</hi> do professe as not to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned
<pb n="11" facs="6"/> their monster of<note n="(c)" place="margin">See Whitguif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in his defence of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare, p. pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nult. Bridges, in his def. of the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. l. 7. p. 559. Hospin. in hist. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. fol. 14. 44. 55. 49. 57. And part. 2. fol. 245. 282. 286. 287.</note>
      <hi>vbiquity,</hi> and other now dissenting opinions, condemning therupon the aduerse doctrines of <hi>Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Suinglius,</hi> for<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luther, Tom. 2. Wittenberg. fol. 503. and tom. 7. fol. 382. Fulke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the censure, p. 101. 155. Hospin. hist. saciam. part. 2. fol. 183.</note> errors most execrable. In like sort the <hi>reformed Churches</hi> (so are they<note n="(e)" place="margin">By Hooker in Eccles. pol. l. 4. sec. 8. p. 101. 183.</note> styled) <hi>of Transiluania, Poland, and hungary,</hi> (who being <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titrinitaries,</hi> and yet otherwise<note n="(f)" place="margin">See Gratianus Prosper in his instrumen tum doctrina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp;c.</note> onely differing from the <hi>Caluinistes</hi> in the <hi>doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Baptisme of infants,</hi> haue together with their milke, sucked the poyson of <hi>Arianisme</hi>) are vpon this like ground euen to this present so car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away against our receiued doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the blessed Trinity, that they forbeare not to compare it to the<note n="(g)" place="margin">See Osiander, cent. 16. l. 2. c. 22. p. 209.</note>
      <hi>three headed Cerberus,</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the same in their sundry<note n="(h)" place="margin">Gratianus, Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sper, Socinus, Gentilis, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetus, Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drata, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> published writinges, (stored with plentiful alledged testimonies of Scripture) for the cheifest brand of
<pb n="12" facs="7"/> al Popish and <hi>Antichristian</hi>
      <note n="(i)" place="margin">See Osiander, cent. 16. l. 2. c. 22. p. 209.</note>
      <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:</hi> And as we can not assure our selues, but that in case of our like supposed educatiō in those opinions, so once in like manner established with the current and countenance of the state, our iudgements (no lesse then theirs) in like sort might haue beene preoccupated and transported with the same errors; so their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample affordeth vs iust forwarning, not to rest secure vpon the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring probability of any such like set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led perswasion whatsoeuer.</p>
   <p>And so much the lesse, if we not onely obserue ingeneral, the great reuoult of late made by so many of the learnedst <hi>Caluinistes</hi> from <hi>Caluins</hi> former receiued, &amp; so much applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note n="(k)" place="margin">See Willet in Rom. c. 9. p. 442. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancth. in Con. Theol. part. 2. p. 111. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingius de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersali gratia. Snecanus in method. de script. p. 124. 430. 441. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stalio in his booke hereof de praedest. Fox in Apoc. p. 473. &amp; sundry others.</note> doctrines, concerning <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, induration, vniuersality of grace</hi>
      <note n="(l)" place="margin">So did Caluin, Beza, and the French Protestantes and our now Puritanes, who are now contradicted by Bancroft in the confer. at. Hampton, p. 36. Whitguift in his def. p. 384. Downham in his def. l. 2. c. 6. &amp; l. 4. c. 2. 3.</note>
      <hi>condemning of Bishops for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian, the</hi>
      <note n="(m)" place="margin">See Willet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Psalm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 122. and the Puritanes in their answere to Downhams sermon, p. 51.</note>
      <hi>denying of Christes
<pb n="13" facs="7"/> descending into hel, the lawfulnes to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry againe in case of diuorce vpon adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery &amp;c.</hi> And the yet further defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many other learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants who wholly<note n="(n)" place="margin">See Fulke de successione Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiast. p. 281. Cooke in his Pope Ioane, in ep. dedic.</note> abandoning their Protestant religion, haue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al submitted them selues to our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke faith; but do also yet further cal to minde in particular, how that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e is almost no man so vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced, who knoweth not that in som things he haith altered his owne former iudgement, and varied from him selfe, condemning vpon a second consideration for false, what he once held for vndoubted and most cleare. Remarkable examples whereof I might geue in<note n="(o)" place="margin">See Hospinian hist. sacram. part. 2. in his Alphabetical table vnder the title, Lutheri in constantia in doctrina.</note>
      <hi>Luther,</hi>
      <note n="(p)" place="margin">See Hospin. hist. sacram. part. 2. fol. 68. 115. 140. and Colloq. Altemberg. fol. 377.</note>
      <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> and others, but I wil onely content my selfe with <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> (a man in the opinion of<note n="(q)" place="margin">In his Scripta Anglicana. vnder the tytle of indicia doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. virorum de Bucero. &amp; p. 944. and vlt.</note> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants <hi>most learned and holy,</hi> who after his defection from our<note n="(r)" place="margin">Osiand. Cent. 16. l. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 33. p. 88.</note> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke
<pb n="14" facs="8"/> doctrine of <hi>transubstantiation,</hi> &amp; <hi>sacrifice,</hi> made his <hi>first</hi> chaunge into <hi>Luthers</hi>
      <note n="(s)" place="margin">Osiand. vbi su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>{pre}ra. and Peter Martir in his treatise of the Lords supper annexed to his common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in english. p. 138.</note> aduerse doctrine of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation,</hi> from which he made <hi>a second</hi> chaunge<note n="(t)" place="margin">In his ep. ad Norimb. et Essengenses. Lauatherus, hist. sacram. fol. 31.</note> into <hi>Suinglianisme,</hi> most vehemently impugning <hi>Luthers</hi> foresaid opinion of <hi>Consubstantiation,</hi> in which respect <hi>Luther</hi> tearmed him<note n="(u)" place="margin">Fabricius in Lutheri, Loc. com. clas. 5. c. 15. p. 50.</note>
      <hi>perfidious:</hi> but from this yet he made <hi>a third</hi> chaunge, whereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing againe<note n="(x)" place="margin">See Schluffel. burge in theol. Caluin. fol. 17. 129.</note>
      <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine <hi>he asked</hi>
      <note n="(y)" place="margin">In his firster edition of his comment. in Ioan. 6. &amp; Math. 26. and in qutauor Euangelia in Ioan. 6. p. 686.</note>
      <hi>pardon of God and the Church</hi> for his former <hi>Suinglian</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,<note n="(z)" place="margin">La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uather in hist. sacram. fol. 31.</note>
      <hi>estranging him selfe</hi> theru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>frō the Tigurin Suinglians, whom he before so much honoured;</hi> after al which he lastly made <hi>a fourth</hi> change, which was his returne againe to <hi>Suinglianisme,</hi> the which he finally professed and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Schlusselburge in theol. Caluin. fol. 70. 17.</note> defended at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and al this at each time of such his alteration or chaunge, with most earnest pretence and protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="8"/> in his so often published vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able doctrine, of vndoubted certan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conceiued from the Scriptures.</p>
   <p>Al which (or any part thereof) I would not be mistaken to apply or intend in any sense or sort fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then onely as thereby in al humble manner to moue your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty vnto a second and more serious consideration, vpon occasion of the now thus propounded and confessed ensuing particulars of <hi>S. Austines</hi> professed religion: wherein if accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that liberty of sincere and plaine speaking, which (as in this case) is no lesse then appertaining (or rather prescribed) to a man of my function, I haue forborne as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, that adulterate placency or Sophistication of insinuating or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing speach, which is not the least infelicity that vsually attendeth vpon greatnes, and in steede therof (according to the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Psal. 119.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Prophets di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting me for to speake of Gods te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies euen before kinges, &amp; not be ashamed) haue with more can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
<pb n="16" facs="9"/> of minde ingenuously (and yet I hope not offensiuely) signifyed to your highnes, that not vndoubtful possibility of erring, from which not Kingly maiesty exempteth humane condition, I am not vnconfident, that in the equity of your Princely iudgement, you wil as in my excuse vouchsaife to approue this worthy saying of <hi>S. Amhrose</hi> to the noble Emperour <hi>Theodosius,</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ambros. ep. 17. ad Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos. prope ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note>
      <hi>neque Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periale est libertatem dicendi negare, neque sacerdotale quod sentit non dicere &amp;c. nihil in sacerdote tam periculosum apud Deum, tam turpe apud homines, quam quod sentit non liberé denunciare.</hi> The zeale of Gods truth, and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted best affections to your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as to my gracious and dread soueraige liege Lord, (whose euer honoured memory with me rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in such respect as almost chare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enfoulded within the purest find on of my loyal heart) haue required at my handes the performance of this duty. The which with most humble and suppliant desire of your
<pb n="17" facs="9"/> maiesties pardon, (which haith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged it selfe to become sanctuary to a greater offender) I do al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, presume hereby to offer vp as sacred to your highnes name, with my dayly continued pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto God, the author of al truth, to direct &amp; preserue your royal heart and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in the waies of his truth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble seruant. <hi>IOHN BRERELEY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>