<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2549_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17810</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4499</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2549</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the life and reigne of that famous princesse Elizabeth : containing a briefe memoriall of the chiefest affaires of state that haue passed in these kingdomes of England, Scotland, France or Ireland since the yeare of the fatall Spanish invasion to that of he sad and ever to be deplored dissolution : wherevnto also is annexed an appendix of animadversions vpon severall passages, corrections of sundry errours, and additions of some remarkable matters of this history never before imprinted</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Webb, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 384, that is 376, 103 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T were well, if, what once the tongue of the
Athenian Crier did to euery Orator, the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of Authority would, to euery Babbler;
<hi>Inter dicere, ne praefatione &amp; affectibus uteren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
&amp; lubere, ut rem mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>rent</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; A law indeed, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
by a necessary disobedience, I must now both
approue, and violate; for I confesse, that in excusing my
selfe, I had rather hazard the <hi>vncertaine</hi> censure of <hi>this</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stentation,
then by concealing an indifferent truth, sit down
to a <hi>certaine</hi> discredit. Know therefore Reader (for I care
not who does) that when I made the first onset vpon this
Exercise, it was my desire rather to see <hi>what I could doe▪</hi> then
care <hi>what I did;</hi> for with the iust expences of a moneths
time &amp; labour, I digested the whole body of this History in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
a perfect frame. I must confesse my way was hard, and my
time as short; insomuch, that by the very transcribing of so
compleat a Volume in such a space, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>and her selfe seem'd
to earne a commendation. But withall I must acknowledge,
that since, I was faine to adde the discretion of my <hi>second
thoughts,</hi> to correct and regulate some grosse absurdities;
which notwithstanding was such, as that it spo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e onely in
interlinings, and marginall references, and not added the
supplement of one sheet to encrease the former bulke. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
thus lickt it so farre, to make it worth the reading, that
I made it almost impossible to be read, (as I first began it, to
ease the troublesome request of a priuate friend, so now) I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
it vp into his hands, to punish him with a peru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all. But
it seemes, when the respects of loue and friendship blin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the
iust censure of a iudicious eie▪ there, weake endeauours may
finde both entertainment and acceptance. Thus fell it out
<pb facs="4"/>
with me; for, (although the conscience of my own imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
could bequeath it no better light, then that that
should consume it) it pleased him to thinke it worth a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
this of the worlds; so that I, (whose conscience and
duty bound me to an equall obseruance of his <hi>Desire,</hi> with
other mens <hi>Commands</hi>) was forced now againe to fashion
my collected errours for the Presse; desiring to publish ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
my <hi>obedience</hi> to my Friend, then <hi>name</hi> to the World.
Then might I haue iustly and boldly said, what <hi>Erasmus</hi>
once did vpon his Edition of Saint <hi>Ieromes</hi> Workes,<hi>—V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
illud &amp; verè dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m &amp; audacter; minoris arbitror Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
suos constitisse libros conditos, quàm nobis restitutos:
&amp; paucioribus vigilijs apud illum natos fuisse, quam apud
nos renatos.</hi> For I may well auerre, that the very reviewing
of my Paines, exceeded the Paines which I reviewed, by so
much the more, as it is easier to commit a fault, then to
finde it, once committed.</p>
   <p>If this serue for an excuse, I cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>acceptance</hi> at thy hands,
if not, <hi>forgiuenesse;</hi> but if thou be not pleased to giue, then
exchange a courtesie, which is nought but this; for
my <hi>defects,</hi> let me haue thy <hi>pardon;</hi> and for
my <hi>deserts,</hi> I'le dispence with thy
<hi>commendation.</hi> Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>