<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FATHER: S. F. S.</title>
           <author>S., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2575_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20946</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7325</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2575</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FATHER: S. F. S.</title>
                 <author>S., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Heraclitus, or, Meditations vpon the vanity &amp; misery of humane life first written in French by that excellent scholler &amp; admirable divine Peter Du Moulin minister of the sacred word in the Reformed Church of Paris ; and translated into English by R.S. gentleman</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Pavier, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 121 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FATHER: S. F. S.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>The naturalre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, that an obseruāt sonne oweth to a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and carefull father, obligeth me to meditate on some thing that may deserue your pervsall, and answere part of your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation: hauing therefore tasted the fruites of many mens invē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I could not finde any sort so holesome for a man of your
<pb facs="3"/> yeares, nor so pleasing to mine ovvne relish as this ensuing treatise of that worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and admirable divine <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Du Moulin,</hi> vvho by his tongue, and pen doth daily win many souls to God, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise would by the subtill delusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sathan, and the persuasiue discourses of vvicked Masse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priests, and sin-plotting Iesuits run headlong to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. I know your expence in my breeding may iustlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire as great a worke as this immediatly frō my selfe, which I shoulde bee as willing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, as you to command, were it not that I looke backe into this age as ful of envious detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiōs, &amp; idle censures, as voide
<pb facs="3"/> of all true iudgement, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Moreover this matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a diuine morality, or rather a morall diuinity woulde seeme too graue for my youth, and too high for my knowledge. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am the rather desirous to make vse of this Translatiō, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it will serue not only as a buckler against those criticall shafts, which some musty quiuer might send out against me, but also as a comfort &amp; restoratiue for your declining age. I haue presumed to dedicate it to your fatherly censure, as being yet vnable to apprehend any other thing that may either adde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to it selfe, or deservedlie attract any favor frō you: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling craving that the errours
<pb facs="4"/> of this Translation may not any way impeach your good opiniō but as you haue formerly▪ so now &amp; ever after you will bind me to rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most observant and respectiue sonne <hi>R. S.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>