<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S259_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17297</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4140.4</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S259</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Conflicts and comforts of conscience : A treatise, shewing how the conscience, in cases of deepest distresse and distraction, may recollect it selfe, and recouer solid and sound comfort. Collected from priuate proofe, for publike profit. By H.B. Rector of St. Mathews Friday street</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 16, 28, 278, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, I here present thee with <hi>A Treatise</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and Comforts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</hi> Which, how su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for thee, I know not: But I am sure, for me. The bitter <hi>Conflicts</hi> of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the birth, may iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name it <hi>Ben-oni, Sonne of Sorrow:</hi> But the <hi>Father, Ben-iamin, Sonne of the right hand</hi>; Or <hi>Barnabas, Sonne of Consolation. They that sow in teares, shall reape in ioy.</hi> Such a tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling could not be bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e in


<pb facs="11"/>
a colder Season; it must incounter many bitter stormes; But beeing strengthened by <hi>Paul</hi>'s Comforter, it runneth aground, not waighing the losse of the Ship, to saue the Soules, though driuen on the Barbarians shore; hoping also, that howsoeuer, as the Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, seeing the Viper leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on <hi>Paul</hi>'s hand, dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him some Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour; but cast off againe into the fire without hurt, changed their minds: So haply it may befall the Authour of this Treatise. Who of set purpose pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing himselfe the maine


<pb facs="11"/>
subiect of these <hi>Conflicts and Comforts:</hi> May h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ply occasion some Readers in their hast to passe vpon him a far harder sentence, then he deserueth▪ What's the matter, say th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y? Adulterers, Fornicatours are onely fit for publicke penance. But let such know, that it becommeth a Minister of the Gospell to be humbled for the lest offence, much more for greater. Blessed be God, by whose Grace I haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne kept for euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting any such act, throughout my whole life. Let the great <hi>Accuser of our Brethren</hi> stand vp,


<pb facs="12"/>
and accuse me in that kind, if hee can. Yet the vile corruptions of nature, and the foule aberrations of life, yea euen meere heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse follies and needlesse frailties, may they not bee cause enough to plunge a man in the deepe, to cause him to abhorre himselfe, and to <hi>repent in dust and ashes,</hi> and that especially when they fall vpon a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred person? Euen holy <hi>Iob</hi> did so. How much more such a one, as being equall to <hi>Iob</hi> in sacrednesse of person, yet is farre infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to him in the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of vertues?</p>
   <p>But they obiect: If it


<pb facs="12"/>
bee no more, who is free? If euerie one should write a Booke of his humaine follyes, the world would not containe them. This sauours of too much nice and needless scrupulosity; Or as done of spl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne, to aggrauate others sinnes, which might passe for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, at least for veniall, were it not for such strait laced Consciences, which grieued for small sinnes, make the greater out of measure sinfull. As the enuious man, to haue both his neighbours eyes put out, is willing to loose one of his owne. How many, yea &amp; sometimes Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men


<pb facs="13"/>
too, may play the good fellowes, bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seene, and ouer-shooes, and yet make no such scruple of it? Or if men espy the least hole in the Ministers coat, they will easily g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t in their whole body, hiding all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities vnder his holely Coat, as silly Papists their sins vnder a Fryers cowle. And may not Papists also, specially their Priests take it in snuffe, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n they shal see common frailties so deepely lamented, as it must needs damme to the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pe Pit of Hell their ordinarie Adulteries, and Fornications, which they


<pb facs="13"/>
account but venials, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a Priest? May they not hereupon grow vpon the simple people, as whose libertie is too much captiued vnder the yoake of such a Ministry, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not brooke in themselues the least aberrations, how much lesse such as they censure and esteeme farre greater in the multitude? Or else may they not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace such Ministers vnto their people, by making Mountaines of their Molehils, while Ministers bewaile their Molehils as Mountaines?</p>
   <p>To this multiplicit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection I answer: First, It


<pb facs="14"/>
were to be wished, that all offenders would giue pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke euidence of their Repentance, if not by Orall confession, yet by an actuall reformation. Secondly, I see no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why any common Christian should inuy, that a Ministers heedlesse smallest slips should in the skales of his owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preponder others head die falls. Thirdly, What Marriners will bee so desperately madd, as to run vpon the Rocke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Pilot sometime in the securitie of a calme fell a sleepe at the Sterne? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> what Seruant will goe


<pb facs="14"/>
cut his own throat, because his Master against his will cut his finger? Fourthly, Why should better taught Christians bee like those vntaught Lystrians, who either Idolatrously will sacrifice to the Apostles▪ or hearing them professing to be men of <hi>like passions</hi> with them, in the turning of a hand <hi>stone</hi> them? Yet, if no remedie, <hi>Let him that is without sinne, cast the first stone.</hi> Fifthly, For the common Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie of all grace; nothing will stop his Serpentine two forked tongue. If a Minister bee altogether blamelesse, hee heares,


<pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>A Puritan:</hi> But if in the least casuall errour obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious, <hi>Worse then a Publican.</hi> Lastly, It is the glorie of the Gospell to make the least sinnes vile in the eyes of the true Professours thereof, to the confusion of <hi>Babel,</hi> with all her Crimsin, Criminall, Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, yet Veniall, yea Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious, Meretricious Sinnes. And it shall euer bee the glorie of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the Gospell, as an euidence of true grace in their hearts, when they shall with a meeke, yet magnanimous Spirit bee able to dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st the sower hearbes of malicious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrations


<pb facs="15"/>
cast in their dish by the profane Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, and to answer them, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Micol,</hi> with a noble resolution, <hi>I will yet bee more vile then thus, &amp; will be base in mine owne sight.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In a word, if any shall beare himselfe bigge vpon such instances as this (of a man made nothing in his owne eyes) thinking to purchase some opinion of sanctitie to blaunch his monstrous lurking lusts, by how much his mouth shall vent the more vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Censures against it: let such learne of the Heathen Poet:
<q>
         <pb facs="16"/>
         <lg>
            <l>Qui, ne tuberibus proprijs offendat amicum,</l>
            <l>Postulat, ignoscat verrucis illius; aequum est</l>
            <l>Poscentem veniam peccatis, reddere rursus.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>Who would bee glad not to offend</l>
            <l>With his swolne bunches his deare friend,</l>
            <l>His warts must pardon; This is iust,</l>
            <l>Who pardon craues, hee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don must.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
But why stand we thus to answer euerie Obiecter? Let this Booke answer for all. Read it. And if it will not satisfie thee: Yet I


<pb facs="16"/>
hope it will aboundan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly satisfie him, for whom it is specially written.</p>
   <p>Yet one obiection more is: That in these loosse and licentious times, it had beene more necessary to reach men the way to repentance &amp; humiliation for sinne, then how to find comfort, being humbled. For most men, though neuer so sinnefull, are apt enough to lay hold on Gods mercie, which yet neuer trod the way of true repentance, thinking it sufficient (as the Thiefe that trusts to his <hi>Neck-verse</hi>) if at the verie end of the Race they can worke


<pb facs="17"/>
force in but one foote, and with a <hi>Peccaui</hi> crowd in at Heauen Gate. For such <hi>Ben-onies</hi> most will bee, to assume the name of <hi>Sonnes of Sorrow,</hi> but not before the giuing vp of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ghost, that bare them. As the Phenix is not bred, but of the dead ashes of the Damme. Most men being as loth to see their sinne dye, as <hi>Hagar</hi> her bond sonne. How many <hi>Iudasses</hi> will neuer repent, confesse, restore, but with the Halter in their hands? Or at the best, as the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> going with Halters about their Hypocriticall neckes to the King of


<pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>Israel,</hi> to flatter God for a pardon. The Vsurer builds no Hospitals, relieues no poore, till he dy, nor many times then, choosing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye, then make his Will. <hi>Balaam</hi> will but dye the death of the righteous as loth to forgoe his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of vnrighteousnesse, while hee liueth. Hee that liues a Theef, would dye a Martyr, though wee read but of one that did so. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci{que} bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us Ante obitū nemo</hi> (in the worst sense) Euerie one would be happy, but not till death. In this regard then it had beene more requisite to show men their folly in defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring


<pb facs="18"/>
their repentance, till either sinne or sicknesse haue made them senselesse of their sinnes, or in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the payment of their debts, till the score grow greater and greater, and they lesse able to pay, turning at length quite Banckrupts: That so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting in time, they may enter in at the Gate of Mercie, before it be quite shut vp, with an, <hi>I know you not: Depart yee workers of iniquitie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Answ.</hi> This obiection (I confesse) is of some moment. Too many (alas!) are readie with <hi>Ioab,</hi> flying to lay hold on the Hornes


<pb facs="18"/>
of the Altar, when yet they haue not made their peace with King <hi>Salomon,</hi> the King of peace. But in case any inordinate liuer shall be brought to a sight and sense of his sin, while hee is yet meat-whole, as we say: here he may, by Gods grace, find comfort. And as for that other taske to teach men the way to repentance, others haue bestowed profitable pains therein; and especially of late a learned and reuerend Predecessour of mine, M. <hi>Mason,</hi> in his <hi>Tribunall of Conscience.</hi> Wherein for the point of moralitie, in the examination of a mans


<pb facs="19"/>
life, he hath taken worthy paynes. Onely I could wish, if his leasure did serue, that hee would bee pleased to add thereunto a Rule how to examine a mans Errours in point of Faith, and of the sound knowledge of the Mystery of Christ. For where this foundation of sound and sauing knowledge is not rightly layd in the heart, as the foundation, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer repentance a man goes about to frame or erect, it either falleth, as built on the Sand, or vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth away in an ayerie imagination. For the purpose: How can a man,


<pb facs="19"/>
that either is ignorant of the grace of Christ, of the Gospell of God, and of the nature of sauing Faith, or else is arrogant in the singularitie of his owne opinion, wherein he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth the whole foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Grace, euer come to true repentance for his sinne? For true repentance is a speciall gift of Grace: It is an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate fruit of sauing Faith illuminating and sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heart, and whole man: and God giues this grace to no malicious ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Grace, but to such as hauing receiued it, are thankefull for it, as a gift


<pb facs="20"/>
of Gods free grace in Christ, flowing from the Fountaine of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall loue in electing vs in Christ, before the World was. So that it may seeme a worthy worke, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie (if any) for the aduersaries of grace, swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to a great height in these last times, as if they would bring another De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge vpon the Earth: to show the way, how such may come (if it be possible) to the <hi>acknowledgement of the Truth,</hi> to repentance and amendment of their Errours, and Sins, <hi>that they may be saued.</hi> Onely it is a question, whether their


<pb facs="20"/>
Errours vphold them in their Lusts, especially Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and Loue of the World, or these their Lusts hold them fast in their Errours. But I will not ouer bouldly presse this Taske vpon any, it being both touchy and tedious. In the meane time, if any shall reape either Consolation, or Instruction by this poore Worke, to the furtherance of their Saluation, and the adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ncement of the glory of him, who set me on worke, it is the Fruit of all my Labour, and <hi>I reioyce therein, yea and I will reioyce.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>