<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2665_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00630</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10765.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2665</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The artes of logike and rethorike [sic] : plainlie set foorth in the English tounge, easie to be learned and practised: togither vvith examples for the practise of the same for methode, in the gouernement of the familie, prescribed in the word of God: and for the whole in the resolution or opening of certayne partes of Scripture, according to the same</title>
                 <author>Fenner, Dudley</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough these Treatises follovvinge, were begunne and ended at the request and for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of some fewe which were desirous of them, for whose cause they are also nowe come vnder the printe: though peraduenture not done (as they say in printe) yet because it is not vnlikely, but by these meanes they will come into the handes of many, who will enquire vpon what groundes I haue aduentured this thing, whiche to some will seeme straunge and newe, yea vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inexpedient, that they are made common to all which are wonte to sit in the Doctors chayre: to other also (which wil neyther greatly mislike the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them into our tounge, nor yet the folowing of the better sorte in that arte, they will carrie notwithstanding the same taste, because they will seeme newer then the newest:) I thought it necessarie to write these fewe following, if not to satisfie them, yet at the least to incline them to a more moderate iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement concerning my labours, then otherwise, the former coniectures will suffer them to come vnto. There is in deede a thirde sorte, which will looke for a defence of these artes in generall, being by them accused as vayne &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. But because their reasonings are such as are to be answered by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them in the darke and from the noyse of sounde oppositions, which will more hurte them and trouble the worlde, then any defence of good aunswere, profite others. I will follow the example of many wise, nay the precept of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, to confute them with silence. To come therefore vnto the firste sorte, there can be nothing more fitte to satisfie them, then to shewe that that whiche they doo but florishe against vs, will deadlie wounde their cause. Howe can they call that newe, the which hath testimonies of the wisestes and auncientest of both sortes. For to omitte the examples of these dayes, whiche haue alreadie brought all artes into Frenche, Dutch, and almost into Englishe, and that by the hande of the most cūningest workemen: What will they answere vnto the knowledge and learning of the Egiptians, wherein Moses excelled, before the Greeke or Romane tounges became generall? Were not their writinges, thinke they, in their owne tounge? yea after that, were not Salomons treatises &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses (whether written or vnwritten) both of naturall things, and of al that is done vnder the Sunne, and therefore of these thinges) were they not done in the most ancient and worthie tounge of the Hebrues? Nay euen their chief maisters nowe, Plato and Aristotle, Tullie, and Quintilian, wrote they not in their owne tounges, and that euen when these artes were more ripe in the tongues of others? So that Tullie is fayne (as he him self somewhere confesseth) to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe from the Grecians, and of others, it is manifest they did it frō the Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Hebrues.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, the ende why these artes haue bin kept in these tounges, doeth not only propte, but also holde vp this our practise, seeing it was done because these tounges being most generall by reason of the spread that the Grecian and Romane Empire had made of them, they were the fittest to bee made the store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house of the worlde for these commodities. A storehouse I saye, not to keepe
<pb facs="3"/>
them for the Romanes and Grecians alone, or for the expert in these tounges their free denizons: but at the least that by their traffike, it might with their gay ne of the praise and glorie, become common to euerie particular nation, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one who had neede might buie of the same. Wherefore seeing the end was with their gayne the commoditie of all, let them not still keepe in this corner to make it rare &amp; excessiuely deere, least the people curse them: especiallie nowe that the famine of prouision to discerne of so many strifes and subtelties, to vnderstande and iudge of so many Treatises as are written both to hurte and benefite the worlde, both in regarde of matters ciuill and diuine, humane and spirituall, doeth daylie crie and call for it. Let them take heede also of open iniustice, for seeing the common vse and practise of all men in generall, both in reasoning to the purpose, and in speaking with some grace and elegancie, hath sowen the seede of these artes, why should not all reape where all haue sowen? at least, why should not some of euerie sorte gleane, though by their cunning they had purchased these artes, as corne fields proper to them selues? Vnlesse the more excellent and necessarie their commodities bee (as couetous men) they will be the more vnmercifull and nigardlie. Neither let them obiect against vs: A sword in a fooles hand: for besides that weapōs are not restrained &amp; tyed only to masters of fence, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> singing to musitions only: the simple play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of these treatises, which drawe men to no curiouse or doubtful discourses, but onely put them in minde of that which they may easilie seeke and knowe in most familiar examples with great fruit and delight, shall sufficientlie aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere for them selues in this behalfe: praying all men to vse them with some studie as their callings may suffer, to strengthen their iudgement, to discerne of the sayinges and writinges of other men, to keepe better that whiche they learne, and not beyond their gifte and callinge, to aduenture to a further vse then they can reache vnto. And thus much for the firste sorte.</p>
   <p>Concerning the seconde I will not deale with euery alteration and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, for some are such as I thinke the verie alteration considered with the common rules nowe receyued of the sounder sorte, to iudge by, will giue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient defence: the other more doubtfull and straunge, I will as brieflie and plainlie as I can mainteyne. Wherein if I go beyonde the capacitie or reach of the vnlearned, they are to be desired either to staye till they haue somewhat la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in these artes, or else not to trouble thē selues at all with this discourse, but leaue it to those for whose satisfaction chieflie it is written. And here our labour shalbe for the Logike: for the other I suppose neede not this defence, as hauing fewe and light alterations. Cōcerning the definition of Logike I will not striue whether well reasoning, which is reasoning accordinge to the arte, be conteyned in the generall of the definition, An arte or no, it is sufficient for me that in my definition there is a true generall, an arte, and a true full difference, by which it differeth from all other artes: namely that it is of reasoning. Nowe whether the proper ende be declared by the addition of well or no, I leaue it to those who will dispute of all the causes and not of the definition of Logike. For there is no reason why the ende of any thing should come into the definition any more then the efficient cause, when as the difference is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore full and sufficient. In inuention that is most generall, which concerneth the distribution of an argumente, that I make it not Artificiall and inartificiall, but firste and arising of the firste, and after deuide the latter into more artificiall,
<pb facs="3"/>
and lesse artificiall. At which none neede greatly to maruell, seeing that reason whiche by arte appeareth the greater force of an other reason to the weaker force it hath in it selfe, and so reasoneth more forcibly as doeth a testimonie, whose force the sayde dependeth vpon other argumentes, it must be both ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall, and arise in part of another: but because it hath neither his force in it selfe, nor arise perfectlie as a definition or diuision, but in parte onely from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argumentes. It may for both causes be well iudged to be an Argumente, arising imoerfectly of the firste, and so be called a lesse artificiall arising of the firste. The generall being touched, the difference in the causes aske the next place, where the referring of the ende vnto the efficient cause, wilbe odiouse: but if it be weighed that by this meanes, the trueth is preferred &amp; the doctrine of the ende which is not commonly discerned from the effect and adioynte, is more cleared, the gayne wil easilie recompence the alteration of the place. For seeing it is a cause onely as it bringeth some force to the verie beinge of the thing, and all the force it bringeth is to moue the efficient or making cause to worke, it followeth that in that respect onely it is a cause. If it be sayd, the end doeth not moue euerie efficient as the ende of naturall and artificiall thinges, as of the eye to see, the plūmet in a clok to force the next causes of the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie motion: the aunswere is, they are deceyued, for as it regardeth these artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall things, it is an effect of the doing of it, and an adiointe in regarde of the force wherewith it is done: and to these things it giueth or bringeth nothing, but receyueth and taketh all from them: but it is a cause onely as it was set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the author of nature, or the artificer to moue him to make this thing apte to this effecte, or to haue these properties: so that my sentence remayneth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarilie true. Neither doo I see what other respect of a cause it can haue, for that which some speake of the perfection it bringeth to the thing, is altogither vntrue, for all the perfection of the thing commeth from the efficient, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the matter and forme as the causes of the thing and the adiointes, as the ornamentes of it: In which respect this perfection is caused, and doeth not cause. The next to this is that the diuision of conceyuing and begetting cause is left out, and iustlie. For when as there ought to be no diuision, but that which ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of some difference of the partes betweene them selues, and of agreement with the whole, there being here no difference in the partes, because the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting cause is referred to procreation, as to his nexte effecte, and the conseruing or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing cause, as to his nexte effect to preseruation: in which respects they remaine onely simple as all others efficientes or making causes: it is to be inferred that they can make no distribution of the efficient cause.</p>
   <p>The like is to be saide, of working by it selfe and by chaunce, whiche make no difference of working or causing: for although in such the principall instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had no such ende or purpose, yet the chiefe worker GOD in his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath, besides this putteth no differēce in that force which bringeth forth effect, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> only betweene the purpose of the chiefe worker of the action, god:<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 11.</note> who worketh all things according to the counsell of his owne will, and the principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument who did it to another purpose. Next to these followe the difference in the disagreeing argumentes, where this is one and the chiefe, that the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of Contraries are lefte out: First into affirming and denying, whiche are no sortes of contraries, but of the manner of vttering contraries, whiche as it falleth not into Logike to handle, so it is nothing to this purpose, because the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb facs="4"/>
ariseth not from any distinction of the contrarietie it selfe, whiche it should doo, if they were diuerse sortes of contraries, but from the difference of expressing one and the same kinde. And this it yet more cleare in the eiuers sortes of these: for relatiues are no contraries, because the contrarietie lyeth in the deniall of the relation, not in the relation: neyther can it in that respecte be a newe sorte of contrarietie, for when all the repugnancie lyeth in these two regardes, the one that being sette as agreeing in the consideration of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to one, it muste be disagreeing &amp; opposite in the same cōsideration one to another, as if it agree with Iacob to be Isaaks father, it must disagree with Isaak to be so, this it hath from the generall nature of opposites, the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte being that one is set against one, that it hath from the generall rule of contrarietie, and further it repugneth not. If saye one it hath this proper that relatiues are here contrarie, the aunswere is that bringeth no newe kinde of contrarietie, and if this be a iust cause of a diuision of contraries, you may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide contraries agayne: some of causes, some of effectes, some of subiectes, and some of adiointes: seeing it maye be sayde, these are causes whiche are contrarie, as it sayde, these are relatiues which are contrarie.</p>
   <p>The like almost may be sayde of the priuatiues, which are contraries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one is naturallie in the subiect as the habite, and the other diueth out or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth it of the habite: for what newe sorte of contrarietie is here? Surely no other but that one is sette against one, for the beeing naturally or not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie in the subiecte, belongeth not the Logision to consider, but the seuerall Maister in his arte, as to the Phisition that health is naturally in the bodye and howe, that sickenes driueth that awaye, and howe: otherwise, why may we not make hurtfull contraries, whereof one is hurtfull to the subiecte, or profitable contraries, whereof one is profitable to the subiecte, as peace and warre to a common wealthe, Vice and vertue to the minder?</p>
   <p>Nowe lette vs consider of those others which they call contradictories, when one affirmeth, and the other denieth, as a man, not a man: iust, not iust. Concerninge these, when all the contrarietie (which they saye) is proper to them, lyeth eyther in the contradiction, it is, it is not: which is proper to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not to inuention, to sette foorth, or that one thing is opponed to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges which it is not: which is no contrarietie, but the opposition of disperates, seeing one is not opponed to one kinde, but one to many kindes, and that equallie, as a man opponed to not a man, is equallie opponed to spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, to fowles, fishes, beastes, vnsensible creatures, &amp;c. in the same not a man: wherefore it followeth, that eyther they must allowe my dooing, or else in the firste bring in confusion whylest they speake of that parte in one parte of the arte, which is proper to the other, and in the seconde confusion and follie both: whylest they make that a contrarie whiche is none, and without all gayne repeate that whiche they haue sufficientlie handled before. Neyther lette any saye they are contrarie, because their is no midle betweene man and not a man, for so there is not betweene man and other things, &amp; yet they are not contrarie but disperates only.</p>
   <p>And thus much for the firste argumentes.</p>
   <p>The leauing out of Notation and Coniugation remayneth onely to bee spoken of in Inuention, the reason whereof is manifest, because it is graunted of all that they haue no newe force, besides the firste, no newe reason or argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="4"/>
arising from the firste: For he is iust, he doeth iustlie, these are co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ingates, referre them one vnto an other, and what is their besides the cause and the effecte? What force or reason more? For that iust and iustlie are formed one of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, apperteyneth to Grammer, that they allude fitlie to the figure of Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike, called Poliptoton, which chaungeth finely the ende or case of wordes.</p>
   <p>The like is to be sayde of Notation, which is the interpretation of a name, which apperteyneth not to Logike but to Dictionaries: as in this, An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is so called, because it argueth, a faithefull man, because he hath faith: what force of reason is there in the first example? of the cause and the effect. What in the other? of the effect and the cause. But is there nothing else? yes. A fitte and elegant vttering of diuers things by wordes, not much, but some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what differing in sounde, as argument, arguing, fayth, faythfull: but this is neither reason, nor newe force of reason; but onely an elegancie of the Trope called Paranomasia, or chaunge of the name. Wherefore let vs keepe them no longer, nowe the honour claymeth them, but according to the lawe turne them home agayne. Thus much for inuention: As for the chaunge in a testimonie, I am contente to leaue it vnto the iudgement of the reader, when hee shall examine it according to the rules of Logike: as also those small differences which are in the seconde parte of Logike, for in that sometimes the firste sorte of a Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logisme is founde in all his partes, there is nowe no longer any reason to trase him vppe onely in an Enthimeme. And thus much for the satisfying of both these sortes. Nowe, if they be not fullie contented, my desire is of the former to beare with that, for the commoditie of others, whiche them selues like not. The other sorte also I praye, to satisfie them selues in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and bettering that which can not yet sufficientlie please them. And so I committe thee to the direction of God his Spirite, whom I praye so to increase thy knowledge by all good and lawfull meanes, as thou mayest discerne things that differ, and walke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence, vntill the day of the Lorde.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>