<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL, BOVN∣tifull and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Elizabeth Hatton, Wife to the right Worshipfull Sir William Hatton Knight, increase of all honorable vertues.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2695_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02132</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12271</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2695</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL, BOVN∣tifull and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Elizabeth Hatton, Wife to the right Worshipfull Sir William Hatton Knight, increase of all honorable vertues.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A maidens dreame : Vpon the death of the right honorable Sir Christopher Hatton Knight, late Lord Chancelor of England. By Robert Green Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Nelson, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL, BOVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and vertuous Ladie, the Ladie Elizabeth Hatton, Wife to the right Worshipfull Sir William Hatton Knight, increase of all honorable vertues.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ourning as well as many (right Worshipfull La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die) for the late losse of the right Honorable your deceased Vnckle, whose death being the common preiudice of a present age, was lamented of most (if not all) and I among the rest sorrowing that my Countrie was depriued of him that liued not for himselfe, but for his Countrie, I began to call to mind what a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect was ministred to the excellent wits of both Vniuersities to work vpon, when so worthie a knight, and so vertuous a Iusticiarie, had by his death left many memorable actions performed in his life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing highly by some rare men to be registred. Passing ouer many daies in this muse, at last I perceiued mens humors slept, that loue of many friends followed no farther then their graues, that Art was growen idle, and either choice schollers feared to write of so high a subiect as his vertues, or else they dated their deuotions no further then his life. While thus I debated with my selfe, I might see (to the great disgrace of the Poets of our time) some Mycanicall wits blow vp mountaines, and bring forth mise, who with their follies did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther disparage his Honors, than decypher his vertues: beside, as <hi>Virtutis comes est inuidia,</hi> so base report who hath her tong bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered by slanderous enuie, began as farre as she durst, now after his death, to murmure, who in his life time durst not once mutter: whervpon touched with a Zealous iealousie ouer his wonderfull ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, I could not, whatsoeuer discredit I reapt by my presumption, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I did <hi>Tenui Auena meditari,</hi> but discouer the honorable
<pb facs="3"/>
qualities of so worthie a Counsellor, not for anie priuat benefit I euer had of him, which should induce me fauorably to flatter his worthie partes, but onely that I shame to let slip with silence, the vertues and honors of so worthie a knight, whose deserts had bin so many and so great towards al. Therfore (right worshipful Ladie) I drewe a fictiō called <hi>A Maidens Dreame,</hi> which as it is <hi>Enigmaticall,</hi> so it is not without some speciall and considerate reasons. Whose slender <hi>Muse</hi> I present vnto your Ladiship, induced therunto, first, that I know you are partaker of your husbands sorrowes, for the death of his honourable Vncle, and desire to heare his honors put in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie after his death, as you wished his aduancement in vertues to be great in his life: as also that I am your Ladiships poore Countrimā, and haue long time desired to gratifie your right worshipfull father with some thing worthie himselfe. Which because I could not to my content performe, I haue now taken oportunitie to shew my duetie to him in his daughter, although the gift be farre too meane for so worshipfull and vertuous a Lady. Yet hoping your Ladishippe will with courtesie fauour my presuming follies, and in gratious acceptance vouch of my well meant labours, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Ladiships humbly at commaund R.</hi> Greene. Nordouicensis.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>