<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface vpon the hi∣storicall discourse of the Grammer warre, first made in Latin by the learned Lord Andrew Guarna of Salerne, and after translated into Frenche, and now for the worthinesse of the histo¦rie turned into English.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2699_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02288</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12419</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2699</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface vpon the hi∣storicall discourse of the Grammer warre, first made in Latin by the learned Lord Andrew Guarna of Salerne, and after translated into Frenche, and now for the worthinesse of the histo¦rie turned into English.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bellum grammaticale : a discourse of great war and dissention betwene two worthy princes, the noune and the uerbe, contending for the chefe place or dignitie in oration : very pleasant &amp; profitable turned into English by W.H</title>
                 <author>Guarna, Andrea</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Pickering, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>95 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Preface vpon the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall discourse of the Grammer warre,</hi> first made in Latin by the learned Lord <hi>Andrew Guarna of Salerne, and after</hi> translated into Frenche, and now for the worthinesse of the histo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie turned into English.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He first and auncient Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers that wrote their Poesies couertly hidden vnder subtile and wily matter, dydde consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>Pallas</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> borne in hir Soueraigne heade to be goddesse of wisedome sayd <hi>Minerue,</hi> and of warre, called <hi>Enyo</hi> or <hi>Bellona.</hi> Gyuing hereby to vnderstande that of one and the same beginning, in one time altogether and in one substance are two principall things inseparately ioyned together: whiche two properties are so knitte, that the one wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other is of no force, and the other without his fellow, of smal or no accompt: Yea, they are the principles whereby men attayne to the top of honoure, and famous felicitie, aduauncing meane men to honor
<pb facs="9"/>
in their life time, and immortall fame after death. They are learnyng and martial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wesse. Of these two together Noble Grece made separation in his two metropolitanes when the Citie of Athens florished in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the citie of Sparta or Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia glorious in feates of armes. The noble fame of the Romains grew by the one, and by the other they did alwayes defend them, so that they dyd successiuely greately sette store by them. The worthie, valiaunt, and myghtie Eloquent <hi>Caesar</hi> was decored with them bothe, and by them dyd eternise hys Renoune. Beholde (gentle Reader) nowe these two so worthie things, whiche are no lesse principals to the gouernement of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, Realmes, Reipublikes, and for all es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of the world to be aptely vnderstode, which did so much ennoble Grece, so gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour the Romaines, and eternise the fame of the great <hi>Caesar,</hi> are in this present small volume comprised, compact together by the industrious and pleasaunt Artifice of the firste Authour, vnder an angry Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and Historicall narration of the Grammer warre, of this pleasaunt and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured
<pb facs="9"/>
historie, no lesse profitable than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable. <hi>Lucian</hi> an eloquent Greke Auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor made the first draughtes in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle of the Alphabet letters: but this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath waded further euen vnto verbes and Nounes, being principall heades of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and to the adherents of speach, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the congruate worde, (being the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pener and the declaratiue of the sense) as otherwise, wherin resteth al arte and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, wherin also all the wisedome of man is comprised: shaping and fourming these two heades, and the auxiliate ayding par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with such fayned personages and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie properties so apt and to them so quicke in qualitie, that hee giueth life, bodie, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon and armour to deade wordes, yea, and sounding voyce, to substances inanimate and without soule: so that the Reader in the lecture of this (though fayned) narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dreadfull discouerie, shall deeme them no more to be vocall wordes, but by a strong iudgement shall thinke them dap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlye disguised, being transfourmed into liuelie persone, going, speaking, and sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly resoning with continuall terrors of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb facs="10"/>
expedicion and exploites, with alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall conflictes of bloudie battaile, not onelie in hostile contention abroade, but also in ciuile, yea, and intestine Warres at home: so that in the discouerie hereof he is nothing obliuious of anye thing that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth to the deduction and safe gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of so great affaires, euen from the first causes and entermixed medlies of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures, vnto the last ende of all their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes and endeuors, with all their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, all their tumults and vproares, with their doubtfulnesse of victory among manie martialistes, how of bloudie battaile diuers losse and daungers doe followe, and how in the ende finall peace ensueth. All which matters be so properlie penned, and so cunningly compact in this tragedie, that the warres of the Peloponnenses, and the ciuile warres of the Affricanes in Thucide, in Salust, &amp; Lucan, are peraduenture more high and diffusedlye described: But with more arte or more compendiouslye, I am sure they are not. So that it is sothly to be saide, that our Author through the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his learned wisedome, doth as the
<pb facs="10"/>
good Geometricians doe, which the inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible greatnesse of the heauens &amp; the earth do reduce in a simple circuit, describing the same in a small sphere or manuel compasse. So hee hath placed the mightie, huge, and fearefull factes of armes vnder the figure of so small a thing as of the congruitie or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordaunce of words in oracion, ioyning let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with weapons, teaching the arte mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taire with the arte litteraire, so well, and so exactlye, that the reader beside the delyght and pleasure that he shall haue in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of so pleasaunt an Allegorie, shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue further benefite: for herein is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented in one conteipt two vnderstandings knit togither, the one proper and naturall, the other tropique and figured. Beside this, he shall comprehende in this same ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie substance and by the onely labor of one reading, those two so worthy things aboue remembred, that doe eternise the fame of their fellowes, that is louers of learning, and prudent martialistes. The science litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raire, and militaire, that is to say, the arte of Grammer, yea the graundmother of al arts and sciences, and the arte militaire of dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="11"/>
warres, vnder pleasaunt Metaphoricall figures, transported and tourned, berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the minde of the litterall vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of small things verball, to the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of greater, more royall and reall, doth manifestly shewe by example the ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mouings, the imperiate desire of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to haue gouernment, the tumultes and parcialities of peoples, the profitable and peruerse counsaile of sundrye counsailers, the seemely sentences, and modest messages of the artificiall erraundes on both partes, their enterprised attemptes &amp; martiall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the somoning of souldiers, the chartes of defiaunce, the denouncing of Heraldes, the high and statelie stomackes of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse parties readie to ioyne Battaile, the seeking of alliaunce in extremitie, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact confederated of cuntrimen, the flights, treasons, espies, embushements their sodain entrappes and skirmishes, the ordinaunces of armes, the placing of the campe, the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of their arrayes, the noble chering of the captaines to their souldiers, the taking of tovvnes, the marching of their men, the cruell conflicts and worthy feates of armes
<pb facs="11"/>
on all sides, the lamentable losse of Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, the cruel combat of the fighters, the great slaughter on both partes, the fearefull flying on all sides, the doubtfull meetinges of many, the indifferencie of their victory, and the finall pernitious accidents that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue through the wars to both sides, the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, the reauing, the rapme and disorder that is then in vre, the depopuling of inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate cuntries, the desolate destruction that diuers are damnified by the commodities and aduantages that one realme enioyeth throughe the detriment of an other: and contrarily the infinite vtilities that ensue, thorowe peace and concorde, to all realmes and reipublikes. All which things are by wonderfull cunning, and pleasaunt fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, by most exquisite rule and perfect methode, treated summarily in this booke, first written in his owne and pure Latine tongue, and after (for the pleasure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that therein may be gathered) was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into our english tongue, through the commaundement of a learned personage, one who is no lesse a louer of learning, than vertuous in condition, who for the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="12"/>
of his example is to be followed as a meete patrone of humaine curtesie.</p>
   <p>Wherefore (gentle reader) when thou art delighted with the profitable lecture of this historicall discourse, attribute the thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of thy good wil to be the causer of this english translation, wherin albeit that there be not the same sweetenesse in our phrase that it hath in his owne tongue, yet I doubt not but it shall seeme that I digresse but ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silie from mine Aucthor: For as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned knowe, it is an absurde and harde mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in this treatise properlie to english the greatest part of those words that touch the argument in apt phrase correspondent to the Latin, sithens the same coulde not bee done by a learned translator into the french, which tongue doeth nearer appropriate it than ours: Therefore whereas of some I may be thought little to alter in translation from the latine Aucthor, therein may the Reader iudge me to followe the Frenche phrase who is my patrone partly in most of my translation, and when I shall seme in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie point to digresse from the french tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slator, I doe it the nearer to followe the first
<pb facs="12"/>
Aucthor, so that the Reader I hope wyll iudge indifferently of my doings. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my translation I thought it requisit (yea, and also no lesse necessarie) to leaue the most parte of the wordes of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their owne tongue, especiallye for that this discourse of the Grammer warre was made vpon the Grammer of the latine tongue first, and not of the french. VVhat will it then auayle (will some saye) to haue translated it into english? whereto in the first place it may thus be aunswered, that for that it was the free good wil of the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slator, that in hys labour on this behalfe thought not to offend, neither to do wrong or displeasure to any, but that through hys meane the simple and vnlearned englishe readers, aswell as the learned latinists, might enioy part of the pleasure that is had in the lecture of this delectable discourse of this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured warre, and bloudlesse battaile, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mortall shot, sweate or Cannon poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And furthermore that his meaning was, for the vtilitie of our english children beginning to studie the latine tongue, who reading this pleasaunt fight in their ovvne
<pb facs="13"/>
tong (as the French in theirs) might learne by waye of mirth and merrie pastime, the principal pointes of the Romayne Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: Finally the same might serue for an exempler aswell historicall for the instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and guide of martiall affaires, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, therin to consider the harmes that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue thorowe the dissention of Princes and great Lords, parents, kinsmen or neighbors, how the communalties of realmes and cū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries can not easelye profite in anye wealth and aboundance, without trafike and quiet passages one to another, and howe dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion procureth diuerse dangerous damma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to them and theirs: Shewing also on the other side the singular benefites that peace procureth, what commodities are enioyed by the vniformitie of kings &amp; Princes raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in one regiment or country louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly togither in one faith, lawe, and tongue, friendly as one: which things (as I suppose) are the principall causes whye this booke was first compiled by mine aucthor, which by chaunce happening into my handes, and by me ouer redde, to my singular delight in both tongues, determined with my selfe to
<pb facs="13"/>
participate parte of my vnderstanding to the youth of my nation, thorowe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of a friende, who might haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded me. VVherefore if I espie the friendlie receipt hereof, in no lesse grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parte, than it was friendly fauoured of some, I shall be the readier encouraged to bid thee hereafter to some better banquet, in the meane whyle let the courteous rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vse a friendly guestes parte, not misly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any thing that is set freely before him. And albeit that this my translation be not so exquisitly englished on my parte as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better learned can doe, yet in considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my painefull good will, I doubt not your friendly receipt of the same. And thoughe that the french tongue (whereout I extracted this worke) in adages and breef termes haue an easier conclusion of speach than our english tongue, yet let the Reader be assured what soeuer termes be altered (if any be) the matter is perfite, pleasaunt and profitable to the reader, and much matter contayned in this small Booke, both of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and delicate lyking, such as the gentle reader maye gather great fruite, wisedome,
<pb facs="14"/>
and worthinesse by, if hee applie his dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence therevnto. And for my parte I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed my labours in this behalfe, not to winne fame or fauour, but to bestowe my leysures well and to fruitfull exercise, to the benefit of my countrey men, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corage those that can doe better to the like exercise. And if any vnfit wordes happen to be espied of better and more eloquent heades, yet I trust that such will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a good worke, for an ill wrighter, neyther a good worde for an ill spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. What or howe effectuall matter is contayned in this Booke, in the sequele is manifest.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>