<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Sir EDWARD COOKE, Knight, one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
           <author>Hering, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2728_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13203.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2728</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Sir EDWARD COOKE, Knight, one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
                 <author>Hering, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Panacea Christiana, or, A Christians soueraigne salue for euery soare : deliuered in two seuerall sermons, and now digested into one treatise : published for the vse of all distressed Christians</title>
                 <author>Hering, Theodore</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bird, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 92, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Sir EDWARD COOKE, <hi>Knight, one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Esides those common enducements which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with others (your Honours more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary zeale and affection to Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Pietie) there are some pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate obligations which haue moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to consecrate the first fruits of my Labours, to your Patronage. It was their command, to whom I owe not obedience and respect on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="3"/> but my-selfe also, that first expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed these lines to the censure of the World, and then shrouded them vnder the shelter of your Winges. For the subiect matter,<note place="margin">Vtinam tam commodum quam acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum.</note> as it suites well with the times; so I presume it will not bee vnwelcome to your Honour. A word in his place, as the Wiseman obserues) <hi>is like Apples of Gold,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 25, 11.</note>
      <hi>with pictures of Siluer.</hi> If this Theame bee not now seasonable, when will it bee? The Church of God goes to wracke abroad: many miseries and calamities presse vs sore at home, &amp; our sinnes threaten more and worse. Satan rageth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his time is but short; his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments flourish: the wicked are in their ruffe, the godly vnderfoot, despised, trampled vpon. The old complaint is not vniustly renewed, that it fals out, <hi>Bonis malè, malis benè,
<pb facs="3"/> Well with the Bad, ill with the Good.</hi> Is it not now high time to minister a word of comfort to them <hi>that mourn in Sion?</hi> What greater comfort then this Oracle from Heauen; <hi>All shall worke to the Best of them that loue God?</hi> Of which number, the Church of God hath good cause to esteeme your Honor, who haue tasted with your Brethren, this <hi>bitter Cup,</hi> and therefore can rellish these <hi>Sweetes</hi> the better. For my part, I know not how to testifie my respects other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then in these kind of Presents, and my hearty prayers for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of your Honour and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which shal neuer be wanting from</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors most humble obseruance,</hi> Th: Hering.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>