<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2728_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13203.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2728</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Panacea Christiana, or, A Christians soueraigne salue for euery soare : deliuered in two seuerall sermons, and now digested into one treatise : published for the vse of all distressed Christians</title>
                 <author>Hering, Theodore</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bird, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 92, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader;</hi> This smal Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate was so penned, as Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; and so Preached, as thou mayest easily guesse, it was neuer inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for ostentation, but for aedification. Jf thou look'st for many Citations and Quotations of <hi>Authors,</hi> thou deceyuest thy Selfe. It was my Ambition (J con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) to draw water out of the fountains, rather then out of the streames. <hi>Dulcius ex ipso fonte bibuntur aquae.</hi> Man purposeth, but God disposeth. The truth is, violence and importunity wrung this for the Presse, which was intended soly for the Pulpit. I know there is great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene a liuing vice, and a dead Letter, as betweene a body anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and a painted body. I know this Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and Censorious Age, will giue but
<pb facs="5"/> harsh entertainment to such a rude and vnpolished <hi>Treatise,</hi> and deeme it more fit to be suppressed in a corner, then to be published to the World; yet my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, A <hi>Widdowes Mite</hi> will find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation with the Searcher of the heart. Besides, J had rather seeme too forward in putting out my Masters money to the Bankers, then to vndergo the Doome of an euill Seruant, for smothering his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in a Napkin. All Starres are not of the same magnitude, yet euery Starre shines in his owne Orbe. If some beames of Comfort conueyghed in these cursorie Meditations, may warme and enliuen any poore drooping disconsolate Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, J haue my ayme, let God haue the Honour and Glory. As <hi>all things,</hi> so this (J hope) <hi>shall worke to the Best.</hi> Read, and consider. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>