<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL And vertuous Gentle∣woman, Mris Dorothey Kyrton of Thrup in Nor∣thampton-shire; All happinesse be mul∣tiplied.</title>
           <author>Huit, Ephraim</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2749_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL And vertuous Gentle∣woman, Mris Dorothey Kyrton of Thrup in Nor∣thampton-shire; All happinesse be mul∣tiplied.</title>
                 <author>Huit, Ephraim</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomy of conscience, or, The summe of Pauls regeneracy : wherein are handled the places of conscience, worship, and scandall, with diuerse rules of Christian practise : very profitable for the weake Christian by Ephraim Huit</title>
                 <author>Huit, Ephraim</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 405 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL And vertuous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
      <hi>Dorothey Kyrton</hi> of <hi>Thrup</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi>-shire; All happinesse be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Find it an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable <hi>Custome,</hi> (Right Worshipfull) in causes of this nature to Dedicate to some wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="3"/>Personage, of <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent note,</hi> those their <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> which yet they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to communicate to the publicke vse of others, either to testifie thankfulness in returne of kindnesses receiued, or to further them in speciall in some good, tending to their <hi>spirituall aduantage;</hi> or lastly, to countenance their <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> against the iniuries of persons ill affected to the <hi>Truth.</hi> This last <hi>respect</hi> is of least vse in these <hi>Halcion dayes of the Gospell,</hi> especially, with vs in
<pb facs="3"/>this Kingdome, where the <hi>Scepter</hi> it selfe is both a Patrone, and practiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of vertue and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The two former Reasons sway my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions (formerly in a disway) to ascribe these my poore <hi>Endeuors,</hi> to your both <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Comfort;</hi> and diuerse weightie Considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons emboldening, and obligeing me hereto. 1. That kind <hi>Respect,</hi> and <hi>Encouragement,</hi> both my selfe, and more worthy <hi>Predecessor,</hi> haue found from your both atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="4"/>countenance, and liberall Contribution, hath deuoted me to the <hi>seruice of your faith.</hi> 2. In that this Subject imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of it in the place of my <hi>Ministery,</hi> was so kindly welcommed by your selfe, and others in your <hi>Family:</hi> a Coppy her of being taken from my mouth, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of your three Neeces, I presume the <hi>Originall Coppy,</hi> being far more perfect, will finde much more gracious entertainment.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>Thirdly, (vnlesse I mistake your <hi>spirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state</hi>) this <hi>Treatise of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> may much further your <hi>Comfort</hi> in <hi>Christ.</hi> Many an honest hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Christian writes bitter things against himselfe,</hi> fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on <hi>Ashes</hi> in stead of <hi>Cordialls.</hi> And this, not for want of <hi>Right,</hi> but <hi>abilitie</hi> to apply their owne promises. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member vpon confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, you haue expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed perplexitie of <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> for want of <hi>assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> A spirituall <hi>sicknesse</hi> of the soule it is indeed,
<pb facs="5"/>but <hi>Ague-like,</hi> it tends not to the impaire, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of health to the whole: a blessed <hi>vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie,</hi> arising from the sense of our owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthinesse, and desire of nearer <hi>cōmunion</hi> with God. But how (you will say) may this <hi>Tract of Conscience</hi> Cure this so great a maladie? Yes, very fitly: this trouble (as I conceiue) arising not from want of <hi>eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> but <hi>skill</hi> in the <hi>Schoole</hi> of <hi>Christ. Conscience</hi> is a discursiue <hi>power,</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting, and applying
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>particular Conclusions</hi> out of <hi>generall promises,</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so by Reflecting on it selfe, discernes in the life the fruits of <hi>holinesse,</hi> and infallible <hi>Characters</hi> of <hi>grace;</hi> from which it gathereth as certaine Demonstrations of <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie,</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>blessednesse,</hi> as either <hi>sense,</hi> or immediate <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration</hi> can haue. Its one thing to <hi>beleeue,</hi> another to discerne the <hi>worke of faith</hi> in vs; the latter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires much <hi>Christian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> and some fruits of <hi>sanctification.</hi> So that
<pb facs="6"/>the true vnderstanding of <hi>Conscience</hi> working in vs, may further our Christian comfort by acquainting vs with the <hi>vprightnesse</hi> of our owne hearts. Vnto your selfe therefore I first cōmend these first fruits of my <hi>Labours</hi> in this kind, for your edification in our <hi>most holy faith,</hi> &amp; encrease of our <hi>Ioy</hi> here, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of <hi>happinesse</hi> with Christ hereafter. Desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous also vnder your vaile it may see light, that others who want the knowledge of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="6"/>helpes, or meanes to procure greater <hi>volumes,</hi> may receiue some <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> refreshing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you shall performe an office of <hi>loue</hi> to me, and of <hi>Comfort</hi> to the Church of Christ, in whose perfection my joyes will surpasse my paines, and Gods glory especially shine forth, in the improouement of my <hi>Talent</hi> to the <hi>truths</hi> aduantage.</p>
   <p>Make vse then of these my <hi>Endeuours,</hi> and other like <hi>Christian</hi> helps, for the enliuing of your
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>zeale,</hi> and furtherance of a well ordered <hi>Conuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Wherein you shall both answere the good opinion I haue, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may haue of your vertuous dispositiō, but also perfect the worke of your owne <hi>saluation,</hi> to the <hi>day of the Lord Iesus.</hi> To whose gracious prouidence, be you and yours euer commended by me.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Knoll</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 20.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in the Faith, <hi>EPHRAIM HVIT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>