<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To diuerse Christi∣an friends in Cheshire, the Authors commen∣dation of his Booke.</title>
           <author>Huit, Ephraim</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2749_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To diuerse Christi∣an friends in Cheshire, the Authors commen∣dation of his Booke.</title>
                 <author>Huit, Ephraim</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomy of conscience, or, The summe of Pauls regeneracy : wherein are handled the places of conscience, worship, and scandall, with diuerse rules of Christian practise : very profitable for the weake Christian by Ephraim Huit</title>
                 <author>Huit, Ephraim</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 405 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To diuerse Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an friends in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> the <hi>Authors</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Apology (deare friends) to such as may blame me herein, is your excessiue Importunity, who will witnesse with me, how many Repulses you haue bidden, or euer I yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to gratifie your desires, in the publication of these my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digested <hi>Meditations.</hi> I of all others might haue beene spared in this <hi>scribling age,</hi> (wherein so much leuitie and ostentation
<pb facs="8"/>in causes of this nature is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant) who am most vnfit, both for the priuacy of my gifts, and esteeme; as also of the Retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of disposition. To say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of my great Imployment, and encombrance aboue many, yet, sith I am ouer-treated here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, let others Iudge of what force your <hi>Motiues,</hi> and my <hi>Inducements</hi> were hereto.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> Your first <hi>plea</hi> was, that bond of <hi>mutuall affection,</hi> continued with tender, and <hi>Christian</hi> Respect for the space (well nigh) of three yeares, wherein I was an vnworthy <hi>Minister</hi> of the <hi>Word</hi> amongst you.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> Besides, you alledge this subiect of <hi>Conscience</hi> was first handl d amōgst you, which <hi>Medications</hi> after reuised, &amp; enlarged in the place of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Charge,</hi> I sent you for your furtherance of <hi>Ioy</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi> Whence you seeme to claime an Interest in my <hi>Ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours</hi> herein.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> When I sent you the <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> hereof, my <hi>Restrictions</hi> you challēge to be very harsh, which though I vsed to preuent abuse, fearing least some <hi>Coppy</hi> should be thrust into the Presse without my priuity, yet withall, they hindered you of that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and communitie of vse, you much desired hereof.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> Lastly, I left you (you say) in sorrow; my departure so sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and vnexpected caused you (that I say not my selfe) much griefe of heart: in lieu whereof I might seeme indebted to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour your <hi>Reconsolation:</hi> to these your <hi>Claimes,</hi> this you affirme addeth <hi>weight,</hi> that <hi>all
<pb facs="9"/>are yours,</hi> whether <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos,</hi> the <hi>gifts</hi> of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery</hi> are the Churches <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Royaltie,</hi> and must be so dispensed, as may best serue her comfort.</p>
   <p>These and the like <hi>Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> swayed my approbation, when I had not the least thought of submitting my <hi>Labours</hi> to the publicke view, or censure. The same forme I vsed in the <hi>Deliuery,</hi> I still retaine, which how euer it may seeme rude to others of better <hi>deserts,</hi> yet I am well assured, is most <hi>famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar</hi> to you, &amp; consequently, most profitable, whose <hi>pure mindes I stirre vp by putting you in Remembrance of the things you haue formerly heard.</hi> To you therefore I commend these my <hi>Labours,</hi> and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, to whom if I should beast
<pb facs="9"/>something of my <hi>Industry</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I should not yet seeme vaine, Let your improouement of them equalize my desire of your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, who so long doe liue <hi>as ye stand fast in the Lord.</hi> Here you haue <hi>Pauls Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy</hi> Anatomized, the <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of Religion</hi> explained, enforced, the <hi>Power of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> with its contrary qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of <hi>good</hi> and <hi>euill</hi> vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: besides, the heads of <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall,</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, with as much breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and dexteritie, as I in my poore <hi>modell</hi> could deuise. How vsefull this <hi>Subject</hi> is, let others Iudge; it sufficieth me, I neuer knew these things fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly and fully handled, at least in so small a <hi>Volume.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherefore sith your <hi>vse</hi> was in a speciall manner Intended,
<pb facs="10"/>you may Iustly be challenged of neglect, in case these lines want either <hi>well-come,</hi> or diligent <hi>obseruance,</hi> in that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of these <hi>Morall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations,</hi> may compose a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate <hi>Christian</hi> life; in which care of yours, I shall take my selfe fully satisfied for the paines I haue taken herein, and your selues the principall gainers by me, who am deuoted to the</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Knoll <date>
            <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb. 20.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Seruice of your faith, EPHRAIM HVIT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>