<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FA∣THER IN GOD, John, Lord Bishop of Chester, my singular good Lord and Patron.</title>
           <author>Hyatt, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2753_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14038</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FA∣THER IN GOD, John, Lord Bishop of Chester, my singular good Lord and Patron.</title>
                 <author>Hyatt, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The preachers president, or, The master and scholler : In a sermon preached at a synode, holden by the Right Reuerend Father in God, Iohn, Lord Bishop of Chester, at Wigan in Lancashire, the 21. of Aprill. 1625. By Iames Hyatt, B. of D. and preacher of Gods word at Liuer-poole</title>
                 <author>Hyatt, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 19, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER <hi>IN</hi> GOD, <hi>John,</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Chester,</hi> my singular good Lord and Patron.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY GOOD LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N obedience to your Lordships pleasure, I doe here humbly present you with that Sermon, which I lately preacht, by your Lordships ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, at <hi>Wigan:</hi> my little leasure, and health at that time, and my lesse skill for such a businesse, made me very vnwilling to vnder-take it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conscious to my selfe that I should not sufficiently discharge it: but your Lordships authoritic imposing it vpon mee, brought me to a necessitie of performing it, as I could; and when I had done it, your Lordship was pleased (to my great incouragement) not onely to speake well of it, but to require a re-view of it from mine hand and pen: And, indeed your fauour and goodnesse to me and mine, hath beene such, and taken so deepe impression in mine heart, that I shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>haue power to denie, whatsoeuer it shall please your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to command, or expect from me, though otherwise, I could rather haue wisht that it might haue slept with me in silence. For, it may be, those defects will be spyed in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which were not so easily obserued in the hearing of it.</p>
   <p>I confesse that the <hi>matter</hi> is, much of it, gathered from others, onely the <hi>method</hi> is mine owne, and if it proue therefore lesse acceptable to some, who by this meanes may chance to haue a sight of it, yet I am confident, that this shall bring no losse to it, in your Lordships acceptation: as well knowing that the <hi>Spiders web</hi> is no whit the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, because it is all wouen out of her owne bowells; nor the <hi>Bee's honey</hi> lesse pleasant and vsefull, because it is gathered from seuerall flowers.</p>
   <p>Whatsoeuer it be, I now commit it to your Lordships Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, humbly desiring (seeing it hath found grace in your eyes) that it may safely shelter it selfe vnder your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and continue with you, if for no other vse, yet as a faithfull pledge of mine hearts thankfulnesse, which hath for euer vowed it selfe to your Lordships ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ice.</p>
   <p>And now, crauing pardon for this boldnesse, I humbly commend your good Lordship to the mercy of God in Christ Iesus, beseeching him, vpon the bended knees of mine heart, to blesse you with health, long life, and happy dayes vpon earth, to his glorie and his Churches good, and with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie hereafter in his heauenly Kingdome.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humbly deuoted Chaplaine, IAMES HYATT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>