<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Anagram upon the Name of the right worshipfull, Sr. Thomas Bowes, Knight, presented to the worshipfull young gentleman, his son and heire, Mr. Thomas Bowes Esquire.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S280_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4863.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S280</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Anagram upon the Name of the right worshipfull, Sr. Thomas Bowes, Knight, presented to the worshipfull young gentleman, his son and heire, Mr. Thomas Bowes Esquire.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Marcus Ausonius his foure bookes of morall precepts, intituled Cato : concerning the precepts of common life. Translated out of Latin hexamiters into English meter by Walter Gosnold Gentleman, servant unto the right worshipfull Sr. Thomas Bowes of Much-bromley hall in Essex</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="brief_poems">
   <div type="anagram_and_acrostic">
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <head>An Anagram upon the Name of the right worshipfull, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Bowes,</hi> Knight, presented to the worshipfull young gentleman, his son and heire, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Bowes</hi> Esquire.</head>
      <list type="anagram">
         <head>Anagram</head>
         <item>THOMA BOWES</item>
         <item>Beatus Homo.</item>
      </list>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>T</hi> ruth, justice, valour, equity, and right</l>
         <l>
            <hi>H</hi> e holds in hand, to doe his country good:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>O</hi> bedient to Gods Lawes, both day and night</l>
         <l>
            <hi>M</hi> aintaining love, in every brotherhood,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>A</hi> lmes deeds, where need requires, he is not slacke</l>
         <l>
            <hi>S</hi> o helpfull to the poore he is that lacke.</l>
         <l>
            <hi>B</hi> elov'd he is of all, hated of none,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>O</hi> nely the bad, because he sinne reproves</l>
         <l>
            <hi>W</hi> here wickednesse is, he doth still bemone</l>
         <l>
            <hi>E</hi> arth wants more such, whose days are but a span</l>
         <l>
            <hi>S</hi> uch like as these, foreshew a blessed man.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="epigram">
      <head>An Epigram upon him that shall finde fault with this Anagram.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>You of this Anagram may disallow,</l>
         <l>The reason is, because thete wanteth you,</l>
         <l>If you be it, that makes my Anagram not right,</l>
         <l>I'le put in you, and then my Anagram is right.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="epigram">
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <head>Another to Momus.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>O Momus why, why doe you scoffe at me?</l>
         <l>In spying faults, where is no faults to see;</l>
         <l>If you doe spoile this Anagram of mine,</l>
         <l>Why blam'st thou me, when as the fault is thine?</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="epigram">
      <head>Another Epigram.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>Some squibbing at my Anagram, said it was wrōg,</l>
         <l>Much like my vers, either too short or else too long</l>
         <l>Say what they will, there wants but halfe a letter,</l>
         <l>Take pen &amp; mendit, and Ile remaine their debter.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="epigram">
      <head>To the envious Reader.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>Pale faced Reader, dost thou envie me?</l>
         <l>I thought thou wouldst have sought hier to clime</l>
         <l>More fitting for your place and pedigree,</l>
         <l>Then to looke downe so low, to view my rime;</l>
         <l>If it be so, 'gainst nature you will see't</l>
         <l>You, face to face, my verse shall dare to meet.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <div type="anagram">
      <head>An Anagram upon the Name of the vertuous and wel disposed young gentlewomen, my much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured friend, and loving kinswoman, Mistresse <hi>Elizabeth Barington,</hi>
      </head>
      <argument>
         <p>wherein is lively set forth the rebellion and daily opposition betwixt the flesh and spirit, nature and grace in the best of
<pb facs="14"/>
Gods children, being more prone by nature to that which is ill, then by grace unto that which is good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 21.</p>
      </argument>
      <q>A good Name is better than great riches, and it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever, <bibl>Prov. 22. 1 Ecclus. 41. 13.</bibl>
      </q>
      <p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>
                  <q>Our Names are written in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <bibl>Luk. 10. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </cell>
               <cell>ELIZABETH BARINGTON.</cell>
               <cell>
                  <q>God exalteth the names of such as keepe his Law. <bibl>Deut. 26. 19.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <table>
            <head>ANAGRAM.</head>
            <row>
               <cell>
                  <q>The spirit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving concerning the inner Man, in mymind, I delight in the Law of God, <bibl>Rom. 7. 22.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </cell>
               <cell>On, git zeale in heart.</cell>
               <cell>
                  <q>Godly sorrow worketh zeale in us, <bibl>2 Cor. 7. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Its good to be zealous in a good thing <bibl>Gal. 4. 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
OR, The flesh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting.
<table>
            <row>
               <cell>
                  <q>O, who shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver mee from this body of sin? The good that I would, that doe I not, but that I wold not do, that do I, <bibl>Rom. 7. 19.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </cell>
               <cell>Git no zeale in heart.</cell>
               <cell>
                  <q>There is a zeale not according to knowledge, <bibl>Rom. 10. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
      </p>
      <p>Thus the flesh stayeth, even the most perfect to goe forward. By nature wee are the children of wrath, sold under sin: but by grace are we made righteous before God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. 5. <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. 24. &amp; 7. 14.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>