<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2803_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17238.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2803</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An amulet or preservative against sicknes and death : in two parts : the first containing spirituall direction for the sicke at all times needfull, but especially in the conflict of sicknes and agonie of death : the second, a method or order of comforting the sicke ... collected and set forth ... by A.M. minister of the Word of God in Henley vpon Thames ; whereunto is annexed a most pithie and comfortable sermon of mortalitie, written by the blessed martyr S. Cyprian Bishop of Carthage, translated into English by A.M. ; together with sundry prayers needfull in time of sicknesse</title>
                 <author>Man, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 316 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>A preface to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He sicknesses and diseases which vexe and annoy these our mortall bodies, together with the remembrance of death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing therupon, how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do they cause both our bodies and minds to quake and tremble? Insomuch, that many times we shake, and are afraid at the onely mention thereof. Verily,
<pb facs="6"/>
the nature of man being such as had rather not be at all, then to be ill appaied, or to be in miserie, cannot whensoeuer these things befall, but be much vexed and perplexed, yea and sometimes readie to faint: And yet behold the sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and death of the soule farre more dreadfull, and more horrible; then which can befall vnto a man, no greater miserie and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. There is no man, but he doth feare and abhorre, yea and by all meanes flie from corporal punishments and afflictions, and from corporall sicknesses and
<pb facs="7"/>
deaths; how much more then should we labour to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chue and auoid the causes of all these euils, which are our sinnes? and how ought we to feare the wrath and displeasure of almightie God, which we daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke against our selues by so manifold sinnes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences?</p>
   <p>If the bodie be neuer so little crazed, we runne straightway to the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we spare no cost nor charge, preferring our life and health before all things else: yea we are content to disburse we care not what, that we may procure reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb facs="7"/>
and preseruatiues for the same; and all to patch vp this tattered garment of our flesh, this rotten car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casse and clod of clay, which notwithstāding must needs very shortly decay and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and be brought to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Why then do we not with like earnestnesse and carefulnesse seeke for remedies against the sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of the soule, being farre more deadly and dāgerous? For, what should it profite a man to liue a whole thousand yeares, and during that time to possesse all the riches in the world, and to enioy the most exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site
<pb facs="8"/>
pleasures of this life without being troubled with any sicknes or griefe, or other calamitie? and in the meane time to haue his soule tainted, and infected with the leprosie of sinne, and in bondage to the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie of Satan? and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to haue God alwaies his vtter enemie, and his wrath and indignation ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging against him, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heauily vpon him? so as he knew, and were assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after this life to suffer and vndergoe the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of eternall death, and condemnation both of body and soule? Hereof our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="8"/>
Christ admonisheth vs, Math. <hi>16.26,</hi> saying, <hi>What shall it profite a man to winne the whole world, and to lose his owne soule?</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in another place, he warneth vs to watch (to wit, ouer our soules) <hi>watch, for ye know neither the day, nor the howre, when the Sonne of man will come.</hi> And lest we should without regard passe ouer farre better things, and things farre more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and should pursue after toyes and trifles, things base and contemptible; therefore he sheweth vs the
<pb facs="9"/>
shortest and surest way, whereby to come vnto true happinesse, which willeth vs,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 6.33</note>
      <hi>First to seeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and the righteousnesse thereof: and then all other things shall be added vnto vs.</hi> We are tormented, and wearied night and day with care, how to liue here, and how to settle and make sure our worldly estate, our riches &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly possessions, and other vaine and transitorie things, which little auaile vs; yea rather which are sometimes causes of great miserie vnto vs, and of
<pb facs="9"/>
foule and horrible sinnes, which drowne men in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and destruction. But in seeking and prouiding our selues of the heauenly riches, how secure and negligent? how sluggish and slothfull? how foolish and how lumpish and bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish are we? and what more strange or more horrible blindnesse and madnesse then this, can there reigne amongst men? So long as we are in health wee haue scarce the least thought in our hearts at any time, of the life to come, or of our death and departure hence. But as soone as we are cast
<pb facs="10"/>
downe with any sicknesse (death now knocking as it were at our dores,) when as wee should stand in the battaile to fight, then at length wee bethinke our selues of taking vp armes, and of prouiding vs wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to fight withal against the diuell and his suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; then we begin to think of repentance, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our liues, and not before: which is a plaine proofe that our faith is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weake and slender, and that we are litle exercised in the Christian warfare. <hi>The Lord herein be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs: Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>Howbeit there is no age vnfit, nor any season vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable, or ouerlate to repent. Repentance is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer too late, so that it be true, and vnfeigned, and that it be done and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med truly and vnfeinedly. But I aduise and counsell, yea and earnestly exhort and admonish all men, to take heede, that they put not off their repentance to that last and most sharpe and dangerous conflict of sicknesse and death. For if euē they (who being strong, &amp; in health) haue all their life time fortified and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med themselues against
<pb facs="11"/>
this howre of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet haue much adoe then to defend themselues from the assaults &amp; temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which will offer themselues at that time: what then will become of such, as (being voide of all feare of God, and hauing hearts that cannot repent) haue led and still leade a dissolute and wicked life? how shall they be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter and to resist?</p>
   <p>Now then, forasmuch as (the haruest being great) the laborers be but few, &amp; that (infinite mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of simple and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people abounding in
<pb facs="11"/>
all places) there are not Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Gods word euery where at hand to instruct and comfort such as stand in need: and those that are, cannot apply themselues to all, nor minister their helpe and comfort at all times: I haue thought good <hi>(Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader)</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and instruction of such as want the present helpe and assistance of godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors and Ministers (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in time of sicknesse,) to offer vnto thy gentle accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance this order and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of comforting the sicke, gathered out of the sacred word of God; most especially
<pb facs="12"/>
for their sakes, which are ignorant, &amp; which are not armed, nor prouided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such occasions, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther furnished with sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of holy Scripture; that in reading or hearing these things read vnto thē, they may receiue true and stedfast hope and comfort: that in the sharpe and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conflict of sicknesse, and agony of death, they neither faint nor perish.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>