<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To all the inhabitauntes of Eng∣land, and other els where that vnderstand the English toung, the translator whisheth true knowledge of God, contained in his word, which is lyfe euerlastyng.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2800_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06525</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16997.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2800</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To all the inhabitauntes of Eng∣land, and other els where that vnderstand the English toung, the translator whisheth true knowledge of God, contained in his word, which is lyfe euerlastyng.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very comfortable, and necessary sermon in these our dayes : made by the right reuerend father, and faithfull seruaunt of Iesus Christ Martin Luther, concerning the comming of our Sauior Christ to iudgement, and the signes that go before the last day. Which sermon is an exposition of the Gospell appointed to be red in the church on the second Sonday in Aduent, and is now newly translated out of Latin into English, and something augmented and enlarged by the translator, with certaine notes in the margent</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>94 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To all the inhabitauntes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and other els where that vnderstand the English toung, the translator whisheth true knowledge of God, contained in his word, which is lyfe euerlastyng.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore tyme, not many yeares since (dearely beloued brethren &amp; countreymen) the Disciples of Antichrist, and Apostles of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, for the establishyng of their Lordes kyngdome (knowyng that the cōtinuance therof, was the increase of their owne esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiō, wealth and pleasure in this world) haue deuised many politicke practises, so wicked and so deuilish, that whosoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth them well, shall soone perceaue they were not inuented without the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle of their Lord and master. Wherof this was the first and chief, and (as I may say) the ground of the residue to keepe all men, both Princes and their subiectes, in ignoraunce of God, &amp; hys word, that they not knowyng the truth, might the more casely be brought into all kynd of deuilish heresies: that they not vnderstanding vice, should not be able to reprehēd the horrible wickednes of Antichrist and hys mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. To this end they haue restrayned all the laity throughout Christendome, from readyng the Scriptures, and haue forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to be Printed in their vulgare tounges, an din stede thereof, haue geuen them to occupie theyr braynes withall, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles


<pb facs="3"/>
of Robin Hood, of Gie of Warrike, of Geuis of Hampton, of the Knightes of the round table, of the iiij. sonnes of Amō, filthy tales, Chaucer, the Court of Uenus, most horrible &amp; blasphemous lyes out of Saintes Legendes, and such lyke. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men beyng drowned in ignoraūce, and detestable heresies, haue bene cast downe headlong into the most miserable pit of hell. But now it hath pleased almighty God, towardes the commyng of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to Iudgement, by the preachyng of hys word, through the workyng of hys holy spirite, to oppresse the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, to cut the hornes of Antichrist, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale<note place="margin">2. Thes. 2. 3</note> the man of sinne: Which sittyng in the Temple of God, boasteth hym selfe as God. Now it hath pleased our Sauiour Christ to diminish the kyngdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, &amp; to aduaunce his owne kyngdome, to deface y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Disciples of Antichrist, and to glorifie hys owne Disciples. He hath dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out the filthy swyne and wylde bores, that haue spoyled hys vineyarde, and<note place="margin">Mat. 20. 1.</note> hath hyred laborers to husband it agayne, that it may yeld hym frute now at haruest tyme, whē he commeth to receiue the same into hys euerlastyng kyngdome: at which tyme hys faythfull seruaūtes shall receiue for their hyre, a peece of money that neuer shall fayle, and shall eate and drinke the frutes of their labours with hym, world without end. Therfore it is conuenient


<pb facs="4"/>
and necessary for all Gods labourers, that is to say, Princes and their Magistrates, Prelates, and all Ecclesiastical Ministers, to labour diligētly in the Lords vineyard, to kepe out these swyne, which Antichrist hath sent to deuoure it: not onely to yoke them, but also to set dogges on thē, which wil both barcke and plucke of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ares, if they enterprise to breake through the hedge, and to route vp y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> vines with theyr deuilishe bookes, altogether voyde of Gods word and of reason, to euery man that hath any vnderstandyng, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. To this end by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our soueraigne Lady the Queenes Maiestie in our Realme, and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in other Realmes, a great number of godly men haue preached diligently, other haue written very profitable bookes of Diuinitie, both in Latin, and in theyr own vulgare toung, and diuers haue translated good bookes out of straunge tounges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their owne language, husbanding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Lordes vineyard, and keepyng out the swyne that endeuer to destroy it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest whom I beyng one more ready to shew my good will, then able to do any great seruice, haue chosen this short Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> the faythfull seruant of God, Grādcapitaine vnder our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christ, and chief hunter of these wyld bores, vnto theyr father the deuill, from whēce they were sent to destroy the sincere


<pb facs="4"/>
&amp; true worshyp of God. This mans Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (I say) concernyng the commyng of our Sauiour to Iudgemēt, and the signes that go before the last day I haue chosen to translate into our English toung, as that which I thought a most cōuenient labour in this last houre of the day, to preserue in<note place="margin">Mat. 20. 6.</note> the Lordes vineyard the ripe grapes from rottyng and from wild beastes, and to hast those that are vnrype agaynst the Lordes commyng, that is to say: to comfort the faythful, to confirme the weake, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct the ignoraunt, in diuers necessary pointes of doctrine, or at the least to geue them a watchword of our Lordes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, that they may now at the length<note place="margin">Math. 24. 49. Mat. 25. 4</note> cease from sinityng theyr felow seruants, and from eatyng and drynkyng with the drunken, and may make them selues rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with oyle in their lampes to receiue hym: that when the trumpet bloweth, and the bridgrome commeth, we may all fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hym into hys euerlastyng tabernacle, therein to lyue with God the father, the sonne and the holy ghost, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastyng ioy. To whom be all prayse, honor, and glory world without ende.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Anno 1569. March 22.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>T. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>