<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Verses upon the Subject.</title>
           <author>Gosnold, Walter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S280_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4863.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S280</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Verses upon the Subject.</title>
                 <author>Gosnold, Walter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Marcus Ausonius his foure bookes of morall precepts, intituled Cato : concerning the precepts of common life. Translated out of Latin hexamiters into English meter by Walter Gosnold Gentleman, servant unto the right worshipfull Sr. Thomas Bowes of Much-bromley hall in Essex</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <head>Verses upon the Subject.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>BEhold, twixt grace &amp; nature, what great strife</l>
      <l>Is in each man, and vertuous womans life,</l>
      <l>Where grace doth put us on, and pricke us forth,</l>
      <l>There nature pullsus backe, as too too loth,</l>
      <l>To doe that which is good, but all the ill</l>
      <l>That can be done, nature will have her will,</l>
      <l>If God assisting puts not to his hand,</l>
      <l>Dame nature over grace, will have command,</l>
      <l>And grace out of our hearts at last will thrust,</l>
      <l>Making us captive to each sinfull lust.</l>
      <l>Get faith, get love, get zeale in heart saith grace,</l>
      <l>But none of these (say nature) doe imbrace.</l>
      <l>For nat'rall man delighteth not in these,</l>
      <l>His appetite, they no waies doe him please.</l>
      <l>Natures chiefe ayme, is his owne glorious praise,</l>
      <l>When grace ne'r seekes it selfe, but God alwaies.</l>
      <l>The ballance is uneven, and overswaid,</l>
      <l>Where grace and nature are together weigh'd.</l>
      <l>Why nature then's so bad, it is no wonder,</l>
      <l>Being that nature is not kept more under.</l>
      <l>Give me a heart, O God, I doe thee pray,</l>
      <l>Where grace, not nature may have chiefest sway.</l>
      <l>Grace doth invite you to get zeale in heart,</l>
      <l>Nature forbids you, thereof to take part,</l>
      <l>Examine well your heart, doe not combine,</l>
      <l>But search your waies, to which you doe incline.</l>
      <l>Where nature good, with store of grace doth meet,</l>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <l>There is a life of harmony most sweet.</l>
      <l>A woman milde, of nature loving kind,</l>
      <l>Indu'd with grace, best fits an honest mind.</l>
      <l>A nature firie hot, a zeale key cold,</l>
      <l>Become no woman living, young nor old.</l>
      <l>Hath nature outwardly adorn'd thy face?</l>
      <l>Decke inwardly thy soule with splendant grace.</l>
      <l>Beg it of God, as he hath given thee store,</l>
      <l>So that he would increase it more and more,</l>
      <l>Proceed, goe on in grace, thy glasse doth run,</l>
      <l>Leave thou not off, untill thy thred be spun.</l>
      <l>Heaven's of more worth, then earthly treasure here,</l>
      <l>Lose earth for heaven, tho friends to thee be deare.</l>
      <l>Lord ravish thou my soule with heavens delight,</l>
      <l>To worke my peace before the dismall night.</l>
      <l>Good nat'rall parts wil stand us in no stead,</l>
      <l>If parted hence from living to the dead.</l>
      <l>Thy name peruse, and beare it in thy mind,</l>
      <l>And see if thou no contradiction find.</l>
      <l>Thou canst not zealous be on no condition,</l>
      <l>But thou shalt even there meet with opposition.</l>
      <l>Resist thou not Gods spirit in thy soule,</l>
      <l>Though Satan instantly doth thee controule.</l>
      <l>Weeds springeth up in every fruitfull ground,</l>
      <l>The like in every one is to be found.</l>
      <l>The flesh against the spirit doth rebell,</l>
      <l>If we the flesh resist, it will be well.</l>
      <l>Sweet Jesus make me zealous in my youth,</l>
      <l>And bold for to maintaine with zeale thy truth.</l>
      <pb facs="16"/>
      <l>But yet O God, I this desire of thee,</l>
      <l>That unto knowledge I may zealous be▪</l>
      <l>The times doth call for zeale, lets pray with zeale▪</l>
      <l>That God in mercy to this land may deale.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>WALTER GOSNOLD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>