<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Postscript.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S280_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4863.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S280</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Postscript.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Marcus Ausonius his foure bookes of morall precepts, intituled Cato : concerning the precepts of common life. Translated out of Latin hexamiters into English meter by Walter Gosnold Gentleman, servant unto the right worshipfull Sr. Thomas Bowes of Much-bromley hall in Essex</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>A Postscript.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not long since it pleased your good Father, out of the courteous favour and loving respect he beares to every schollerlike action, to grace mee with a worthy acceptation of an Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram which once I presented unto him, upon his owne Name, which, lest antiquity should race it out of the old stocke, by processe of time▪ which weares, eates, and consumes up all things; you being his eldest Sonne, of his Name, and every way like unto him, I have thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive it in the young branch, by presenting of it the second time unto your selfe that as it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents and shewes what your fathers life is, and
<pb facs="13"/>
hath beene: so it may demonstrate and lay ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> unto you, not onely what your life ought to have beene, and what it now should be, but what it must be, if ever you would be truely like your Father, or have your life and Anagram con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre and agree together, and therefore let it be your care, to looke daily upon it, as in a glasse, that thereby you may be put in mind, to see whether or no you are, or desire truly to be such a one, as the Anagram of your Name doth foreshew you to be, that you may with the more safety arrive at the wished haven of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse happinesse, which every blessed man shall one day be pertaker of. In which navigation, or progresse, upon the tempestuous Sea of this wide world, I leave you to that perfect guide and sure pilot, Christ Iesus, who hath both the winds, and waters at his command, to bring you with safety to his Fathers House: to which place, the Lord of his mercy bring you, and us all, being the full fruition of the reward laid up for all such as leade a blessed life.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>