<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Postscript.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S280_Ba2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4863.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S280</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Postscript.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Marcus Ausonius his foure bookes of morall precepts, intituled Cato : concerning the precepts of common life. Translated out of Latin hexamiters into English meter by Walter Gosnold Gentleman, servant unto the right worshipfull Sr. Thomas Bowes of Much-bromley hall in Essex</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="64"/>
   <head>A Postscript.</head>
   <p>THis foresaid example giveth a good lesson to all honest discreete and wise women, that they may keepe secret all things touching or apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the estate of their husbands, that they shew it to no creature living; for oftentimes it chanceth, that in open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of small matters, commeth much harme, and most times, when they thinke least thereon. A close mouth (as the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is) makes a wise head, and a foolish woman is easily knowne by her much ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. In being close and secret, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in such things as men would have kept close and in secret, can come nothing but good and quietnesse; for a word is like an arrow in a bow; when the arrow
<pb facs="65"/>
is shot and gone from the bow, it maketh a noyse, and cannot returne againe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it taketh his lighting place: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, a word, when it is spoken, and gone out of the mouth, it cannot come againe before it be disperst unto the auditors and standers by, aud of them is heard and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, either in the good or evill part; therefore it is good to have in memory, and marke well the saying of the wiseman <hi>Salomon;</hi> first thinke a thing twise or thrice before thou speake it, and take good heed and regard to what end and effect it may turne and come unto before thou o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penest thy mouth for where much babling is, there must needes be offence▪ she that refraineth and bridleth her tongue, is wise; an innocent tongue is a noble trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and as one wisely saith; silence in a woman is a speciall vertue. It is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to see a dumbe Grashopper, because
<pb facs="65"/>
the whole kinde of them is garrulous: yet more wonderfull it is to see constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and silence in women, because their Sex is mutable and loquacious, the toung is an unruly member, especially in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans mouth; but where grace is, it is easily bridled: the tongue is called the gate of life and death, and that in this respect, for by it the lives of our selves and others are daily hazarded, as you may see in the story immediatly going before. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would once againe advise all wise and discreet women, or that would so bee thought and accounted, when their tongues at any time shall be most active, and nimble for discourse, to thinke upon <hi>Catos▪</hi> wife, that they reveale not in any wise, any secret, whereby any mischiefe may come thereof: for by a word spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and that to her neare friend, and to one of her owne Sex, which one would
<pb facs="66"/>
have thought would have kept her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, into what great perill had shee like to have brought her husband and her selfe. Labour then to amend your own imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in this one thing, otherwise the danger and shame in the end will light upon your selves, as the verse herefol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing doth shew:
<q>
         <l>Women whose tongues before their wit doth run,</l>
         <l>Oft speaks too soone, &amp; rues when they have done.</l>
      </q>
But this is not written onely to be marked of women, but also of all persons, of what estate and degree soever they bee, that have any matter of secret or counsell committed unto them, that they may hereby learne and beware how they shew or declare any thing that they shall heare, see done, or said in any counsell, for many times, by uttering of a small thing, great inconvenience doth come, and much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to things pretended.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>