<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the judicious and indifferent Reader, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Meen, Joshua</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2818_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07397</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17780.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the judicious and indifferent Reader, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Meen, Joshua</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vickers challenge : claiming a maintainance as due by proofes out of the gospell : wherein is manifested, that there is a competencie due unto them by Ios. Meene, vicker</title>
                 <author>Meene, Joshua</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vavasour, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 74 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the judicious and indifferent <hi>Reader, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">A Preface apologeticall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are sundry learned and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treatises extant in the behalf of the Clergie for their competent maintenance, and touching their right unto the tithes.</p>
   <p>To omit the Ancients and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigue Authours, observe how no few of our owne Nation have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in this necessary and pious subject: as the right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers in God, the Lord Bishop <hi>Andrews,</hi> the Lord Bishop <hi>Carlton,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Moreover, the right Worshipfull Sir <hi>Henry Spilman,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Sempell,</hi> Doctor <hi>Tillessie,</hi> Doctor <hi>Mayer,</hi> Doctor <hi>Rives,</hi> Master <hi>Hooker,</hi> Master <hi>Roberts:</hi> from some of whose Works in this kinde, I do freely acknowledge my self to have received no small furtherance.</p>
   <p>There are likewise other famous Writers besides, which although altogether unknowne to mee, shall neverthelesse with these spoken of, be immortalized by their devout and solid lines to this purpose. Although alas too true it is, that through the deep-rooted corruption of this deplorate season, their excellent endevours this way have not attained a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed event. Wherupon some may censure my pains herein at this present, as audacious and fruitlesse.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>Yet I conceive it cannot be amisse to continue discourse in a case of that consequence: neither is it reason to leave our just claime, whiles we wrongfully lose our true right.</p>
   <p>Moreover, the bringing of the matter into frequent mention (though in a weaker manner) may prove a suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessefull means to make those godly and judicious Authours to be better read over and againe revolved, whose argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments well considered will appear sufficient to confound the adversary, and to end the controversie. It may also put men of the best ability in mindeto manage the businesse.</p>
   <p>Further the manifold dangers of execrable facriledge ought to stirre up every competent person to devise and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all possible remedies against her perillous oversprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
   <p>Surely the prophane supposall that it was never divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed for the Ministers of the Gospell to be mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with tithes, &amp;c. But to live as it were, upon stipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie Almes, is an errour inweeded in the minds of no few folks of more then ordinary wealth and place.</p>
   <p>And the accursed contagion thereof doth daily diffuse it selfe farre and neer, yea, and that not seldome, into worser degrees.</p>
   <p>Insomuch that now no few feare not nor blush to finde fault with the payment of the tenths, not onely nuder ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of an obliterate and cancelled Judiciall currant amongst the <hi>Israelites:</hi> but also under discredit of a Leviticall and unlawfull Ceremonie, disanulled at the comming of Christ.</p>
   <p>This grievous mischief in these perverse times seemes grown to that great height, that now any parcell of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the right of the Church, though never so properly deduced from the text, and never so piously intended, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth for the most part, a common hatred and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble scandall of a covetous and trouble some man.</p>
   <p>I could exemplifie thus much without travelling farre from my own Parish, and with no little sorrow shew at large
<pb facs="4"/>what a world of unconscionable customes, and compositions are most obstinately, and overpowringly maint ained against the Church, by fockes of eminent wealth, and credit, besides the ordinary rankes.</p>
   <p>Moreover I might mention, that no lesse ridiculous then injurious wresting of the Statute of case of tithe wood, that the Mother freeth the Daughter, namely if the body bee above twenty yeares old, then the top, although put to firing must be freed from tithing; which most unjust ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity findoth, notwithstanding no few Patrones, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst some of the Law-professours, to the extreme preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>I might yet remember some worser matter, namely glebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands detained by sundry persons of no small wealth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme in this world, from the Church, appearing neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse upon record, Terriers, and other sufficient testimonies, ploinely to belong thereunto.</p>
   <p>Surely when as I seriously consider the worldly wisedome, wealth and place relucent in some of those that deale thus unjustly with the Church: Behold the charitoblest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, which I can make of their actions, is to feare they are unfortiuately lapsed into the foresaid errour against ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp;c. And so whiles they pretand onely to allow us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries, they unconscionably leave us to all extremities.</p>
   <p>Finally, the publishing of this Treatise proceedeth not forth without the private incouragements of some of my learned brethren of the Clergie.</p>
   <p>To conclude, the most gracious God seemeth in these dayes to have in a specialler manner compassionately looked upon the calamitous estate of his oppressed Church, by sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us a Prince very propitiously inclined for her good: He hath also vouchsafed us many pious Prelats; noble and honorable personages, Judges, Lawyers, and some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eaymen of no little worth, devoutly tendring in their proper ranks, therelief and right of the Church.</p>
   <p>Neither is the paternall good will of my religiously in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Diocesan to succour my distressed Vicaridge a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="5"/>of small moment to animate. Moreover the courteous favour of that learned &amp; vertuous Knight Sir <hi>Nathanael Brent</hi> in this kinde to my selfe in particular, besides others. I may justly adde the good Offices done me this way, by our Right Worshipfull Archdeacons in this Diocesse, Doctor <hi>Binge</hi> and Master <hi>White:</hi> Also the free and honest coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell in this case of Doctor <hi>Talbot,</hi> indeared unto the Clergy by his affection, and fidelity towards them.</p>
   <p>Last of all, the promised assistance of my very worthy friend and wonted refuge, in many malevolent and Sacrilegious projects, and practises against me in my Parish, namely the Right Worshipfull Master <hi>Thomas Talbot</hi> Esquire, &amp;c. the glory of the place were he liveth.</p>
   <p>The generall condolement and clamour, through the whole Countrey, of all well affected children of the Church. (which know this miserable Vicaridge) at the extreme dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion betweene the great burden of the Cure, and the poore pittance of the meanes to sustaine it with.</p>
   <p>Surely, none of these premisses but have some force and weight: And therefore all of them considered together, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but prove very ponderous to induce, and perswade mee for Sions sake not to hold my peace, and remaine silent: But rather (in the willingly acknowledged weakenesse and slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse of my abilities) to imploy my best endeavours, as a dutifull Son, in the humble service of our holy and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mother the Church.</p>
   <p>And in all reverence and lowlinesse of mind, I cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully submit them unto the Censure of my Ecclesiasticall Superiours.</p>
   <p>Farewell in the Authour of all welfare, Christ Iesus; to whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghost, three persons and one God, be all honour and glory for evermore. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy Servant in the Lord,</hi> Ioshua Meene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>