<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLY DIS∣posed, vertuous, and faithfull-brest∣ed Robert Grey Esquire, one of the Grooms of his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, his poore Well-willer, wisheth his best wishes. Hic es Supra.</title>
           <author>Rowley, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2820_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07528</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17911a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2820</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLY DIS∣posed, vertuous, and faithfull-brest∣ed Robert Grey Esquire, one of the Grooms of his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, his poore Well-willer, wisheth his best wishes. Hic es Supra.</title>
                 <author>Rowley, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A faire quarrell : with new additions of Mr. Chaughs and Trimtrams roaring, and the Bauds song, neuer before printed : as it was acted before the King, by the Prince His Highnesse seruants [brace] written by Thomas Midleton, and William Rowley, [brace] gent</title>
                 <author>Middleton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Trundle, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>77 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLY DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, vertuous, and faithfull-brest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Robert Grey</hi> Esquire, one of the Grooms of his Highnesse Bed-Chamber, his poore Well-willer, wisheth his best wishes. Hic es Supra.</head>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is but a Play, and a Play is but a Butt, against which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny shoote many Arrowes of Enuy, 'tis the weaker Part, and how much more noble shall it be in you to defend it, yet if it be (as some Philosophers haue left behind'um) that this Megac<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sme, this great world, is no more then a Stage, where euery one must act his part, you shall of necessity haue many part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, some long, some short, some indifferent, all some, whilst indeed the Players themselues haue


<pb facs="3"/>
the least part of it, for I know few that haue lands, (which are a part of the World) and therefore no grounded men, but how soeuer they serue for mutes, happily they must weare good cloathes for atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, yet all haue exits and must all be stript in the Tyring-house (<hi>viz,</hi> the graue) for none must carry anything out of the stocke, you see Sir, I write as I speak, &amp; I speak as I am, &amp; thats excuse enough for me. I did not meane to write an Epistle of praise to you, it lookes so like a thing, (I know) you loue not <hi>Flattery,</hi> which you exceedingly hate actiuely, and vnpleasingly accept passiuely: indeed I meant to tell you your owne, that is, that this child of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses is yours, who euer begat it, tis laid to your charge and (for ought I know) you must father and keep it too, if it please you, I hope you shall not bee asham'd of it neither for it has beene seene (though I say it) in good companies, and many haue said it is a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some pretty spoken infant, now be your owne iudge, at your leasure looke on it, at your pleasure laugh at it, and if you be sorry it is no better you may be glad it is no bigger.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>
               <hi>Yours euer.</hi> William Rowley.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>