<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Readers, and in special to my welbeloved and re∣spected, the inhabitants of the City of Bristoll; those of my charge at Barkley in Glocester-shire, and my deare Kindred and Coun∣trey-men in Staf∣ford-shire.</title>
           <author>Chetwind, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S287_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5127.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S287</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Readers, and in special to my welbeloved and re∣spected, the inhabitants of the City of Bristoll; those of my charge at Barkley in Glocester-shire, and my deare Kindred and Coun∣trey-men in Staf∣ford-shire.</title>
                 <author>Chetwind, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The strait gate and narrow way to life : opened and pointed out upon Luk. 13, 23, 24. By Edward Chetwind, D.D. and Deane of Bristow</title>
                 <author>Chetwynd, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>58, 270 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Readers, and in special to my welbeloved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected, the inhabitants of the City of Bristoll; those of my charge at <hi>Barkley</hi> in <hi>Glocester-shire,</hi> and my deare Kindred and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men in <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-shire.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He dangerous security, and irreligious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of these last and <hi>peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times,</hi> which every unpartiall eye discerneth, and every true
<pb facs="10"/> Christian hart deploreth &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth; as it first occasioned me to make choice of the Scripture opened in this Treatise, for a Text: so hath the farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration hereof, at length made me not unwilling, to publish for more generall use, what at first was by preaching hereupon more privately deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, to the end to discover such malignant humors, and withall to awaken and rouze up such carelesse sleepers from out of their golden dreame (not unlike that of the <hi>hungry man</hi> in the Prophet) of secured safety.<note place="margin">Isai. 29.8.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> In which endeavour, as <hi>my witnesse is in heaven, and my record on high,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 16.19.</note> that mine aime is wholly, <hi>to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb facs="10"/> righteousnes unto my maker,</hi> and withall,<note place="margin">Iob 36.3.</note> as an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter to declare vnto man his righteousnesse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 33.23.</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting from our Saviours mouth, how to attaine to end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse happinesse: so have I beene stirred up, and encouraged, by a twofold powerfull motive: viz. the consideration of the <hi>necessitie,</hi> and hope of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> For the former: That I may take leave (in silence of my betters) to set downe what mine experience (being in comparison but of <hi>yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>) hath observed,<note place="margin">Iob 8.9.</note> touching the humours of the world in this main point of the pursuit of happines: it seemeth to me, that even the whole christian name,
<pb facs="11"/> and nation, may iustly fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one of these two heads: viz. either such as willingly <hi>feede on ashes,</hi> suffering their owne <hi>seduced hearts to deceive them,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai 44.20.</note>
      <hi>being not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their soules, or to say, is there not a ly in our right hand?</hi> or else such as by the example and multitude of the forenamed, are dangerously <hi>disheartned</hi> in their safe and sincere course.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4</hi> For why alas? (to dispose the former band of seduced soules, into two companies:) first, some there are, who entertaine not so much as any shew of desire or care of entring into life, nay as if they <hi>had made a covenant with death and hell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai. 28.15</note> or rather
<pb facs="11"/> with their seduced soules, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that Article of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme,</hi> that <hi>there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heaven nor hell:</hi> how may they bee seene running a loose and licentious race, of most abhominable prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, wallowing in whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, blasphemies, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennesse, and what not defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wickednesse; refusing to be taught or told of the wayes of God, yea in effect, as those in <hi>Iob,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 21.14.</note> bidding <hi>the Almightie depart from them,</hi> being such who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire not <hi>the knowledge of his waies:</hi> or if they be threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the comming and terrours of the Lord, like those mockers in <hi>Peter, aske,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Pet, 3.2.</note>
      <hi>where is the promise of
<pb facs="12"/> his comming?</hi> and drawing in the same yoke, and with the same cords, with those in <hi>Isa.</hi> challenge and dare the highest Maiesty with, <hi>let him make speed: let him hasten his worke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai. 5.19.</note>
      <hi>that we may see it; &amp;c.</hi> or if happily their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at any time tell them by secret gripes, that they must expect a iudge and iudgement: yet how is their resolution made carelesse and desperate, by their damnable abuse of the doctrine of Gods predestination, that <hi>all must be as God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined: what need they then to take further care, seeing they can neither al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor</hi> (as they thinke) <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what God hath fore-ordained.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>5.</hi> But besides these mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, whom more then hellish unbeliefe, hath made in this particular worse then the very Divels themselves, <hi>who beleeve and tremble:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, how many are there, of a <hi>second order,</hi> not so despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, who professing some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and hope of life, may yet be observed, miserably to erre and wander, in the wayes of death?</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> For why? some flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themselves in wickednesse, accounting the gate of heaven to bee wide and open, and the passage obvious and easie to enter, when they will, as if, <hi>Christ dyed for all,</hi> or as if the bare name of Christ were a gate to <hi>let in all, Papists, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptists, Familists,</hi> or any
<pb facs="13"/> sect of Religion, unto life; and whereat by faith onely (which they count no such great matter) or at the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest, by an after repentance, they may come to enter, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they list, though it be at the very last.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7.</hi> Others stay without, willing to enter, but loath to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture. Why? but becaus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> they are as <hi>Moab</hi> setled <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> their lees:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 48.11. Zeph. 1.12.</note> or as those in <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phany, frozen on thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> dregges:</hi> resolved befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hand, whatsoever the Lord voice be, to <hi>goe downe int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Egypt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier 42.14.</note>
      <hi>to enioy,</hi> as yet, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> pleasures, profits, and credit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this present world, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore account they him their ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my that shall by <hi>telling them truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 4.6.</note> forwarn thē to flee with
<pb facs="13"/> speed <hi>from the wrath to come:</hi> or if they will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded to yeeld any thing, it is but with <hi>Agrippa</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>almost Christians:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 26, 28.</note> or if you would have them abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, you must perswade others to be so also, at least to suffer them to bee vnderided in their forwardnesse.<note place="margin">Pro. 21.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>So doth the desire of the slothfull slay them,</hi> whiles <hi>their hāds refuse to worke;</hi> wishing to be happy, but not regarding to be holy: willing to be saved, but loath to be restrained of their fleshly liberty: content to heare of dying well, but fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring if in their life they refraine from iniquity, to <hi>be made a prey:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa 59.15.</note> or at least <hi>a butte</hi> for the arrowes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochful tongs; w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> difficulties
<pb facs="14"/> rather then they will undergoe, they suffer themselves with the multitude, to fall downe the streame, into undoubted lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8</hi> And yet a third sort there is in greater danger, whiles they thinke themselves secure and out of danger; as being conceited that they are entred already within the gate, and walking in the wayes of life when as indeed, they are but groping (as the blind <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi>) in the darke,<note place="margin">(Gen 19.11.)</note> not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found the dore. Such as like the luke-warme Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> thinke themselves rich and <hi>wanting nothing,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> when they are but poore. Who, howsoever, for making some profession, and holding some outward correspondency with
<pb facs="14"/> God and his word, so as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they may keepe peace and friendship with the world: they are so conceited of their owne perfection, that they are ready with him in the Gospel, who thought he had done all, to aske <hi>what more is wanting</hi> to them?<note place="margin">Mat. 19.20</note> yet it is lamentably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, how they deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, with a shew <hi>of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and deny the power thereof,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5</note> taking on them the profession, but yet not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining <hi>the love of the truth that they may be saved.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Th. 2.10.</note> As a iust punishment whereof, how many do we see given over to strong delusions <hi>to beleeve lyes?</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Kin. 28.21</note> either to halt as Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>betweene two opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi> or to embrace with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest eagern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse a false Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
<pb facs="15"/> because (which in the <hi>Prophet</hi> heartned the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Iewes in their abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations) their forefathers have therein trodde before them?<note place="margin">Ier 44.17.</note> or because, these wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es of superstition, seeme some of them strict and narrow, and therefore likely to bee the wayes of life? yea, how many whilome made good shew, and seemed to shine bright, as starres in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of heaven, who are by the <hi>Dragons taile smitten to the earth?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rev. 12.4.</note> by their fall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king manifest how they were but comets at the best; whiles relapsed and having lost <hi>their first love,</hi> they are as water once made hote, growne colder for the heating, and become scoffers and deriders, <hi>Ismael-like,</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/> or as <hi>Michol,</hi> if not worse, of any that shall in sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie set themselves reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingly to walke in the wayes of God.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <hi>9</hi> Finally (for conclusion of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s complaint, discovering the great necessity, as I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, of dealing in this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) whiles thus the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of those that are stiled with the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, <hi>despise, or neglect,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk 7.30 Heb. 2.3.</note>
      <hi>the counsell of God, and this great salvation,</hi> how doe they not onely sinne a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst their owne soules, <hi>iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging themselves unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of everlasting life?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 13.46</note> but also (which is more to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented) by their opposite multitude, and example,
<pb facs="16"/> dangerously daunt and dismay the harts both of Gods faithfull Ministers in their painfull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and generally, of true hearted Christians, in their holy conversation. Those, whiles they see so little fruit of the travaile of their soules, if not happily open defiance, if they shall once proceede unto particulars,<note place="margin">Luk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.19.</note> as <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> did with <hi>Herod;</hi> These, while they finde so little countenance or acceptance of their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours after sincerity, if not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a sway of times and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to hinder them from <hi>cleaving without separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto the Lord.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="10">
      <hi>10</hi> A remedy, and as it were counterpoison, against all which dangerous infections, as our Saviour shall seem to give,
<pb facs="16"/> in that his counsell to his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, to strive with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment earnestnesse, <hi>to enter in at the strait gate, and</hi> to walke in the <hi>narrow way</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to life: so have I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended as a second motive, for encouragement to this worke, the hope conceived hereby of <hi>profit,</hi> if the Lord shall vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to affoord his blessing from above, whiles in the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and applying of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours answer touching these two maine points of truth, <hi>that the number to be saved is but small: and the manner dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult:</hi> we shall aptly meet with every kind of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned humors.</p>
   <p n="11">
      <hi>11</hi> As first with the first sort of <hi>despisers,</hi> by way of <hi>commination,</hi> (and <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi>
      <pb facs="17"/> withall, of their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed blasphemies, and reasonings against the Lord) whiles, to appale (if it may be) their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate spirits, they be charged as guilty of murdering their owne soules, and threatned as scorners alone to suffer, to bee swept away with the besome of destruction, and cast into the burning lake: Gods iustice, in reiecting them, standing meane while cleare, and their condemnation proved iust, as wholly by themselves deserved, who neuer so much as entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the desire of grace, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the counsell of God in his word, that they might bee saved.</p>
   <p n="12">
      <hi>12</hi> Farther, with the other sort, that neglect this great sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, whiles, either they
<pb facs="17"/> thinke it easie to be had hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or are loath for it to leave the world, or think they have already interested themselves therein: our dealing shall be found to be, by <hi>instruction, correction,</hi> and faithfull <hi>counsell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="13">
      <hi>13</hi> For first, our labour is by way of <hi>doctrine,</hi> to instruct and confirme them in the truth, here by our blessed Savior pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded both touching the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that shall be saved, that, viz. howsoever they be many in themselves, yet are they in comparison with them that perish, but as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Lord</hi> (not I) resolving this point, maketh the simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) as the <hi>wheat cornes</hi> in comparison with the <hi>chaffe,</hi> a <hi>tithing▪</hi> or a <hi>gleaning,</hi> or a <hi>remnant,</hi> few of
<pb facs="18"/> many, a <hi>little flocke:</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so touching the manner of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining unto salvation, <hi>that it is difficult and not so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie.</hi> Since howsoever Christ Iesus, the gate and way of life, and so all the porches and paths compris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d under him, be in themselves faire and spatious; yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o seeme they not (neither inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d are) to the carnall slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards, who choose rather to wander in the many by wayes of death, then to walk constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conscionably in this <hi>one</hi> onely way of life. <hi>Strait</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and narrow: not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it selfe, but alasse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause men are by nature, either blin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d cannot find the gate, or stiffenecked and stuffed with worldly pelfe, that they brooke not to stoope, or strip them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
<pb facs="18"/> that they may get in: or delighting to rove, they endure not to be bounded, no not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the pales of the law of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: or finally, they feare if they should be forward, to be encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with the briers and bushes lying in the path. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects by mans own corruption the gate and way of life is made strait to enter, and narrow to walke in, except with violence and earnest strife.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <hi>14</hi> And hence therefore, is our iust <hi>correction</hi> in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place inferred to discover their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olly, who conceiting it a small matter to enter into life, or being loath to leave the world, stay wandring without, whiles racking Gods mercy without his leave, they forslow the time, deferring to set out
<pb facs="19"/> upon their iourney, untill the evening of their age, thinking then fittest to begin an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after life, when their hoare haires call them to think on death. When as alasse poore soules, they wot not how sodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ere they mistrust their state, the pits mouth may be shut up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, neither consider how their conclusion must necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, as the premisses were framed, and their death answer the tenor of their life; which whiles they neglect to reforme, foolishly preferring earth to heaven, and the winning of the world, to the assuring of their pretious soules: little comfort may they have, in the frequent company that passe along with them as beasts in herds unto the shambles, toward destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
   <p n="15">
      <pb facs="19"/>
      <hi>15</hi> To recall whom, and warne all, to looke unto their wayes, our <hi>counsell</hi> may bee found to be thirdly, this same of our Saviour in the Text, to all that long after life, to strive with earnestnesse to <hi>enter in at the strait gate:</hi> not to walke after the fashions of the world: nor to awarrant themselves to doe what they see many doe. No, but rather to trie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, whether they be entred within the gate, and walking in the wayes of life: that is, in faith, repentance, obedience, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> in Christ lead to life: Wherin whiles many only with a formality of outward professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, miserably deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, boasting of what they have not received; or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sled and drawne aside by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of the wicked, fall from
<pb facs="20"/> that stedfastnes which they once professed: our care you shal finde to be, both to put in <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> against the false wayes seeming strait, and withall to yeeld <hi>direction</hi> with advice how to find, and enter the true wayes of life; yea further, how to examine and try our estate, for both entrance and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, in every of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that none be misled or fall away that belong to God So may our dealing be found to be, with the severall sorts of such as are seduced.</p>
   <p n="16">
      <hi>16</hi> And accordingly also, with the other sort, of such as are in danger to faint, and be disheartned in this course our dealing will be found, fitting their condition by way of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and encouragement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="17">
      <pb facs="20"/>
      <hi>17</hi> First, to the faithfull Minister, not to faint though he be found fault with, for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the truth, neither to be discouraged, if he be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to winne all to embrace the truth but rather to reioyce in God, for the gain of any though some few; yea, or if not any, yet in the saving of his owne soule, by approving of his faithfulnes unto the Lord; with whom howsoever the successe be, his iudgement shall be favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his reward assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
   <p n="18">
      <hi>18</hi> Secondly, to the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, who though but few, yet if truely faithfull, and of the little flocke, need not to fear or be discouraged, since for them a Kingdome is prepared, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, whiles by the <hi>renevving</hi> of
<pb facs="21"/> their hearts, and <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of their former evill wayes: by their <hi>zeale</hi> to draw others with them unto God: and hearty <hi>love</hi> unto the Saints and servants of God: (sure notes where they be sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, of a right faith in Christ) they can finde themselves to walke: how can they but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with ioy unspeakeable and glorious, in the riches uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable of Gods free love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; who hath severed them from the refuse of the world, reserving them as vessels of mercy unto himselfe. Wherfore to encourage them, howsoever maligned by the world, and by their separation from the world in danger to be made a prey; our labour finally will be found, to discover how these gates and
<pb facs="21"/> wayes, that seeme to the carnall man so strait and troublesome, are yet in themselves, and unto them that once are entred into them, pleasant and of delight. The other sort that walk in the broad way, being indeed those that endure the most wretched slavery under hard masters (worse farre then <hi>Pharaohs</hi> taske-masters) sin and satan: when as they though walking solitarily, are the only blessed and happy brood of travailers, whose leader is Christ Iesus, whose guard the holy Angels, whose footsteps are directed by Gods blessed Spirit of truth, their glory, though as of the Kings daughter inward, yet surpassing, being Christs beauty put upon them: finally their reioycing in this life, though
<pb facs="22"/> by others unconceiveable, and their end assured peace.</p>
   <p n="19">
      <hi>19</hi> These things (according to the measure of my poore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent) as I have endeavoured with perspicuous plainnes to set before the eyes of my Christian and indifferent Readers; so for farther light of understanding and helpe of memory, I have thought good to draw them summarily into a briefe table, containing the method and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of the treatise follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which hauing been first deliuered in diuers sermons; &amp; since connected in one entire discourse without distinction, is now for the Readers refreshing divided into chapters, where in yet there is (as the table refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the severall chapters, sheweth) a coherence and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation
<pb facs="22"/> of the whole: The curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous question being onely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; for discovery of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme and curiosity of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, so as to make way to our Saviours gracious answer: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording us the two maine notes of doctrine (then which I know not any more needfull to be ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or which are more hardly digested by the carnal and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious heart; which hath made me the more to labour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and make them plaine.) The former, touching the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that shall be saved, that— <hi>they are in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son but few</hi>—and the later, touching the manner of attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to salvation, that— <hi>it is to flesh and bloud no easie matter</hi>—which therefone all had need to looke diligently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="23"/> that would attaine to life, Since this is certaine, God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure that man should seek to finde out or prescribe unto himselfe any other way to life, or yet refuse to walke in that, which his wisedome hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed and sanctified in his word of truth, and wherein the faithfull in all ages have passed unto glory.</p>
   <p n="20">
      <hi>20</hi> Now the fruit of these my labour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, as Christian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie together with my <hi>speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all calling,</hi> bindeth me unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, to wish to all Christian hearts, who shall take paines to reade them; so doe particular reasons of important respect perswade me in especiall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to recommend them, with most hearty wish of profite to those, who are before by name
<pb facs="23"/> mentioned; <hi>viz.</hi> my beloved hearers of the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> together with those who are now of my more speciall charge in the Lord, not without an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate remembrance of, and respect unto those, that are my kindred and countrimen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the flesh.</p>
   <p n="21">
      <hi>21</hi> As for the first of those, who were eare witnesses of the deliverie of this truth; my desire is (God having beene pleased, since that time, to call me (howsoever not altogether from them, yet) from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary exercise of my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie among them) to leave this <hi>tract</hi> as a <hi>standing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrāce</hi> unto them,<note place="margin">Act. 20.31. 2 Pet. 1.15.</note> both of what they have been taught in this most necessary point, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of my most unfained love to
<pb facs="24"/> their soules; heartily wishing and seriously warning them so to <hi>looke to themselves,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Ioh. 8.</note> that those good affections to the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row vvay; vvhich my selfe haue much reioyced heretofore to observe in them, may not now decay or die within them, God having stil continued, and yet continuing amongst them, so powerfull a ministery for the preserving, and (if themselves be not in fault) improving of those his graces in them.</p>
   <p n="22">
      <hi>22</hi> Secondly for those whom God hath pleased (in mercy I trust both unto them and my selfe) to make my great and speciall charge, as I cannot but reioyce with that good man <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 11.23.</note> to see <hi>the grace of God,</hi> by others labours before hopefully begunne in some of
<pb facs="24"/> them; so would I <hi>exhort all of them,</hi> that <hi>with purpose of heart</hi> they would <hi>ioyne</hi> themselves, and even <hi>cleave inseparably unto the Lord,</hi> willing, by inserting here this mention and remembrance of them, to testifie mine affection, and how as God can beare me <hi>record,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 1.8.</note> I unfainedly long <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2 3 Ioh. 4.</note> and am even <hi>iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous over them, rejoycing</hi> in nothing more, then to see any of them <hi>walking in the truth:</hi> neither desiring any thing more, then to be able in the last day to yeeld up for them <hi>mine accounts with joy,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> yea to have them as <hi>my joy and crown of rejoycing in the presence of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ at his comming,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Thes. 2.19.</note> which hovv may I hope sooner
<pb facs="25"/> then by aiming to set before them in the whole course of my ministery what in this treatise is opened and pointed out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, even the straite gate and narrow way of life: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in whiles they shall endeavour carefully to walke, they shall with one labour, become their Ministers <hi>glory,</hi> and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves also attaine to <hi>glory,</hi> which God grant.</p>
   <p n="23">
      <hi>23</hi> Finally, for the third sort, of my deare kindred and countrimen, since it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Lord (who appointeth to every one of his servants, both his portion and his place of service) to call and send me, as he did <hi>Ionah</hi> unto <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iona 3.2, 3 Act. 16.10. Luc. 4.16.</note> or as <hi>Paul</hi> into <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> that I cannot <hi>as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours manner was</hi> stand up
<pb facs="25"/> in the Synagogue of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth;</hi> to instruct them of mine owne Tribe and Familie,<note place="margin">Ver: 23.</note> in the wayes of God, nor be as an home-borne Physitian, to apply Gods balme for healing of the sores of the daughter of mine owne people: yet God forbid that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection towards mine owne bowels, and native soile, should be so farre extinguished as that I should not (with the Prophet and holy people in the Psalme) importune the <hi>Lord, to arise and have mercy thereon;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 102.13.</note> and in the meane time delight in the stones, <hi>and have pitty on the dust ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Verse 14.</note> For whose peace, and speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prosperitie, as, <hi>for my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kindred sake</hi> I am bound to pray;<note place="margin">Psal 122.8.</note>
      <hi>mine harts desire being for them,</hi> as
<pb facs="26"/> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> was for his nation of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 10.1.</note> that they may have the meanes &amp; grace of life: so doe I desire in this absence, to send and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this as a present pledge and pawne of my respectfull love and due remembrance of them. Who being of a dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ingenious, and not averse from the best things, want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so much as <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 62.6.</note> to make them see and shunne all reliques of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition, and with Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, to make them <hi>ready as a people prepared for the Lord.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc 1.17.</note> For whom though I cannot say in that height of the Apostles superabundant zeale, that I <hi>would bee separated from Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 9.3:</note> or with <hi>Moses,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exo 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.32</note>
      <hi>be blotted out of the book
<pb facs="26"/> of life,</hi> yet shall I desire with the same Apostle for his beloved <hi>Ephesians</hi> continually to bow my knees <hi>unto the Father of our Lord Iesus Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph 3.14, 15. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>(of whom is named the whole family in heaven and in earth) that hee may grant them according to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his glory, to bee strengthned by his spirit in the inner man, that Christ may dwell in their hearts by faith.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="24">
      <hi>24</hi> And even so recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending these my labours to Gods blessing, who alone is all in all, <hi>giving the encrease,</hi> and them, and all those, whose Christian hearts shall in since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of truth desire the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.7.</note> to life eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall, <hi>unto God &amp; the word
<pb facs="27"/> of his grace, who is able to build farther,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note>
      <hi>and to give them an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong al them that are san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified: as being able to do exceeding abundantly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that wee aske or think according to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that worketh in us.</hi> I take leave.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Bristoll,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Ianuary 20.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord Iesus, <hi>EDWARD CHETWIND.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>