<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>T., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2915_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13312</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23621.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2915</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>T., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ready path to the pleasant pasture of delitesome and eternall paradyse : so called, bicause herein is declared how, and by what meanes, we shall easily obtayne the surprising pleasures of heauenly felicitie</title>
                 <author>I. T.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Judson, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT THE WHOLE worlde be miserably plunged, and daungerously drowned in the terrible seas of Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie wrath, and sore displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, yet (most deare christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) such are the vnspeakeable riches, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable treasures of his heauenly mercy, that be wyll not disdaine to relieue vs, to saue vs, to helpe vs, to holde vs, to heale vs, and to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vs, in the most pleasaunt, and comfortable rest of his most gracious, and eternall fauour, if with humble mindes, with sorowfull, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt heartes, wyth a constaunt, and liuely fayth, we will prostrate our selues before the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting throne of his immortall Maiestie, hoping to be mercyfullye, paciently, and graciouslye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, onely for the merites of Christ Iesus, our onely triumphant, and mightie Sauiour. But bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause men nowe in these our dayes are in hart hardened, in lyfe lycentious, in loue lasciuious, in maners miserable, in wordes wylfull, in sense vnsauerie, in doings disordered, in talke vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, in wyt wylde, in reason retchlesse, in rage vnreasonable, in foly forwarde, in fansie fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde,
<pb facs="3"/>
in vice venimous, in vylanie vaunting, in soule sinfull, in charitie colde, in furie fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, in faith fruitlesse, and to conclude, in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning themselues gracelesse, and godlesse: it is necessarie before they can haue accesse to God in mercie through Christ Iesus, before they can passe to the most pleasaunt habitation of Gods euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, and immortall kingdome, before they can be enfraunchised CytiZens in heauenly Ierusalem, that they expell pride, banishe arrogancie, expell hypocrisie, detest all impietie, clense awaye the dregges of stinking Poperie, washe out the spottes of disobedient adulterie, and wype out the blemish of all blasphemous ydolatrie, which by none other meanes can more conueniently bee brought to passe, then by consideration of the terrible threates of God against obstinate, harde hearted, and rebellious aduersaries, against stifnecked, vngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and disobedient seruaunts, against vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, vnthankefull, and gracelesse children, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, which contemptuouslye dispise his commaundements, which spitefully neglect his fatherly counsell, which wylfully transgresse his holye lawes, which disobediently refuse to giue eare to his aduise and censure, which voluntarily cast themselues headlong, into the perillous pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
<pb facs="3"/>
and gaping goulfe of all abhominable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanesse, vnlawfull wickednesse, and extreme miserie. I haue therefore (deare christian) in this my short treatise, wherein my principall, and especiall purpose is to bring men to the most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, profitable, and holesome exercise of godly prayer, first declared the horrible estate, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death of such, who doe not, and will not prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise earnest, and hartie prayer, nowe whilest God doth lende them leasure, and giue them oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to reforme their loosenesse of lyfe, to returne vnto him with hope of mercie, to escape the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce ready to be poured out vpon stifneckned sinners. I haue (I say) first declared, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly proued, that such, vnlesse they repent, shall haue none other ende, but eternall condemnation in the bottomlesse pit of hell fire in most bitter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nguish &amp; immortal miserie. Secondarily I haue plainely set foorth with certaine proofe, the most happie ende, the blisfull estate, the good condition of those, who with hartie minde, and earnest af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and pure Zeale imbrace the godlye prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of perfite prayer. By the first part, the terror of Gods intollerable vengeaunce maye batter downe the strong walles of prowde, and vnbroken hartes, by the seconde, the brused consciences of
<pb facs="4"/>
the sorowfull christians, may be happily repaired, and raised vp againe. By the first, sleepy security may holesomely be banished, by the second, godly certainetie of saluation maye easily be procured, through the first, mans hart maye be wounded, through the second, it may be salued, by the first mans mind is, as it were, launched, by the second, healed, by the first, roughly scoured, by the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond freshely bewtified, by the first, opened, by the second clensed, by the first, cut out, and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by the second, polished, by the first, halfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the bondes of cruell Sathan, by the second, safely brought into the gracious fauour of our immortall Sauiour. Thirdly, least something should seeme to bee wanting, for the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the simple Christians, I haue brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye giuen certaine rules, and precepts, wherewith if alwayes our prayers be well ordered, we shall vndoubtedly obtaine our good requestes at the handes of God, which thing assuredly as it is profitable at all times, so in these our most my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable, and wofull dayes, it is most necessarie. For when our enimies doe inuade vs, it is then tyme to prepare to battaile. When vice raigneth, then it is necessarie to see, that vertue be succou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. When Sathan triumpheth, then it is highe
<pb facs="4"/>
time to pray, that he may be displaced. When true humilitie once is defaced, then it is time for hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrysie to be suppressed, and nowe when rebels rage, sometime in inward cogitations, sometimes in outward irruptiōs, it is necessary for the helth, and safegarde of good christians with earnest and hartie mindes, to desire God, that all their enimious wicked enterprises maye bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, their endeuours ouerturned, their deuillish purposes altogither disappointed, and that the princely estate of our most gracious, and godly so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lady, Queene EliZabeth, may for euer bee mightily preserued, worthily maintained, and most prosperously confirmed, which I beseech God in the bowels of Christ Iesus mercyfullye to graunt. For prayer in what estate soeuer we be, is eyther our onely stay, comfort, refuge, and conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or else our principall defence, and safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde. There withall the subtile assaultes of craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Sathan are easily escaped, his sleightes auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, his rage refrayned, his furie brideled, and all his endeuours vtterly disturbed. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise, by prayer especially the mercies of God are liberally graunted, his grace obtayned, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour founde, his loue allured, and his gracious goodnesse bountyfully bestowed. Wherefore let vs
<pb facs="5"/>
imbrace the godly practise of hartie prayer, as the sure seale of our eternall saluation, as the pledge of our redemption, as the certaine token of our blessed election, and so vndoubtedly wee shall at the last raigne for euer, and euer with Christ in all felicitie in his glorious, and immortall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which he graunt for the merites of his most precious passion, to whome with the father, and the holy ghost, be all honor, praise, and glory, world without ende. Amen.</p>
   <closer>God saue our Noble Queene ElyZabeth, and sende continuall peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst hir louing subiectes.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>