<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Any that can Read.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2920_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13510</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23804</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2920</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Any that can Read.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Taylors revenge, or, The rymer William Fennor firkt, feritted, and finely fetcht ouer the coales : wherein his riming raggamuffin rascallity, without partiallity, or feare of principallity, is anagramatized, anotomized, &amp; stigmatized : the occasion of vvhich inuectiue, is breifly set dovvne in the preface to the reader</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London ; Netherlands--Rotterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To Any that can Read.</head>
   <p>BE thou either Freind or Foe or indiferent, all's one,
Read, Laugh, like or dislike, all the care is taken: The
cheifest cause why I wrote this, was on set purpose to please
my selfe. Yet to shew thee the meaning of this little Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
Imagin this <hi>Epistle</hi> to be the doore, and if thou please
come in and see what stuffe the whole Frame is made off.
Be it therefore knowne vnto all men, that I <hi>Iohn Taylor
Waterman,</hi> did agree with <hi>William Fennor,</hi> (who Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantly
and falsely entitles himselfe the Kings Maiesties
<hi>Riming Poet</hi>) to Answere me at a triall off Wit on the
<hi>seauenth of October last</hi> 1614. on the <hi>Hope</hi> stage on
the <hi>Bank-side,</hi> and the said <hi>Fennor</hi> Receiued of me ten
shillings in earnest of his comming to meete me, whereu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
I caused 1000 bills to be Printed, and douulg'd my
name 1000 wayes and more, giuing my Freinds and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
of my acquaintance notice of this <hi>Bear-garden</hi> ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet
of daintie Conceits, and when the day came that the
Play should haue been performed, the house being filld with
<pb facs="4"/>
a great Audience, who had all spent their moneyes extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily:
then this Companion for an <hi>Asse,</hi> Ran away &amp;
left me for a <hi>Foole,</hi> amongst thousands of critticall Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers:
where I was ill thought of by my freinds, scorned
by my foes, and in conclusion, in a greater p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>zzell then the
blinde <hi>Beare</hi> in the midst of all her whip broath; Besides
the some of twenty pounds in money, I lost my Reputation
amongst many, and gaind disgrace in stead of my better
expectations. In Reuenge of which wrongs done vnto me
by the said <hi>Ryming Rascal,</hi> I haue written this I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ectiue
against him, cheifly because the ill looking Hound doth
not confesse he hath iniur'd me, nor hath not so much
honesty as to bring or send me my money that he tooke for
earnest of me: but on the contrary part, he Railes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses
me with his callumnious tongue, and scandalizet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
me in all Companies where he heares me nominated. But
in a word, Reader when thou hast read this that followes, I
thinke thou wilt Iudge me cleare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f the many false Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
that are laid vpon me. So I leaue thee to thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iderations,
and I proceed to my Exclamations.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine as thou art mine,
IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>