<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PRAYER OF THE AVTHOVR TO OVR BLESSED LADY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2953_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14612</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24924.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PRAYER OF THE AVTHOVR TO OVR BLESSED LADY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The contrition of a Protestant preacher, converted to be a Catholiqve scholler : conteyning certayne meditations vpon the fourth penitentiall psalme, Miserere composed by Iames Waddesworth, Bachlour of Diuinitie in the Vniversity of Cambridge, &amp; late parson of Cotton, and of Great-Thorneham in the County of Suffolke, who went into Spaine with the Kinges Maiesties first Embassadour-Legier, as his chaplayne</title>
                 <author>Wadsworth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 112, 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>A PRAYER OF THE AVTHOVR TO OVR BLESSED LADY.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>O</hi> Most pious Virgin Mary, Mother of God: I desire th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e by the great loue thou bearest to thy deare Sonne my Lord &amp; Sauiour Iesus-Christ: That thou wouldest vouchsafe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for me true sorrow for my sinnes, a perfect keeping of all my Senses, an humble Resignatiō of my selfe, &amp; the exercise all those vertues wherewith thou didst so highly please thy diuine Sonne. I also most humbly request thee to direct my wayes in those pathes which may be most agreable to the will of thy Sonne, &amp; profitable for the saluation of my Soule. Amen, sweet Iesus.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>