<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Iudicious Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2967_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14982</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25290.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2967</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Iudicious Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A triple cure of a triple malady : that is of [brace] vanity in apparell, excesse in drinking, impiety in swearing [brace] by E.W, Doctor, and Professor of Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Weston, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 298, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Iudicious Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is not the best ground in the world, which will not abound with bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, bryars, &amp; ill weeds if it be not well tilled; nor any natiō of so good a disposition, which will not become vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ouergrowne with euill manners and customes, if it want good education, examples of true vertue, documents of wisdome, and perfect Discipline. Yea it is obserued, that the best &amp; quickest wits, if they be not well instructed, commonly breake out into actions of most violēt, &amp;
<pb facs="5"/> outragious vices: as the strongest and best furnished ship, sayling most swiftly &amp; ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuocably towards shallows and rockes, is in most danger to miscarry by shipwracke.</p>
   <p>Such also as are accounted to be of a good nature, that is, to be pliable, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to giue contentment to others from their owne bounty and affection, do soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest fall into debasements by the ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their fellowes, whome they haue neither prouidence to eschew, nor courage to reprehend; but suffer themselues to be entangled with good fellowship, as byrds with lime-twigs, and so perish wittingly by their owne facility.</p>
   <p>I need not here to aggrauate the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity which ariseth by these occasions, nor the necessity of good Counsell to hinder their Progresse, and beate men backe from ill Company: nor how great wrong those do to their Countrey and Friendes who hinder such as haue most need of helpe, from conuersation with such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as imploy their endeauours most lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably
<pb facs="5"/> in the setting forward of vertue, and repressing of vice; for the ensuing discourse will sufficiently declare it.</p>
   <p>Only this I would haue thee (Prudent Reader) to vnderstand, that my drift is not to write of these subiects, by way of amplification, or laboured colours of stile, but only to lay downe briefly some princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall arguments that confirme the truthes which I seeke to perswade; obseruing the methode, which nature, and practice of doctrine require in like cases.</p>
   <p>And for entrance to the extirpation of these three pernicious vices, &amp; better vnderstanding of all that followeth; it may please thee to consider first the force of custome, to change opinion euen in the most palpable and sensible thinges. As is proued by a prisoner which hath liued some tyme in a stinking prison, and is no more troubled with the bad sent that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed him in the beginninge, and were inough to make another which should come a new out of the fresh ayre, to cast
<pb facs="6"/> his gorge.</p>
   <p>The same is exemplified by that which hapned to <hi>Plutarke</hi> his guest, who bidaē to dinner by his frend, could eat nothing the first day, because, forsooth, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife of the house, whome he supposed had dressed the meate, was blear-eyed. The next day he had the like difficulty to ouercome his apprehension, yet he eate something. But the third day, custome had abated his auersion so farre, that he eate his meate as well as the rest. This is taught vs in the old saying, <hi>ab assue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis non fit passio:</hi> and we might bring a thousand other examples to confirme it.</p>
   <p>The secōd obseruation may be, that (as it is sayd) in apparell and the like, fooles bringe vp fashions, and oblige wise men to follow them, many times against their willes, not to be holden for singular.</p>
   <p>The third is deduced from these two, that discre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>te men and women, which are become Apes in apparell, not by desire but vpon opinion of necessity, and not to
<pb facs="6"/> be noted of singularity, if they did as they would, and should do if they did well, will be glad to see the vanity which thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues already mislike, layd open in such sort, as those that had not discretion to fall into the account of their folly by themselues, may at least reflect vpon it, and acknowledge it when they reade it plainly set downe.</p>
   <p>And this was to be remembred before hand in the abuse of Apparell: for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Drinking and Swearing are so foule &amp; foolish of thēselues, as they need no more (but to be considered) to be dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted by any reasonable man. For the rest, such I meane as by custome of sinne are transformed into beasts, be not capable of discipline, but must be left to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and iustice of Almighty God: who keep thee euer (Gentle Reader) in the feare of his Iudgements, and loue of his mercy. From my lodginge the 20. of <hi>August. 1616.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>