<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Propositions that are proved in this Discourse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S2974_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15363</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25640</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S2974</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Propositions that are proved in this Discourse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The discovery of a world in the moone, or, A discourse tending to prove, that 'tis probable there may be another habitable world in that planet</title>
                 <author>Wilkins, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                            <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 209, 4 pages, illustrations, diagrams</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="111"/>
   <head>The Propositions that are proved in this Discourse.</head>
   <list>
      <label>
         <hi>Proposition</hi> 1.</label>
      <item>That the strangenesse of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is no sufficient reason why it should be rejected, because other certaine truths have beene formerly esteemed ridiculous, and great absurdities entertayned by common consent. <hi>By way of Preface.</hi>
      </item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 2.</label>
      <item>That a plurality of worlds do's not contradict any principle of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or faith.</item>
      <label>
         <pb facs="111"/>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 3.</label>
      <item>That the heavens doe not consist of any such pure matter which can priviledge them from the like change and corruption, as these inferiour bodies are liable unto.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 4.</label>
      <item>That the Moone is a solid, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, opacous body.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 5.</label>
      <item>That the Moone hath not any light of her owne.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 6.</label>
      <item>That there is a world in the Moone, hath beene the direct opinion of many ancient, with some moderne Mathematicians, and may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be deduced from the tenents of others.</item>
      <label>
         <pb facs="112"/>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 7.</label>
      <item>That those spots and brighter parts which by our sight may bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished in the Moone, doe shew the difference betwixt the Sea and Land in that other World.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 8.</label>
      <item>That the spots represent the Sea, and the brighter parts the Land.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 9.</label>
      <item>That there are high Mountaines, deepe vallies, and spacious plaines in the body of the Moone.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 10.</label>
      <item>That there is an Atmo-sphaera, or an orbe of grosse vaporous aire, immediately encompassing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Moone.</item>
      <label>
         <pb facs="112"/>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 11.</label>
      <item>That as their world is our Moone, so our world is their Moone.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 12.</label>
      <item>That tis probable there may bee such Meteors belonging to that world in the Moone, as there are with us.</item>
      <label>
         <hi>Prop.</hi> 13.</label>
      <item>That tis probable there may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants in this other World, but of what kinde they are is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine.</item>
   </list>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>