<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL SEMI∣NARIE PRIESTS, MONKES, FRIERS, IESVITES, AND ALL LAY-PROFESSORS of the present Romane, falsely pre∣tended Catholike faith, grace and true conuersion in Christ IESVS.</title>
           <author>Copley, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S299_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19326</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5742</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL SEMI∣NARIE PRIESTS, MONKES, FRIERS, IESVITES, AND ALL LAY-PROFESSORS of the present Romane, falsely pre∣tended Catholike faith, grace and true conuersion in Christ IESVS.</title>
                 <author>Copley, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Doctrinall and morall obseruations concerning religion : vvherein the author declareth the reasons of his late vn-enforced departure from the Church of Rome; and of his incorporation to the present Church of England: teaching, maintaining and defending the true Christian catholike and apostolike faith, professed by the ancient primitiue church, most conspicuous in the outward vertues and constant sufferings of many holy bishops and other good Christians, glorious in the crowne of martyrdome. By Iohn Copley seminarie priest</title>
                 <author>Copley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moore (More), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 242, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL SEMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NARIE PRIESTS, MONKES, FRIERS, IESVITES, AND ALL LAY-PROFESSORS of the present Romane, falsely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Catholike faith, grace and <hi>true conuersion in Christ</hi> IESVS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHereas now some monthes are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-passed since my conformitie to the Church of England; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue hitherto beene silent, withdrawing myselfe to further the contemplation of those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements which lead mee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; my zeale of truth and knowledge of your great spiritual miseries who liue wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in a cloud of ignorance, depriued of the most comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table beames of true Christian faith, working by the heate of charitie in mens soules, enforceth me to dedicate these my doctrinall and morall obseruations vnto your selues, as standing in most need of them. My intention in dedicating
<pb facs="3"/>them to you, is no other then true compassion of your soules dangerous estate, not seeing nor knowing your owne erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous doctrines taught in the present Romane Church; of which I dare say many of you are sincere zealous professors with onely regard to your soules health, and the kingdome of heauen, esteeming that aboue all things to bee the chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest to bee sought for in this world, is in truth it is; and therefore your case the more worthie of Christian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseration, and true Apostolicall endeauours for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie out of your so perillous and lamentable a condition, which, according to the small portion of that talent that Almightie God hath vouchsafed to bestow vpon mee, I haue endeuoured to shew vnto you by this Treatise, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you curteously and charitably to accept in good part, with no lesse humility and care of your owne soules good, then I do present it vnto you with a sincere desire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the most tender bowels of Christ Iesus. Vouchsafe to reade it with deliberate iudgement; examine well the spirit wherewith it is written; weigh the substance and contents rather then the manner or circumstances of my writing; the stile is but plaine and familiar; you shall find no affectation of eloquence in it; because my labours and paines taken herein, haue been rather for the profit of your soules, then for the recreation of your wits. I know well that neither the planting of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> nor the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of <hi>Apollo</hi> can redound to your profit, vnlesse God giue encrease and prosper the successe; and therefore lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the encrease to God, and desiring you most attentiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reade these my obseruations, deliberately to ponder them, and effectually to follow them: I most kindly take my leaue of you with Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> charitable words: <hi>Pax
<pb facs="3"/>Dei quae exuperat omnem sensum custodiat corda vestra &amp; intelligentias vestras in Christo Iesu.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.7.</note> The peace of God which passeth all vnderstanding keepe your hearts and intelligences in Christ Iesus. <hi>Resting this 13. day of Iune, Anno Domini, 1612.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A most zealous friend and louer of your soules: IOHN COPLEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>