<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT RE∣uerend Father in God, THOMAS Lord Byshop of LONDON, my Ho∣nourable good Lord: all Grace, Prospe∣rity, and Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Crakanthorp, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S308_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19548</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT RE∣uerend Father in God, THOMAS Lord Byshop of LONDON, my Ho∣nourable good Lord: all Grace, Prospe∣rity, and Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Crakanthorp, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon at the solemnizing of the happie inauguration of our most gracious and religious soueraigne King Iames : Wherein is manifestly proued, that the soueraignty of kings is immediatly from God, and second to no authority on earth whatsoeuer. Preached at Paules Crosse, the 24. of March last. 1608. By Richard Crakanthorpe, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Crakanthorpe, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father in God,</hi> THOMAS Lord Byshop of LONDON, my <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable good Lord: all Grace, Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and Happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE manifolde and waighty Ecclesiasticall affaires, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Lordshippe is daily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, and many times wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; partly in aduancing the sincere profession of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truth, and partly in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the happy tranquility of this most renowned Church, haue often occasioned me to remember the words, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of that learned father <hi>S. Augustin.</hi> Though besides those <note n="a" place="margin">Innumerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas curas. Aug. lib. de oper. Monac. ca. 29.</note> innumerable Ecclesiasticall cares which hee sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and of which he said, that almost none would beleeue them, but such as had experience of them, he was daily incumbred also with the iudiciall hearing of verie many secular causes, for which as he saith, <note n="b" place="margin">Non de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro non de ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gento, non de fundis &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, pro qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quotidie sub<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> isto capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te salu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>amur. vt dissen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>iones hominum ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minemus. Aug Epist. 147.</note> he was daily with al reuerence attended and saluted by the people; yet some in that age most vniustly blamed both him &amp; other Bishops,
<pb facs="3"/>
as being desidious, and like the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> tying heauie burthens on other mens shoulders, which themselues would not touch with their litle fingers (&amp; who can pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly escape that censure, if the indefatigable industry &amp; toile of S. <hi>Augustine</hi> could not quit him thereof?) He then with a most serious and solemne protestation answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <note n="c" place="margin">Aug l. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Monac. cap. 29.</note> I call Iesus Christ to witnesse vpon my soule, that I had much rather giue my selfe to reading, praying, and other spirituall exercises, yea to daily handy-workes, then indure the most tumultuous perplexities of other mens causes about their secular businesses, either (<note n="d" place="margin">Vel i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>dican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do dirimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, vel inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniendo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidendis. ibid.</note>) iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to end them or by perswasion to preuent them.</p>
   <p>The cogitation heereof, had almost perswaded me not to withdraw your Lordshippe, so much as to the viewe of these my slender labours, but that the seuerall bandes of duty which I owe vnto your Lordship, ouer-swayed with me heerein at the last. For hauing not onely beene called (as from little <hi>Zoar</hi> to <hi>Ierusalem</hi>) by that message which to me was no other then the voice of God, though some younger <hi>Samuels,</hi> may perhappes mistake it to bee <hi>Elias</hi> voice; but further also in that straitnesse of time, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily encouraged by your Lordship to this seruice; the fruit of my labours therein (if it be any) I iudged it my duty to present to him, by whose Authoritie and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they were first vndertaken.</p>
   <p>Againe, seeing my heartie and sincere desire heerein, was to testifie my vnfaigned loue, first to Gods truth, and then to the peace of our <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> in both which, I expect no lesse then the seuerest censures of two, in themselues op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite, and both of them very rigorous aduersaries, who contrary to the Apostles <note n="e" place="margin">Ephes. 4, 15.</note> rule, either follow not the truth, or follow it not in loue: I was emboldened in both these to
<pb facs="3"/>
intreat protection vnder your Lordships name, as one who liuing vnder your Lordships, both publicke and Domesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call gouernment, haue, and do daily see manie assured ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments of your Lordships zeal to the one, and prudence ioyned with great moderation in the other.</p>
   <p>Besides, I must and do with thankefulnes acknowledge, which I haue often heeretofore gladlie recounted, a good part of that light with which God hath in mercie vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed vnto me, to haue bin receiued frō that faire burning lamp, which many years in our Vniuersitie, your L. verie often and happilie helde forth vnto vs: then especiallie, when in the last yeares of our late Soueraigne, &amp; in those, as some thought, declining daies; wherein the children of <hi>Babylon,</hi> vpon some vainly conceiued hopes, I know not what, began somwhat insolently to insult. At which most needfull time it cannot bee forgotten, how the religious, constant &amp; godly zeal of your <hi>L.</hi> being one most eminent in that place, did animate &amp; incourage many others, my selfe among the rest, who then sat at the feet of <hi>Gamali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and who by those words vttered in fittest time, by the tongue of the learned, found in our selues, how truly the <hi>Wiseman</hi> saide, <note n="f" place="margin">Eccles. 12, 11</note> The words of the wise are like goads, and like nailes fastned by the maisters of the assemblies.</p>
   <p>If in these respectes I present this small pledge of my dutie, to your Lordshippe, and with a willing heart offer this mite vnto the <hi>Lords Treasury,</hi> let me in excuse of the slendernesse thereof, vse those fit words of <hi>S. Ierom.</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Hier. Apol 2. aduers. Ru<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>in.</note> Euery man offers in Gods Tabernacle according to his ability; some offer Gold, and Siluer, and precious stones, others bring Silke, and Purple, and Scarlet, and fine lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, <hi>Nobiscum bene agitur si obtulerimus pelles &amp; caprarum pilos.</hi> Howsoeuer it bee, I gladly submit
<pb facs="4"/>
it to your Lordships graue wisedome, and to the Church of God, euen in those most submissiue words and maner, which I long since learned of the most learned S. <hi>Austen,</hi> and which (beeing heere expressed) in all my speeches and writings, I earnestly desire to be vnderstood; <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> (<note n="h" place="margin">Aug lib, 15. de Trinit. cap. vlt.</note>) <hi>Deus, Quaecunque dixi de tuo, agnoscant &amp; tui, Si qua de meo, &amp; tu ignosce &amp; tui.</hi> Blacke Notley in Essex. May, 15. 1609.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships Chaplaine in all duty, most humbly to be commanded,
RICHARD CRAKANTHORPE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>