<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Epilogue vnto the Reader.</title>
           <author>Turberville, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3107_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14017</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24325.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3107</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Epilogue vnto the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Turberville, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of falconrie or havvking : for the onely delight and pleasure of all noblemen and gentlemen : collected out of the best authors, aswell Italians as Frenchmen, and some English practises withall concerning falconrie heretofore published by George Turbervile, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Turberville, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>382 pages, illustrations, 4° in 8's</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <pb facs="190"/>
   <head>❧ The Epilogue vnto the <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>LO Reader here, the end of this my booke,</l>
      <l>Though not the end of my good will and loue,</l>
      <l>Bestowe thy paines hereon a while to looke,</l>
      <l>As I imployed my head for thy behooue:</l>
      <l>It shall suffice if thou do not reprooue</l>
      <l>This slender worke, compilde for thy delight,</l>
      <l>Whose friendly looke my labour shall requite.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I count my toyle and trauaile but a game,</l>
      <l>I deeme the dayes not long or spent amisse,</l>
      <l>If so I may vnto thy fancie frame</l>
      <l>This booke of mine which all of Hawking is,</l>
      <l>Than which there can be found no better blisse</l>
      <l>In my conceit to such as loue the glee,</l>
      <l>And force the fields where brauest pleasures be.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I must confesse, my Hammers haue but hewde</l>
      <l>That royall Rocke, which others found of yore,</l>
      <l>I do but tread the path which others shewde</l>
      <l>Vnto their friends, to make their skill the more:</l>
      <l>I but translate a garment made before:</l>
      <l>Which if I do with gallant shape to view,</l>
      <l>I deeme as much as if I made a new.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="191"/>
      <l>For hard it is to stalke in others steppes.</l>
      <l>He thinkes himselfe a thrall that marcheth so:</l>
      <l>He iumpes in ioy that at his pleasure leapes,</l>
      <l>And is not forst in others feet to goe:</l>
      <l>Nothing more leefe than liberty you know,</l>
      <l>Which no Translatour hath I vndertake,</l>
      <l>Vnlesse that he his Authours sence forsake.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which vaunt I dare, I seldome here haue done,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Zforcino</hi> knowes, and can controll me then,</l>
      <l>Italian borne, whose booke I over-runne,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Giorgies</hi> eke compilde with learned pen,</l>
      <l>Assuredly these two were skilfull men,</l>
      <l>And wistfull well what Hawkes and hawking ment,</l>
      <l>And all things else that further this intent.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To <hi>Tardiffe</hi> eke the Frenchman I appeale,</l>
      <l>To <hi>Malopyn,</hi> and <hi>Mychelyn,</hi> cunning wightes,</l>
      <l>Let <hi>Artelow<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>he</hi> be witnesse how I deale,</l>
      <l>In field affaires, or else in river flights,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Cassyan</hi> eke who well of hawking wrytes:</l>
      <l>All these I wish as Iudges in the case</l>
      <l>Where I corrupt or alter any place.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Some men perhaps will wonder that I wrote</l>
      <l>Of slately hawkes, and byrdes of rare delight,</l>
      <l>And blazde it out but in so base a note,</l>
      <l>As scarce will please the gallant Courtiers sight,</l>
      <l>Who weyes no gold that is not burnisht bright:</l>
      <l>His curious eare but hardly will digest,</l>
      <l>Sweet Musickes sound, that is not of the best.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="191"/>
      <l>For mine excuse and for my simple pen,</l>
      <l>To answere thus, I feare I shall be faine,</l>
      <l>Sith charge of Hawkes committed is to men,</l>
      <l>That Nobles serve for yearely hyre, and gaine,</l>
      <l>(Who are not fine but homely mates and plaine)</l>
      <l>My purpose was, to set them downe the trade,</l>
      <l>To man their Hawks, and how they might be made.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For Peeres (I know, and you must needs agree)</l>
      <l>Regard no more but onely to behold</l>
      <l>The fleeing Hawkes, their ioy is but to see</l>
      <l>The haughty Haggard worth her weight in gold,</l>
      <l>To slay the fowle at brooke with courage bolde,</l>
      <l>With Hawkes they never deale in other sort,</l>
      <l>Their servants feed, and they enioy the sport.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which if be so, the lowe and playnest stile</l>
      <l>Doth best agree the Falconers mind to fit,</l>
      <l>To carpe it fine with those that haue no guile,</l>
      <l>A ieast it were and signe of slender wit,</l>
      <l>The writers ought the readers vaine to hitte.</l>
      <l>This was the cause I wrote my booke so plaine,</l>
      <l>I told it earst, I tell it now againe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The modest mind I know, will rest content,</l>
      <l>With this excuse, and brooke mine answere well,</l>
      <l>Of other some perhaps I shall be shent.</l>
      <l>Whose sullen breasts with secret envie swell,</l>
      <l>Who pleaseth all, deserues to beare the bell.</l>
      <l>But if the Courtier fancy this my booke,</l>
      <l>I scorne the proud disdainfull Momus looke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="192"/>
      <l>Falconers farewell, at pleasure doe pervse</l>
      <l>These leaves and lines, each picture and each page.</l>
      <l>Readers adue, I have no farther newes,</l>
      <l>I can but wish you ancient Nestors age,</l>
      <l>Vnto whose doomes my writings here I gage:</l>
      <l>To cure your Hawkes or make your cunning more,</l>
      <l>If ought be here, I clappe my hands therefore.</l>
      <l>My Muse, and I, haue done the best we can,</l>
      <l>To learne you how your Hawkes to lewre &amp; man.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>George Turbervile.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <q>
      <l>Liuor, edax rerum, tu{que} in vidiosa vetustas,</l>
      <l>Omnia destruitis.</l>
   </q>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="192"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>