<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader, and in speciall to my worthy good Friends, in and a∣about the City of London, Peace, and setling of mind.</title>
           <author>Sedgwick, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3177_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11846</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22149.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3177</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader, and in speciall to my worthy good Friends, in and a∣about the City of London, Peace, and setling of mind.</title>
                 <author>Sedgwick, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eye of faith open to God : unfolded in a sermon preached at the funerall of that vertuous and religious gentlewoman, Mrs. Julian Blackvvell, together with a narration of her vertuous life and happy death by John Sedgvvick</title>
                 <author>Sedgwick, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 112 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader, and in speciall to my worthy good Friends, in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about the City of <hi>London,</hi> Peace, and setling of mind.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He shaking of<note place="margin">A double temper of men in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mes of danger.</note> the water doth not more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the mudd that's at the bottome, nor the beating of the pulse the distemper of the body; then Times of Danger doe
<pb facs="7"/> bewray men in point of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or excesse: now men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare<note place="margin">1. To be carelesse.</note> either to be carelesse and gracelesly secure, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their eyes bound up, and their consciences so seared, that they neither see or feare any danger: or to be over-fearing: having their<note place="margin">2. To be over feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> eyes too open upon, or their hearts too much affected with the sadnesse, and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the times; the first sort I leave to the vanity of their minde, and sinfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of their courses, assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them that their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in carnall security is to them an evident fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner
<pb facs="7"/> of their future mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the latter sort I shall advise to consider of these two things: First, that the<note place="margin">The Springs of over-much fearing.</note> over-much fearing of mans heart in evill times doth arise, from a false eye, or a wrong foundation: I meane the eye, and the Arme of flesh; he that at such time hath no other eye to see withall, then that by which he seeth every thing, or being able to pierce no deeper, or looke no higher then naturall reason, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward objects can helpe him, shall be sure to finde that his senses will faile him, and his troubles sinke him:
<pb facs="8"/> Besides, the <hi>Arme of Flesh</hi> trusted unto, and relied upon, will make him to ebb and flow, and shall hold his spirit in a course of such constant agitation, that in the end he shall flagg and faint: Flesh at the best is too weake a prop to stay the soule, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine impeacher, and empai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of mans confidence, and comfort; and who so doe put it into the place of a god, shall undoubtedly find from it the deceivings of a creature. Secondly, that the best way to quit our selves of an over-fearing heart in the daies of trouble, is to get
<pb facs="8"/> an eye of Faith, which alone shuts up the eye of sense, and getteth such views of Gods Love, Power, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that God is knowne to be, and also made the sole stay, and staffe of the soule; upon whom whosoever truly trusteth he is in such safety, that no malice of men or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels can endanger him. My Brethren, had we the Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call eyes of faith, we should feare lesse; though times vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to sense are distressefull, and almost desperate: this alone can see a better issue then carnall reason can apprehend, and an higher power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect
<pb facs="9"/> and guard then humane helpes are either liekly or able to affoord; this will make a man waite till the fifth Scene of the Tragedy is acted, knowing that troubles have their turnings, as spring-tides have their eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings: This eye <hi>David</hi> had in his troubles, as the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Discourse will shew you, and this eye I wish unto you all, that your confidences and comforts may abound: and though I hope that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you have this eye, yet beholding your dimnesse, and weaknesse, I have sent unto you these following Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="9"/> upon a Text given unto mee, to preach on at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of Mistrisse <hi>Iulian Black well,</hi> and I desire that they may have the same worke upon you that was wrought upon <hi>Elisha's</hi> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that by them you may be enabled to rid your mindes of those base and unbeleeving feares, wherewithall you have beene too long and too much assaulted and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and may direct your soules amid your troublesome cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and distractions to your onely resting place, namely, the strong God in whom all safety and securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="10"/> is to be found, which is the onely thing aimed at in the publique Preaching, and sought for in the private prayers of him that is your daily remembrancer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IO: SEDGVVICK.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>