<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honorable Lord Charles Haward,
Baron of Effingham, Knight of the noble order of the
Garter, Liuetenant of her Maiesties Counties of Sussex and Surrey.
Constable of her Maiesties Honor and Castle of Win∣sor,
Lord high Admirall of England, Ireland, and VVales, and of the
Dominions and Isles of the same, of the Towne of Callis and
marches thereof, Normandy, Gascony, and Geynes, Captaine
generall of her Maiesties Seas and Nauie royall, and one of
her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell. Iohn Dauis
wisheth increase of honour and
perfect felicitie.</title>
           <author>Davies, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S319_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19937</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6368.4</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S319</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honorable Lord Charles Haward,
Baron of Effingham, Knight of the noble order of the
Garter, Liuetenant of her Maiesties Counties of Sussex and Surrey.
Constable of her Maiesties Honor and Castle of Win∣sor,
Lord high Admirall of England, Ireland, and VVales, and of the
Dominions and Isles of the same, of the Towne of Callis and
marches thereof, Normandy, Gascony, and Geynes, Captaine
generall of her Maiesties Seas and Nauie royall, and one of
her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell. Iohn Dauis
wisheth increase of honour and
perfect felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seamans secrets : deuided into 2. partes, wherein is taught the three kindes of sayling, horizontall, peradoxall [sic], and sayling vpon a great circle : also an horizontall tyde table for the easie finding of the ebbing and flowing of the tydes, with a regiment newly calculated for the finding of the declination of the sunne, and many other most necessary rules and instruments, not heeretofore set foorth by any / newly published by Iohn Dauis of Sandrudge</title>
                 <author>Davis, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>92 pages, illustrations</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honorable Lord Charles Haward,
Baron of Effingham, Knight of the noble order of the
Garter, Liuetenant of her Maiesties Counties of Sussex and Surrey.
Constable of her Maiesties Honor and Castle of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor,
Lord high Admirall of England, Ireland, and VVales, and of the
Dominions and Isles of the same, of the Towne of Callis and
marches thereof, Normandy, Gascony, and Geynes, Captaine
generall of her Maiesties Seas and Nauie royall, and one of
her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell. Iohn Dauis
wisheth increase of honour and
perfect felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable and my especiall good Lord, as by
the instinct of nature all men are desirous of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
and take pleasure in the varieties of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
so it is likewise ingraffed by the same benefit of
nature, in the harts of true nobilitie, not onely to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
the vulgare sort, but also to cherrish, support, and
countenance all such as shall in due course prosecute
their vocation: and as such practises either specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
or mecanicall, shall receiue sauourable place in
the honourable opinion of nobilitie, by so much the
more shall the practiser be esteemed: which is the cause that at this time imboldneth
me, to present vnto your most honourable fauour this smal treatise of Nauigation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a breefe collection of such practises as in my seuerall voyages I haue from experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
collected Among which in my three seuerall attempts for the discouery of the
Northwest passage, thereby to finde a shorte and nauigable course vnto the riche and
famous Countries of <hi>Cathayo, China, Pegu,</hi> the Isles of <hi>Molucan</hi> and <hi>Philli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina,</hi>
that thereby to the great and inestimable benefite of our Countrie, there might
be a rich and plentifull trade procured betweene vs and the said nations in short time
to be perfourmed, and with great safetie in regarde of the course: which action and
discouery (by meanes of that honourable Counseller Sir <hi>Frauncis Walsingham</hi>
Knight, principall Secretary to her Maiestie) was with good resolution accepted by the
Merchants of London but in the decay of his honourable life, the attempt was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb facs="3"/>
quailed: but howsoeuer mens mindes alter, yet vndoubtedly there is a passage
nauigable, and easie to be perfourmed by that course (whensoeuer it shall please God
to reueale the same) by inuincible reasons, and sufficient experience to be proued: and
although before I entred into that discouery, I was sufficiently perswaded of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie
thereof, by historicall relation substantially confirmed, whereof to the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
I made sufficient proofe, but especially to my worshipfull good freend Master
<hi>William Sanderson,</hi> the onely Merchant, that to his great charges with most constant
trauaile did labour for the finishing thereof: yet I thanke God that of late it hath
beene my very good chaunce to receiue better assurance then euer before of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie
of that passage, and such was my vehement desire for the perfourmance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
that thereby I was onely induced to goe with M. <hi>Candishe</hi> in his second attempt
for the South Seas, vpon his constant promise vnto me, that when we came to the
<hi>Callifornia,</hi> I should there haue his Pinnice with my owne Barck (which for that
purpose went with me to my great charges) to search that North west discouery vpon
those backe partes of <hi>America,</hi> but God hath otherwise disposed our purposes in his
deuine Iudgements, for M. <hi>Candishe</hi> being halfe way through the straights of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilane,</hi>
and impatient of the tempestious furiousnes of that place, hauing all his Ships
and company with him, returned for <hi>Brasill,</hi> by the authoritie of his commaund, whē
with a leading winde we might haue passed the same, and returning more then 80.
leages toward <hi>Brasill,</hi> my selfe being in his Ship named the <hi>Desire,</hi> without Boate,
Oares, Sayles, Cables, cordage, victuals, or health of my companye sufficient for that
attempt, was seperated in a frette of weather, and forced to seeke the nex shorte for my
releefe, and recouering a harborow by vs named Port Desire, being in the lati. of 48.
deg. did there repaire my most miserable wantes, and there staying foure moneths in
most lamentable distresse, did againe conclude with my company to giue an other at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
to passe the straights, as my best meane to gaine releefe. And three times I
was in the South Seas, but still by furious weather forced back againe: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
all this my labour to perfourme the voyage for his profite, and to saue my
selfe, (for I did aduenture and my good freends for my sake 1100. pounds in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.)
M. <hi>Candishe</hi> was content to account me to be the authour of his ouerthrowe,
and to write with his dying hand that I ranne from him, when as his owne Ship was
returned many moneths before me,</p>
   <p>I am bolde to make this relation vnto your Lordship, onelye to satisfie your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
of my conuersation, for were I faultie of so foule a crime, I were worthy of tenne
thousand tormentes, in presuming to present this Treatise to your honourable Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
and now referring my cause to your Lordships consideration, I will again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
to my purpose.</p>
   <p>In those Northwest voyages where Nauigation must be executed in most exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
sorte, in those attempts I was enforced to search all possible meanes required in
<pb facs="3"/>
sayling, by which occasion I haue gathered together this breefe treatise, which with my
selfe I doe dedicate to your most honourable protection, being desirous if it lay in my
power, to doe farre greater matter in your Lordships seruice, hoping of your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
pardon, because it is onely done to shew my dutifull affection, and not for any
singularitie that the worke containeth, For I thinke there be many hundreds in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
that can in a farre greater measure and more excellent methode expresse the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
arte of Nauigation, and I am fully perswaded that our Countrie is not inferiour
to any for men of rare knowledge, singuler application, and exquisite execution of the
Artes Mathematick, for what Strangers may be compared with M. <hi>Thomas Digges</hi>
Esquire, our Countryman the great master of Archmastrie, and for Thericall specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
and most cunning calculation M. <hi>Dee</hi> and M. <hi>Thomas Heriotts</hi> are hardly to
be matched: and for the mecanicall practises drawnefrom the Artes Mathematick,
our Countrie doth yeelde men of principall excellencie, as M. <hi>Emery Mulleneux</hi>
for the exquisite making of Globus bodies, and M. <hi>Nicholas Hellyar</hi> for the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie
of portrature hath the praise of Europe, M. <hi>Baker</hi> for his skill and surpassing
grounded knowledge for the building of Ships aduantageable to all purpose, hath not
in any nation his equall.</p>
   <p>And now that I may returne to the painefull Seaman, it is not vnknowne to all
nations of the earth, that the English goeth before all others in the practises of say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
as appeareth by the excellent discouery of Sir <hi>Franncis Drake,</hi> in his passage
through the straights of Magilane, which being then so rawly knowne, he could not
haue passed, vnlesse he had beene a man of great practise and rare resolution: so much
I may boldely say, because I haue seene and tasted the frowardnes of the place, with
the great vnlikelyhoode of any passage to be that way.</p>
   <p>I might heere repeate the most valiant and excellent attemps of Sir <hi>Hugh Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lougbie,</hi>
Sir <hi>Iohn Hawkins,</hi> Sir <hi>Humfry Gilbert,</hi> and your Lordships seruant M.
<hi>George Raymond,</hi> with diuers others that haue giuen most resolute attempts in the
practises of Nauigation, as well for the discouery as other execution, whereby good
proofe is made, that not onely in the skill of Nauigation, but also in the mecanicall
execution of the practises of sayling, we are not to be matched by any nation of
the earth.</p>
   <p>And sith Nauigation is the meane whereby Countries are discouered, and comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
drawne betweene nation and nation, the word of God published to the blessed
recouery of the forraine of castes from whome it hath pleased his deuine Maiestie as
yet to detaine the brightnes of his glory: and that by nauigation common weales
through mutuall trade are not onely susteined, but mightily enriched by whole hard
aduentures such excellent benefites are atchieued, for by his exceeding great hazzards
the forme of the earth, the quantities of Countries, the diuersitie of nations, and the
natures of Zones, Climats, countries and people, are apparantly made known vnto vs:
<pb facs="4"/>
Besides, the great benefites mutually interchanged betweene nations, of such fruites,
commodities, and artificiall practises wherewith God hath blessed eche perticular
Countrie, coast, and nation, according to the nature and scituation of the place.</p>
   <p>For what hath made the Spaniard to be so great a Monarch, the Commaunder of
both Indias, to abound in wealth and all natures benefites, but onely the painefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie
of his Subiects by Nauigation: their former trade was onely figs, Orenges, and
Oyle, but now through Nauigation it is brought to be golde, siluer, pearles, silkes, and
spice, by long and painefull trade recouered. Which great benefites onely by her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties
louing clemencie and mercifull fauour he doth possesse: for if her highnes and
her most honourable Lords would but regarde the small distance betweene her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
and those famous rich kingdomes, the easines of the passage being once dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered,
(the Northwest I meane) with the full sufficiencie of her highnes Subiects to
effect the same, there could then be no do doubt but her stately seate of London should
be the storehouse of Europe, and a nursse to all nations, in yeelding all Indian commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities
in a farre better condition, and at a more easie rate then now brought vnto vs,
exchanging commodities of our owne store, with a plentifull returne at the firste
hand, which now by many exchanges are brought vnto vs.</p>
   <p>Then should the Spaniard againe returne to his olde trade, and our sacred Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
be seated the Commaunder of the earth: which trade and most fortunate
discouery, we aboue all nations ought most principally to regarde, because of the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie
and inviolable force of our Shipping, which is not onely the commaunding
fortresse of our Countrie, but also the dread of our aduersary, and glory of our nation:
wherein we doe in no sorte flatter our selues▪ for it was made apparant to all nations
of the earth, by the late most famous conquest that her Maiestie had against the
huge supposed inuincible fleete of the Spaniard, being by her Nauie vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund
of your Lordship who there in person and in place of her Maiestie, to your
eternall glorious same did disgrace their glory, and confound their force, and manifest
their weakenes by their dastardly flight, through Gods prouidence and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships
stately resolution.</p>
   <p>Then sith Nauigation is a matter of so great moment, I suppose that euery man is
bound in dutie to giue his best furtherance thereunto: among whome as the most
vnmeete of all, yet wishing all good to the painefull traueller, I haue published this
shorte treatise, naming it the <hi>Seamans Secrets,</hi> because by certaine questions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded
and answered, I haue not omitted any thing that appertaineth to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
of Nauigation, whereby if there may growe any increase of knowledge or ease
in practise, it is the thing which I cheefely desire.</p>
   <p>To manifest the necessary conclusions of Nauigation in breefe and shorte tearmes
is my onely intent, and therefore I omit to declare the causes of tearmes and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition
of artificiall wordes, as matters superfluous to my purpose, neither haue I laide
<pb facs="4"/>
downe the cunning conclusions apt for Schollers to practise vpon the shore, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
those things that are needfullye required in a sufficient Seaman: beseeching your
honourable Lordship to pardon my boldenesse, and with your fauourable counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
to regarde my dutifull affection, I most humblye commit your good
Lordship to the mercies of God, who long preserue your
health with continuall increase of
honour.</p>
   <p>From <hi>Sandrudge</hi> by <hi>Darthmouth</hi> the 20. of
August 1594.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all dutifull
seruice to commaund,
Iohn Dauis.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>