<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly affected Reader, I. D.
and I. W. doe hartily wish the howerly
encrease of a true sauing knowledge, by the
reuelation of Iesus Christ.
So be it.</title>
           <author>W., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S323_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20000</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6439</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S323</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly affected Reader, I. D.
and I. W. doe hartily wish the howerly
encrease of a true sauing knowledge, by the
reuelation of Iesus Christ.
So be it.</title>
                 <author>W., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Dialogicall discourses of spirits and diuels : Declaring their proper essence, natures, dispositions, and operations: their possessions, and dispossessions: with other the appendantes, peculiarly appertaining to those speciall points. Verie conducent, and pertinent to the timely procuring of some Christian conformitie in iudgement: for the peaceable compounding of the late sprong controuersies concerning all such intricate and difficult doubts. By Iohn Deacon. Iohn Walker. Preachers</title>
                 <author>Deacon, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 356, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the godly affected Reader, I. D.
and I. W. doe hartily wish the howerly
encrease of a true sauing knowledge, by the
reuelation of Iesus Christ.
So be it.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Christian <hi>Reader,</hi> we doe (in this
following <hi>treatise</hi>) present to thy pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
consideration, our priuat opinion
concerning the vndoubted <hi>possession</hi>
and <hi>dispossession</hi> of <hi>Diuels.</hi> Assuring our
selues to gaine foorthwith thy holy
approbation heerein: so farre foorth
especially, as thou perceiuest the same
to fall foorth pat in euerie point with
the infallible truth of the Lord. The originall occasion of this
our lately attempted enterprise: did <hi>primarily</hi> proceed from
those late <hi>vnwoonted occurrents</hi> which accidentally fell foorth
in our countrey, about the supposed <hi>possession</hi> and <hi>dispossession</hi>
of <hi>Sommers.</hi> An <hi>accident</hi> (we doe freely confesse) no lesse no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously
knowen throughout the whole land then diuersly
entertayned, according to the variable &amp; diuers affections of
men. The maine <hi>argument</hi> of the <hi>treatise</hi> it selfe, is a matter
(we assure thee) not rashly resolued vpon, but seriously held
and maintayned (by the one of vs especially) for many yeeres
past: as fiue hundred yet liuing are able to witnes, and the
other of vs also (in an <hi>experimented</hi> knowledge) both can and
doth testifie the same by these presents. For the verie first
newes of this newly supposed rare <hi>accident,</hi> recalling vs both
afresh to some serious consideration of our former set <hi>studies:</hi>
did so diuersly affect our <hi>mindes</hi> with a diuerse and contrarie
<hi>iudgement</hi> (the one verie constantly <hi>auouching,</hi> the other no
lesse confidently <hi>impugning</hi> that falsely pretended <hi>action</hi>) as
we both became resolute (with tooth and nayle) to trie forth
the certaine <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>vntruth</hi> at the least, of our sundrie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits
concerning the matter in <hi>question.</hi> Yea, and (which more
is) we so deepely deuoted our selues to the timely support of
<pb facs="6"/>
those our seuerall <hi>opinions:</hi> as no one labour (how loathsome
soeuer) was yrkesome vnto vs, which tended that way, but in
the least shew of appearance. For what one <hi>Librarie</hi> was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ransackt,
or learned <hi>brother</hi> vnconferred withall wheresoeuer
we came: to further vs both in those seuerall points we seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
held? What one iourney was refused, or present toyle
vnattempted, to trie foorth the sound truth of such flying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
as ranne all abroad: and all this for the more enabling,
and the better furnishing of vs to that our former determined
skirmish? What sundrie and often <hi>recourses</hi> the one to the
other? What <hi>entercourse</hi> of writings? What mutuall
<hi>conferences?</hi> What hot disputes? What <hi>arguings?</hi> What <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerings?</hi>
What <hi>replies,</hi> and <hi>reioynders:</hi> or euer we could fitly
accord about the seuerall <hi>questions</hi> propounded betweene vs?
And (which is more to be considered) the <hi>contention</hi> it selfe
concerning these <hi>matters,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 15. 37. 38.</note> it became no lesse violent then that
betweene <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> about the hauing of <hi>Iohn Marke</hi>
in their companie: in so much as we eftsoones departed asun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the one from the other. Howbeit that onely wise God,
who turneth the infirmities of his <hi>seruants</hi> to the furtherance
of his glorie, he did so moderate our <hi>mindes</hi> concerning the
<hi>action</hi> in hande, as wee both of vs fully resolued to stande
fast to our <hi>tacklings:</hi> and thereupon also (by an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable
couenant) did foorthwith conclude to continue
this newly attempted <hi>controuersie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> vntill (by the verie sway of
<hi>truth</hi>) the one be enforced, <hi>dare manus,</hi> to hold foorth the <hi>hand,</hi>
and submit to the other. And herein also we found euerie
hower, the fauorable assistance of <hi>Gods holy spirit</hi> for the time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
suggesting of many strange and vnwoonted <hi>matters,</hi> which
haue not hetherto beene vsually heard of concerning the
<hi>question</hi> it selfe. With these many <hi>meditations</hi> and seuerall
<hi>conferences</hi> we were wholy taken vp, till the verie <hi>truth</hi> it selfe
(as we verily beleeue) began (after many debatings and bic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerings)
to breake foorth like the <hi>sunne</hi> in his strength,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 10. 11.</note>
Whereupon also, we eftsoones began to <hi>speake both of vs but
one and the selfesame things:</hi> and (which more is) being now
knit together in one <hi>minde</hi> and one <hi>iudgement</hi> concerning
these seuerall matters, we determined foorthwith to put
downe in writing, whatsoeuer had deliberately passed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
vs. Purposing withall to vse the priuate contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="6"/>
of these our <hi>primarie labours;</hi> as a prouoking sharpe <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pur</hi>
to pricke vs eftsoones an ende vnto the timely vndertaking
of the like priuate conference, in some other <hi>matters</hi> else of
like waightie importance. That (being by this meanes seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred
quite from all secular cares) we might the more freely
imploy our whole <hi>mindes</hi> to such secret <hi>meditations</hi> as should
further the timely discharge of our seuerall <hi>duties.</hi> Perceiuing
moreouer by the timely dispatch of this one intricate <hi>matter:</hi>
that two <hi>conscionable ministers</hi> conioyning their studies (being
both of them industrious &amp; bent wholy in hart,<note place="margin">Eccles. 1. 12. 13.</note>
      <hi>to search and to
find forth wisedome by althings that are done vnder heauen</hi>) might
(by such mutuall endeuours) verie easily accomplish many
profitable <hi>workes</hi> for themselues and some others. Howbeit,
for the putting ouer of these our priuate labours to the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
veiw of the world,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reasons for the hetherto sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing of this present treatis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> that (we assure thee) was neuer in our
thoughts at the first: no, we did fully resolue to keepe these
our <hi>conferences,</hi> from the sight of all others, saue onely our
selues, for these following <hi>reasons.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>First, we were greatly discouraged from the <hi>publication</hi>
hereof in an onely regard of our proper <hi>imperfections,</hi> for the
skilfull determining of such intricate doubts: acknowledging
our manifold wants to be such &amp; so great, as we were mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
afraid to put the due trial of our skil vpon <hi>termes.</hi> And for
this cause we durst not attempt the tendring of our owne, but
hourely expected from some others of more <hi>maturity; a booke
better ballanced,</hi> for the timely encoūtring with such late bred
<hi>broiles</hi> as concerned especially those vnwonted occurrents.</p>
   <p>Secondly, our said purpose for publishing this <hi>treatise,</hi> was
also eftsoones nipt in the head; by often recounting the <hi>new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled
nicenesse</hi> of this present age: wherein, nothing almost,
is now pleasing to any (especially the <hi>curious companions</hi>) but
that which (being euery way concluded first in <hi>scholasticall
forme</hi>) is also, very finely florished ouer with a <hi>Ciceronian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish.</hi>
And therefore perceiuing these our labors to come short
of such reckoning: we verely perswaded our selues, that, this
<hi>plaine coine of ours,</hi> would hardly passe with those <hi>cinicall censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi>
for currant good <hi>paiment.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly, the <hi>maturity</hi> and ripenesse of many <hi>ministers,</hi> and
others among whom we conuerse: was not the least stoppage
vnto vs. For, we are not ignorant, that men (now a daies) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="7"/>
very acute in conceite, &amp; too too much ready (with <hi>eagle-like
eies</hi>) to prie exactly into any thing publisht in <hi>print:</hi> are
euery way able, and apt enough also to <hi>censure</hi> (so sharply as
may be) the <hi>published labours</hi> of others, how lazy or <hi>leaden-hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
soeuer in laying foorth their owne proper <hi>talents</hi> to the
greatest aduantage.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, our <hi>compassionable care to profit,</hi> and our exceeding
great <hi>loathenesse to preiudice the parties</hi> them selues, or to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate
(with the waight of one finger) the present afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of those whom this <hi>treatise</hi> of ours more especially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes:
hath hitherto forestalled our purpose from publishing
our present labours. Being in very great feare that these our
<hi>pretious balmes</hi> (how soueraine soeuer) <hi>would rather breake their
heads,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psalm. 141. 5. Luc. 10. 34.</note>
      <hi>then bind vp their bleeding wounds:</hi> the <hi>physicall composition</hi>
of our <hi>oile</hi> and our <hi>wine,</hi> it is so <hi>vntoothsome a triacle</hi> to their
<hi>distempered humour,</hi> and vnsauory tast.</p>
   <p>Lastly, we haue thus long been held back from making our
<hi>conferences</hi> common to others, in an especiall regard of that
<hi>christian conceit</hi> which we haue hitherto had of their christian
<hi>conformity</hi> to a more dexterity: together with the needlesnes
(as we thought) in publishing any other new <hi>matter</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
this argument. Both, because <hi>authority</hi> it selfe had seised
vpon them long since: and for that also the <hi>printed report</hi> of the
<hi>commissioners iudiciall proceedings against them,</hi> might (as we ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
thought) haue been fully sufficient (for many respects) to
quiet their <hi>passionate spirits,</hi> and to calme the turbulent <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests</hi>
arising from thence. For, if <hi>the good man of God</hi> (he hauing
a far better <hi>cause</hi> and <hi>calling</hi> then these men,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 15. 13. 14.</note> to persist and
hold out in his purpose attempted) did notwithstanding, very
duetifully submit to <hi>Amaziah his princely commaund</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<hi>his silencing:</hi> we verily perswaded our selues, that <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ene
Elizabeths authenticall commission concerning ecclesiasticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
and causes,</hi> (in due regard of <hi>their dueties to God and her
Maiesty</hi>) might haue enioined them, both to lay their hand
on their mouth, and to put a present end to their further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,
in a practise especially so directly opposite to her
<hi>princely prerogatiue</hi> so <hi>authentically debated,</hi> and the same so <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially
also determined.</hi> Loe, these (in effect) were the <hi>maine
reasons</hi> them selues which hetherto with held vs both, from
profering our labours to the publique <hi>veiw</hi> of the <hi>world.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
If happely it seeme strang vnto any, that we should now so
suddainely desist from such a determined purpose; it may
please them to consider afresh, that, for as much as some <hi>male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours</hi>
(notwithstanding their palpable crimes) <hi>in a mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented
humour,</hi> doe couertly vndermine and nibble in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
the honourable credit of her <hi>Maiesties high commission:</hi>
therefore <hi>busie must needs haue a band.</hi> And, in that onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
(besides the importunities of such as haue eftsoones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderately
perused the <hi>worke</hi>) we also our owne selues <hi>haue had
our latter cogitations,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reasons, for the now publishing of this present treatise.</note> concerning some seasonable manifestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
thereof at this present, and that more especially for these
following reasons.</p>
   <p>First, our harty true <hi>zeale</hi> to the glory of <hi>God,</hi> the same also
entermingled eftsoones with some christian care for many
poore ignorant soules, as also, with an vnfained loue of that
<hi>truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tertul. in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logetico.</note>
      <hi>quae nihil veretur nisi abscōdi,</hi> which <hi>feareth</hi> nothing more
deepely, then <hi>to be fearefully entombed in the gulph of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse:</hi>
doe, euen peremptorily prouoke vs both, to proceede
<hi>recto pectore,</hi> with all integrity and vprightnesse of hart, in the
now publishing of this our entended <hi>enterprize.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, we are so much the more willingly drawen to
exhibit our <hi>trauels</hi> to publique vew: by how much we do now
very plainely perceiue, that, <hi>our Antagonists printed opinion,</hi>
concerning the <hi>perpetuity</hi> of such <hi>supernaturall</hi> and <hi>miraculous
operations</hi> in these daies of the <hi>Gospel:</hi> doth fearefully shake,
and very shrewdly vndermine the certeinty and <hi>vndoubted
assurance of that sacred religion</hi> which we all iointly professe.
For, if our said <hi>religion</hi> standeth perpetually in need to bee
eftsoones confirmed afresh, by the <hi>extraordinary seale</hi> of any
such <hi>extraordinary or miraculous actions?</hi> How then should we
certainely know when the vndoubted assurance thereof is
certainely and sufficiently confirmed vnto vs? Sith that thing
which eftsoones admitteth such <hi>essentiall supplies:</hi> doth impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiuely
import some manner of imperfection, in some shew
at the least.</p>
   <p>Thridly, we were also the rather perswaded thereto, in an
especiall regard of that <hi>fearfull effect</hi> which must necessarily
succeed so absurd a conceit. For this their pestilent opinion
which concerneth the <hi>working of miracles in these daies of the
Gospell,</hi> what doth it else (in effect) but iniuriously put vpon
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>faithfull professors,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 24. 23. 24.</note> the liuely <hi>cognizance,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 17. 31.</note> the <hi>liuerie</hi> or <hi>badge of
that Antichristian brood,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Thes. 2. 9. 10.</note> to whom the vnwoonted accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of such <hi>lying signes and woonders</hi> (by the speciall permis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of God) doth <hi>peculiarly and properly appertaine</hi> from time
to time. And therefore, that any true professour of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
should now appropriate that selfe same <hi>power</hi> to himselfe
which onely is proper to <hi>Antichrist:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>:<note place="margin">Hieron. de illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribus.</note>
      <hi>aut Plato Philonissat, aut Philo Platonissat:</hi> either the
<hi>Protestant</hi> he plaies kindly the <hi>Papist,</hi> or the <hi>Papist</hi> he plaies
correspondently the <hi>Protestant</hi> at least: for in this spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
point, the one is not apparantly discerned from the
other.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, we were now the more forward that way, because
this their <hi>pestiferous opinion,</hi> doth offer directly a verie shrewd
checke to such other verie <hi>reuerend Preachers,</hi> as either cannot
or dare not (vpon any the like <hi>extraordinarie occasion</hi>) aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
(hand ouer head) vpon any the like <hi>exordinarie course.</hi>
For had not these preposterous practises with a prouident cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection
beene warily preuented in time: surely, the <hi>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
sort</hi>
(whose shallow reach concerning especially such <hi>intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
cases,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lucianus.</note>
      <hi>neque coelum neque terram attingere potest,</hi> and whose
<hi>censure</hi> herein is like to <hi>hearbe Iohn in the pottage</hi>) they would
(notwithstanding their wants whatsoeuer) <hi>vno ore,</hi> with one
mouth (as it were) haue cried foorth thus, <hi>M. Darel, M. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,</hi>
he is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, the onely <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uiner</hi> of <hi>signes</hi> and of <hi>woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi>
his <hi>ministerie</hi> shall haue my onely <hi>applause.</hi> Yea, and
(which more is) the very <hi>country Dames</hi> they would with their
<hi>tatling toongs haue told it in Gath,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1. 20.</note> that <hi>M. Darel</hi> alone he hath
<hi>Delphicum gladium,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aristotoleles.</note> the double edged <hi>Delphicall sword:</hi> both
to <hi>gard</hi> the <hi>good Christian,</hi> &amp; to <hi>girde</hi> vp the <hi>Diuell</hi> in a corner.
As for our silie <hi>Sir Iohn</hi> he is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Aristophanes.</note>
      <hi>Asinus portans
mysteria, an asse in a fryers cowle, a cipher in Algurisme:</hi> or rather,
<hi>a leaden sword in a siluer scabbard.</hi> And thus the whole countrey
they would (in continuance of time) verie fearfully haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
vnto the <hi>Corinthian factions,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 4. 7.</note>
      <hi>some holding of Paul, and some of
Apollos:</hi> where as it is <hi>the Lord alone who giues the encrease.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Fiftly, an apparant necessity for the now publishing of this
or some other like <hi>treatise,</hi> very apparantly breakes foorth to
the view of the <hi>world:</hi> in an especiall regard of the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience,
or rather the most palpable absurdity ensuing
<pb facs="8"/>
so absurd an <hi>opinion.</hi> For, if that with such other supposed <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous
actions,</hi> are now (as them selues very fondly auouch) ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
by the onely vertue and power of the <hi>true iustifying
faith:</hi> what wonderfull <hi>scruple of conscience</hi> might that so <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd
a conceit</hi> procure to such silly poore soules, as (being eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soones
perswaded of their <hi>iustifying faith</hi>) can at no hand ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
the like <hi>admirable actions?</hi> Considering especially, that
one and the selfesame <hi>faith,</hi> cannot possibly but haue (in
some measure at least) the very selfesame <hi>effects.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Sixtly, we are now the more foreward in publishing <hi>these
our late labours abroad to the world;</hi> as wel, to intimate our <hi>harty
desires</hi> for the timely satisfying of others, about the fearefull
<hi>possessions,</hi> and <hi>dispossessions of diuels,</hi> as also (if this our proper <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi>
be deemed but doubtfull) to procure from some others
of better ability, a more <hi>absolute censure,</hi> or <hi>iudiciall determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
concerning these so intricate and doubtfull <hi>occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Seuenthly, we doe now the rather exhibit these our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<hi>conferences</hi> to the consideration of all: that we might (by
this meanes) more especially make knowen to the world, our
christian care for the timely recouery of the <hi>principall parties</hi>
them selues: who (hauing hitherto,<note place="margin">Iude 22.</note> but lightly regarded the
<hi>christian compassions</hi> of such as haue carefully sought their
<hi>christian conuersion</hi>) must now (of necessity) <hi>be saued with feare,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iude 23.</note>
      <hi>through a more violent withdrawing of them from the fier,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to <hi>Ben-Sirah</hi> his sacred aduise, saying thus as followeth.
<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Ben-Sirah in suis prouerbijs. Item, citatum inuenies in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras Mesle.</note>
      <hi>idest. Sapientem
nutu; et stultum fuste. Correct the wise with a nodde: and, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
with a club.</hi> Signifying thereby vnto vs, that, whereas all
manner of lenitie is foorthwith to be vsed towards those
that are <hi>tractable:</hi> the <hi>knottie or knurrie hard logs,</hi> doe craue
strong <hi>yron wedges,</hi> and many <hi>hard strokes</hi> to bring them in
good order.</p>
   <p>Eightly, we were also the more willing in this our deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
purpose, the rather to put some present good ende (if
we possibly might) to the indirect dealings, and preposterous
proceedings of such as haue preposterously taken vpon them
those preposterous <hi>practises.</hi> Who (being by all outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
of truth, and perhaps in their owne <hi>conscience</hi> to)
verie <hi>iudicially</hi> conuinced for grosse <hi>malefactors:</hi> doe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb facs="9"/>
all this verie <hi>malapertly</hi> endeuour to mannage their
owne <hi>contradictorie courses,</hi> against the <hi>authenticall counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds</hi>
of her Maiesties lawfull authority.<note place="margin">Eccles. 10, 20. 1. Pet. 2. 13. 17.</note> Yea, and this also
with most apparant <hi>deprauings, disgracings, reuilings</hi> and <hi>taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</hi>
Moreouer, with <hi>lying,</hi> with <hi>cogging</hi> and <hi>circumuenting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises.</hi>
Whereas <hi>Ladie truth,</hi> the more <hi>simple shee is,</hi> the more
<hi>shining shee is:</hi> at no hand affecting any such <hi>bumbasted braua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos,</hi>
to support or beare vp her <hi>vnanswerable edicts,</hi> how base or
how simple soeuer in outward appearance.</p>
   <p>Ninthly, we were lead in like manner to this late publike
proceeding, in an especiall regard of our woonderfull loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
that so many palpable vntruths, and such pestiferous <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi>
(as in those their published <hi>Pamphlets</hi> and printed <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies</hi>
are broached but lately abroad, to the dangerous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching
and desperate enchanting of many poore ignorant
<hi>vnstable soules</hi>) should so passe vnderhand <hi>in the publike veiw of
tagge and ragge,</hi> without the timely controlement of any: or
runne abroad (as they doe) from hand to hand for good cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
payment, or euer <hi>they be tried with the touch-stone of truth,</hi>
and before they be throughly waighed with the approoued
<hi>waights of the sanctuarie:</hi> or not hauing vpon them some <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretiue
stampe</hi> or discerning <hi>censure</hi> at least.</p>
   <p>Lastly, our <hi>loyall obedience,</hi> and conscionable duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the timelie vpholding of the <hi>Magistrates</hi> authenticall
authoritie and credit, which these men (in all the rest, more
especiallie, in that their verie last vndutifull deprauing <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets</hi>)
like petie yoong <hi>presses,</hi> vnderminingly haue publisht
in print, <hi>without any her Maiesties authenticall priuiledge:</hi> was
not (we assure thee) <hi>the least motiue in duty,</hi> (howsoeuer <hi>the last
in degree</hi>) to this our lately pretended purpose. The <hi>premisses</hi>
therefore exactly considered, &amp; the <hi>reasons</hi> themselues being
dulie perpended in a more dutifull regard of <hi>her Maiesties su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent
authority ouer al persons &amp; causes in Christ:</hi> we doubt
not at all, but that (notwithstanding our former <hi>resolutions</hi>
concerning the <hi>respectiue suppressing</hi> of these our priuate en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours)
the <hi>wiser sort,</hi> will verie willingly <hi>dispence</hi> with their
publishing now at this present especially: wherein (it may
shrewdly be feared) <hi>the wilde trees of the Forrest doe couertlie
combine themselues of a verie set purpose to make the proud bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-bush
some mightie Magnifico in their secret assemblies.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iudg. 9. 8. &amp;c.</note> These
<pb facs="9"/>
occasions considered with a right respect, we doubt not at all,
but, that <hi>this our now published Treatise,</hi> will bee deemed as a
<hi>worde deliuered in due season:</hi> to so many especially, as doe sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
affect <hi>the glorie of God:</hi> as doe (with a prouident cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection)
endeuour <hi>to propagate the Gospel of Christ:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 122. 6. 7.</note> brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
as doe conscionablie praie for, and dutifullie pursue that
prosperitie of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 85. 10. 11.</note> wherein <hi>righteousnesse and peace haue
kissed each other.</hi> As for the rest, we waight euerie hower when
their <hi>lauish toongs</hi> will be <hi>lashing abroad,</hi> and their <hi>intemperate
pens</hi> will be <hi>Printing in corners, King Achab his</hi> peremptorie
<hi>proclamation</hi> against vs: exclaming in their outrage, &amp; crying
vnto vs,<note place="margin">1. King. 21. 20.</note>
      <hi>Haue you found vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. King. 22. 8.</note>
      <hi>O our enimies, haue you found vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi>
And will you <hi>in no wise prophesie any other but euill vnto vs?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Well, whatsoeuer will be the issue of that their intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<hi>humour,</hi> all their <hi>exceptions</hi> (how virulent soeuer) they
must be such (we are sure) as concerne either our <hi>persons:</hi>
or our <hi>cause</hi> at the least.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Their exceptions against our persons,</hi> they must respectiuelie
concerne, either our <hi>skill in learning:</hi> or, <hi>our cariage of life.</hi>
Touching any our <hi>great skill of learning,</hi> we both know, and do
freely confesse (as before) that we are (euen in our owne eies)
<hi>minimi Apostolorum,</hi> the verie <hi>last</hi> and the <hi>least of ten thousand:</hi>
that we were <hi>borne out of due time,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 8. 9.</note> and are vtterly vnwoorthy
the neme of <hi>publike preaohers.</hi> Howbeit, by the grace of God,
<hi>we are that we are,</hi> &amp; <hi>his graces</hi> (we hope) <hi>they were not bestowed
vpon vs in vaine.</hi> Besides all this, the more vnskilfull we be for
such <hi>publike writing,</hi> the more able our aduersaries are (with
their exceeding <hi>great skill</hi>) to <hi>answere whatsoeuer we write.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for our carriage of life, their <hi>exceptions</hi> that way, they
must haue a more speciall relation, either to our <hi>precedent:</hi> or
to our <hi>now present practises at least.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Our <hi>precedent practises</hi> (when they were at the woorst) they
were none other then those that doe ordinarily attend vpon
the <hi>corrupt nature of men:</hi> and therfore howsoeuer they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
(in any <hi>Pharisaicall conceit</hi> of their owne proper
strength) may haply imagine themselues to be able to <hi>stand,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 18. 9. 11. 12.</note>
      <hi>let them</hi> (if they be wise) <hi>beware least they fall.</hi> Howbeit, if for
any <hi>matters</hi> past (either truely knowen,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 12.</note> or vncharitably su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected)
the vile venim of their venemous <hi>spirits</hi> would swell
their cankred harts in sunder, vnlesse (after their accustomed
<pb facs="10"/>
manner with all men) they should <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Beza annotat. in Math. 1. 19.</note>
      <hi>expose our
persons to publike reproches:</hi> we will verie willingly vndergoe
whatsoeuer <hi>disgrace the Lord</hi> (for this cause) allotteth vnto vs.
And (which more is) we will with patience endure,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 9. Aristophanes.</note> that these
furious <hi>dead dogs</hi> doe <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Canem excoriatam
excoriare: stay afresh our newly flaine carkasses,</hi> and adde afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to our affliction. Assuring our selues that our gratious
God who giues them this leaue <hi>to curse poore Dauid afresh</hi> (so
soone as proud <hi>railing Shimei</hi> hath spit foorth his venemous
spite to the full,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 9. 10. 11. 12.</note> and vented the vttermost force of his limited
furie) he will then (in a great mercie) behold our <hi>afflictions
this day,</hi> and bestow some present <hi>new blessing vpon vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Touching any our now <hi>present practises</hi> (howsoeuer the
<hi>common calumniatours</hi> of men may happely measure the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
of our steps,</hi> by their owne <hi>proper footings,</hi> and so ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reache
vs a large inch at the least) we doe here in the honour
of <hi>Gods</hi> holy name (with the protestation of our harts) very
freely acknowledge, that, albeit we our owne selues do know
more by our selues then all the world else: yet (we praise our
good God) we do (at this present) know nothing by our selues
that may make vs afraid to <hi>confront the very holiest of them all
to their face;</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 4.</note> though (notwithstanding all this) <hi>we are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
iustified in the presence of him who iudgeth the hart.</hi> In the
meane time, we thinke it some part of <hi>brotherly duety,</hi> to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne
all those our <hi>calumnious accusers</hi> of this; namely, that if
they still make it their speciall glory to vndergo the <hi>gung-far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers
office,</hi> or if they doe still take a singular pleasure to be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling
and raking in euery mans <hi>channel</hi> euen vp to their <hi>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes:</hi>
may happily (in the end) defile their <hi>faire fingers,</hi>
and procure a foule sauour to their owne proper <hi>persons.</hi> And
therefore we do frendly aduise them, to desist from those <hi>cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion-like
courses in time:</hi> or if (because <hi>antiquum obtinet Crito</hi>)
their tatling toongs must needs he tampring that way in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
at least: then, let them begin first (as we say) <hi>ab ipso lare,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aristides. Math. 7. 5.</note>
      <hi>to
be holy at home:</hi> let them first <hi>make a Saint of their owne proper
shrine:</hi> yea let them first <hi>pull foorth the beame from their owne,</hi>
or euer they entermeddle with <hi>the little moate in their poor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
brothers eie.</hi> Otherwise, they should shew them selues very
like to the slouenly <hi>barber,</hi> who (being to to curious in cutting,
in washing and in trimming of others) hath no care at all how
<pb facs="10"/>
deformedly he seemeth him selfe. Or, like to the <hi>curious eie,</hi>
which very readily espieth the <hi>least spot</hi> that may be in any
one member <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> body: but, beholdeth not the foule vgly
<hi>blemishes</hi> it hath in it selfe. Briefly, else should they declare
themselues to be the <hi>hundred eied Argos</hi> in other mens <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi>
but, the <hi>one eied polyphemus</hi> in their proper affaires: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the old <hi>rustick verses</hi> saing thus.</p>
   <q>
      <l>In rebus proprijs ijt Argus in Polyphemum.</l>
      <l>Rebus in alterius, transit Polyphemus in Argum.</l>
      <l>Proud Argus, he plaieth Polyphemus at home:</l>
      <l>Polyphemus plaieth Argus abroad like a mome.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Briefly, let them withall assure them selues,<note place="margin">In Gemara cap. 6.</note> that howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
we two doe determine with <hi>Drusius</hi> and say,<note place="margin">Item in Glossa Thalmudica.</note>
      <hi>Audire prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stat,
quam dicere maledicta:</hi> It is <hi>much better to here euil of our
selues, then to speake any euil of another</hi>) yet, eftsoones it so comes
to passe, vt, <hi>qui pergit quae vult dicere, quae non vult audiet, that
he which takes pleasure to speake what he please, he must now and
then be content to heare what he would not:</hi> according to our <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish
prouerbe</hi> which saith:<note place="margin">In Elie, id est, in the height of his pride.</note>
      <hi>qui mock at mockabitur:</hi> he that moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
others in <hi>Elie,</hi> shalbe mocked him selfe at <hi>Abbington.</hi>
And all this (in the <hi>iust iudgment of God</hi>) is but <hi>lex talionis,</hi>
      <note place="margin">At Abington, id est, on the gallowes that Northhampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire feolons are hanged vpon.</note>
      <hi>the
rendring of like for like.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Their <hi>exceptions</hi> more especially concerning our <hi>cause,</hi> they
are such as respect either the <hi>matter</hi> it selfe, or our <hi>manner</hi> of
handling the same.</p>
   <p>The <hi>matter</hi> it selfe whatsoeuer, we doe freely offer to their
<hi>publike view</hi> and are verie well willing the <hi>truth</hi> thereof; be
tried downe to the <hi>branne.</hi> In the triall whereof, if happely it
fall foorth to be either <hi>hay,</hi> or <hi>straw,</hi> or <hi>stubble,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 12. 13.</note> and so by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
become vtterly vnfit for <hi>the building in hand:</hi> we are
content that the same be foorth with reiected of all, as a <hi>roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
rapsody</hi> vnworthy the reading.</p>
   <p>Touching <hi>our manner of handling the cause,</hi> their <hi>exceptions</hi>
that way must necessarily be such as concerne the very <hi>forme
it selfe:</hi> or our <hi>order in following the same.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>First for the <hi>forme it selfe,</hi> the same (you see) is <hi>Dialogicall:</hi>
the which forme (we are sure) is no lesse <hi>ancient</hi> then <hi>authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi>
approoued of all, and therefore we know no one <hi>reason</hi> as
yet, why we also our selues may not iustly challenge the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge</hi>
thereof if we please. If any may happily imagine we
<pb facs="11"/>
haue purposely propounded to our selues this <hi>dialogizing</hi>
manner of dealing of a very set purpose: to the end, that by
such a <hi>prosopopoeia,</hi> or faining of <hi>persons,</hi> we might gaine greater
liberty to propound what seemeth good to our selues, and to
girde at whose <hi>persons</hi> we please: our answere is this, that, the
<hi>speakers</hi> produced in this present <hi>discourse,</hi> they are such as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
concerne the <hi>matters in question:</hi> and therefore, no
man may iustly be offended therat, but he only that is tainted
with those erronious <hi>absurdities,</hi> which vnder that name, are
so couertly touched. Neither may any be iustly greeued, that
we haue put downe manie moe <hi>obiections,</hi> then <hi>our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
woulde euer haue made: for therein, we haue rather <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,</hi>
then <hi>foundered</hi> the free passage of their <hi>cause</hi> whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.
Yea, much more for mannaging their <hi>cause,</hi> is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by vs, then hath hitherto beene heard from themselues,
or from any their <hi>fauorites:</hi> although wee haue purposely
<hi>ploughed with their hey four</hi> from time to time,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14. 18.</note> that we might
be the more readie <hi>in reading their riddle.</hi> And therefore, they
haue no reason to be grieued against vs for any thing, vnlesse
happily for this: namely, for that (to spare them a labour) we
haue framed them their <hi>answere</hi> aforehand, and buttoned vp
their lips, or euer they begin to speake.</p>
   <p>Lastly, for <hi>our order in folowing the cause:</hi> we wotte not well
what to <hi>answere,</hi> before wee heare what they <hi>obiect.</hi> In the
meane time, this we plainely protest; that if we haue beene to
<hi>briefe:</hi> it was because we principally effected thy ease. If we
haue been too <hi>tedious:</hi> the more was our toile. If we haue been
<hi>to soft:</hi> it was in regard of thy holy sinceritie. If we haue beene
something <hi>too sharpe:</hi> it was in respect of the <hi>parties</hi> vnsauerie
taste. If we haue beene <hi>to milde:</hi> it was purposely done to
breake (<hi>with Goates bloud</hi>) their <hi>Adamant harts.</hi> If we haue
beene <hi>too bitter:</hi> that bitternes proceedes not from our <hi>maner
of handling,</hi> but is onely in the <hi>bad matter of their humour, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
the same.</hi> If we haue beene <hi>too remisse in our answers:</hi>
it was, because we found themselues <hi>ouer retchlesse in all their
replies.</hi> If we haue beene <hi>too rough in reproouing:</hi> it was onelie,
because <hi>experience</hi> hath taught vs, that <hi>the restie dull Iade, doth
stand in most neede of the roughest rider of all, to curry his coate.</hi>
Briefly,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 22.</note>
      <hi>whatsoeuer we haue beene:</hi> for their owne, and thy sake
we haue <hi>beene the same,</hi> as knoweth best the searcher of all
<pb facs="11"/>
harts. For as we haue set downe nothing but that, which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>God</hi>) we are hitherto perswaded is true: so haue we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured
with all our endeuors, to drawe thee and them to the
timely participation thereof. And therefore, let <hi>matter</hi> and
<hi>maner</hi> be what it will be: let vs finde this effect, and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
no fauour at all in their <hi>answere.</hi> Onely, this is all we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
for the present: namely, that the <hi>Answerer</hi> would put
downe his owne name to his <hi>answere:</hi> that so, we our selues in
<hi>replying,</hi> and they in <hi>impugning,</hi> may mutually know our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<hi>Antagonists,</hi> which we holde a verie dutifull, an vpright,
and honest proceeding. Otherwise, wee may iustly imagine,
that they do either distrust their owne cause: or stand in some
feare of discredit concerning the same. This course (gentle
<hi>Reader</hi>) if haply our <hi>night-birds</hi> refuse, and yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
will couertly flutter their wings, and keepe a vengeable
coyle in <hi>Conuenticles</hi> and corners, like <hi>the Owle in an Iuie bush
that dares not endure the birdes of the day:</hi> then (for thy further
satisfaction heerein) do thou eftsoones propound to the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>
themselues and their <hi>fauorites</hi> whatsoeuer, these folowing
<hi>Queres.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>1 Let it first be enquired,<note place="margin">Queres, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the publike priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing Bookes.</note> whether our gratious <hi>Queene
Elizabeth</hi> hath absolute authoritie from God (for the
timely preuenting of <hi>errours,</hi> of <hi>schismes,</hi> and of <hi>facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
as also, for the happie continuance of <hi>publike
peace</hi>) to establish in any her princely <hi>Dominions</hi> an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niforme
order; that, no one <hi>Booke, Pamphlet,</hi> or <hi>Paper</hi>
whatsoeuer shall be publisht in <hi>Print,</hi> before the same
be exactly reuiewed by some <hi>speciall persons</hi> deputed
thereunto, and haue also a <hi>publike priuiledge</hi> from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
their hands for such publike passage?</p>
   <p>2 Whether all true harted subiects (euen in consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
towards <hi>God</hi> and her Maiestie) be not very strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
bound to a precise obseruation of such an <hi>esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished
order:</hi> and that therefore, when any <hi>erronious
or offensiue opinion</hi> shall passe from the <hi>Presse</hi> with <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
priuiledge;</hi> whether the partie himselfe who espi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
and desireth presently to encounter therewith, be
<pb facs="12"/>
not (before he shall publikelie proceed to such <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
encounter</hi>) bound in conscience and dutie, first to
<hi>intimate that errour to publike authoritie:</hi> that by such
<hi>intimation,</hi> either the <hi>author of the errour</hi> may be made
to <hi>retract</hi> it, or the <hi>partie enforming,</hi> at least may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
a <hi>speciall Commission</hi> for some orderly procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
in the publike confutation thereof.</p>
   <p>3 Lastly, whether such, &amp; so many Bookes, pamphlets,
or papers whatsoeuer, as heeretofore, or heereafter do
couertly passe vnderhand from the <hi>Presse</hi> in a <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
course:</hi> be not (in an especiall regard of that <hi>authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
order</hi>) verie highly <hi>displeasing to God,</hi> and greatly
<hi>derogatorious to her Maiesties prerogatiue royall,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
all <hi>persons</hi> and <hi>causes in Christ:</hi> and whether
those <hi>Bookes, pamphlets,</hi> or <hi>papers</hi> so disorderly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht
abroad, are not (for such vndutifull disorder) to
be iustly esteemed of all true harted <hi>subiects,</hi> such <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
libels</hi> as doe <hi>insolently encounter with,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<hi>vndermine her Maiesties princely preheminence:</hi>
and that therefore, the verie <hi>authors</hi> themselues, they
are to be reputed and punished as <hi>pestiferous Libellours
against publike authoritie?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>When the maine parties them selues, or the <hi>malcontented
papists,</hi> whom (as <hi>miracle-mongers</hi>) we haue throughout our
whole <hi>treatise</hi> euen purposly matched togither, and endeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
(with one and the selfesame stone) to beat downe for ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling
<hi>blacke-birds</hi> both at a clap. When as they (we say) or
any one of them all haue fully resolued thy <hi>minde</hi> concerning
these <hi>Quaeres:</hi> then let them (in Gods holy name) verie free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
proceed in their <hi>answere</hi> and spare not.</p>
   <p>Otherwise, if (in an onely distrust of their <hi>cause</hi>) they shall
yet couer their <hi>weaknes,</hi> and excuse their not <hi>answering</hi> for
want of <hi>authoritie:</hi> it shall be their best, either humbly to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
themselues to her Maiestie, or all ioyntly togither (with
the proscribed <hi>Apollonits</hi> before <hi>Apollo his golden tables</hi>) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
pitifully to bewaile the irrecouerable subuersion of their
<pb facs="12"/>
seducing <hi>oracles,</hi> through the manifestation and mightie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> crying thus:
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.<note place="margin">Eugubinus, de perenni Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losop. lib. 3.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Heu tripodes lugete, perit praesagus Apollo, <hi>i.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Ay me alas tripodes, perisheth presager Apollo.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>These things thus dispatched in order, it followeth now ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
fitly in place to vnfold vnto thee the whole platforme ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued
throughout the whole worke.</p>
   <p>First, therefore we haue <hi>alphabetically</hi> put downe the seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
names of the seuerall <hi>authors,</hi> whose seuerall authorities
are purposely by vs produced: to the ende that whosoeuer
will, may (by knowing their names) make diligent inquirie
into all the <hi>quotations,</hi> and see whether we of our selues haue
propounded any one point, which some others of <hi>antiquitie</hi>
haue not before vs directly pointed vnto.</p>
   <p>Then next, we haue placed in order the <hi>seuerall arguments</hi>
of eche seuerall <hi>Dialogue:</hi> to the ende that such and so many
good <hi>soules</hi> as (being perswaded of <hi>some points</hi>) are yet verie
doubtfull concerning some other: might (if they please not
to peruse the whole) make their speciall choice of that which
they chiefly affect.</p>
   <p>In like manner, we haue <hi>methodically</hi> prefixed before the
maine <hi>treatise</hi> it selfe, a briefe <hi>Analysis</hi> or summarie <hi>resolution</hi>
of al the whole <hi>tractate:</hi> and al this of very set purpose to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
to thy view (at a blush) the whole bodie of the <hi>Booke,</hi>
and the verie strict <hi>order</hi> it selfe, which (albeit the whole be
deuided into <hi>Dialogicall Discourses</hi>) we haue precisely obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
throughout the whole worke.</p>
   <p>After all this, we haue put downe the <hi>maine discourse</hi> in a
<hi>Dialogicall forme,</hi> and purposely produced sixe such seuerall
<hi>speakers</hi> therein, as should by their seuerall <hi>significant names,</hi>
supply whatsoeuer might tend to the timely effecting of an
absolute <hi>tractate</hi> concerning such matters.</p>
   <p>For first, <hi>Philologus</hi> signifieth <hi>a Louer of talke:</hi> and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senteth
such <hi>persons</hi> as trudge to and fro; tatling these newes
without any regard or due search into the soundnes thereof.</p>
   <p>Then next <hi>Pneumatomachus,</hi> signifieth a <hi>fighter</hi> or <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
against the essentiall being of Spirits:</hi> and representeth
those <hi>Swinish Saduces</hi> of old, and those <hi>godles Atheistes</hi> now in
our daies, who hold there are neither <hi>Spirits nor Diuels.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="13"/>
Then thirdly, <hi>Lycanthropus,</hi> signifieth a man <hi>essentially trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
to a wolfe:</hi> and representeth such <hi>persons</hi> as do hold (with
tooth and naile) the <hi>transformation</hi> of <hi>diuels.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Then fourthly, <hi>Exorcistes</hi> signifieth a <hi>coniurour</hi> or <hi>caster
foorth of spirits and diuels:</hi> and representeth those <hi>persons</hi> that
doe hold (in these daies of the <hi>Gospel</hi>) a <hi>real, or actual possession of
diuels</hi> at the least.</p>
   <p>Then fiftly, <hi>Physiologus</hi> signifieth <hi>a discourser of natures se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes,</hi>
or a <hi>naturall philosopher:</hi> and representeth such <hi>persons</hi> as
(by the onely <hi>light of reason</hi>) are able to discouer the grose and
palpable <hi>absurdities,</hi> ensuing such <hi>phantastical &amp; absurd opiniōs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Then lastly, <hi>Orthodoxus</hi> signifieth one of an <hi>approoued or
vpright iudgement:</hi> and representeth all such <hi>illumined diuines</hi>
and others, as are able by the sway of <hi>reason,</hi> the authority of
<hi>writers,</hi> and plaine euidence of <hi>scripture to censure the obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
and very soundly to set downe the infallible truth. Al these
are introduced as <hi>actours</hi> in these our <hi>discourses:</hi> the which also
we haue purposely deuided into eleuen <hi>seuerall dialogues.</hi>
And this, partly, for an ease to thy <hi>memory</hi> by auoiding that
intricate, that endlesse and tedious toile, which otherwise
would haue wearied thy <hi>spirits:</hi> if (without intermission) thou
haddest been intirely tied to the whole <hi>treatise</hi> it selfe. And
partly also, to point foorth vnto thee the <hi>principall matters</hi>
which are principally handled throughout the whole <hi>work.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, we haue in the end of the <hi>booke, summarily</hi> also an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
a <hi>table</hi> of all the <hi>principall points,</hi> the <hi>speciall matters,</hi> the
<hi>seuerall syllogismes,</hi> and the <hi>sundry expositions</hi> of such places of
<hi>scripture,</hi> as are any way pertinent to the maine purpose it
selfe: that, by the onely <hi>direction</hi> thereof, thou maist find forth
(with a trice) whatsoeuer thou wishest to see concerning such
rare and vnwonted <hi>occurrents.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And now (gentle <hi>Reader</hi>) least happily the curious sort
should cry out and say, <hi>Quid de pusillis tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>magna prooemia?
What needs so great a cry for so little wool?</hi> we will therefore no
longer withhold thee from the <hi>treatise</hi> it selfe. Beseeching the
<hi>God of peace, to giue thee peace alwaies, by all meanes. Grace be
with all them that loue the Lord Iesus to their immortality. Euen
so:</hi> come Lord Iesu. <hi>So be it:</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine euer in the Lord,
<hi>I. D. I. W.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>