<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY Loyall hearted, learned, well∣accomplished Gentleman, Mr. Archibald Rankin.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3387_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23813.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3387</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY Loyall hearted, learned, well∣accomplished Gentleman, Mr. Archibald Rankin.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Wit and mirth : chargeably collected out of tauernes, ordinaries, innes, bowling greenes, and allyes, alehouses, tobacco shops, highwaies, and water-passages : made vp, and fashioned into clinches, bulls, quirkes, yerkes, quips, and ierkes : apothegmatically bundled vp and garbled at the request of old Iohn Garrets ghost by Iohn Taylor, water-poet</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Gosson, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY Loyall hearted, learned, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accomplished Gentleman, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Archibald Rankin.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>BEeing inioyned by the Ghost or <hi>Genius</hi> of old <hi>Iohn Garret,</hi> (a man well known and beloued) to collect, gleane, or gather, a bundle or trusse of Mirth, and for his sake to bestrow the stage of the melancholly world with it; and withall to present it to some one generous spirit, who was old <hi>Iohns</hi> friend; I thought vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to whom I might haue made my Dedication, who were both Royall, Honorable, Worshipfull, and all wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected towards him: As to mention
<pb facs="3"/>
one for all, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of the world, &amp; richest Iem of her sex, that Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of the two inestimable Iewels, <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Fortitude;</hi> to that illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous peerelesse Princesse I might haue recommended it, to whose seruice, and for whose happinesse, his life and best endeauours, with his prayers and implorations at his death, were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly consecrated. But my man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners conceiuing the subiect of this Booke, of altogether to triuiall a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be sheltred vnder the shadow of the wings of transcendent and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Maiestie; I stept so many steps down the staires with my inuention, where by good fortune I met with you, whom I knew did loue that old honest mirrour of mirth, deceased; and whom the world better knows, are a true deuoted friend to honest harmelesse mirth; and laudable recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
   <p>I therefore entreat you, that (when
<pb facs="3"/>
your more serious affaires will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) you would bestow the looking vpon these my poore and beggarly wardrobe of witty lefts, whom I dare not call <hi>Apothegmes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And because I had many of them by relation and heare-say, I am in doubt that some of them may bee in print in some other Authors, which I doe assure you is more then I doe know; which if it bee so, I pray you but to conniue or tollerate, and let the Authors make twice as bold with me at any time.</p>
   <p>Thus wishing euery one to mende one, whereby the rent and torne gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Threed-bare Time may be well and merrily patched and repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, crauing your pardon, with my best wishes, I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Yours euer in the best of my best <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</salute>
      <signed>IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>