<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull her louing Bro-Master
Pearse Edgecombe, of Mount Edge∣combe
in Deuon. Esquier, mercie and peace
from Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Dowriche, Anne</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S352_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7159.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S352</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull her louing Bro-Master
Pearse Edgecombe, of Mount Edge∣combe
in Deuon. Esquier, mercie and peace
from Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Dowriche, Anne</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The French historie, that is, A lamentable discourse of three of the chiefe, and most famous bloodie broiles that haue happened in France for the Gospell of Iesus Christ : namelie, 1. The outrage called the winning of S. Iames his streete, 1557, 2. The constant martirdome of Annas Burgans one of the K. Councell, 1559, 3. The bloodie marriage of Margaret sister to Charles the 9, anno 1572 / published by A.D</title>
                 <author>Dowriche, Anne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Orwin, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Russell, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull her louing Bro-Master
Pearse Edgecombe, of Mount Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe
in Deuon. Esquier, mercie and peace
from Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull, and my louing
Brother, I haue heard it often &amp;
truelie reported; That, Lawes
maie be broken, but Nature can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be forgotten. I finde the force
of this in my selfe: if I finde not
the like in you, I blame not your
nature, but the contrarie crossings of those politique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
that hinder the working of it. VVhen I had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
this present Pamphlet, I saw that the simplicitie of
it required a Patron; &amp; the often remembrance of your
former curtesies inforced me to make bolde with you.
Consider not therefore the worthinesse of the worke, but
rather the will of the worker: for though the one maie
iustlie be condemned, yet the other deserues to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
This Booke which proceedes vnder your prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
if you consider the matter, I assure you it is most
excellent and well worth the reading: but if you weigh
the manner, I confesse it is base &amp; scarce worth the see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
This is therefore my desire; that the simple attire of
this outward forme, maie not discourage you from seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the cōfortable tast of the inward substance. You shall
<pb facs="3"/>
find here manie things for comfort worthie the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
and for policie the obseruing. This hath beene
my ordinarie exercise for recreation at times of leasure
for a long space togeather: If I were sure that you
would but take halfe so much pleasure in reading it, as
I haue in collecting and disposing it: I should not neede
anie farther to commend it. If you finde anie thing that
fits not your liking, remember I pray, that it is a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
doing. The thing it selfe will sufficientlie prooue
this to be true. Thus committing the patronage of this
my recreation vnto your protection, and you withmy
good sister in law your wife, &amp; all your children to the
Lords tuition, I cease to troble you: <hi>Honiton,</hi> the 25.
day of Iulie. 1589.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing Sister
<hi>Anne Dowriche.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>