<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE MOST NOBLE AND MOSTE VER∣tuouse princesse Quene Anne, wyfe vnto the moste excellent prynce our moste gra∣ciouse soueraygne lorde, kynge HENRY the. VIII. Tho∣mas Elyot knyghte desy∣reth all honour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1540</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S366_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21309</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7657.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE MOST NOBLE AND MOSTE VER∣tuouse princesse Quene Anne, wyfe vnto the moste excellent prynce our moste gra∣ciouse soueraygne lorde, kynge HENRY the. VIII. Tho∣mas Elyot knyghte desy∣reth all honour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of good vvomen, deuised and made by Sir Thomas Elyot Knyght</title>
                 <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1540</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ <hi>TO THE MOST NOBLE AND MOSTE</hi> VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouse princesse Quene Anne, wyfe vnto the moste excellent prynce our moste gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouse soueraygne lorde, kynge <hi>HENRY</hi> the. <hi>VIII.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Elyot knyghte desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all honour.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER THAT I</hi> had diligently rad and considered, the lyfe and history of queene zenobia, a ladye of mooste fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouse renoume for her excellente vertues and moste noble courage: I was ryghte desyrouse, that it shulde be radde in our owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, wherby women (specially) moughte be prouoked to imbrace vertue more gladly, and to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspecte in the bryngynge vp of theyr children. But with that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination
<pb facs="3"/>there came also to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, the vngentyll cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of many men, whiche do set theyr delyte in rebukynge of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, althoughe they neuer recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued displeasure, but often tymes benefyte by theym: ye whan theyr wanton appetite stereth them, they offer to serue them, and doo extoll them with prayses ferre aboue rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son. which thyng I of my nature abhorrynge, determyned (for the reuerēce that all honest men ought to beare to the vertuouse and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl sort of good women) to prepare for thē a sufficient defence agaynst yl mouthed reporters. Than forth with entred in to my fantasy the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uise of this lyttell treatyse, wherin I dyd imagine, that the tyme were nowe whan zenobia lyued, whiche was about the yere after the incar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation
<pb facs="3"/>of Chryst. CC .lxxiiii. whan also the noble Aureliane was Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Rome. And to induce that noble pryncesse to declare her owne lyfe, I deuised a contention betwene two gentylmen, the one named Caninins, the other Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didus. Caninius lyke a curre, at womennes condicions is alwaye barkynge, but Candidus, whiche maye be enterpreted benygne or gentyll, iudgeth euer wel, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth but seldome: betwene thē two the estimation of womankind commeth in question. And after longe dysputation, wherin Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus (as reason is) hathe the pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, at the laste for a perfyte conclusiō, Queene Zenobia by the example of her lyfe, confirmeth his argumētes, and also vainquisheth the obstynate mynde of frowarde
<pb facs="4"/>Caninius: and so endeth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whiche I doo dedycate vnto your hyghnes mooste noble pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, humbly desyryng your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in suche wyse to accepte my good wyll and seruice and this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell warke as your owne, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your gracis protection and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour it may saufely passe through the daungerouse rase of dysdayne and enuy, and be receyued thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ioyousely of al good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mē in this your noble realme, who by the onely example of your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent maiestie, maye be alway desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse to imbrace vertue and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylnesse, wherein consisteth verye nobilitie.</p>
   <q>
      <l>¶ Often readynge</l>
      <l>Causeth good vnderstandynge.</l>
   </q>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>
      <figure>
         <figDesc>coat of arms of Sir Thomas Elyot</figDesc>
         <head>FACE AVT TACE</head>
      </figure>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>