<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author to the curteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S373_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3119</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author to the curteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mathematical ievvel : shewing the making, and most excellent vse of a singuler instrument so called: in that it performeth with wonderfull dexteritie, whatsoeuer is to be done, either by quadrant, ship, circle, cylinder, ring, dyall, horoscope, astrolabe, sphere, globe, or any such like heretofore deuised: ... The vse of which iewel, is so aboundant and ample, that it leadeth any man practising thereon, the direct pathway ... through the whole artes of astronomy, cosmography, ... and briefely of whatsoeuer concerneth the globe or sphere: ... The most part newly founde out by the author, compiled and published ... by Iohn Blagraue of Reading gentleman and well willer to the mathematickes, who hath cut all the prints or pictures of the whole worke with his owne hands. 1585</title>
                 <author>Blagrave, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Venge, Walter</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 124 pages, 2 plates, folded table, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Author to the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is strange (gentle Reader) to speake of the breuitie, methode, plainnesse and facillitie, whereby this <hi>Iewel</hi> performeth all and that with the vttermost, which I haue in my title auouched, yea &amp; to be admired, that one onely &amp; so single an instrument should performe so infinite a number of conclusions, more then I thinke I shall euer haue time to write, and those no base stuffe inuented to fill vp a volume as in other bookes are many thrust in to small purpose. Wherefore be not sparing of a little paines at the first entrance to vnderstand the particularities of your <hi>Iewel</hi> though it seeme a little harde, and assure your selfe being once entred, that neuer instrument was more easie and pleasant: the 2. booke especially the second part will, I presume, sufficiently instruct you. I haue besides here following set an Index or Table directing to the exposition of any harde terme chancing in the way. Neuer giue ouer at the first reading though any thing seeme hard rather aske a little helpe. And if yee desire to be excellent perfite in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, abridge my whole worke, and you shall finde it will stand you in more steede then 20. times rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I haue alwayes done so with any booke I liked of. I craue nothing for my part but that ye will lightly passe ouer euery escape of mine and the Printers, which I doubt wil fal out in ouer many places (the coppy in truth being brought vnto him very defuse and enterlined) though none I hope so great to alter the sense of the matter, which I could not helpe, by reason I haue bene wonderfully letted as is too too wel knowne to the world, for these 6. or 7. yeares togither in the behalfe of my friends, who were monstrously troubled for no lesse then their whole liuings &amp; possessions, wherein my part also somwhatlay, by certaine promoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mates or to terme them more aptly concealed knaues, who after that some of them had (as they thought) filcht away all our euidences, though by the great prouidence of God the chiefest were strangly preserued, then was there no subtill, indirect or corrupt dealing to be imagined but they practised it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs. For, ioyning with a famous lewde pettifogger they got by his meanes commissions out, and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces found vpon stelth at pleasure to entitle the Queene thereto as concealed lands, whereby they had it vnder the broad seale before we heard any inckling of it, and came vpon vs with a write of Intrusion, to farther which action, and others after that: they fell to such packing, shifting, suborning wresting seducing &amp; such diabolical practises &amp; that so hardly followed it, that the world was a great whiles <hi>Aequidubium</hi> of our successe. It is a world to speak of al their wicked drifts, which bicause it would be but a glasse, wherein vile people of like disposition might see the whole commō welth of villanous trechery, I here omit, togither with their names: and the rather I do it, for that in conscience I thinke they would reioyce and glory to bee in print though for egregious knauerie, euen like that lewd fellow that set <hi>Dianaes</hi> temple on fire to get him a lasting name. And yet one of their auncestors in the booke of monuments is in print alredie looking through a Pillorie which I cannot helpe. Wherfore (curteous Reader if any thing be amisse blame those ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillers of the common welth, those vnconscionable hunters of mens titles, those wicked <hi>Hamons,</hi> being such, of whom it may rightly be said, <hi>Qui nunc in terra, viuunt hic quasi viuerra, Cuniculos vellens pauperes de limine pellens,</hi> who hindred my trauailes, &amp; brought me dayly out of course with my deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: so that commonly at the ende of euery Terme I was with <hi>Penelope</hi> newly to begin againe my webbe. And for one two yeares togither could scarce intende to looke on booke, by meanes whereof my minde alwayes being troubled, and partly by meanes of my young yeares, then wanting iudgement when I wrote the first coppy of some part of this work, I know I haue harshly written some things therin, wel neare vnto the middle of the third booke, which to this day being aboue 7. yeares betweene, leisure would neuer allow my riper yeares fully to tranlace to my minde, and therfore you must vse a little the more industrie to vnderstand it. For since our 6. yeares turmoile in law ended, I haue bene so greatly called away with other needfull affaires, and so much applied for measuring of land, platting serueying and such like, that time hath bene shorter with me then before. Besides that I was forced to cut al the prints my selfe to my great paines and let of time, that had it not beene for the importunacie of sundrie Gent. my friends who perceiued the singuler commoditie of the instrument, that were desirous to haue me publish it with speede, least time should by some meanes haue set it quite aside, I would either haue had sufficient time to haue fined it, and new written the coppie, or staide it still in my studie, but being as it is, I must request euery man to take in good part some part of my ill hap, promising to make amends with a little more diligence in my next sixe bookes of the <hi>Iewel,</hi> which I purpose with as much speede as I can after these to publish. And thus wishing my selfe present at euery doubt with my hartie good will farewell this 20. of Ianuarie 1584.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>