<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faultes escaped.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S373_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3119</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faultes escaped.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mathematical ievvel : shewing the making, and most excellent vse of a singuler instrument so called: in that it performeth with wonderfull dexteritie, whatsoeuer is to be done, either by quadrant, ship, circle, cylinder, ring, dyall, horoscope, astrolabe, sphere, globe, or any such like heretofore deuised: ... The vse of which iewel, is so aboundant and ample, that it leadeth any man practising thereon, the direct pathway ... through the whole artes of astronomy, cosmography, ... and briefely of whatsoeuer concerneth the globe or sphere: ... The most part newly founde out by the author, compiled and published ... by Iohn Blagraue of Reading gentleman and well willer to the mathematickes, who hath cut all the prints or pictures of the whole worke with his owne hands. 1585</title>
                 <author>Blagrave, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Venge, Walter</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 124 pages, 2 plates, folded table, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>Faultes escaped.</head>
   <p>PAge <hi>2.</hi> line <hi>42.</hi> for DN reade N, pag. <hi>2.</hi> line <hi>52.</hi> for DEB reade DE, pag. <hi>10.</hi> line <hi>34.</hi> for my Iewel reade on my Iewel, pag. <hi>11.</hi> line <hi>23.</hi> for DE read nothing, p. <hi>13.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> for vz. MA. read in A, p. <hi>13.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> for MA read in A, p. <hi>13.</hi> l. <hi>9.</hi> for from read for, p. <hi>16.</hi> l. <hi>7.</hi> for <hi>108.</hi> read <hi>180.</hi> p. <hi>20.</hi> l, <hi>24.</hi> for first read fift. p. <hi>21.</hi> l. <hi>30.</hi> for one of the Limb read on the Limbe, p. <hi>24.</hi> l. <hi>30.</hi> for line leuel read line of leuel. pag. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>47.</hi> for <hi>60.</hi> out of <hi>60 ⅓.</hi> read then taking <hi>38 ⅓.</hi> out of <hi>60 ⅓.</hi> pa. <hi>29.</hi> l. <hi>53.</hi> in the centre read the centre, pag. <hi>32.</hi> l. <hi>21.</hi> for oblique ascens. read oblique descension, p. <hi>35.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> for and halfe the reade and halfe the: p. <hi>35.</hi> l. <hi>44.</hi> for layd the deg. r. lay the deg. p. <hi>38.</hi> l. <hi>8.</hi> for distāce from r. distāt from: p. <hi>38.</hi> l. <hi>19.</hi> for but the Finit. r. but moue the Finit. p. <hi>44.</hi> l. <hi>27.</hi> for point found, r. point: p. <hi>45.</hi> lin. <hi>15.</hi> for of the <hi>12.</hi> houses, r, of the <hi>12.</hi> house. p. <hi>49.</hi> l. <hi>14.</hi> for <hi>7 ½.</hi> of the clock r. <hi>7.</hi> of the clocke: p. <hi>49.</hi> l. <hi>26</hi> for vpwards <hi>20.</hi> deg. r. vpwards <hi>90.</hi> deg. p. <hi>49.</hi> l. <hi>38.</hi> for of the limb on the r. on the lymb of the: p. <hi>51.</hi> l. <hi>9.</hi> for which luminaries r. which the luminaries: p. <hi>51.</hi> l. <hi>51.</hi> for I would needs, r. example, &amp;c. p. <hi>51.</hi> l. <hi>59.</hi> for his must r. this must: p. <hi>52.</hi> for THG of the ☉ r. TG of the ☉ p. <hi>53.</hi> l. <hi>32.</hi> for <hi>53.</hi> almost r, <hi>35.</hi> almost: p. <hi>54.</hi> l. <hi>36.</hi> for Sunne r. summe: p. <hi>58.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> for with the dist. read which is the dist: p. <hi>58.</hi> l. <hi>8.</hi> for MY r. in Y: p. <hi>69.</hi> l. <hi>23.</hi> for thence from the r. thence on the: p. <hi>72.</hi> l. <hi>40.</hi> for shewing her r. sheweth her: p. <hi>72.</hi> for the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. and azim. r. the latitude and azim p. <hi>76.</hi> l. <hi>40.</hi> for in euery <hi>90.</hi> deg. r. in euery parte <hi>90.</hi> deg. p. <hi>77.</hi> l. <hi>34.</hi> crossing MA r. cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing in A: p, <hi>79.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> for GD or M r. GD or VM: p. <hi>81.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> for CB knowne r. CB vnknowne: p. <hi>87.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> for to be AK, rea. BAK, p. <hi>87.</hi> l. <hi>29.</hi> for in A, from r. in AA, from: p. <hi>87.</hi> l. <hi>52.</hi> of the said r. or of the said: p. <hi>8.</hi> l. <hi>24</hi> for and the <hi>17 ⅓,</hi> r. and the pole <hi>17 ⅓.</hi> p. <hi>93.</hi> l. <hi>56.</hi> for yet knowne r. yea knowing: pag. <hi>104.</hi> l. <hi>49.</hi> for Iewell or meridian r. Iewell our meridian, p. <hi>107.</hi> l. <hi>33.</hi> for A plumbe for the flat reade A, plumbe from the flatte: pag. <hi>109.</hi> lyne <hi>19.</hi> for this complement reade his complement pag. <hi>111.</hi> li. <hi>18.</hi> for place r, plat: p. <hi>111.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> for AKC r. AKG: pa. <hi>111.</hi> lin. <hi>24. 55. deg.</hi> r. <hi>56. deg.</hi> pag. <hi>112.</hi> for deliuation of inclining dials re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining read declination of inclining dials declining. pag. <hi>119.</hi> lin. <hi>29.</hi> for Baluinus read Balbinus.</p>
   <p>Gentle Reader, take a litle paynes to amend these smal faults which I wold aduertise you to do before you read the booke. Though the sence of the matter and the figures explaning the meaning would, I know, haue caused the learned to espie these faults easily: yet for ease of the yoūg learner, I haue taken this paines to shew them downe: note that in numbring the lines for these faults I haue neuer accounted the title of any chap.</p>
   <p>Note also that a little before the impression I left 2. chapters out at the beginning of the 2. book, &amp; therfore you shall find in the rest of the bookes, the 2. book 20. chap. auouched when it is meant now the 18. and the 31. when it is the 19. &amp; so of the rest, which I though good to warne you of.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>