<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of certaine supplies for the better finishing of the figure of the Iewell ioyned to this booke, and first for the Mater and his Limbe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S373_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3119</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of certaine supplies for the better finishing of the figure of the Iewell ioyned to this booke, and first for the Mater and his Limbe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mathematical ievvel : shewing the making, and most excellent vse of a singuler instrument so called: in that it performeth with wonderfull dexteritie, whatsoeuer is to be done, either by quadrant, ship, circle, cylinder, ring, dyall, horoscope, astrolabe, sphere, globe, or any such like heretofore deuised: ... The vse of which iewel, is so aboundant and ample, that it leadeth any man practising thereon, the direct pathway ... through the whole artes of astronomy, cosmography, ... and briefely of whatsoeuer concerneth the globe or sphere: ... The most part newly founde out by the author, compiled and published ... by Iohn Blagraue of Reading gentleman and well willer to the mathematickes, who hath cut all the prints or pictures of the whole worke with his owne hands. 1585</title>
                 <author>Blagrave, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Venge, Walter</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 124 pages, 2 plates, folded table, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>Of certaine supplies for the better finishing of the figure of the Iewell <hi>ioyned to this booke, and first for the</hi> Mater <hi>and his</hi> Limbe.</head>
   <p>YOu see that in the vndermost halfe ADB of the vttermost space of the <hi>Maters Limbe,</hi> there are certayne great blacke numbers seruing indeede to the houres of the night, the very like must you set in the other halfe ACB in redde inke to serue the day houres, then in the middlemost space of the <hi>Limb,</hi> which you see numbred from the Equinoctial CD ending at either pole in 90, I would haue you set the like numbers in redde ynke beginning from either pole and ending at the Equinoct. CD with 90. So much for the <hi>Limbe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now for the <hi>Mater</hi> I would haue you with a pen or pensil, &amp; very good ynke or colour, make euery 3. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian counted on ech way from the axetree line so much bigger, that they might easily be seen from the rest, which is done for ease of memory &amp; speedy nūbring them. But on this condition, that those aboue the axtree line towards C be done with red ynk or colour, the other with black. So much for the <hi>mater,</hi> the rest you may learn in the 2. book 3. chap. but that I would haue the Figures of the houre circles seruing to the day, and the caracters of the South signes to be red, the rest blacke: and if you doe guild the tropicks, pole circles, axetree, Eclipticke and Equinoct. line, then would the spheare shew in kinde.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Now for the Reete.</head>
      <p>FIrst read ouer the 2. booke 6. 8. &amp; 9. chap. then would I haue the south half of the zodiack caractered and nūbred with red ynke, &amp; likewise the south starres a litle shadowed, &amp; their names written in red, the rest al in black. As for cutting out of the <hi>reete</hi> it is taught in the said 9. chap. or rather the 4. book 1. chap.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Of the Theoricke or Calender.</head>
      <p>TO saue the making of a seueral print, I haue placed the circles &amp; diuisions of the Theoricke on the out side of the <hi>reete,</hi> and are to be cut off from the <hi>reete</hi> in the circle ABCD described, as you see through the middest of the innermost graduation onely touching the extreames of the zodiack C and D. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in write the monethes and dayes of the whole yeere as I haue begunne with Ianuary, and the names of the signes as I haue begun with Aries: also the saints daies or names as in the 2. booke is shewed, which done clap it on the backe of the <hi>Iewel,</hi> so that the centre agree thereto, and within it you may place what deuise lyketh you best.</p>
      <p>Lastly, wheresoeuer I haue committed any fault by slip of knife for want of handinesse, beeing that these were the first that euer I cut, I must request you to amend it with your pen, and assure your selfe if you handle this paper instrument wel in the pasting that he retch not, and take care in the cutting out of the branches &amp; barres, he wil serue you a long time to better vse then one of mettall, beeing charily kepte, if you get very fine pastboord made of purpose, and then spred your paste very fine thereon, &amp; quickly laying on this picture &amp; clappe it streight into a presse before it bee thorowe wette with the paste, so maye you keepe it from ret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. I would wish you to make experience by some other peece of paper of like bignes first before you vē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture your picture.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>