<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Fift Commandement.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3982_Fr2_3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3982</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Fift Commandement.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the morall lavv, or Ten Commandements of almightie God : set dovvne by vvay of exercitations. VVherein is contained an explanation of diverse questions and positions for the right understanding thereof. Together with an explication of these scriptures which depend upon, or belong unto every one of the commandements. All which are cleared out of the originall languages, the customes of the Iewes, and the distinctions of the schoolemen. By Iohn Weemse, of Lathocker in Scotland, Preacher of Christs Gospell</title>
                 <author>Weemes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 254, 30, 348 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div n="5" type="commandment">
   <head>Fift Commandement.</head>
   <list>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. I.</label> HOw the second Table is like unto the first. <hi>Pag. 1.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. II.</label> Of the duties of the wife to the husband. <hi>Pag. 15</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. III.</label> Of the husbands duty to the wife. <hi>Pag. 20</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. IIII.</label> Of the the duty of children to their parents. <hi>Pag. 24</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. V.</label> Of the parents duty to their children. <hi>Pag. 30</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. VI.</label> That parents should correct their children. <hi>Pag. 36</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. VII.</label> Of the provision for the eldest. <hi>Pag. 39</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. VIII.</label> Of the provision for the daughters. <hi>Pag. 45</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. IX.</label> Of the Imposition of the name to the child. <hi>Pag. 50</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. X.</label> Of the duty of the servants to their Masters. <hi>Pag. 53</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. XI.</label> The Masters duty to their servants. <hi>Pag. 63</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="148"/>
            <hi>EXERCITAT. XII.</hi>
         </label> Of the duties of subjects to their King. <hi>Pag. 68</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. XIII.</label> Of the spirituall fathers and the honor due to them. <hi>Pag. 75</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <label>EXERCITAT. XIIII.</label> Of the Promise annexed to the fift Commandement. <hi>Pag. 79</hi>
      </item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>