<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3985_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13568b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3985</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>1577. The firste volume of the chronicles of England, Scotlande, and Irelande : Conteyning the description and chronicles of England, from the first inhabiting vnto the conquest. The description and chronicles of Scotland, from the first originall of the Scottes nation, til the yeare of our Lorde. 1571. The description and chronicles of Yrelande, likewise from the firste originall of that nation, untill the yeare. 1547. Faithfully gathered and set forth, by Raphaell Holinshed</title>
                 <author>Holinshead, Raphael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hunne, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2 volumes (8, 126, 1 leave, 289, 9, 22, 2, 518, 30, pages, 28 leaves, 115, 9 pages, 4, 291-659, 700-981, 990-1593, 1, 1593-1876, 34 pages), illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is dangerous (gētle</hi> Reader) to range in so large a fielde as I haue here vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, vvhile so many sundry men in diuers things may be able to controll mee, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent vvittes of our countrey (as vvell or better occupied I hope) are able herein to surpasse me: but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beste able do seeme to neglect it, let me (though least able) craue pardon to put thē in minde not to forget their natiue coūtreis praise (vvhich is theyr dutie) the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theyr vvorthie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie men, by elders aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and the dauntyng of the vicious, by foure penall examples, to vvhiche ende I take Chronicles and Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ought chiefly to be vvritten. My labour may shevv mine vttermost good vvill, of the more learned I require their further enlargement, and of faultfinders dispensatiō till they be more fully enfourmed. It is too commō that the least able are readiest to finde fault in maters of least vveight, and therfore I esteeme the lesse of their carping, but humbly beseech the skilfull to supplie my vvant, and to haue care of their dutie: and eyther to amend that vvherin I haue fayled, or be content vvith this mine ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. For it may please them to consider, that no one can be eye vvitnesse to all that is vvritten vvithin our time, much lesse to those things vvhiche happened in former times, and therefore must be content vvith reportes of others. Therein I haue bene so careful, that I haue spared no paynes or helpe of frendes to search out either vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or printed auncient Authours, or to enquire of moderne eye vvitnesses, for the true setting dovvne of that vvhiche I haue here deliuered: but I finde such vvant in vvriters for the necessary knovvledge of things done in times past, and lacke of meane to obtayne sufficient instructions by reporters of the time present, and herevvith the vvorthie exploytes of our countrey men so many, that it greeueth me I coulde not leaue the same to posteritie (as I vvished) to their vvel deserued praise. But I haue here imperted vvhat I could learne, and craue that it may be takē in good part. My speech is playne, vvithout any Rethoricall shevve of Eloquence, hauing rather a regarde to simple truth, than to decking vvordes. I vvishe I had bene furnished vvith so perfect instructions, and so many good gifts, that I might haue pleased all kindes of men, but that same being so rare a thing in any one of the best, I beseech thee (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) not to looke for it in me the meanest.</p>
   <p>But novv for thy further instruction to vnderstand the course of these my labors. First cōcerning the Historie of Englād, as I haue collected the same out of many and sundry Authours, in vvhome vvhat contrarietie, negligence, and rashnesse, somtime is founde in their reportes, I leaue to the discretion of those that haue perused theyr
<pb facs="5"/>
vvorkes: for my parte, I haue in things doubtfull rather chosen to shevve the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of their vvritings, than by ouer ruling them, and vsing a peremptory censure, to frame them to agree to my liking: leauing it neuerthelesse to eche mans iudgement, to controlle thē as he seeth cause. If some vvhere I shevv my fancie vvhat I thinke, and that the same dislyke them, I craue pardon, specially if by probable reasons or playner matter to be produced, they can shevv mine errour, vpō knovvledge vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I shalbe ready to reforme it accordingly. VVhere I do beginne the Historie from the first inhabitation of this Isle, I looke not to content eche mans opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the originall of them that first peopled it, and no maruell: for in matters so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne, if I can not sufficiently content my selfe (as in deede I cannot) I knovve not hovv I should satisfie others. That vvhiche seemeth to me most likely, I haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, beseeching the learned (as I trust they vvill) in such pointes of doubtfull antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to beare vvith my skill. Sith for ought I knovv, the matter is not yet decided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the learned, but still they are in controuersie about it: <hi>Et adhuc sub iudice lis est.</hi> VVell hovv soeuer it came first to be inhabited, likely it is that at the first the vvhole Isle vvas vnder one Prince and Gouernour, though aftervvardes, and long perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture before the Romaines set any foote vvithin it, the Monarchie thereof vvas broken, euen vvhen the multitude of the inhabitants grevv to bee great, and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion entred amongst them, vvhich hath brought so many good policies and states to ruyne and decay.</p>
   <p>The Romaines hauing ones got possession of the continent that faceth this Isle, coulde not rest (as it appeareth) till they had brought the same also vnder theyr sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection: and the sooner doubtlesse, by reason of the factions amongst the Princes of the lande, vvhiche the Romaynes (through their accustomed skill) coulde turne very vvell to their moste aduauntage. They possessed it almoste fiue hundreth yeares, and longer might haue done, if eyther their insufferable tiranny had not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken avvay from them the loue of the people, asvvell here as elsvvhere, either that their ciuill discorde aboute the chopping and chaunging of their Emperours, had not so vveakened the forces of their Empire, that they vvere not able to defende the same against the impression of barbarous nations. But as vvee may coniecture by that vvhiche is founde in Histories, aboute that tyme, in vvhiche the Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire beganne to decline, this lande stoode in very vveake state: being spoyled of the more parte of all hir able menne, vvhiche vvere ledde avvay into forreine regions, to supplie the Romayne armies: and likevvise perhaps of all necessarie armour, vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, and treasure: vvhiche being perceyued of the Saxons, after they vvere recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the Ile to ayde the Britons against the Scottes and Pictes, then inuading the same, ministred to them occasion to attempt the seconde conquest, vvhiche at length they brought to passe, to the ouerthrovv not onely of the Brittish dominion, but also to the subuersion of the Christian religion, here in this lande: vvhiche chanced as appeareth by Gildas, for the vvicked sinnes and vnthankefulnesse of the inhabitants tovvardes God, the chiefe occasions and causes of the transmutations of kingdomes, <hi>Nam propter peccata, regna transmutantur à gente in gentem.</hi> The Saxons obteyning possession of the lande, gouerned the same being deuided into sundry kingdomes, and hauing once subdued the Brytons, or at the leastvvise remoued them out of the most parte of the Isle into odde corners and mountaynes, fell at diuision among themselues, and oftentimes vvith vvarre pursued eche other, so as no perfect order of gouernement could be framed, nor the Kings grovv to any great puissance, eyther to moue vvarres abroade, or sufficiently to defende themselues against forreyne forces at home: as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly vvas perceyued, vvhen the Danes and other the Northeasterne people, being then of great puyssance by sea, beganne miserably to afflict this lande: at the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uading as it vvere but onely the coastes and countreys lying neare to the sea, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervvardes vvith mayne armies, they entred into the middle partes of the lande: and although the Englishe people at length came vnder one King, and by that meanes
<pb facs="5"/>
vvere the better able to resist the enimies, yet at length those Danes subdued the vvhole, and had possessiō thereof for a time, although not long, but that the crovvne returned againe to those of the Saxon line: till shortly after by the insolent dealings of the gouernours, a deuision vvas made betvvixt the King and his people, through iuste punishmente decreed by the prouidence of the Almightie, determining for their sinnes and contempt of his lavves, to deliuer them into the handes of a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and therevpon vvhen spite and enuie had brought the title in doubte, to vvhom the right in succession apperteyned, the Conquerour entred, and they remayned a pray to him and his: vvho plucked all the heades and chiefe in authoritie, so cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vp by the rootes, as fevve or none of them in the ende vvas lefte to stande vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. And herevvith altering the vvhole state, hee planted lavves and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces as stoode moste for his auayle and suretie, vvhich being after qualified vvith more milde and gentle lavves, tooke suche effect, that the state hath euer sithence continued vvhole and vnbroken by vvise and politike gouernement, although dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, sometime by ciuill dissention, to the ruyne commonly of the firste mouers, as by the sequele of the historie ye may see.</p>
   <p>For the Historie of Scotlande, I haue for the more parte follovved Hector Boete, Iohannes Maior, and Iouan, Ferreri Piemontese, so farre as they haue continued it, interlaced sometimes vvith other Authours, as Houeden, Fourdon and such like, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not often, bicause I meante rather to deliuer vvhat I founde in their ovvne Histories extant, than to correct them by others, leauing that enterprice to their ovvne countrey men: so that vvhat soeuer ye reade in the same, consider that a Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tishman vvritte it, and an English man hath but onely translated it into our language, referring the Reader to the English Historie, in all maters betvvixte vs and them, to be confronted therevvith as he seeth cause. For the continuation thereof I vsed the like order, in suche copies and notes as Maister VVolfe in his life time procured me, sauing that in these laste yeares I haue inserted some notes, as concerned matters of vvarre betvvixte vs and the Scottes, bicause I gotte them not till that parte of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Historie vvas paste the presse.</p>
   <p>For Irelande I haue shevved in mine Epistle Dedicatorie in vvhat sorte, and by vvhat helpes I haue proceeded therein, onely this I forgotte, to signifie that Giraldus Cambrensis, and Flatsbury, I had not till that parte of the Booke vvas vnder the presse, and so being constreyned to make poste haste, coulde not exemplifie out of them all that I vvished, neither yet dispose it so orderly as had bene conuenient, nor penne it vvith so apte vvordes as might satisfie either my selfe, or those to vvhose vevve it is novv like to come. And by reason of the like haste made in the Impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, vvhere I vvas determined to haue transposed the moste parte of that vvhiche in the Englishe Historie I had noted, concerning the Conqueste of Irelande by Henry the seconde out of Houeden and others, I had not time thereto, and so haue lefte it there remayning, vvhere I firste noted it, before I determined to make any particular collection of the Irishe Histories, bicause the same commeth there vvell inough in place, as to those that shall vouchsafe to turne the Booke it may appeare.</p>
   <p>For the computation of the yeares of the vvorlde, I hadde by Maister VVoulfes aduise follovved Functius, but after his deceasse Maister VVilliam Harison made mee partaker of a Chronologie, vvhiche hee had gathered and compiled vvith moste exquisite diligence, follovvyng Gerardus Mercator, and other late Chronologers, and his ovvne obseruations, according to the vvhiche I haue reformed the same. As for the yeares of our Lorde, and the Kings, I haue sette them dovvne accordyng to suche Authours as seeme to bee of beste
<pb facs="6"/>
credite in that behalfe, as I doubte not but to the learned and skilfull in Histories, it shal appeare▪ Moreouer, this the Reader hath to consider, that I do beginne the yeare at the natiuitie of our Lorde, vvhiche is the surest order in my fantasie that can bee follovved.</p>
   <p>For the names of persons, tovvnes and places, as I haue bene diligent to reforme the errours of other (vvhich are to be ascribed more to the imperfect copies thā to the Authours) so may it be that I haue somevvhere committed the like faultes, either by negligence or vvant of skill to restore them to their full integritie as I vvished, but vvhat I haue performed asvvell in that behalfe, as others, the skilful Reader shall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily perceyue, and vvithal cōsider (I trust) vvhat trauel I haue bestovved to his behofe in these tvvo volumes, crauing onely, that in recompence thereof, he vvill iudge the best, and to make a frendly cōstruction of my meanings, vvhere ought may seeme to haue escaped, either my penne or the Printers presse, othervvise than vve could haue vvished for his better satisfaction. Many things being taken out as they lie in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours may be thought to giue offence in time present, vvhiche referred to the time past vvhen the Authour vvritte, are not onely tollerable but also allovvable. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good Reader I beseech thee to vvay the causes and circumstances of such faultes and imperfections, and consider that the like may creepe into a far lesse volume than this, and shevv me so much fauour as hath bene shevved to others in like causes: and sithēce I haue done my good vvil, accept the same, as I vvith a free and thākful minde do offer it thee, so shall I thinke my labour vvell bestovved. For the other Histories vvhiche are already collected, if it please God to giue abilitie, shall in time come to light, vvith some such briefe descriptions of the forreyn regions, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they treate, as may the better suffise to the Readers contentation, and vnderstanding of the maters conteyned in the same Histories, reduced into abridgements out of their great volumes. And thus I ceasse further to trouble thy pacience, vvish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thee (gentle Reader) so much profite, as by reading may be had, and as great cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort as Goddes holy spirite may endue thee vvith.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>