<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honourable sir Henry Sydney Knight, Lorde Deputie Generall of Irelande, Lorde president of Wales, Knight of the moste noble Order of the Garter, and one of hir Maiesties priuie Counsel within hir Realme of Englande.</title>
           <author>Holinshead, Raphael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3985_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13568b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3985</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honourable sir Henry Sydney Knight, Lorde Deputie Generall of Irelande, Lorde president of Wales, Knight of the moste noble Order of the Garter, and one of hir Maiesties priuie Counsel within hir Realme of Englande.</title>
                 <author>Holinshead, Raphael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>1577. The firste volume of the chronicles of England, Scotlande, and Irelande : Conteyning the description and chronicles of England, from the first inhabiting vnto the conquest. The description and chronicles of Scotland, from the first originall of the Scottes nation, til the yeare of our Lorde. 1571. The description and chronicles of Yrelande, likewise from the firste originall of that nation, untill the yeare. 1547. Faithfully gathered and set forth, by Raphaell Holinshed</title>
                 <author>Holinshead, Raphael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hunne, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2 volumes (8, 126, 1 leave, 289, 9, 22, 2, 518, 30, pages, 28 leaves, 115, 9 pages, 4, 291-659, 700-981, 990-1593, 1, 1593-1876, 34 pages), illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="572"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honourable sir Henry Sydney Knight, Lorde Deputie Generall of Irelande, Lorde president <hi>of Wales, Knight of the moste noble Order of the</hi> Garter, and one of hir Maiesties priuie Counsel within hir Realme of Englande.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Aking in hande right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable</hi> to gather the perticular Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of diuers Countries and Nations, to ioyn vvith a Cosmographie, vvhich one Reginald VVoulfe late Printer to the Queenes Maiestie, meant to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishe in our English tounge: vvhen I came to cōsider of the Histories of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, I founde my selfe so vnprouided of helpes, to set dovvne any perticular discourse therof, that I vvas in dispaire to enterprice to vvrite any thing at all concerning that realme, othervvise thā incidently, as fell to purpose, to touche the same in the Historie of England.</p>
   <p>At length yet as Maister VVoulfes vse vvas to imparte to me all suche helpes as he might at any hande procure for my fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance, in the collections of the other Histories, vvherevvith I specially dealte, his happe vvas to light also vpon a copie of tvvoo Bookes of the Irishe Histories, compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by one Edmond Campion, fellovv somtime of S. Iohn Baptists Colledge in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, very vvell penned certenly, but so briefe, as it vvere to be vvished that occasion had serued him to haue vsed more leysure, and thereby to haue deliuered to vs a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger discourse of the same Histories: for as he himselfe confesseth, hee had not paste tenne vveekes space to gather his mater: a very shorte time doubtlesse for suche a peece of vvorke. But hovve breefe so euer I founde him, at the persuasion of Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster VVoulfe, vpon the hauing of that copie, I resolued to make shift to frame a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Historie of Irelande, in like maner as I had done of other Regions, follovvyng Campions order, and setting dovvne his ovvne vvordes, excepte in places vvhere I had mater to enlarge that (out of other Authours,) vvhich he had vvritten in briefe: and this I haue thought good to signifie, the rather for that I esteeme it good dealing in no vvise to defraude him of his due deserued prayse.</p>
   <p>But novv after I had continued the Historie, and enlarged it out of Giraldus Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brensis, Flatsbury, Henry of Marleburgh, and other, till the yeare. 1509 in vvhich that famous Prince Henry the .viij. began his reigne, some of those that vvere to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stovv the charges of the Impression, procured a learned Gentleman Maister Richard Stanyhurst, to continue it from thence forvvarde as he savv occasion, being furnished vvith mater to enlarge the vvorke, vvhereof for those later times I founde my selfe vtterly voyde, more than that vvhiche Campion had deliuered. VVhat I haue done herein, your Honours discretion shall easily cōceyue. For the imperfection sith it is
<pb facs="573"/>
the first that hath bene set forth in Printe, I craue most humbly pardon of your good Lordshippe, beseeching you rather to respect my good vvill than the perfectnesse of the vvorke, vvhiche the vvantes considered for the orderly furnishyng thereof, is not to be looked for in the skilfull, muche lesse in me the meanest of all, and least able to performe it. Hauing presented the right Honorable the Erle of Leycester vvith the Historie of Scotlande, to vvhome (as I haue hearde) Campion made Dedication of his booke, I coulde not remember me to vvhome I might more conueniently offer this my trauell in this Historie of Ireland, than to your Lordship, being hir Maiesties Lieutenant in that Realme. And therfore in most humble vvise I exhibite the booke to your Honour, beseeching the same to beare vvith my bolde attempt therein, and to receyue it in good parte from him that vvished to haue more amplie satisfied your good Lordshippes expectation, if abilitie might haue ansvvered good vvill.</p>
   <p>Thus I beseech the Lorde to guyde your harte in his holy vvayes, and to furnish you vvith politike prudence and skilfull knovvledge, to gouerne in your estate and office, so as your doyngs may redounde to his glorie, the suretie of hir Maiesties do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion there, your ovvne aduancement in Honour, and consequently to the sure supporte and peaceable quietnesse of the true and loyall subiectes of that Realme.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours most humble to commaunde, RAPHAEL HOLINSHED.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>