<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3985_Fr4_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13568b</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3985</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>1577. The firste volume of the chronicles of England, Scotlande, and Irelande : Conteyning the description and chronicles of England, from the first inhabiting vnto the conquest. The description and chronicles of Scotland, from the first originall of the Scottes nation, til the yeare of our Lorde. 1571. The description and chronicles of Yrelande, likewise from the firste originall of that nation, untill the yeare. 1547. Faithfully gathered and set forth, by Raphaell Holinshed</title>
                 <author>Holinshead, Raphael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hunne, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2 volumes (8, 126, 1 leave, 289, 9, 22, 2, 518, 30, pages, 28 leaves, 115, 9 pages, 4, 291-659, 700-981, 990-1593, 1, 1593-1876, 34 pages), illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="665"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas (gentle Reader) it was meant that the three Chronicles of Englande, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and Irelande, with their descriptions shold haue come forth al in one volume, and that the descriptions and abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Histories of other countreys should haue bene set forth in an other: So it fell out, that the Chronicles of Englande grew so large, as they whiche were to bestow the coste aboute the Impression, were not onely driuen to stay the Impression of the same descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and abridgements of the Histories of other countreys, till God might graunt better abilitie and meane to publish the same, but also to deuide the Chronicles of these three regions into two volumes. And bicause that the one parte of the Chronicles of England before the Conquest, and the entire Chronicles of Scotland, and Irelande, with their descriptions, would make but a like volume, vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the English Chronicles after the conquest, it hath bene thought good thus to deuide them as yee may see, wherin I haue to aduertise thee, First that the table an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to this booke, doth serue to bothe the partes of the English Chronicles, aswell before the Conquest, as after: and also that for the yeares of the Lord, as in the Preface is conteyned, I do begin the same at Christmas, and for the yeares of the Kings, I haue as neare as I coulde placed, where the same beginne. Although it may be that I haue some where fayled, through the contrarietie of Authours, as to the skilfull in Histories it may appeare, of whome I doubt not but to purchas pardon, sith I haue done therin my vttermost good will.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>