<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Additions.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S3982_Ba2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S3982</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Additions.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the morall lavv, or Ten Commandements of almightie God : set dovvne by vvay of exercitations. VVherein is contained an explanation of diverse questions and positions for the right understanding thereof. Together with an explication of these scriptures which depend upon, or belong unto every one of the commandements. All which are cleared out of the originall languages, the customes of the Iewes, and the distinctions of the schoolemen. By Iohn Weemse, of Lathocker in Scotland, Preacher of Christs Gospell</title>
                 <author>Weemes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 254, 30, 348 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="additions">
   <pb n="347" facs="333"/>
   <head>Additions.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 73. 24.</p>
   <p>The conscience bindeth more than the Law of the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, <hi>Let every soule be subject to the higher power, Rom.</hi> 13.1. the supreme power hath a Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above inferiour powers, and this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bindeth all men both in soule and body, and <hi>Iames</hi> giveth the reason, because <hi>There is one lawgiver who is able to save and destroy, Iam.</hi> 4.12. and Christ saith, feare not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the soule; but rather feare him which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to destroy both soule and body in hell. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28, it is onely contempt of the Magistrats Law which defileth the conscience, <hi>primario</hi> it is this, because he disobeyeth Gods Law which commandeth obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Magistrate, but the Commandement of the Magistrate, <hi>non influit primario &amp; per se in conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</hi> The Commandement of an inferior Magistrate, obligeth as well as the Commandements of the supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Magistrate, but the conscience is the immediate Deputy alwayes under God for the internall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but here we must put a difference, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 77. <hi>L.</hi> 17.</p>
   <p>In the age before Christ, the Doctors of the Iewes tooke titles to themselves to be called <hi>Rab, Rabbi,</hi> and <hi>Rabban;</hi> and they say <hi>Rabbi</hi> was lesse than <hi>Rabban,</hi> for they called few of the Doctors <hi>Rabban; Rabbi</hi> was their common Title, but <hi>Rabban</hi> was their highest Title.</p>
   <p>But why doth Christ forbid to call any man Master. <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
      </label>
   </p>
   <p>This Title is not condēned simply by Christ, <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
      </label> but this kind of <hi>Rabbi,</hi> or Master-ship, so to be called Master, as the Schollers to have their faith pinned upon their sleeve, and their faith to rest simple upon them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="348" facs="334"/> the Lord will have our faith immediatly depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and if an Angell from heaven should preach another Gospell let him be accursed, <hi>Galath.</hi> 1.8.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 182. 8.</p>
   <p>The Innocent blood when it was shed, was not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated but by the blood of him who killed, but he who casually killed, the blood which he shed did not bring on guilt properly; but rather a ceremoniall pollution, because it defiled the Land; and therefore it was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the death of the high priest.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag,</hi> 174. <hi>L.</hi> 33.</p>
   <p>Polygamy in a large sense is called adultery, and so incest is called fornication, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>it is reported com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly that there is fornication among you,</hi> the fathers make it a middle sin betwixt adultery and fornication; having a respect to their knowledge and the times wherein they lived; but respecting the first institution, it was adultery.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 182.</p>
   <p>The bill of divorce was permitted to be given by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> to obviate their unjust divorces; but for adultery there was death, for suspition of adultery there was the bitter water.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pag.</hi> 313.</p>
   <p>To praise men in that which they are most defective, is vile flattery, <hi>Paul</hi> was farre from this, when he said to the <hi>Corinthians, what shall I say to you; shall I praise you in this; I praise you not</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. So to humor them in their ambition, such was <hi>Tertullus</hi> to <hi>Faelix, Act.</hi> 24.2. <hi>Seeing that very worthy deeds are done unto this Nation by thy providence, we accept it alwayes, and in all places, most noble Faelix, with all thankfullnesse.</hi> Such flatterers are like a false Glasse which makes things to seeme more than they are.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="334"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>