<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4051_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09462</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19747.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4051</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Satans sophistrie ansuuered by our Sauiour Christ : and in diuers sermons further manifested by that worthy man Maister William Perkins. To which is added, a comfort for the feeble minded: wherein is set downe the temptations of a Christian</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Edgar, Eleazar.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 186 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>GEntle Reader, in the life of that worthie man
Master Perkins, his books for the most part were
printed at Cambridge. The onely reason was,
his desire to be Corrector to his owne bookes. Since
he departed this life, some good men haue brought
me certaine labours of his. I desire not to print them
to make gaine to myselfe, but because I would not
haue his labours to be lost. He was heard of many by
his speech, read of many in his writings, and his works
haue bene translated into many languages. Mislike
not this booke, because it was printed at London, his
auditors can tell it was as he spake it. If you say, it was
hard to write as he spake: know this, that he obserued
his auditors, and so spake, as a diligent Baru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> might
write verbatim al that was spoken by this Ieremiah.<note place="margin">Ier. 36. 18.</note> Vse
this, and communicate that which thou hast of his.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>