<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</title>
           <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4074_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19694</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6113.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4074</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of faith : vvherein is declared how a man may liue by faith, and finde releefe in all his necessities. Applied especially vnto the vse of the weakest Christians. By Ezekel Culuervvell</title>
                 <author>Culverwell, Ezekiel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 367, 5, 361-497, that is 499, 21 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE leading of
a happy Life
(the attaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
whereof
this Treatise
directeth vnto)
is that which
all desire; but
Gods truth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
discouereth, and Faith only enioyeth. In
the first <hi>Adam</hi> our happinesse was in our
owne keeping, but he by turning from God
to the creature, made proofe what, and
whence he was, a creature raised out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
and without the supporting power
of Him in whom all things consist, subiect
to fall into a state worse then nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
Hence God out of his infinite power,
depth of goodnesse, intending the glory of
his mercy in restoring man, would not trust
man with his owne happinesse; but would
haue it procured and established in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of a second <hi>Adam,</hi> in whom we reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
a suter estate then we lost in the first:
for though <hi>Adams</hi> soule was ioyned to God,
yet that knitting was within the contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb facs="6"/>
and changeahle liberty of his owne
will, but now we are brought to God, in
an euerlasting couenant of mercy by Faith
in Christ, who by taking the nature of man
into vnitie of His person, and not the person
of any, became a publike person, to be Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
of eternall saluation to all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
him; and so gathering vs that were
scattered from God into one head, bringeth
vs backe againe to God by a contrary way
to that whereby we fell, that is, by cleauing
to God by faith frō whom we fel by distrust.
A fit grace for the state of grace, giuing the
whole glory to God, and emptying the soule
of all selfe-sufficiency, and inlarging it to
receiue what is freely wrought and offered
by an other: thus wee come to haue the
comfort, and God the glory of mercy,
which sweete attribute, mooued him to set
all other attributes on worke to make vs
happy. Out of the bowels of his mercy, as
he chose vs to eternal saluatiō in Christ, so
vouchsafeth he all things necessary <hi>to life
and godlinesse.</hi> And as the same loue in
God giueth vs heauen, and furnisheth vs
withall things needfull in the way, vntill
we come thither: So the same Faith which
layeth hold on the promises of necessary as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance,
comfort, prouision and protection:
and this office it performeth in all the seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
stations of this life, vntill it hath
brought vs vnto the enioying of Him <hi>in
whose presenceis fulnes of ioy and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
for euermore.</hi> Wee see that same
<pb facs="6"/>
loue in parents which mooueth them to gaue
an inheritance to their sonnes, mooueth
them likewise to prouide for them, and to
traine them vp in experience of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
care. So it pleaseth our first and best
Father, besides the maine promise of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
to giue vs many other rich and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
promises, that in taste of his goidnesse
and truth in these, we may at length
yeeld vp our soules to him, as to our faith
full Creator with the more assured comfort;
and the longer we liue heere be more roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in Faith. <hi>I know whom I haue tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 12.</note>
saith aged S. <hi>Paul.</hi> But alas how little
is that we know of his waies! because we
obserue him no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, making good his word vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
vs. <hi>All his waies are mercy and
truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 25. 10. 12. 6.</note> and euery <hi>word</hi> is a <hi>tryed</hi> word.
For the better helpe of Gods people to know
there portion in those good things,<note place="margin">Psal. 31. 19.</note> which
their Father not only layes vp for them for
times to come, but laies out for them heere
as his Wisedome seeth fit: this reuerend
and holy man of God hath compiled this
Treatise, wherein he layeth open the veines
of promises, hidden in the Scriptures, to the
view of euery Christian, and digesteth
them in their order, and withall sheweth
their seuerall valew and vse for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying
of a holy life, vvhich vvits-lesse
exercised of themselues, would not so vvell
haue discerned.</p>
   <p>For the benefiting by vvhich Treatise, it
vvill not bee inconuenient to know these
<pb facs="7"/>
foure things. First, that it supposeth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
grounded in the knowledge of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and properties of God, of Christ and his
offices, of the couenant of grace and such
like; because as in an arch one stone settles
an other, so there is such a linking together
of points in diuinitie, that one strengtheneth
another. For from vvhence, hath Faith
that efficacie, but because it is that which
is required in the couenant, to lay hold on
the free promise? And vvhence haue the
promises their strength but from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
nature of Iehoua, who giueth a being
to his Word, and is at peace with vs by the
all-fufficient sacrifice of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour
of the new couenant? Words haue their
validity from the authoritie of the speaker:
were not faith founded on the word of an
infinite God so throughly appeased, the
soule would sinke in great temptations,
whereas now euen mountaines vanish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
a beleeuing soule. For what is all to
Christ, and vvho is able to subdue all to
himselfe? Hence it is that now we are by
Faith safer then <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradise,<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 21.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
we haue a promise which he wanted.
Safer it is to be as low as hell with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise,
then as high in Paradise without it,
because Faith wrought by the power of
God, hath what strength God hath on
whom it resteth, and therefore worketh such
wonders.</p>
   <p>But howsoeuer the knowledge of these
things serueth the argument in hand, yet it
<pb facs="7"/>
must not be expected, that hee should bee
long in these things which are but coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
and should be foreknowne: which I
speake, because some of weaker iudgement
not considering the iust bounds of Treatises
may expect larger handling of some things.
Whereas he hath laboured especially to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish
the argument in hand and not to load
the discourse. In the second place, it must
be knowne that the fruit of these things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
to such as are in Christ, in whom all
promises are yea and Amen, made and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.
Hee that by the immortall seed of
the Word and Spirit is borne againe, may
claime a title to that he is borne vnto. For
cleering of this there be three degrees of
promises, one of saluation to absolute and
personall obedience, but this by reason of
weakenesse of the flesh driueth vs to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire
in our selues, and so to the second pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
of life by Christ: This requireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but receiuing by Faith, which is
wrought in those that are giuen to Christ,
whilst grace is offered, the Spirit cloathing
the words with a hidden and strong power,
and making them operatiue; when they are
commanded to beleeue, their hearts are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
to beleeue. To persons in this state are
made a third kinde of promises of all that
is needfull in this world, vntill all promises,
end in performance; of both these promises
and the last especially this book speaketh of.
Thirdly, it must be pressed vpon those that
meane to profit, that they resolue to come
<pb facs="8"/>
vnder Christs gouernment, and be willing
to be ledde by the Spirit into all reuealed
truth. Wisedome is easie to such as are
willing, and the victorie is as good as got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
when the will is brought from thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
to base affections, to resolue to bee
guided; for such a heart lyeth open to Gods
gracious working, and the Spirit readily
closeth with such a spirit as putteth not
barres of obstinacy.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, We must know in the
fourth place, that when we are at the best,
we shall yet be in such a conflicting state, as
that we shall long after that glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of the sonnes of God, after we haue done
the worke God hath giuen vs to doe. For,
God will haue a difference betwixt heauen
and earth, and sharpen our desire of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
of his kingdome, which nothing doth
so much, especially in times of outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie,
as those tedious combates of the
inner man; and yet let this raise vp our spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
that it is so farre, that this remainder
should preiudice our interest in happinesse,
that thereby we are driuen euery day to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
our claime to the promise of pardon,
and so to liue by Faith, vntill this vncleane
issue be dried vp. These sowre hearbs helpe
vs to relish Christ the better. Moreouer,
though in this life our endeauours come
short of our desires, and we alwaies allow a
greater measure then we can attaine vnto:
yet we may by stirring vp the graces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
in vs, and by suing God vpon those
<pb facs="8"/>
promises of his Spirit and Grace, whereby
he hath made himselfe a debter vnto vs,
come to that measure whereby wee shall
make the profession of religion glorious, and
louely in the eyes of others, and comfortable
to our selues: and so shine farre brighter
then others doe. Why then doe we not in the
vse of all sanctified meanes begge of God,
to make good the promises wherein he hath
caused vs to trust? Doe we not beside life
of our bodies, desire health and strength, to
discharge all the offices of ciuill life! and
why should we not much more (if the life
of God be in vs) labour after health and
vigor of spirit, and for that annointing of
the holy Ghost, whereby we may doe and
suffer all things, so as we may draw others
to a liking of our waies? The truth is, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
laboureth to keepe vs vnder vnbeleefe
of particular promises, and from renewing
our couenant, in confidence that God will
perfect the worke that he hath begun, and
not repent him of his earnest. So farre as
thus we cherish distrust, we lie open to Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tan.
Strengthen Faith, and strengthen all.
Let vs therefore at once set vpon all duties
required, and be in loue with an holy life,
aboue all other liues, and put our selues
vpon Gods mercy and truth; and we shall
be able from experience so farre to iustifie
all Gods waies, as that wee would not bee
in another state for all the world. What
greater encouragement can we wish, then
that our corruptions shall fall more and
<pb facs="9"/>
more before the Spirit: and we shall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to doe all things through Christ that
strengthneth vs.</p>
   <p>To make these waies of God more plaine
vnto vs, this paines is taken by this man
of God. Not to disparage the labours of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
holy men, (as far as I can iudge) there
is nothing in this kinde more fully, indici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously,
&amp; sauorily written, with greater eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of a Spirit, perswaded of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and truth of what it sets downe: And
(though distinct from respect to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor)
the Treatise deserueth much respect,
yet it should gaine the move acceptance, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially
of those that are babes and yong
men in Christ, that it is written by a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of long and Reuerend esteeme in the
Church: who hath begunne in all these
rules to others. As for our bodies, so for
our soules, wee may more securely rely
on an olde experienced Physition. Hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth
it vnto thee, hauing felt the
kindly working of it, vpon himselfe.
The Lord by his Spirit conuey these truths
into thy heart, and vppon good felt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
in thy soule, remember to desire God
that he may still bring forth more fruite
in his age vntill hee hath finished his
course with credit to the Gospell, and an
assured hope of a blessed charge.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Grayes Inne,</dateline>
      <signed>RICHARD SIBBS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>