<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST CHRI∣STIAN, RIGHT NOBLE, MOST EXCELLENT AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES by the grace of God, KING of Great BRITTAIN, France, and Ireland, Defender of the true Christian Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4097_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25689.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST CHRI∣STIAN, RIGHT NOBLE, MOST EXCELLENT AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES by the grace of God, KING of Great BRITTAIN, France, and Ireland, Defender of the true Christian Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hexapla: that is, A six-fold commentarie vpon the most diuine epistle of the holy apostle S. Paul to the Romanes : wherein according to the authors former method sixe things are observed in euery chapter. 1. the [sic] text with the diuers readings. 2. Argument and method. 3 the [sic] questions discussed. 4. Doctrines noted. 5. Controversies handled. 6. Morall vses observed. Wherein are handled the greatest points of Christian religion: concerning iustification by faith, c.3,4. the fall of man, c.5. the combat betweene the flesh and the spirit, c.7. election, c.9. the vocation of the Iewes, c.11. with many other questions and controversies summed in the ende of the table. Diuided into two bookes: the first vnto the 12. chapter, containing matter of doctrine: the second belonging to exhortation, in the five last chapters. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Greene, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 444, 447-531, 5, 533-587, 586-746, 22 pages, 2° ; dedication signed andrevv vvillet</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN, RIGHT NOBLE, MOST EXCELLENT AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, <hi>IAMES</hi> by the grace of God, KING of Great BRITTAIN, France, and Ireland, Defender of the true Christian Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Racious Soueraigne: As I haue heretofore (by Gods speciall grace assisting me) trauailed in some bookes of the old Testament, so now I haue assayed to doe the like in the newe:<note place="margin">Non potest quisquam mare navigare incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidus, nisi qui ante in flumini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus navigarit, Ambros de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, lib 4. Sicut frumentú gemino mola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opere cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum nite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cir, Hierome. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Prophetis &amp; Euangelio, non tria, sed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num tabernacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. hom. 5. in Leuit.</note>
      <hi>For like as one cannot saile in the Sea without feare, that hath not first tried the riuers:</hi> so the deepe Sea of mysteries in the newe Lawe cannot well be sounded, vnlesse we haue first coasted by the old: and betweene them both, <hi>as the wheat betweene the two milstones,</hi> so the truth is tried out: <hi>Origen</hi> well obsetueth, that this was S. Peters error when he would haue had three tabernacles, for Christ, Moses, and Elias: for I haue read (saith he) <hi>that for the Prophets and the Gospel, there are not three but one taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle:</hi> There is the same substance of both, and one truth: both the Prophets and Apostles were ministers of the same house, wherein are diuerse mansions: the one shewing vs onely (as it were) the neather roomes, the other bring vs into the vpper chamber, where Christ eare his passeouer with his disciples:<note place="margin">Mark. 14.15.</note>
      <hi>Bernard</hi> well noteth that the diuine Scriptures haue a threefold grace;<note place="margin">Diuinae Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae triplicem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent gratiam, deliciotae ad fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porem, solidae ad nutrimentú, efficacesad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decinam, in Cantic. ser. 67.</note>
      <hi>they are pleasant to the tast, solide for nourishment, and efficacious for medicine:</hi> the first of these is seene specially in the old Scriptures, which is adorned with prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall types and figures, as meate curiously addressed to the tast: but the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of nourishment, and efficacie to heale, is most found in the newe.</p>
   <p>And thus hauing made an entrance into the Apostolicall writings, I haue made choice of S. Pauls epistles, and among them of this to the Romanes, which is as a key vnto the rest: which as <hi>Augustine</hi> saith of the Gospel of S. Iohn, <hi>est contra omnes haereticos,</hi> is against all heretikes: this one epistle bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe all both old and newe heresies:<note place="margin">In Scripturis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi loquitur De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, non minore fide, quam si ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi ore ad os lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queretur. de duplic. Martyr.</note> and that which <hi>Cyprian</hi> affirmeth of the Scriptures in generall, <hi>that God speaketh there as verily, as if he spake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs face to face:</hi> so in this diuine epistle such heauenly oracles are vttered, as if they were deliuered with Gods owne mouth.</p>
   <p>There are few either old hereticall positions, or newe popish errors, which if they be propounded plainely, may not be confuted by this epistle; If I say,<note place="margin">Ecclesiae victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria est, vos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte dicere, quod sentitis, &amp;c sententias ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stras prodidisse superasse est. Hierome ad Cresiphon.</note> If I say, they will vtter their minde plainely without equiuocating trickes, and sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticated doubting: for as <hi>Hierome</hi> saith, <hi>it is the victorie of the Church for you to speake plainely that you thinke, and to bewray your opinions is all one as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We blesse God, who hath raised vp your Maiestie as a notable instrument
<pb facs="3"/>
both of discouering and disswading Popish error and superstition: to these your gracious proceedings in the building of Gods spirituall house, all your faithfull subiects and true hatred Christians vse those ioyfull acclamations, which the people did to <hi>Zorobabel,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Zachar. 4.7 9.</note> when he brought forth the head stone, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>grace, grace vnto it:</hi> of <hi>Zorobabel</hi> it is said, <hi>his hands haue laid the foundation of this house, his hands also shall finish it.</hi> And we all hartely pray, that by your Princely hands, this worke by you happely begunne, vtterly to extirpate Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish superstition,<note place="margin">Nondum vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus est, qui vindicat, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t in coeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> adoratur, nondum vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur in terti. de bon. pattent.</note> may in good time be perfitly accomplished: We craue not reuenge vpon our aduersaries for their malice, for as <hi>Cyprian</hi> saith, <hi>Christ is not yet reuenged, who shall take reuenge, and he who is worshipped in heauen, is not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged in earth:</hi> But our desire is, that such wholesome lawes as are alreadie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted, may effectually be executed, to bridle Popish recusancie, to cause those to returne, which are alreadie seduced, and to keepe them from infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are not yet peruerted:<note place="margin">Ille haereticum interficit, qui haeriticum non patitur: nostra autem correctio viuifecatio est. lib. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lag.</note> for as <hi>Hierome</hi> well saith, <hi>he killeth an heretike that suffereth him no longer to be a heretike: as for our correction, it is their quickning.</hi> God hath made your Highnesse as the Pilote and steeresman to guide this little ship of the English Church, that it dash not vpon the rockes of false reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: the ministers of God are as the oatemen: they which are lustie and strong to work,<note place="margin">Ingemui tantá nobis in esse ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligentiam, vt nec veritatem possemus astru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, cum alij valeant pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate inculcare mendacium. de vir. perfect. Tanta debet esse merces e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelizantis regnum, qua ne{que} contriste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ne{que} txtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur. in 1. Tim. 3 Illam stellam seruantes, quae Magos perdux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ad Christum.</note> would be set to their tackling: of such we may complaine with <hi>Hierome, I mourned to see such negligence among vs, that some cannot defend the truth, whereas they are forward to thrust vpon vs lies for truth, &amp;c.</hi> others would labour at the oares, but they are feeble and want strength: such would be encouraged, as <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith, <hi>such ought to be the reward of him that preacheth the glad tidings of the kingdome, that he neither thereby be discouraged, nor lifted vp, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus while both the sturdie marriners doe fall to their busines, and the weake saylers are hartened to play their parts, your sacred authoritie guiding the helme, we may at the length bring the ship by Gods grace safely to the shoare, fearing nothing while we follow our load-starre Christ Iesus, &amp; as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose</hi> saith, <hi>obserue that starre which brought the wisemen vnto Christ:</hi> who in his good time, we trust, shall conduct this our ship, with our Soueraigne Pilote, the noble officers, the painfull marriners, and the patient passengers, vnto the hauen of euerlasting life: Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble subiect, ANDREW WILLET.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>