<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4097_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25689.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hexapla: that is, A six-fold commentarie vpon the most diuine epistle of the holy apostle S. Paul to the Romanes : wherein according to the authors former method sixe things are observed in euery chapter. 1. the [sic] text with the diuers readings. 2. Argument and method. 3 the [sic] questions discussed. 4. Doctrines noted. 5. Controversies handled. 6. Morall vses observed. Wherein are handled the greatest points of Christian religion: concerning iustification by faith, c.3,4. the fall of man, c.5. the combat betweene the flesh and the spirit, c.7. election, c.9. the vocation of the Iewes, c.11. with many other questions and controversies summed in the ende of the table. Diuided into two bookes: the first vnto the 12. chapter, containing matter of doctrine: the second belonging to exhortation, in the five last chapters. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Greene, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 444, 447-531, 5, 533-587, 586-746, 22 pages, 2° ; dedication signed andrevv vvillet</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I offer vnto thy iudgement and charitable view (Christian bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) a Commentarie vpon the most diuine Epistle of S. Paul to the Romanes: wherein are handled the cheife points of Christian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning iustification by faith, the combate betweene the flesh and the spirit, election, vocation of the Gentiles, the reiection, and finall conuersion of the Iewes: whereof I may say as Ambrose, of Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamins sacke: <hi>facco soluto reluxit argentum,</hi> the sacke beeing loosed, the siluer appeared: so this epistle beeing vnfoulded, the treasure hid therein will shew it selfe.</p>
   <p>Blessed Paul is by the Lords owne mouth called <hi>electum vas,</hi> a chosen vessell:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act. 10.15.</hi>
      </note> and this epistle of his is as a pretious vessell, that containeth in it most heauenly liquor: S. <hi>Peter</hi> giueth this testimonie of S. Pauls epistles,<note place="margin">
         <hi>2. Pet. 3.15.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>that he writ according to the wisedome giuen vnto him:</hi> his writings are both diuine and wise: <hi>Augustine</hi> well calleth him, <hi>nutritorem Ecclesiae,</hi> the nourisher of the Church: as he saith to the <hi>Corinthians, that he gaue them milke to drinke:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Cor. 3.2.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>quae Pauli epistola non melle dulcior, non lacte candidior?</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>de sanct ser. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> what epistle of Paul (saith <hi>Augustine</hi>) is not more sweete then honie, and whiter then milke?</p>
   <p>But of all other writers <hi>Chrysostome</hi> is most ample in setting forth the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this our Apostle: comparing the cleernesse of his doctrine, with the brightnes of the heauens, yea preferring it: The heauens (saith he) all this while haue beene seene, yet mooue not much: but Paul preaching but a short time, <hi>totum orbem attraxit,</hi> hath drawne the whole world after him: the heauen's doe keepe their course and goe no further: <hi>mentis Paulum sublimitas omnes coelos transcendit,</hi> but the sublimitie of Pauls minde went beyond the heauens: <hi>astra cum fierent, &amp;c.</hi> the Angels wondred at the starres when they were made, <hi>hunc vero Deus admiratus est, &amp;c.</hi> but God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe wondred at Paul: saying, <hi>this is a chosen vessell vnto me:</hi> the heauens are oft cast ouer with clouds, <hi>Pauli mentem nulla abnubilauit tentatio:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>in cap. 1. epist. ad Roman. morali.</hi>
      </note> but no tentation did ouercast the mind of Paul: Thus excellently <hi>Chrysostome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the reading of this Commentarie, let the Reader obserue: that in the diuerse rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, V. standeth for Vatablus, L. for the vulgar Latine, Be. for Beza, S. for the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riake, T. for Tremellius translation, B. for the great Engish bible, Ge. for the Geneva translation, Gr. for the Greeke, and sometime, Or. for the originall.</p>
   <p>Those my trauels I commend vnto the Church of God, praying for the prosperitie thereof, and crauing againe their mutuall prayers: that as S. Paul saith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>2. Thess. 3.1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the word of God may haue a free passage, and be glorified, &amp;c.</hi> As for my selfe, I trust I shall be more and more resolued to say with S. Paul, <hi>I passe not at all, neither is my life deare vnto my selfe, so that I may fulfill my course with ioy, and the ministra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which I haue receiued of the Lord Iesus, to testifie the Gospell of the grace of God:</hi> To whom be praise for euer, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>