<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY REVE∣REND FRIEND Mr. IOHN DOVVNAME, Bachelar in Diuini∣ty and Preacher of Gods Word.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4124_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00321</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1045.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4124</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY REVE∣REND FRIEND Mr. IOHN DOVVNAME, Bachelar in Diuini∣ty and Preacher of Gods Word.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The psalme of mercy, or, A meditation vpon the 51. psalme by a true penitent</title>
                 <author>I. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 363 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FRIEND M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN DOVVNAME, Bachelar in Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>and Preacher of Gods Word.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>REVEREND SIR.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>WHen first I fell into my grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous affliction, as a man surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with a mighty Tempest, I did in the midst of mine astonishment, bethinke my selfe, how to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my courses to the appeasing
<pb facs="3"/>
of Gods anger, (whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> crosse proceeded) and the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of my perplexed soule, the mayne marke whereat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> aymed. In that case I suddaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and strongly resolued to take Gods Booke into my hand, &amp; by it, as by the true Card and compasse; to saile safely thorow the sea of this worlds troubles, in hope ioyfully in the end to arriue at the hauen of rest and true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Among the bookes of holy Writ, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> mine eyes and thoughts specially vpon the <hi>Psalmes</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> which are a short and sweete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of all Scripture, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> mysteries therein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized. Among the Psalmes I conuersed more frequently, in those that are singled from the rest, and stiled by a speciall
<pb facs="3"/>
title, <hi>The Penitentialls,</hi> as the fittest medicines for my malady, which are (as one saith) the Anatomy of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and the heart, as it were, of the new man. True it is, (which I confesse ingenuously, though to mine own reproach) that albeit I had very often heretofore heard and red those Psalmes (wherein <hi>Dauid</hi> his pangs and passions, are liuely described) with a kinde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> delight, and pleasing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, as men behold Tragedies on a stage, and reade lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble stories: Yet could I not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rellish, and truly tast them, whiles I liued in quietnesse and contentment, nor indeed, vntil I had by personall experience, felt in some proportion <hi>Dauid</hi> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and wounded spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.
<pb facs="4"/>
So true is that, which sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of the Fathers haue obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note place="margin">Bern. ad frat. in Mon.</note> and Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in these words; <hi>You shall neuer rightly vnderstand</hi> Dauid, <hi>vntill by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you haue put on the very affections, in which</hi> Dauid <hi>his Psalmes were endited;</hi> for none can expresse a passion that feeles it not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the penne deliuer but what it copieth out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>Now being best acquainted with mine owne disabilities and defects; I did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> chuse this Plaine-song to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, being the prime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Penitentiall,</hi> and a liuely Character of a true Mourner, though shaped to the particular condition of Dauid,
<pb facs="4"/>
yet fitting euery penitent sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, because it seemes to require the compunction of the heart, rather then the consideration of the head; an imitation ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then an interpretation, an application, rather then an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
   <p>This is <hi>The Psalme of Mercy,</hi> by excellency, so called, because it begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with <hi>Miserere,</hi> which prisoners indicted, and conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, for lesser fellonies, at our Assizes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, doe so often call and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for, at the Iudges hands. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that can neither vnderstand nor reade the Latine tongue, can say it by rote (as they say) and doe craue mercy, in desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be put to reade, this Psalme of mercy. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="5"/>
all question, the most holy, and iust man vpon earth, had neede to beg of the great Iudge of heauen and earth, that hee will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to heare him read with his tongue, and tune with his heart, this sweete, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Psalme of mercy in his daily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, lest he be condemned when hee comes to be arraigned at the grand Assizes: When all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors without witnesse or Iury, are to be accused &amp; conuicted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of their own consciences; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> not to appeare, it will bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, and to appeare without this Psalme of mercy, it will be intolerable.</p>
   <p>For who is he among the sonnes of men, that may not truly say, with that ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>A sinner I am, spotted<note place="margin">Tertul. de Paenit.</note> with all manner of staines, borne for nothing else, in this life, but to act repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance all my life</hi> (what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther person <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> I sustaine) vpon the stage of this world.</p>
   <p>Vpon perusall of the Psalme, and some few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> thereof (for I did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> many) chewing the Cud, as it were; I haue cast it and them into mine own mold, expressed the sense in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> plaine language, and paralelling mine with <hi>Dauids</hi> perplexities, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied his plaisters to my sores: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> with the same measure of spirit, I hope with the like successe of grace.</p>
   <p>If you meruaile, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Diuine should aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="6"/>
the conceiuing, much more the publishing of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of this nature: My answere is briefely; That the subiect of it belongs to the art of Christianity (which euery man is bound to know) and not onely to the profession of Diuinity; and that, in absence of the Master, one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> now and than teacheth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he that learnes of his Schoolefellow, will some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times apprehēd it sooner from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> from his Master.</p>
   <p>And I hope to suffer the more gentle censure, for suffering this weake Essay to see light in this Age, which is actiue in scribling and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, euen to ryot and excesse: because I see mens wills of their gifts to charitable vses daily
<pb facs="6"/>
printed, to incite others by their example, to the like courses. Why then may not any man declare &amp; publish, the pious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of his soule, (as it were) and set the presse on worke, to expresse and record his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, build his tombe of black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Marble, &amp; erect it in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Gods people; that by loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Ensignes, and reading the Epitaph, others may be mooued, as in Christian affection to condole with him, so by a kinde of reflection, to mourne for themselues.</p>
   <p>If a man would prouide a mourning suite for his sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull heart, what hurt or losse were it, to see diuers formes and fashions to make choyce of for patternes? The more course the Stuffe, and
<pb facs="7"/>
lesse curious the fashion, the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the grat <hi>Dueil</hi> or so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne mourning. My model may better please some mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then a better. If no other vse be made, The often itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and frequent renouation of this matter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vsuall and ordinary resort to houses of mourning, may giue occasion to refresh and reuiue that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine passion, which should euer liue in vs, till it dye with vs, to wit, Repentance.</p>
   <p>What fruite others may reape by this my meditation, I know not, but sure I am, that by entertayning the time, and employing my thoughts vpon this subiect, I haue excluded a world of idle fancies, and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous cogitations (which otherwise would haue seized
<pb facs="7"/>
vpon me) and swallowed many indignities, and discontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that would haue distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the peace of my soule, had it not beene foreprized, by an exercise of this nature, as an Antidote against such poisons.</p>
   <p>The cause why I present and submit it to your view and censure, is not only for that I reuerence your great learning and singuler piety, well knowne to our whole Church by your sundry books; but specially in a recognition of the much contentment I found in that worke of yours, which deseruedly beares the Title of <hi>Consolations for the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or the Third part of the Christian Warfare,</hi> which gaue the first ouerture to our accquaintance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat
<pb facs="8"/>
sundry conferences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs sithence, to my no small comfort, as I doe in all thankefulnesse professe. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it shall dye in your hands, vpon your priuate perusall, or liue a while, and so passe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through the hands of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I leaue wholy to your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. You shall beare the blame on the one side; howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, you bee like, to receiue small thankes on the other.</p>
   <p>The God of all consolation, returne with interest, into your owne bosome, those com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorts, which you so freely and plentifully haue imparted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in true Christian affection. I. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>