<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE ALAN COTTON Knight, Lord Maior of the Citie of London; And to the Right Worshipfull the Sheriffs, and all the Aldermen of the same, All blessiings of this life, and of the life to come.</title>
           <author>Brookes, Matthew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4166_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16944</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3837</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4166</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE ALAN COTTON Knight, Lord Maior of the Citie of London; And to the Right Worshipfull the Sheriffs, and all the Aldermen of the same, All blessiings of this life, and of the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Brookes, Matthew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse, May 30. 1626 : vvherein may be seene whom we are to repute hereticks, and schismaticks, what sleights they vse to deceiue, Gods iust iudgements on them, and how we may escape those nets which they lay for vs : also good councell to the magistrate, minister, and subiects, necessary for these times by Mattheuu Brookes</title>
                 <author>Brookes, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE ALAN COTTON Knight, Lord Maior of the Citie of <hi>London</hi>; And to the Right Worshipfull the Sheriffs, and all the Aldermen of the same, All blessiings of this life, and of the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>Right Honourable, and
Right Worshipfull,</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His poore Discourse desired of many of my friends, to be seene in Print, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioneth for your fauourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and comming naked, hopeth to bee welcomed for Gods sake. Your godly hatred of superstition, and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister practices in Religion, (as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the loue which you beare to the truth of <hi>Christ,</hi> and to those who endeuour to the vttermost of the graces which God hath giuen them, to set forth the same in his Church, for the manifestation of his glory) may sufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade you to giue it entertainment.</p>
   <p>It is a discouery of the wyles of Hereticks and Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, by which they deceiue the hearts of the simple, and reape to themselues no small aduantage. Therefore though neither sumptuously Apparrelled in the robes of
<pb facs="3"/>
Learning and Eloquence, to adde grace vnto it; Nor credited by the authority of the Author (which two things are wont to finde many friends, and doe buy the good liking of men) it may recompence you the losse of time in reading it. (But I hope you will not deeme so small a hindrance at any thing, especially where an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture is made for a necessary gaine.)</p>
   <p>The Author for his part hath to say for himselfe, that his respect of you all augmented by that Reuerend regard which euery one of you hath euer had to Workes of this nature (or rather generally to all the labours of <hi>Christ</hi> his Haruest men) hath emboldened him to present you with these his first fruits, a little handfull of Goates haire, and yet vsefull for that Tabernacle which the Lord willeth to be made.</p>
   <p>And he doth begge that you will be pleased to accept of this, according to the syncerity of his affection, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing that if herein hee hath done you the least seruice, hee shall blesse God for it, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours and worships in all Christian duties, MATTHEVV BROOKES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>