<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To all suche Readers as haue care of their bodylie healthe.</title>
           <author>C., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4169_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4304</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4169</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To all suche Readers as haue care of their bodylie healthe.</title>
                 <author>C., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An hospitall for the diseased : Wherein are to bee founde moste excellent and approued medicines, aswell emplasters of speciall vertue, as also notable potions or drinkes, and other comfortable receptes, bothe for the restitution and the preseruation of bodily healthe. Very necessary for this tyme of common plague and immortalitie, and for other tymes when occasion shall require. With a newe addition. Gathered by T.C</title>
                 <author>T. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 78, that is 75, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶To all suche Readers as haue care of their bodylie healthe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe prouidente a Patrone, and bountifull a father, the Lorde of life is vnto vs vnthankfull and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous children, his manifolde bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, doe testifie: Yea, the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of his kindnesse is herin prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally declared. For whereas our owne naturall corruption, woorketh daylie in vs the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment out of his fauoure, and the daunger of reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: He notwithstanding, in consideration of our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, with draweth not his compassion from vs, but in all our necessities, reachyng out his helpyng hande vnto vs, is most readie (as he is alwaies able) to plucke vs out of the pitte of perdition, whereinto the hainousnesse of our transgressions (as it were with a gab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e,) haleth vs perforce. O gracious God, howe shall sinners worthily aduaunce the excellencie of thy loue? Who shal giue them an harte to conceiue thy kindnesse? Whence shall they haue vtterance to sounde out thy mercie: Of themselues (because they are vesselles of wrath) they cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe to perfecte a woorke: thou therefore whiche art the perpetuall spring of all goodnesse, giue it them: O giue it them, and they shall haue it: yea and in the hauing of it, they shall magnifie thy name, extoll thy power, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile at thy mercie. Where is one, among thousande thousandes, that looking vppon the Heauens, moste glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously beautified: vppon the earth, moste plentifully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched, vppon the frame of his owne bodie, moste Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically created: but shall of compulsion acknowledge the omnipotencie of God, and confesse the vnmeasurable greatnesse of his goodnesse, and loue towarde man: The Heauen, to maintaine life and light: the Earth, to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure and sustaine Nature; all creatures, liuyng in lande
<pb facs="5"/>
or water, to supple his wantes: nothing to bee reckoned and named, whiche he hath not moste liberally giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, as appointyng hym Lorde and soueraigne, but them his vesselles and seruauntes. Against hunger, leaste thou shouldest famishe, hee hath prouided nourishment. Against thirste, leaste thou shouldest perishe, he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned fauourie Liquours. Against colde, leaste thou shouldest dye in thy nakednesse, hee hath giuen thee cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And what hath he doen beside: Hath he not hadde speciall regarde to thy condition and estate: I meane to the health of thy vndie, and the safetie of thy soule▪ Yes, yes: and that is euidently proued by the manifolde reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whiche hee hath prepared to restore thee to sounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of limu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and life, and by the free course of the pearle of his Gospell, which is the Iewell of all Christian ioye. In consideration of these so manie good graces of God, what doth Christian duetie require: (I speake to all, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whose veiwe and censure this preface shall bee presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.) Lette them take the sweet Sacrifice of thankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and burne the same vppon the Alter of an humble harte, that the redolent and perfumed incense of the same ascendyng vppe into Heauen, maie smell sweete in his nostriles, whose speciall delighte is in suche a burnte of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring and oblation. Thus muche haue I saied by waie of aduertisement, vppon occasion of this presente booke, whose benifittes as they are diuers, so are they singuler: and in them all is Gods goodnesse highly commended. Note my wordes, and then iudge of the value and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse of the booke. Art thou diseased in thy heade: Art thou greeued in thy harte: Arte thou payned with ache▪ Art thou tormented with a Feuer: Art thou wounded: Arte thou troubled with any yrkesome sore: Doeth thy sight fayle: Doeth thy hearing ware weake: Doeth thy
<pb facs="6"/>
youth weare awaie: Doth age creepe on a pace: Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doest thou feele thy selfe infected with the poyson of the Plague and Pestilence: Then delaie no tyme, but with a small price buy a gemme worth golde, (this booke I meane) whiche though it be little in quantitie, yet it is greate in qualitie and vertue. Here (as in a cunning Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries shoppe (are receiptes of sundrie sortes proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, where with the rage of any sore maie bee mittiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the nippyng smarte of any vlcere or wounde asswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the venome of any maladie expelled: and the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of health restored. Thus muche in breefe, by a souden blushe iudge of the rest, esteeme it as it is, a necessarie implemente for any householder, yea in the nexte degree to our dayly foode and nourishment to bee esteemed. Thanke God for it, and vse it in thy neede. Here thou hast succour to serue thee in thy sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thus farewell in Christe. T. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>