<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4305_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11314.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4305</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chronicle and institution of the Order of the seraphicall father S. Francis· : Conteyning his life, his death, and his miracles, and of all his holie disciples and companions. Set foorth first in the Portugall, next in the Spanish, then in the Italian, lastlie in the French, and now in the English tongue. The first tome</title>
                 <author>Marcos, de Lisboa, Bishop of Porto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 426, 417-600, 599-747, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE multitude of bookes which now adayes are printed with purity and elegancie of tongues and languages, are so aboundant, that it causeth many to reiect the reading of such as they ought to haue alwayes in hand for edification and profit of their soules, and not for curiositie, in regard that though al good and true doctrine, ought to be highly esteemed as the nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the soule (the foode wherofis, the intellectuall vnderstanding of the truth:) yet ought the discret and Christian Reader to consider how different is the fruit collected of one booke, before an other, that with the greater profit he may dispose of his houres, and keep his cogitations employed, and that as bookes encrease, so may augment in him discretion and iudgement of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them: that so he may of each of them gather some fruit. And certainly I admire that, sith when we see avenimous beast we are terrified and tremble, for feare of his poyson: how we are so senceles, as with delight to read heretical or dissolute bookes, considering that they corrupt good manners, and induce to vices and vanities: which are also most subtill venime, wherto making the least approach, it taketh such roote in vs, and doth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="4"/>
so budde foorth, that empoysoning our soules, it becometh incurable. And which is yett worse, we permit our selues easily to be infected, because the scope and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of such bookes are pleasing vnto vs, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to our appetite and to our lasciuious inclinatiō: and thus according to the custome, presenting poyson vnder a sweet or alluring bayte. And therfore if the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and carefull Christian, desire to obserue any due course in his reading, sith it so much importeth him, lett him vnderstand, that next to the doctrine of faith, and the counsels of holy scripture, no other can euer so much aduance him to purchace vertues, and hate vices, as the frequent and ordinary reading of the conuersation and life of the holy seruantes of almightie God, considering with all that is a natural thing, that to attempt a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and dangerous enterprise, we are therein much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re induced by example then by any persuasions of whom soeuer: though we acknowledg them to be certainlie true. None could be found that would resolue ioyfully to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the vertue of pouerty, humility, chastity, fasting, and other penitētiall labours, if he knew not that others, not only with wordes exteriourly, but really with worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes haue embraced the same: Neither was it for any other cause, that our Lord IESVS Christ would person<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naly come into this world, but by example to shew vs the way of our saluation, and his holy wil, because the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples &amp; aduertissementes of his faithfull seruantes, would not suffice to retire vs from our euill conuersation and
<pb facs="4"/>
way, and to setle vs in his, no not the preceptes which he had giuen in the first written law. But when he began to walke this way, how many were there that would accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagny him, very seriously seruing him euen till their death, and this only for his loue? The Church therfore knowing right well the glory that redoundeth to almightie God, and the fruit which men gather by the memory of the life of our lord IESVS Christ and of his sainctes, doth euery day propose and sett them before our eyes, in the diuine office, in the sacrifices and solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that it should not be tedious vnto vs to follow and imitate them whome we prayse, and whose memory we honour, and that likewise we should not esteeme it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourious to walke that way, which alone conducteth vs to eternall life. Hereof mayest thou consider (deuout Reader) what vse, almightie God maketh of his elect, in fauour of vs, because we are (saith S. Iohn) coadiutors to the saluation of soules, we may hence also conceiue how greatlie we are obliged to the trueseruantes of God, who haue so put themselues to paines in the exercise of vertues, that they haue left the way open, that such as seeke it may finde it, and by their examples haue taught vs which it is, and with whath force and industry we may attaine vnto true glory. Those of former ages guided on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by naturall light, did vse exceeding diligence, to induce and animate themselues by the examples of their famous predecessours, vsing them as so many spurres vnto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, to the end they might in no time be defectiue in the
<pb facs="5"/>
obligation they had both to their natiue country, and to their owne honour: and indeed the milke wher with they nourced their childrē in their publique schooles, was the generous actes of their ancestours, which were red vnto them in poemes, and orations, that by meanes of those examples, the children might be affected to vertue, and enflamed with desire of glory, although it was more vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne then vertuous. This is of such force, that euen at this present, many of our Christians following the same pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, cause their children to spend the most entiere parte of their age, in committing to memory, the heroyicall actes of the ancient Grecians and Latines. But would to God that too many did not employ and wast all their life in this study, and that many others were not more affected to Homer, Cicero and Virgil, then to IESVS Christ. O extreme indignity of Christians.! deseruing sharp reprehension and eternall punishment, in regard that they glory to be imitatours of the superstitious Gentils, who as they wanted faith, and the true light illuminating the hart of Christians, so was not their vertue true and solid, but exteriour and vaine. And although that in that time of obscure darcknes, they gaue to men some sparckle of light, some litle knowledg of vertue, more with wordes then with effect, these Pagans neuertheles persiste in obscurity euen in the cleare day of the true light of our lord IESVS Christ, the soueraigne truth and perfection, and are vnworthy to be honoured in comparison of true Christians, who being illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
<pb facs="5"/>
with the light of faith, can easily discerne, iudge and condemne the world with his vnwise adherentes: because as the Apostle S. Paul Saith, the spirituall man<note place="margin">1. Cor. 20</note> knoweth and iudgeth al thinges: Pagans on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, glorying and esteemning themselues wise with their eloquence, become sottish and ignorant, as hauing attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted and giuen vnto creatures, that which appertayned only to the Creatour: but they whose cogitation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is more setled and grounded on the diuine will and doctrine then humane, and do follow celestiall, not earthly Philosophy: such, I say shal only arriue to heauen, whence first discended their knowledge, they cannot erre, being taught by the eternall wisdome, neither shall they euer want glory, euen amōg mortall people, though they haue with all possibility shunned the same, but shalbe illustrious to all the world. For though anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity haue exceedingly honoured great ambitious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonnes, that desired to leaue some memory and renowne of themselues in this world after their death: yet our holy mother the Church doth farre more exalt and make more glorious our Sainctes continually in the predicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, feastes, and solemnities, which for them and in their honour are celebrated; besides that we beleeue that they liue and gloriously raigne in heauen, in the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Lord. So that the true seruantes of God are blessed among Angels, and honoured among men, as eminent sainctes, as great they are, and worthy of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. Altars are euery where consecrated, and chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="6"/>
bult in their names, their images are honoured, their wordes and workes are highly commended and preached, their reliques are reuerenced and worshipped on earth, their soules glorified in heauen, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and excellent workes both ancient and moderne, which our lord in them, and by them hath wrought, are with exceeding great glory admired. Our Lord euen in this world recompenceth his elect, who not in appare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, but in effect are vertuous and holy, and incorruptedlie conserue their faith to their Creatour. When was there euer found in any time among the ancient naturalistes, such constancie, such faith, temperance, magnanimity, sweetnes, mercy, iustice, fortitude, and loyaulty, as hath bin found in our Christians, who by no kinde of threates or faire speeches of Tyrantes, could be induced, to leaue their obedience vnto God, could neuer be corrupted by any promise or recompence, nor haue bin inclined by any kinde of flatteries or fauours, but persisting firme &amp; constant in the truth, haue nothing esteemed nor feared the terrible and horrible tormentes, were they neuer so barbarous, nor in the extremity of them, or death it selfe, but haue alwayes remayned immoueable and inuincible in true vertu &amp; piety, not desiring reuenge or detriment to the persecutours or executioners, but pardon and sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, praying vnto God for them. And all this, not att their death only, but euen in their life. For there is no kinde of vertue, wherin the sainctes haue not excelled, some in purity of virginity, others in continencie, with
<pb facs="6"/>
great labour subiecting the flesh to the spirit, that euen on earth leading a life more angelical then humane, they might purchase eternall glory in heauen: others renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing kingdomes, estates, and dignities, others distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their goodes among the poore, much more highly esteeming the piety of God, and charity to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in a base and submissiue pouerty, then any other temporall thing: to thend that being disburdened of the care of these transitory riches, they might with more ease, study to purchace those of heauen: and in the end, for so much as, where they knew it to concerne the honour, glory, or seruice of God, they haue not spared to permitt their bodies to be tormented after what sort soeuer: they haue bin therefore so pleasing vnto his maiestie, that he hath graunted them power to cure the diseased, to cast out deuils, to raise the dead, to foretell future thinges, to vnderstand and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate the diuine misteries, and finally to doe such thinges, as the diuine might can only doe. Lett then the eminencie of Kinges, Princes, and of all qualities of wealthy people ancient and moderne be confounded, sith they are, and euer more haue bin vanquished and surmounted by vs (poore and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) in honour and knowledg. Lett the subtilty of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers be whist and silent, sith these who haue trulie reposed their faith in almightie God, shal know and finde the soueraigne good. I coniure thee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, gentle Reader, by the loue which thou owest
<pb facs="7"/>
to IESVS Christ our Redeemer, to represent before the eyes of thy spirit, the glory and eternall riches, which the least of the seruantes of our Redeemer IESVS Christ shall in the most blessed kingdome of heauen perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enioy: and with the same eyes afterward to behold all the goodes of the earth vnited together, paragonizing them with those of these Religious, there will not so much as one only thought abide within thee, vntill thy hart hath quite contemned them▪ and as recordeth Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, if all the Empires of the earth, in comparison of heauen and of the moone, be so litle that no esteeme should be had of them, because betwene them there is no proportion, how much lesse will they appeare, being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to the Emperiall heauē, the blessed country of the<note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.</note> elect, where according to S. Paul, our conuersation is? It is then very reasonable, that the life of this Saincte be seriously read, to the end to imitate him, yea before many other, sith hereof we learne how we may pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chace the true eternall goods or riches, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promises of God, we expect and hope for. To this end it is that our Creatour doth dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and regarnish his Church, with new examples of his saincts, that Christians becomming weake &amp; feeble, might resume force to meritt their saluation, in seruing almightie God from the bottome of their hart. For in them is represented vnto vs the vertue of faith, the life of IESVS Christ and together with it, the imitable life of his sainctes. He will that there be seculer Preistes, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb facs="7"/>
of the order of S. Hierome, S. Augustin, S. Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, S. Bernard, S. Dominick, S. Francis and others: that in them we might alwayes haue before our eyes, his life and Passion. Sith then so pious a lesson or reading produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth such fruit, thou mayest well persuade thee (good Reader) how profitably shalbe employed the time, the paper, and labour, which is spent in writing the chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles of them that haue bin true imitatours and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentations of the life of our Redeemer IESVS Christ. How well in like sort their time shalbe spent that employ their eyes and vnderstanding in this lesson, not only to square out a Religious life to such as desire to embrace it, but euen to learne what ought to be the life, what the comportmentes of true Christians, that with their workes desire at least to appeare such: by reason that the kingdome of heauen must be attayned by a combatt to<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 11▪</note> be made, and by force of armes, which is an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise of valerous Champions or warryers: and this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible wrestling is not to be made against mortall and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane creatures, according to the Apostle, but against<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.</note> wicked spirittes, as subtill and malicious, as they are po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent &amp; puissant. If thou wilt know them, thou shalt here finde their extreme audacity discouered, their fraudulent delusion published, their offensiue armors manifested, and their assaultes repulsed. If then thou be inclined to war-like exercise, thou shalt here obserue most noble prowesses and heroicall actes against the deuils, subdued by the champions of IESVS Christ: If thou takest
<pb facs="8"/>
content in honours, thou shalt here see how highly the true freindes of God are honoured in earth and in heauen, yea and feared in hell. If thou affectest science, of these thou shalt learne, the true knowledge of the fraudes and deceiptes of the world, and especially true wisdome, which is, first the knoledge of God, then of thy selfe: If thou apply thee to the actiue or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue life, thou shalt here finde a great expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of morall vertues, and of contemplations more then humane, of communion and diuine vnion: breifely if thou make profession of Christianity as thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, thou shalt here clearly see figured in two tables, what it is to be a Christian, and with what partes he ought to be qualified that maketh profession therof. And that in the doctrine and in the examples of sainctes, two thinges are necessary to our saluation: so that thou shalt here finde a remedy very proper and conuenient to all they desires, and for all thy necessities. Now writing the life and examples of the Frier Minors the especiall seruantes of God, by them, I meane the disciples of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther S. Francis, and of those holy Fathers that did imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him, who are the principall parties of this historie, they point out vnto vs the true rule and obseruance of the tree instituted by the said Father S. Francis, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring many in these dayes to blush att their faultes and transgressions. Other Religious personnes shall in like sorte make their benefitt hereof, sith all Religious, touching their profession, are a like, Besides, euery other
<pb facs="8"/>
Christian may gather some fruit hereof, if he will bestow the labour to receiue it, as all haue equally graces and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of God, by the worthy merittes of his sainctes, Francis, Antony, &amp; others: when with them they study to seeke the loue of God and their neighbour. Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers then deserue prayse and gratitude of our partes for hauing so well conserued the memory of these glorious saints, with a feruent desire to further soules, though they haue not laboured to publish their liues, in a lofty and polished stile, with a connexion of choice wordes, as the precise and curious would desire; But they consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that the deuout Reader leauing the flowers and leaues, would only take hold of the fruit. Now to content and satisfie the Readers, when they shall light on such thinges as are not vulgare, which they shall finde in these chronicles: I haue bin willing here to insert and adde the names of the Authors, whome in this present history I haue principally vsed, and this for greater light and direction: who are these ensuyinge.</p>
   <list>
      <item>The legend of Brother. Leo, Br. Angelus, and Br. Rufinus, all three companions of S. Francis.</item>
      <item>The legend of Brother Thomas of Cellano.</item>
      <item>The legend of Brother Leonard of Bessa.</item>
      <item>The great and litle legend of S. Bonauenture.</item>
      <item>The Flowers of the Religious of S. Francis, and his companions.</item>
      <item>The ancient chronicles, that breifely treat of the most me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable matters of the order.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="9"/>
Vrbertin Casal, in his booke intituled Vita Christi.</item>
      <item>The monumentes.</item>
      <item>The historicall mirrour of Br. Vincent of the Order of the Preachers.</item>
      <item>The ancient memoriall of the order.</item>
      <item>The history of S. Anthonius Arch-bishop of Florence.</item>
      <item>Master Aluaro of the lamentations of the Church.</item>
      <item>The legend of S. Antony, S. Clare, and other sainctes.</item>
      <item>The legend of the fiue Martyrs of Marocco, of S. Crosse of Coimbra.</item>
      <item>The booke of Conformities.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>