<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
TO THE MOST RELIGIOVS ENSIGNE-BEARERS OF S. CLARE; THE ENGLISHE POORE CLARES IN GRAVELINGE, THE AVTHOR WISHETH VICTORIOVS TRIVMPH.</title>
           <author>Francis, Cla.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4305_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11314.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4305</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
TO THE MOST RELIGIOVS ENSIGNE-BEARERS OF S. CLARE; THE ENGLISHE POORE CLARES IN GRAVELINGE, THE AVTHOR WISHETH VICTORIOVS TRIVMPH.</title>
                 <author>Francis, Cla.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chronicle and institution of the Order of the seraphicall father S. Francis· : Conteyning his life, his death, and his miracles, and of all his holie disciples and companions. Set foorth first in the Portugall, next in the Spanish, then in the Italian, lastlie in the French, and now in the English tongue. The first tome</title>
                 <author>Marcos, de Lisboa, Bishop of Porto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 426, 417-600, 599-747, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="2"/>
TO THE MOST RELIGIOVS ENSIGNE-BEARERS OF S. CLARE; THE ENGLISHE POORE CLARES IN GRAVELINGE, THE AVTHOR WISHETH VICTORIOVS TRIVMPH.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Aturalists amongst other elaborate curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities of nature not vnworthy moralyzinge reporte of the Salamander, that contrarie to the inclination of other beastes her life is cherished by the fier, which by reason of its furiouse violence to others is tearmed <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum implacabile,</hi> an element with all most impossibilitie to be asswaged: whence may be plausably verified the Phisiciās pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb that. The same drugge cures &amp; kills, vnderstandinge accordinge to the diuersity of the patients maladie. Noe maruell then most, Reuerend mother, and Religiously deuoted Sisters, if I after my long experience of your allmost Salamander like life, by dedicatinge this booke to your Religious vewe, should ad fresh coles to kindle or rather cherish your long since kindled fier of Deuotion (wherin you liue contrarie to those in the world of your Sects.) And noe meruell if therin I should giue you a receipte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of diuers poysons (for soe they are to Heresie) since I see they are peculiar restoratiues and infallable Antidotes to your sores, for what sooner cures a longing, then to satisfy the appetite with the thing lōged for? which earnest desire or longinge it pleased you (Right worthyly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious) to manifest by your zealous importuninge me to preuayle with a third, that could and would vndertake the Translation of this worke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rō French wherin it was impressed to our vulgar tounge, for your more facile and pleasant reading of the liues of so famous worthies who are indeed as exemplars, or soe manie plattformes for direction of your all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie initiated iourney. Which being with much difficultie obteyned, &amp; after longe expectation finished by the greate paynes of an extraordinary deuot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of your order, and particularly of your couent, whose will it also is that by reason you were only in cause of the Translation, &amp; through your entreati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> only it was prouided for in the impression, that the whole volume of his labors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hold be shadowed vnder your matronadge. I haue not therfore enforced you to foster a straunge feture, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to which
<pb facs="3"/>
your selues are mothers, neyther haue I donne it making myne owne head my counsell howse, but with aduise of the Authore and other benefactours of the worke, since therfore yee haue daigned to begett it, be contented to conserue it against what difficulties the world shall oppugne it. Yee haue for your encouradgment heerin infallably assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of infinitly redoubled merit For as casuists hould, whatsoeuer is produced to publike vse, by how much it is a cause of further good or hurte to the imbracer of it, in equall measure is the increase of merite or demerite to the Setter forth, and therfore it is thought of Caluin (whom our countrey rules) that accidentally, by how much his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie increaseth, his torments encrease; yee therfore on the contrarie, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther respectinge your owne merite by being more then semie authors, and patronesles of a worcke of soe greate expectance, or els meerely <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amore amic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ia,</hi> as Phylosophers tea me it, reflecting one the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for <hi>Non n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>b s nati sumus,</hi> wee are not borne to our selues, yee haue reason to accept it vnder your shelter: To this end yee haue an Anthem in the office of our holie Father S. Francis instituted by reason of a diuine oracle, wherin it was reuealed to him, that hee should not only be sollicitous for himselfe, but studdie the good of others; S. Paule witnesseth of him selfe that he could be contented to loose heauen that he might win it for others; heere is a miraculous charitie, yet ye are not driuen to that extreamity, but by being a meanes of others arriuall into heauen, ye encrease your owne ioyes. Agayne; neyther lett the title of patronesses deterr you, as if it sauoured of the world which ye haue abrenunciated, or as if it did not correspond with your Religious simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie which ye haue embraced; for the great affinitie of the worke with your truly simple dispositions, of it selfe did challenge you; For if ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you respect the subiecte, it is a Chronicle of SS. wherein nothinge cann be expected but meere simplicities; Agayne it is of S. Francis SS. who was a mirrour of simplicitie; if you respect the method in the handlinge tis fitted to the matter, as your selues will soone experience: Your office therefore in matronizinge, is but with your wonted sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie to offer the transtatours labours to god almightie for successe: Wherein I would entreate you to offer vpp mee as your deuoted seruāt,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>CLA. FRA.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>