<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READERS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4350_Bo3_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04633</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14753.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4350</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READERS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bartholmevv fayre : a comedie, acted in the yeare, 1614. by the Lady Elizabeths seruants. And then dedicated to King Iames, of most blessed memorie; by the author, Beniamin Iohnson</title>
                 <author>Jonson, Ben</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 88, 2, 93-170, 75, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>TO THE <hi>READERS.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>IN this following <hi>Act,</hi> the <hi>Office</hi> is open'd, and shew'n to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall,</hi> and his <hi>Princesse Pecunia,</hi> wherein the <hi>allegory,</hi> and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the <hi>Author</hi> hath hitherto beene wholly mistaken, and so sinister an interpretation beene made, as if the soules of most of the <hi>Spectators</hi> had liu'd in the eyes and eares of these ridiculous Gossips that tattle betweene the <hi>Acts.</hi> But hee prayes you thus to mend it. To consider the <hi>Newes</hi> here vented, to be none of his <hi>Newes,</hi> or any reasonable mans; but <hi>Newes</hi> made like the times <hi>Newes,</hi> (a weekly cheat to draw mony) and could not be fitter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, then in raising this ridiculous <hi>Office</hi> of the <hi>Staple,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the age may see her owne folly, or hunger and thirst after pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish'd pamphlets of <hi>Newes,</hi> set out euery Saturday, but made all at home, &amp; no syllable of truth in them: then which there cannot be a greater disease in nature, or a fouler scorne put vpon the times. And so apprehending it, you shall doe the <hi>Author,</hi> and your owne iudgement a courtesie, and perceiue the tricke of alluring money to the <hi>Office,</hi> and there cooz'ning the people. If you haue the truth, rest quiet, and consider that</p>
   <q>Ficta, voluptatis causa, sint proxima veris.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>