<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4378_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06705</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17156.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4378</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Adams tragedie : declaring Satans malice and subtiltie, mans weaknesse and miserie, and his deliuerance from eternall captiuitie</title>
                 <author>Mabb, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Ephraim.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Downes (Downe), Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 100 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the losse of a Blessing, made <hi>Esau</hi> weepe; and the losse of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, made <hi>Rachell</hi> mourne: But now behold, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Blessing and Children, but also Parents and Paradise lost to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.<note place="margin">Gen. 50.10.</note> It is true that <hi>Ioseph</hi> and the <hi>Egiptians</hi> made a great mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for <hi>Iaakob;</hi> but the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation both of <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> should be greater, for the death of <hi>Adam;</hi> who by creation was holy and righteous, the image of God: by deputation, Lord and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder ouer the whole World, the vicegerent of God: by bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, the Father of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb facs="5"/>
the inheritaunce of God: and by institution he was placed in <hi>Eden,</hi> the Garden of God: and yet the Garden, Inheritance, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and Sanctitie, all forfeited and lost together. Here then is the stratageme and instrument that effectes this Tragedie:<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note>
      <hi>Satan</hi> that lyer, that murtherer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, maligning <hi>Adam,</hi> and in <hi>Adam</hi> all mankinde, deuised and practised how to draw <hi>Adam</hi> to rebell against God. <hi>Adam</hi> was deceiued by the subtiltie of the <hi>Diuell,</hi> and he did rebell. God was displeased by the breaking of the Commaundement;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> Sinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Death preuayled. Wherefore I intreate thee (christian Reader) which art the Child of <hi>Adam,</hi> to peruse this Treatise with regard; not curiously excepting against, but graciously accepting what a
<pb facs="5"/>
free and well meaning minde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto thee, whereby thou shalt see thy Fathers and thine owne estate, by what meanes yee were lost; how worthily condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, how graciously redeemed, and how ioyfully receiued.<note place="margin">Luke. 10.4.</note> That so at all times, and in all places, thou mayst tremble, and feare, and loue, and honour, and prayse the Lord thy God. To whose infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, heauenly direction, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly protection, I heartily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee, for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>I. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>Psal. 119 52.39,.</bibl>
      <q>I remembred thy iudgments of old, o Lord, &amp; haue been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted: for thy iudgments are good.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>