<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS SOVERAINE, THE KINGS MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Pont, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4419_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09838</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20100</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4419</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS SOVERAINE, THE KINGS MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Pont, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Against sacrilege : three sermons preached by Maister Robert Pont: an aged pastour in the kirk of God</title>
                 <author>Pont, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO HIS SOVERAINE, THE KINGS MAIESTIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I would think it an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie thing to presente your Highnesse with such a meane Pamphlet as this; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Ser mones; vnlesse the argument thereof craued a powerfull Protector and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone. For besides, it speaketh the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without coloured Rethoricke of wordes, the matter therein entreated, is odious in the eyes &amp; eares of many, who find themselues tuitched as guilty of Sacrilege. Herefore I could se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ke no other retreate, but vnder your highnes wings: who (besides ye would gladly heare the trueth simply spoken) haue also your parte in this turne. For your Highnesse is no lesse interest then the Kirk, in the wrongfull abusing of the Kirk-rents. And as to me, the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how far it is from my heart, to procure wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly the hatred of any person, great or smal. Yet in respect of the charge I beare; and that it
<pb facs="6"/>
is very vncomely for my gray-haires (my one foote being alreadie in the graue) to play the hypocrite or flatterers parte: But to discharge a good conscience in this and all other behalfes belonging vnto my calling: Herefore reposing vppon your Maiesties good minde and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance against all calumniators of mee, for this my plaine dealing; and humbly submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this and all other my laboures, to your hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse censure and correction, in any thing I shalbe found to haue failed or spoken amisse, I humbly take my leaue: Beseeching the Lorde of Heauen to further and aduance all your Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse good and godly intentions, to therefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all abuses within your Land.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Hienesse subject with obedience and Prayer,
ROBERT PONT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>