<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ire∣land, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>P., J.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4427_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10242</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20521.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4427</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ire∣land, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>P., J.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The heart of the king, and the king of the heart, or, A briefe vnfolding of that remarkable proverbe of the royall preacher : written in the time of His Maiesties abode at Plimmouth, and preferred vnto him in his returne from thence, anno 1625 : together with a short meditation vpon 2. Sam. 24.15, preached at a weekely lecture in Deuon, in those fearefull times of mortalitie by J.P. Master of Arts and minister of the gospell</title>
                 <author>Pyne, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 56 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE <hi>PRINCE</hi> CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD King of Great <hi>Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most gracious Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T might iustly bee cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured as an intolerable rashnesse in your vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Subiect, that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so lately pardoned for his great audaciousnesse, should
<pb facs="3"/>
yet againe presume in the same kind; had he not read charactered in your very countenance, <hi>Quanto maior tanto melior,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">August.</note>
      <hi>Quanto melior tanto mitior,</hi> that your Sonereigne Greatnesse made way for your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Goodnesse, and boundles Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes; and beene confident that it would graciously consider, that albeit it were an vnwonted presumption for so meane a Subiect to aduance in so short a space, to so high a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, two seuerall paper-presents (as vnworthy to be read, as euery way vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie) yet the rare presence of so great an Highnesse as the eldest eye hath not seene in these parts of your Dominions, (which are not so farre distant from your Royall Mansions, as their people are neerely linked to
<pb facs="3"/>
the seruice of your Maiestie) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that great and generall emulation of your loyall Subiects, stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to doe your Maiestie some accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table seruice in this vnusuall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, might be admitted to mediate vnto your Royall fauour for a renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the former Pardon, and giuing acceptance to the same person, who with as much loyall respect as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with the same prostrate humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie deuoteth this his second seruice to your sacred selfe, in your Princely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from the period of your long progresse; humbly desiring the Lord of Hoasts to prosper your Maiesties Royall <hi>Marriage, Leagues, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies, Armies</hi> and <hi>Iourneyes,</hi> that they may tend to the Glorie of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,</hi> the terror of your Enemies,
<pb facs="4"/>
the assurance of your safetie, the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of your deiected Sister, and the comfort of your deuoted Subiects, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom, euen in that long <hi>Roll</hi> extended in the Westerne <hi>Chart,</hi> there shall euer be found while life shall remayne,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most loyall and obedient Subiect, <hi>J. P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>