<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4427_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10242</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20521.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4427</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The heart of the king, and the king of the heart, or, A briefe vnfolding of that remarkable proverbe of the royall preacher : written in the time of His Maiesties abode at Plimmouth, and preferred vnto him in his returne from thence, anno 1625 : together with a short meditation vpon 2. Sam. 24.15, preached at a weekely lecture in Deuon, in those fearefull times of mortalitie by J.P. Master of Arts and minister of the gospell</title>
                 <author>Pyne, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 56 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>ANd thus Gentle Reader, I haue communicated vnto thy view these precedent pape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> which were penned (for the most part) in great want of time, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thou are already aduertised. Yet are they sent abroad, without adding, altering, augmenting or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of any materiall passage; that so they may follow their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall Copy, which (together with another Tract, not yet publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed) found acceptance at the hands of our Dread and Deare So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne. In respect of whose gracious Aspect, I haue the more cause to presume of thy fauour, or (if that may not bee obtayned) the lesse reason to esteeme thy Censure.</p>
   <pb facs="32"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>