<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>R., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4449_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21347.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4449</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Testis veritatis : The doctrine of King Iames our late soueraigne of famous memory. Of the Church of England. Of the Catholicke Church. Plainely shewed to bee one in the points of prædestination, free-will, certaintie of saluation. With a discouery of the grounds naturall politicke of Arminianisme. By F. Rous</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 92 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>HAuing heard of a publike declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Doctor</hi> Palca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell <hi>in his</hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Febr. 27.</hi>
      </note> made by a reuerend and right worthy Diuine, of his Most Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majesties Resolution and Decree, to oppose <hi>Arminianisme,</hi> I thought it a fit time to put in order some pieces, which being set together, might amount to an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Proofe and Testimonie, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, herein hath merited most glorious and incomparable Titles, euen such as haue in them the Weight and Substance of High and supreame Excellencie.</p>
   <p>For first, herein Hee is the Successor of his Father (as in Bloud and Royalty, so) in his excellent Thoughts, Designes, and Actions: for this is a proceeding and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in the same worke, wherein the most learned King, and absolute Iudge of Doctrines, began a most noble Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. His zeale in this matter, would not bee bounded with the seas, but on the wings of an heauenly fire flying beyond them, it there consumed the fifties and their Captaines, it dissolued the Bands of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the truth.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Secondly, herein the Title of Nursing Father of the Church, a Title giuen to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Kings by the heauenly Oracles, more strongly fastneth and spreadeth the Roote of it. So that at once the same Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, hereby acquireth the Dignitie, both of a perfect Sonne, and a glorious Father. When the Doctrine of a Church is cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed▪ the life of a Church is cherished; and when a contrary Doctrine is opposed, then the Doctrine of a Church is cherished.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, hereby the Title of Defender of the Faith, hath still more Realitie put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and it is made more vnlike to those empty Titles, that haue the Word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and not the matter within.</p>
   <p>Each of these I hope shall appeare in that which followeth. For though it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists of many seuerall pieces, like vnto broken accounts, yet I hope, being all set together, they will arise to make vp the promised summes, both in weight and number.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>F. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>