<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>I., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4459_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13053</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23345.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4459</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>I., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The survey of London : containing the original, increase, modern estate and government of that city, methodically set down : with a memorial of those famouser acts of charity, which for publick and pious vses have been bestowed by many worshipfull citizens and benefactors as also all the ancient and modern monuments erected in the churches, not only of those two famous cities, London and Westminster, but (now newly added) four miles compass begun first by the pains and industry of John Stow, in the year 1598 ; afterwards inlarged by the care and diligence of A.M. i the year 1618 ; and now compleatly finished by the study &amp; labour of A.M, H.D. and others, this present year 1633 ; whereunto, besides many additions (as appears by the contents) are annexed divers alphabetical tables, especially two, the first, an index of things, the second, a concordance of names</title>
                 <author>Stow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 534, 527-652, 655-770, 773-939, 29 pages, illustrations, coats of arms, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I may give you a reason of such things as the Iudicious and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
Censurer may deeme blemishes and imperfections in this
<hi>Worke:</hi> For the Order, you may be pleased to understand, it is
not so absolutely Methodicall as I could wish it were, yet needs
none other <hi>Apologie,</hi> than the length of time it hath beene grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to this Bulke, and Mortality of the <hi>Authors,</hi> who have spent (two of them
now) their lives in the disquisition of venerable <hi>Antiquity</hi> concerning this <hi>City.</hi>
The Learned know, Men are all <hi>various</hi> in their Opinions, as in their <hi>Faces</hi> you
hardly finde of a Nation two that resemble in all proportions, so in their <hi>Minds</hi> is
there as much discrepancy, and then must there needs be the same or more in their
Writings, the expresse Image of their Minds. And this is the <hi>Fate</hi> of our present
<hi>Worke,</hi> which begun Methodically, hath not beene so well prosecuted, whether out of
difference in <hi>Iudgement,</hi> or want of <hi>Information,</hi> I dispute not: Probable it may
be, the desire of inserting all things for the delight of the <hi>Reader,</hi> might breed this
want of Method, and the rather am I induc'd to incline thereto, since every dayes
Experience teaches, how unstable oftentimes and incertaine Friendship is, when she
promises Information in this kinde: Yet this, the ingenuity of a courteous <hi>Reader</hi>
will excuse, since the Benefit compensates the Wrong.</p>
   <p>And to administer a salve to this sore, and prevent Distraction in the <hi>Reader,</hi>
in this last Impression have you variety of <hi>Tables,</hi> succinct and pithy, yet not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure:
In the beginning, the whole body of the <hi>Book</hi> dissected into sixtie <hi>Chapters,</hi>
whose short <hi>Contents</hi> epitomize the Substance of the <hi>Work:</hi> Then briefe <hi>Schemes</hi>
as well of all the <hi>Churches</hi> in and about <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster</hi> foure miles
compasse, as of all the <hi>Halls</hi> and <hi>Companies</hi> of this Honourable <hi>City,</hi> both Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betically
ranged with reference to their proper places. Lastly, that nothing might be
wanting which should bring ease and furtherance to the Studious <hi>Reader,</hi> have
you a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Authors,</hi> on whose authority the truth of our Assertions may
depend.</p>
   <p>Neither leave we you heare: In the end also have we furnished it with two exact
<hi>Tables;</hi> The first an <hi>Index,</hi> containing in it the chiefe <hi>Streets, Lanes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits,</hi>
stately <hi>Houses</hi> of <hi>Noblemen, Innes</hi> of <hi>Court, Chancery,</hi> and other
ancient <hi>Monuments</hi> of this <hi>City,</hi> not without the admixion also of worthy <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
and <hi>Customes</hi> of <hi>Citizens.</hi> The other a <hi>Concordance</hi> of those, whose
<hi>Honour</hi> in their <hi>Office, Charity</hi> in their <hi>Almes, Memory</hi> in their <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
hath acquainted <hi>Posterity</hi> with their <hi>Names:</hi> By this Guide, hee who
boasts his Birth in a Magnificent <hi>City</hi> (as the Ancient did in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Athens)</hi>
may with great facility finde his Ancestors in their <hi>Honours, Almes giving,
Tombes,</hi> or other memorable and worthy Actions here recorded: For instance
(not to exceed our Memories) finde the name of <hi>Anderson</hi> in the <hi>Concordance,</hi>
and according to the first figures <hi>(105. a. ¶)</hi> turne to the Page, and you have his
Liberality or Benefaction to <hi>Brazen-nose</hi> College in <hi>Oxford;</hi> then consult the
second <hi>(291. a. ¶)</hi> in like manner, and you have his Monument in Saint <hi>Olave
Vpwel's</hi> Church: so the third <hi>(592. b. ¶.)</hi> and you shall finde him there She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe,
<hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1601. The same order is observed in the rest, onely for distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
sake, I have added these letters. <hi>B.</hi> to such as have beene <hi>Bishops,</hi> and
<hi>M.</hi> to those that have borne the Office of <hi>Maior.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus have we endevored to prevent Distraction, and reduce the copious Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
of this <hi>Worke</hi> to heads, for the <hi>Readers</hi> ease; not without a great deale of
Paines, Care, and Charge: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udicious can give the best estimate of the Paines;
of the Care none better than he that hath reaped benefit by the reading; as for the
Charge, the proportion of the Volume speakes, especially to the skilfull in that My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery;
to which if you adde the length of time (now almost three yeeres) it hath lyen
under the Presse, there is none but may conceive the greatnesse thereof. Yet no
small satisfaction to all these may you afford (Gentle <hi>Reader)</hi> by your candide and
courteous acceptance, with a future encouragement (in this, or the like) to the ready
endevours of him that will study to be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Servant,
C. I.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>