<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERIE VVOR∣shipfull, vertuous, and reli∣gious Gentlewoman, Mistresse Eliza∣beth Foord, wife vnto the worshipfull ma∣ster Th. Foord of Ilsington in Deuonshire Esquire: R.M. dayly prayeth the rich blessings of God, to be powred down vpon them, their kindred and posteritie, to their comforts in this life, and to their eternall sal∣uation in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S450_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07289</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17683a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S450</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERIE VVOR∣shipfull, vertuous, and reli∣gious Gentlewoman, Mistresse Eliza∣beth Foord, wife vnto the worshipfull ma∣ster Th. Foord of Ilsington in Deuonshire Esquire: R.M. dayly prayeth the rich blessings of God, to be powred down vpon them, their kindred and posteritie, to their comforts in this life, and to their eternall sal∣uation in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Saint Peters watch word : the end of all things is at hand / digested into eight chapters, and published by R.M. minister ; perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>(10, 80, that is 161) pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERIE VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, vertuous, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Gentlewoman, Mistresse <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Foord, wife vnto the worshipfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Th. Foord</hi> of Ilsington in Deuonshire <hi>Esquire: R.M. dayly prayeth the rich blessings</hi> of God, to be powred down vpon them, their kindred and posteritie, to their comforts in this life, and to their eternall sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He dayes of man, being compared with eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, may be likened vnto one sande on the Sea shore, vnto one grasse vpon the ground, or to one starre in the firmament, matched with all the rest: for if a man coulde liue, as some almost haue liued, <hi>a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares,</hi> yet all those yeares, are but <hi>as one day with God.</hi> The ignoraunce
<pb facs="3"/>whereof, hath made men imagine, that it is a very long while agone since God created man; and that seeing the world hath continued so many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares; therefore that it shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue an ende: yea the worser sort do thinke, that either God hath not at all determined to destroy this worlde; or, if he haue determined and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed so to do, that then he hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his promise. And therefore say many times to themselues, <hi>Where is the promise of Christ his comming,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? And wherefore doth he make so long delay?</p>
   <p>Whereunto our Sauiour himselfe doth answere, if we would vouchsafe to heare him; and sweares because we shoulde beleeue him: <hi>Beholde I come shortly:</hi> And, <hi>surely I come quickly,</hi> tary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for no mans pleasure, one minute of an houre longer, then is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and appoynted, which appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, though no man may curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously inquire of; yet euery good Christian wil dayly think of it, &amp; thank
<pb facs="3"/>God, for any good thing that may put them in remembrance of the same.</p>
   <p>Among which number of true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Christians, because I knowe your worship to bee one, and such a one whereof in my charge, I take greate comfort, as well for your godlinesse, as for your kindnesse extended vnto me; I therefore offer vnto your meeke Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, by way of dedication, these my poore labours (howsoeuer imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or vnpolished) which at times of leysure, I haue collected since my first comming vnto you; through the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and presentment of your kinde husband, and my very worshipfull and louing Patron. Publishing the same in this sort, for the benefite of all, but (through their owne fault) for the comfort onely of all such, as either do, or hereafter shall vnfainedly loue and looke for the comming of our Lorde Iesus Christ to their immortalitie.</p>
   <p>Beseeching the diuine maiestie, to giue vs grace and patience, cheerfully to passe ouer this our pilgrimage in his
<pb facs="4"/>feare, and in some discharge of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in a good conscience, to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and to some good of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; howsoeuer the world, and the childrē therof, shall esteeme of vs or of any thing we do: that so at last to our endlesse ioy, we may heare that sweet sentence of our sauiour pronounced vnto vs, <hi>Euge bone serue &amp; fidelis: Well done good and faithfull seruant, thou hast beene faithfull in few things, I will make thee ruler ouer much, enter thou into the ioy of thy Maister:</hi> Which God of his mercy grant, through the merit of his sonne, by the assistance of Gods holy spirit; who seale the assurance therof in our hearts: to which holy and blessed Trinitie, be ascribed all prayse, power and maiestie, for euer, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships as much bounden vnder God, as his life is worth; and in the Lord euer to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</hi> Radford Mauericke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>