<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4590_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19239</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5652</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4590</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations and praiers gathered out of the sacred letters and vertuous writers : disposed in fourme of the alphabet of the Queene Her most excellent Maiesties name : whereunto are added comfortable consolations (drawen out of the Latin) to afflicted mindes</title>
                 <author>Conway, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>416+ pages, 16° in 8's</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="20"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>I Deeme it vvil be cause of greate woonder to thee (gentle Reader) that I, whom neither daily experience of Learning hath instru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted, long vse of exercise hath perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ne yet the frequented Studye of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>acred Muse hath authorised, would enterprise the Publication of any woorke, and hazarde the daunger of detracting tōgues: chiefly of so pure, &amp; Diuine a cause, as effect of Prayer, which I doo not committe to open Eies, as a thinge worthye of Learned viewe: or deeming the store of like matter rare to thy Age, hauinge choyse, and abundaunce, neither yet thorow Pride of Vaine glory moo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="21"/> or otherwise, that I would bee reputed more Religious, then Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous. Chiefly haue I wrought the same, Priuileaged through the Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Loue my gratious Gouernesse, hath in all Vertue, to approche her stately presence, as the Image of my devvtiful memorie, boast of my true Loyaltie, and vievv of my deepe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery. Consequently being tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with infinite troubles: Broken with the Ankor of many cares: res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trained of Libertie: spurned of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: forsaken of health: forgotten of Friends: couched in Caue of deep Foregetfulnesse: My faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice misconstrued: sinister practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses allowed: my true Loyaltie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="21"/> suspected and with my renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Soueraigne sinisterly defaced. Emong these rigorous rages of ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kours raigne: emong these fretting furies of fickle, blinde, and frowarde Fortune: emong these cruel chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Worldely choking calamities: Emōg these sturdy striuing streams of stubborne stormye state: Sith I find nothing that geueth my consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming carkas comfort, but only Pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er being the most redy calme to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pease these troublesome tempestes: and further findinge it the faithfull Imbassidour, &amp; perfect Pathe to eche mannes eternall blisse, haue thought it not altogether in Vaine, &amp; repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte, to deuide with thee (gentle
<pb facs="22"/> Reader) the excellencie, and benefite of the same, to be holden with thee, as a daily exercise of thy delights, and most sure staffe to all thy purposes: so shalt thou shun the shipwracke of all aduersitie, and continevv with increase, the beawtie of thy prospe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie. Make mee thy Presidente, I beseeche thee, searche the records of my passed Life. Credite not Fame, who wanteth truthe, and measure in all thinges: and when thou wilte enter Iudgement, haue reason for thy guide, and dewe proued Actes for thy ground: so shalt thou not erre.</p>
   <p>Which recorded in minde, rifle the race I haue runne, I pray thee vnfold the Table of my Actes good, or ill.
<pb facs="22"/> I boast a life, free from deede, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of any disloyaltie againste my renowmed Soueraigne. I compare a Harte so true, and faithfull in the Weale of my Natiue Countrie, as may equal (I protest before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty of the highest) the beste, and not inferiour to the truest. Yet I acknovv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge I worthily beare this my exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led libertie (whose Fruites in parte I offer thee) for that I haue rebelled against the Omnipotente GOD, and my chiefe LORDE: for that I haue been negligente of his Precepts, and slouthfull in this vse of Holy Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Whervnto, I hope easie perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion shall suffise, so to incorporate thee in Loue, Felowshippe, and daily
<pb facs="23"/> exercise, as sharpely to take reuenge of thy sluggish body, in whatsoeuer Daye thy vngratefull Spirite shall become negligente of thy dewetie therin.</p>
   <p>Consider, I pray thee, the paine, Passion, merites, and immense good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, of a milde, louing, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sauiour Iesus Christe, towarde thee: forgeat not, that beinge deade throughe Sinne in thy firste Father ADAM, and worthily condemned to eternall dampnacion. He, without other mocion, then his own mercy, brought thee to liue againe. If this so great mercie, cannot bring in the bondes of thy owinge dewtie, and mooue thee by daily vse of thankes
<pb facs="23"/> geuing through harty Praier, to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel the records of such gratitude, be yet reduced, by considering the scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching paines prepared in guerdon of the vngrate, and reprobate. Accepte the troubles, wretchednesse, &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdomes of this lothsom life, as true Figure of his fauoure, and signes of his blessing: be not vnthankfull by omission of Prayer toward so natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and more then louing a Father, that he hath stauled thee on earth, not onelie replenished with manie wholesom Hearbs, Flowers, Fruites, Waters, Trees, Plants, &amp; manie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Creatures to thy behoofe and Subiection, but hath farther geuen thee a most comfortable and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb facs="24"/> promise, and graunt of his holy Spirite, &amp; deuine grace, to arm, guide and defende thee, so well, a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst the traines of thy Aunciente foe Sathan, as also how to vse these his wonderful workes, louing kind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, and great mercie so that with heartie and faithfull Praier, thou call to him for the same, yea and hathe left thee a form of Peticion, by Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to him for all thy necessities, and lastlie hath geuen thee, a speciall cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, to Praie, promising to heare and graunt thy request.</p>
   <p>Wherfore it is requisite to thee &amp; such as praie: Firste well to consider of this promisse, whereby may bee kindled in them a more Ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
<pb facs="24"/> Faithfullie to pray, for without this speciall commaundemente en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning vs to praie, except also God had promised hee woulde heare vs, neither thou nor anie creature, could obtaine the least thinge by his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And here thou maist see when we obtaine any thing the graunt is not to be attributed to our praiers, or worthinesse, but to the vnspeake<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able goodnesse of GOD, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth our praiers with his promise and commaundemente, wherby hee dooth mooue vs to praie, that wee may learne he is carefull for vs, and much more ready to graunte then we to aske or receiue. And because he offreth to vs more goodnes then
<pb facs="25"/> either wee dare, or can in any wise desire, let that blessed bountie of GOD so kindle and confirme thee, that thou alwaies praie without doubting.</p>
   <p>For speciallie in acceptable prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is required: that we mistrust no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the prouidence of the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by that he chieflie promiseth that he will heare vs, and gaue a precept of praying, onely to settell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our sure beliefe that he vvould heare vs: as in the .21. of Mathew and .11. of Marke is saide: <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer you aske Praying, beleue you shall receiue it, and it shall be geuen you.</hi> Luke likevvise. 11.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Euery one that asketh, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,
<pb facs="25"/> he that seeketh, findeth, and to him that knocketh, it shalbe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</hi> With these and like, so well promises as commaundementes, thy minde is to be confirmed faithfullie to praie, assuring thy self thou shalt receiue all that thou doest aske. But if thou doubt of the will of God, in thy Praier, &amp; praie rashlie, thou cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittest tvvo offences. First, because thorowe thine owne fault, thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of lesse valevv, and laboure in vaine. <hi>For</hi> (saith S. Iames) <hi>If any man require ought of God, lette him aske with Faith, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge: For hee that doubteth, is like a Surge of the Sea, which is tossed of the winde, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb facs="26"/> with violence: N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ither let that man thincke he shall receiue any thing of his Heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, because his hart is not sure &amp; quiet: for Faith kepeth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> harte quiet, that it may receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> guift of God.</hi> The other is that thou be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeuest in God as in a light and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous Person: deeminge him ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not able to perfourm his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, or that he vvill not. These plucke avvay the Glory and Name from the high God, (which beleue he is not faithfull and true.) And this Sinne is so great, that of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian it maketh a Heathen: for God is not only denied in this Sinne, but he is vtterly thereby lost, neither is
<pb facs="26"/> there any hope of recouery, so longe as thou abidest in this infidelitie.</p>
   <p>And if it happen to any that prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vvithout sure trust, that he ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine any thing, that guifte is geuen of God (being angry) to the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction bothe of Body and Soule: that at the least somme Honour may be done to the holy Scriptures, whiche may be vttered from menne full of sin, distrust and contempt of God.</p>
   <p>Furthermore they doo not iudge right, vvhiche thincke to obteine in prayer by their ovvne vvorthinesse.</p>
   <p>This is not to be regarded, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou be vvorthy, or vnvvorthy, that praiest: for praier consisteth not in the worthinesse vvhiche wee
<pb facs="27"/> bring, but in the infallible truthe of Goddes promise. And truly, if praier be grounded, eyther vpon it selfe or any other, it is vayn &amp; frustrate: yea thoughe it seeme to proceede from the Godly affectes of the Harte, and eies pouring out aboundant teares of Water, or Bloud. But let vs praie to be Iudged vvorthy and bee hearde, because vvee perceiue, oure ovvne vnvvorthynesse, and are bolde through the only goodnesse of God and Faith. Although thou percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest thy selfe vnvvorthy in desert, ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to aske, or receiue any thinge of thy Celestiall Father, let this only be regarded, that thou shalt obtain it through the honour of his name,
<pb facs="27"/> vvhich is true: and let not thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuing Faith holde his promise, for an vntruthe: Neyther shall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthynesse hinder thee, as also thy vvorthinesse shall nothinge further thee. But Vnbeliefe onely shall damme thee, and Faithe shall make thee vvorthy, and saue thee. Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentely therfore bevvare that thou neuer deem thy self vvorthy to pray or receiue, but euen vvhen thou fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leste thy selfe able boldely to leane to the sure, and true promises of thy chiefe Creatoure: of vvhose mercy, thou oughtest to bee so muche the more sure, because euen as hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised thee vnvvorthy, and vvithout deserte, that hee vvill denie thee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
<pb facs="28"/> So likevvise, thoughe thou be vnvvorthy, yet he vvil heare thee, that he may perfourme the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses he gaue thee. So that nothinge is left to thy deserts, or vvorthinesse but the truth, &amp; mercie of the most Highest do chalenge all thinges to themselues. From vvhence al pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mises flovve as oute of a Fountaine, that this s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ying might be fulfilled: Psalm. 25. <hi>All the wayes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Lorde are mercy and truthe:</hi> for his mercy vve do se in his promises and his Truthe vvhen they are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and kept. And likevvise in the Psal. 32. <hi>Mercie and Truthe are in his way:</hi> that is they are mette and seene, ioyned togeather in any
<pb facs="28"/> one vvorke or guift, vvhiche vve ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine in our prayers. Finally vvee ought so to moderate our Faithe in Goddes promises, that vvee assigne no end, time, or place, to the Maiesty of the Highest, but leaue all to his Will. Wisdome, and Omnipotencie, beinge sure it shall be donne: Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> although ther appeare neither place, time, nor reason, hovv it shall bee brought to passe. It is sure his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine vvisdom farre better knovveth and forseeth then vvee. Therefore beleeue GOD, and referre all to his vvill and disposicion: so shall hee bring to passe thy demaund by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, if no other vvay it may be.</p>
   <p>As in the people <hi>Israell</hi> vvhiche
<pb facs="29"/> beleeued God vvould deliuer them from their Enemies, yet appeared there no meane hovv: Suddainely he opened the Redde Sea, and gaue them safe passage, and the Enemies all he ouervvhelmed and drovvned.</p>
   <p>Likevvise the holy <hi>Iudith,</hi> vvhen shee hearde the Citie of <hi>Bethulya</hi> had taken Counsel, and determined that vnlesse God vvithin fiue Dayes vvould send them help, they vvould yeelde the Citie to the Enemie, shee greatelye rebuked them, sayinge: <hi>Who are you which thus tempt the Lord: This communication is not to prouoke mercie, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to stirre anger, and kindle wrath. Haue you set a time for
<pb facs="29"/> the Mercy of the Almighty, and will you appoynt a Day in your owne Iudgement?</hi> This Faith in the holy Woman vvas so vvel accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the God of all Victorye, that vvith a maruailous meane he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered her, that she cutte of the Head of <hi>Holifernes,</hi> and preserued the Citie vvith bitter repulse to his vvhole Army. Likevvise Paule saith Ephes. 3. <hi>This is the manner of God, that he will do all thinges by a farre other, and more better way, then we can pray him or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstand.</hi> So vve perceiue our selues to be far inferiour, then that vve may appoynt, or prescribe in our prayer, time, or, place, manner, or other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance.
<pb facs="30"/> Wherfore cease thou not (gentle Reader) to praye, and refer all to his Diuine will, stedfastly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing that he vvill not faile to heare and helpe thee. So shalt thou make his brightnesse shine vppon thee, procure his tender kindenesse, tovvard thee: dravve his Rodde, the Lot of thy vnbeleeuing, from thee and be as <hi>Mounte Sion,</hi> that can not be remooued, but stand fast for euer and euer. To the stately top of vvhiche blessed Mansion, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall thy vvillinge foote be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to ascende, if vvith minde, and memory thou obserue and imitate the Holy Ambrose who teacheth thus: Sit oratio pura, sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex,
<pb facs="30"/> dilucida, atque mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festa, plena grauitatis &amp; pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deris, non affectata, eligan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, sed intermissa gratia.</p>
   <p>For the true, and acceptable prayer consisteth not in the rablemente of vvordes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e yet in the vehemencie of voyce, but in the stedfastnesse of thy beleife in the beavvty of thy desires, and in the pure intentiue thoughtes of thy hart fixed on his Diuine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies at such time as thou doost pray.</p>
   <p>It auaileth not othervvise, thou seke him vvith long laboure of lips, thy minde distracte vvith vani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es &amp; thy Harte in Pilgrymage vvith
<pb facs="31"/> Worldly carefulnes: vvherof if thou make scruple through insufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of this vnlatened Writer, let the saying of the Sage satisfie thee, vvho telleth mans Prayer to be of perfect value vvhen he acknovvledgeth him selfe to be brickle Clay, and Duste: humblinge him selfe: chalenginge no vvoorthynesse of Vertue to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self: but confessing vvholy the good he doothe to proceede of the onely motion, and mercie of his Heauenly Maker, attributing to him only the due glorie, and praise. This, Iohn vvorthely confirmeth: Deus adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Spiritu, &amp; Veritate: <hi>I say then</hi> Non in magnificis, &amp; amplosis ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis adoratur. Whiche lette suffise
<pb facs="31"/> thee (gentle Reader) from mee, and be eased in farther trouble of my vnlearned stile: yet knovv from me, hovv hardlie I haue bin distressed in gathering the same to thy behoofe, both anoied vvith anxiety of minde by condition of place, and of taking my diet vvithout vse of any T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher (beeinge estranged all other meanes) theron vvith leathie Pensell of Leade, to bringe to thy gratefull Hand, this small Quantitie of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Foode, vvhich I hope vvil moue thy humble Nature to allovve thee rather of this my good vvil, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. In anie learned skill that I offer thee, I confes, I maie not vvel boast: Neither doo I assure thee, my selfe
<pb facs="32"/> not to haue erred. I can not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge singularitie: Yet graunt mee (gentle Reader) thy pacient peruse, and Freendlie correction vvhen my Faults present their number before thy learned vievve: so shalte thou free thy selfe from foule Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and geue me equall paie of my paines: Wherin I haue not fedde thee with Sugred sape distilling frō PERNASSO. I hold it an vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt discord in Heauenlie H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: not because MERCVRIE ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed him in ARGOS Bloudde, do I refuse his ayde, but because I am taught by the Apostle that Faithe is not grounded in the bewtie of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours Eloquence, ne yet in Pride of</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <pb facs="36"/>
   <pb facs="36"/>
   <pb facs="37"/>
   <pb facs="37"/>
   <pb facs="38"/>
   <pb facs="38"/>
   <pb facs="39"/>
   <pb facs="39"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>