<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the true Catechisers of his Church, the true grace mercy and peace of the true God, be true encouragement.</title>
           <author>Downing, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4617_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20776</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7158.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4617</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the true Catechisers of his Church, the true grace mercy and peace of the true God, be true encouragement.</title>
                 <author>Downing, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The catechisers holy encouragement to the profitable exercise of catechising in the Church of England</title>
                 <author>Downing, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Bird, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the true Catechisers of his Church, the true grace mercy and peace of the true God, be true encouragement.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I should accuse you for writing your many Catechismes, I should rather discourage yours from reading them, then excuse my selfe for pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning these encouragements for vs all to Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing. Yet (let it be spoken with all humility) if you in the crowd of Catechisers each one find an excuse for all the company; I hope (if it be not presumption) you all will hold me excused, for these small encouragements for you all, being but one; If you obserued, the two Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on the otherside of the former leafe, you may easely perceiue, these things were one day Preached as Sermons of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the Eares of Parents, Gouernours, and old men, in the Congregation; if you will see the leaues that follow hereafter, you may vnderstand they were Catechising waies in the Hands of little ones in writing, for their encouragement, another day; I should then be very sorry, that what day soeuer they shalbe seene by your Eyes, you will see the motes that are in your brothers eyes, that labour to shew you, though vnworthily the encouragements that they haue seene: but I hope you will ioyne your Hearts in prayer, that God by all meanes, whether great or small, will harten vs all in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exercise. And so</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>right humbly I rest your poore Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Lord. THO. DOWNING.</signed>
      <dateline>Aldermanbery London.</dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>