<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue ❧ Gylis Coucheman to all Christē Readers vnto whō this boke shal come, Wysheth grace, mercye &amp; peace frō God the father of our Lorde Iesus christe, wyth encreace of repentaunce and amendemēt of lyfe thorow our Lord and onely Sauyour, &amp; by the workyng of the holy spyryte. Amen.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S469843_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07535</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5870.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S469843</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue ❧ Gylis Coucheman to all Christē Readers vnto whō this boke shal come, Wysheth grace, mercye &amp; peace frō God the father of our Lorde Iesus christe, wyth encreace of repentaunce and amendemēt of lyfe thorow our Lord and onely Sauyour, &amp; by the workyng of the holy spyryte. Amen.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exhortatyon or warnynge, to beware of greater plagues &amp; troubles : then are yet come vppon thys realme, for the synnes and wyckednes commytted there in</title>
                 <author>Coucheman, Giles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>(unpaged), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue ❧ Gylis Coucheman to all Christē Readers vnto whō this boke shal come, Wysheth grace, mercye &amp; peace frō God the father of our Lorde Iesus christe, wyth encreace of repentaunce and amendemēt of lyfe thorow our Lord and onely Sauyour, &amp; by the workyng of the holy spyryte. Amen.</head>
   <p>LYke as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> almyghty eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal god of his tēdre mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy &amp; loue, not onely crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mā at the begīning after his own similitude &amp; likenes, but also whan he was loste, most graciously redemed hī, &amp; broughte hym out of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. Euē so whan mā (ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regarding his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful creation, nether his most deare redemption) gropethe in darckenesse, in vyce and
<pb facs="3"/> blyndnes, lyeth in the deuils prison, and goeth in the way of dāpnacion, God alwayes setteth vp hys lighte before hym, sendethe thee message of hys worde vnto hym, she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth him what case he is in, geueth hym warnynge, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the pryson dore, calleth him out of the deuyls seruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, telleth him what daunger it is to bee hys bondman, or seruaunte vnto synne. Thys doth God alwaye before he punishe &amp; plague the worlde. This (I say) hath euer ben y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worke of god sēce the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, as the stories and Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes of al the holy Byble doeth testyfye.</p>
   <p>And thoughe we had no writinges of gods actes in times past, yet hath he prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tysed
<pb facs="3"/> and vsed thys same his wonderfull worcke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye vppon vs nowe in oure dayes, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> lyke as we muste nedes cōfesse that we ar crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of god, &amp; redemed by his only mercy in hys deare sōne Iesus christ. So can we not denye, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we haue hearde his holy message, had no lesse preachinges &amp; warninges of daūgers to come, then other haue had before our dayes. Yea euē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same merciful god that sēt Noe to preach righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse vnto thee wicked world, and cōuerted the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuytes by his word in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the prophet Ionas, hath done euē so w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vs in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry cōdicion, &amp; some (thākes be to hī therfore) hath he brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght out of darknes into hys
<pb facs="4"/> wonderful light &amp; out of the deuyls seruice into the kīgdō of his most deare sonne.</p>
   <p>But alas &amp; wo to this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful world, for like as a great nōber that be in prysō of sathā wil not come forth whā thei ar called &amp; the dore set opē, but go on stil stōblin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in darknes whan the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of light is offred them.</p>
   <p>Euen so, yf any mā playe a wyse mās part, &amp; do as he is warned by gods worde, he shal haue a greate sort,<note place="margin">Thei that forsake y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> law pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se thee vngodlye, but soche as kepe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lawe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borrethe them, prou xxviii</note> yea a nōber of scornefull mockers (the whych because the man wyl not daunce in the deuils morys with theym, nor kepe theyr company in the bonda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of synne &amp; vyce, neyther rōne with them vnto like cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusyon) that wyll laughe
<pb facs="4"/> him to scorne &amp; mock him euē to his face, &amp; lyke as whan a true poore mā cometh out of prysō, he shal haue mo to stād gasing and gaping vpō him thē to do him good, or to hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe hī to his fees, euē so now, that god of his mercy hathe called some of vs out of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thās prysō &amp; frō the worldly wicked doers, my lordes fole w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his cōpanions stādeth sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vpō vs &amp; mocked vs, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause we sit not styl w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> other prysoners in sīne &amp; vice, ther goeth an apostle (sayth one) ther goeth one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> new bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrē,<note place="margin">Foules ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horreth thē that eschu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth euyll. prou. xiii, c</note> sayth another, ther go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, a iustifier of hī self, saith another, ther goeth one that wyl lyue w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out sinne, sayth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother, and thus is it come to passe that who so euer wil
<pb facs="5"/> folowe Christ and hys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and forsake euyl in his lyfe &amp; conuersation, he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spysed &amp; hated of the world, &amp; also mocked &amp; iested vpon. But the disciple is not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his master, nether the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte aboue hys lorde, for yf they haue called the good man of the housholde Belza<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bub, how moche more shall they cal thē of hys houshold so.<note place="margin">Yf I were a fleshelye felowe &amp; a preacher of lyes &amp; tolde them that they myght syt bybbing &amp; bollynge &amp; be dronkē, o that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete for thys peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Mich. ii. c</note> O Lord why doo men so moch mocke vs, &amp; scorne vs, for wel doyng, surely I can not tell, except it be for thys cause, that they be nothinge mynded to folowe christ thē selues, for yf they were, they wolde not do so.</p>
   <p>O Lord wher to is thys worlde come, for lyke as we had neade in tymes paste to
<pb facs="5"/> haue soch an Apostle as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly S. Paule was, to rebuke the vayne cōfydence that mē dyd put in theyr worckes, &amp; to tell vs that no worke of our doyng, but fayth of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des workinge, doeth iustifie vs in hys syght.</p>
   <p>Euen so now, we had no lesse nede of soch an Apostle as was holye S. Iames, to rebuke thys horrible vnthā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefulnes of men, that profes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>singe them selues to be chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiās, &amp; to holde of Christes old fayth, &amp; are yet dead vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al good worckes, receyue not the word of god in meke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, cast not away al vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse &amp; maliciousnes, but are swyft to speake, to talcke, to iangle, &amp; to take displeasure, and are forgetful hearers of
<pb facs="6"/> thee worde and not lyuers there after boastynge theym selues to bee of gods pure &amp; vndefyled relygyon,<note place="margin">They say that they knowe god, but with theyr dedes they do denye hym. Titu. ii. c</note> and yet refrayne not theyr tongues frō euyl, viset not the poore, the frendlesse and thee deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in theyr trouble, nether kepe them selues vndefyled from thys worlde.</p>
   <p>What an occasyon might soche an apostle (as holy S. Iames was) haue to wryte another, yea a more sharper Epystle, seynge so manye pretendynge to be of Iesus christes olde faythe and rely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyon, and are yet so parcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and haue soche a carnall respecte of persons, are not ryche in faythe, but despyse thee poore, practyse not thee lawe of godly loue, talcke &amp;
<pb facs="6"/> Iangle of faythe not hauin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the worckes therof, cloth not thee naked, helpe not the poore too theyr ryghte, nor regarde not theyr necessyte, haue but a deade faythe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare not by good and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worckes the true and olde faythe of Christ, and are but vayne beleuers, haue not the effections workyng &amp; lyuing fayth that Abraham had.</p>
   <p>Howe wold holy Saynt Iames reproue these bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers vp of straunge doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; false opynyons, these blasphemers, backbyters, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyers of good men, false tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of goddes trueth, dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblers wyth the same, ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye fyre (as they saye) wythe one hande, and water in the other, pretēding to be lerned
<pb facs="7"/> and yet bryng not forthe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> worckes of good conuers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion in mekenes out of god wysdome, but in froward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, and oute of carnal doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne, are churlysshe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vneasye to be intreated.</p>
   <p>Wherefore moste dear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Readers, who so euer of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hathe bene slacke to folowe thee good lyfe and Godlye conuersatyon that Sayncte Iames (and all thee holye scrypture besydes) requyreth to bee in theym whyche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse thee holye relygyon of oure sauyoure Christe, lette hym nowe take better hold, turne agayne to thee truth, And folowe that louynge exhortacyon whyche holye S. Iames makethe in thee latter ende of hys Epystle,<note place="margin">Iame. v. b</note>
      <pb facs="7"/> and lette vs that haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed thee holye relygyon of Chryste in dede (not onelye bee contente too abyde anye storme or trouble for it, or to bee mocked, scorned, and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>secuted, yea and put to death therfore, yf it so please god) but also euerye one of vs to hys power, in hys harte by feruent prayer, in his mouth by good woordes, and in all hys bodye by vertuous conuersacyō and good Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>styan workes, helpe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure that thee blessed word of god, maye haue thee due honoure belongynge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and that the same whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it hathe loste thorowe the vngodly behauiour of so me, may thorowe thee grace and goodnesse of God bee
<pb facs="8"/> wonne agayne in oure goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lyuing, that god maye hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of vs better seruauntes, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Prince true subiectes, &amp; ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> neyghbours more vnfayned louers, then many haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> before vs.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>