<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The principal matters handled in the Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4697_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02915</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13056</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4697</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The principal matters handled in the Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A shorte declaration of the mistery of iniquity</title>
                 <author>Helwys, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 212 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The principal matters handled in the Booke.</head>
   <p>A Declaration vvith proofe, that these are the days, of greatest tribulation, spokē of by Christ. Mat. 24. vvherein the abhominatiō, of desolatiō is seene to be set in the holy place.</p>
   <p>That there hath bene a generall departing from the faith, and an vtter desolation of all true Religion.</p>
   <p>That the Prophesie of the first Beast. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 13. is fulfilled vnder the Romish spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall povver and Gouerment.</p>
   <p>That the Prophesie of the Second Beast is fulfilled vnder the spirituall povver &amp; Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Arch-Bishops &amp; lord Bishops.</p>
   <p>Hovv Kings shal hate the vvhore, &amp; make hir desolate.</p>
   <p>VVhat Great Povver and authority: vvhat honor, names &amp; titles God hath given to the King.</p>
   <p>That God hath givē vnto the K. an earthly kingdome vvith all earthly povver against the vvhich, none may resist but must in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges obey, vvillingly, either to do, or suffer.</p>
   <p>That Christ alone is K. of Israell, &amp; sitts vpon Davids Throne, &amp; that the K. ought to be a subiect of his Kingdome.</p>
   <p>That none ought to be punished either
<pb facs="6"/> vvith death or bonds for transgressing against the spirituall ordināces of the nevv Testamēt, and that such Offences ought to be punished onely vvith spirituall svvord and censures.</p>
   <p>That as the Romish Hyrarchy say in vvords they cannot err: so the Hyrarchy of Arch-Bs. &amp; lord Bs. shevve by their deeds, they hold they cannot err: &amp; herein they agree in one.</p>
   <p>The false professiō of Puritan-isme (so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) &amp; the false Prophet is thereof discovered.</p>
   <p>Their tvvo deceitfull excuses for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoeing of all those thinges, they cry out against, made manifest.</p>
   <p>The false professiō of Brovvnisme (so called) plainely laid open vvith their false Prophetts, and vvith their false supposed seperatiō from the vvorld.</p>
   <p>The vanity of their most deceitfull distinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betvvixt a false Church, and no Church (vvherevpon their vvhole false building stands) made evident.</p>
   <p>Some perticuler errors in Mr. Robinsons booke of iustification of Separatiō, laid open.</p>
   <p>That no mā iustifying anie false vvay, or anie one error, though of ignorance, can be saved.</p>
   <p>The perverting of those vvords of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Christ Mat. 10. vvhen they persecute you in one Citie, flee into another, contrary to all the meaning of Christ plainly shevved.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>