<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, RO∣BERT EARLE OF SALISBVRY, KNIGHT OF THE MOST HONORA∣BLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, VIS∣count Cranborne, Lord Cecill of Esingdon, Lord high Treasurer of England, &amp;c. Maister of his Ma∣iesties court of Wards and Liueries, Chan∣cellor of the Vniuersity of Cambridge, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable priuy Councell.</title>
           <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4706_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03647</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13776</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4706</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, RO∣BERT EARLE OF SALISBVRY, KNIGHT OF THE MOST HONORA∣BLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, VIS∣count Cranborne, Lord Cecill of Esingdon, Lord high Treasurer of England, &amp;c. Maister of his Ma∣iesties court of Wards and Liueries, Chan∣cellor of the Vniuersity of Cambridge, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable priuy Councell.</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Baculum geodæticum, sive viaticum. Or The geodeticall staffe : containing eight bookes: the contents whereof followe after the epistles. Newly deuised, practised, and published by Arthur Hopton gentleman</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur, 1587 or 8-1614</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 75, 1, 81-112, 109-347, that is 374, 10 pages, 1 folded plates, 3 folded tables, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT EARLE OF SALISBVRY, KNIGHT OF THE MOST HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, VIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Cranborne, Lord Cecill of Esingdon, Lord high Treasurer of England, &amp;c. Maister of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties court of Wards and Liueries, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the Vniuersity of Cambridge, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable priuy Councell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man right Honorable, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a precious stone, bearing the splendor of any rich mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garite, but straight hasteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the best lapidiste, whose happy allowance thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth a rare affectation, and inestimable valew of the gem: so standeth it with your Honour, the curious Lapidiste of our most excellent wits, to whose touch euery refined tong offereth the quintessence of his best inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And therefore some, whose industries haue laboured in the treasury of Diuinity, some in the necessity of humanity, some in the delectation of
<pb facs="3"/>the Politicks, some in the affectation of the Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomicks, some in Philosophy, others in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry, haue all brought the depth of their golden studies, to bide the touch of your noble allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: so that after-ages may rightly admire what noble Mecoenas it was that so inchayned the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring wits of this vnderstanding age to his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly censure, which will not a little magnoperate the splendor of your well knowne Honour, to these succeeding times. Which seeing, &amp; hauing found this sparke of the Mathematicks, neuer yet seene before, am bold to craue your noble appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, that it may goe (though vnworthy) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the rest of those worthy Iewels, that alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy haue past the proofe of your singular iudgmet: So shall we haue great hope, that the radiant beames of your resplendent wisdome, fauorably shining a little hereon, in short time wil reuiue the Mathematicks (the Phoenix of Arts) from the ashes of obliuion, that they may sit in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome amongst the sweet inuentions of the age, and in our owne language sing forth the eternall glory of learning, as well as in other nations it doth. Euery Muse (noble patron of vertue) hath long since found a double-topped Pernassus in England to solace vpon, saue onely Vrania; euery Muse hath her delicious Helicon to sport in, saue only Vrania; euery muse hath sipt of the sweet Nectar, saue onely Vrania. Erato hath wonne a
<pb facs="3"/>crowne, Vrania wants a garland: then let me hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly implore your Honour, graciously to protect the fruits of this estranged Muse vnder the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the sweete branches of your neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying glory, which is all-sufficient to infatuate and annihilate each viperous malediction of the enuious Pierides. I know there be bookes extant treating of the art of measuring ground of, which a part of this booke also consisteth; but they be lame and defectiue, euen as a number of our sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyors be, that thrust themselues into businesses without ability to performe: wherefore I haue endeauored (my good Lord) as well to redresse wants in the one, as replenish art in the other, not doubting (seeing it becomes so requisite &amp; neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary a faculty) but to make the serious student a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereby to benefite his country and common wealth very much.</p>
   <p>Lastly (to cease troubling your Honour) if the dedication of bookes in any part may giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement to great men for peculiar fauors and many singular graces shewen, then doth du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bind me obsequiously to remunerate your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable fathers respect of our name and poore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to whom my ancestors were, (and of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary consequence, my selfe to your Honour am) euer obliged. And vpon that foundation I builded the hopes of this presumption, which if it proue firme, shall animate me hereafter, to
<pb facs="4"/>aime to reach in some higher straine the Diates<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saron of your memorable vertues. Thus in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice at command, in duty bound, and in prayer continuall to the Almighty for your good Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, I end, resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>In all humble duty at your Honours commaund, ARTHVR HOPTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>