<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THOMAS NEWTON TO THE Reader, in the behalfe of this booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4704_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03327</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13447</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4704</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THOMAS NEWTON TO THE Reader, in the behalfe of this booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Falles of vnfortunate princes : being a true chronicle historie of the vntimely death of such vnfortunate princes and men of note as haue happened since the first entrance of Brute into this iland vntill this our latter age : whereunto is added the famous life and deat of Queene Elizabeth, with a declaration of all the warres, battels and sea-fights, wherein at large is described the battell of 88 with the particular seruice of all such ships and men of note in that action</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Aspley, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 547+ pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THOMAS NEWTON TO THE Reader, in the behalfe of this</hi> booke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S when an arming sword of proofe is made,</l>
      <l>Both steele and iron must be tempred well:</l>
      <l>(For iron giues the strength vnto the blade,</l>
      <l>And steele, in edge doth cause it to excell)</l>
      <l>As each good Blade-smith by his Art can tell:</l>
      <l>For, without iron, brittle will it breake,</l>
      <l>And without steele, it will be blunt and weake:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>So bookes, that now their faces dare to show,</l>
      <l>Must mettald be with nature and with skill:</l>
      <l>For nature causeth stuffe enough to flow,</l>
      <l>And Art the same contriues by learned quill</l>
      <l>In order good, and currant method still.</l>
      <l>So that, if Nature frowne, the case is hard:</l>
      <l>And if Art want, the matter all is mar'd.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The worke, which heere is offred to thy view,</l>
      <l>With both these points is full and fitly fraught;</l>
      <l>Set forth by sundrie of the learned Crew:</l>
      <l>Whose stately stiles haue <hi>Phoebus</hi> garland caught,</l>
      <l>And Parnasse mount their worthy worke haue raught:</l>
      <l>Their words are thundred with such maiestie,</l>
      <l>As fitteth right each matter in degree.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Reade it therefore, but reade attentiuely,</l>
      <l>Consider well the drift whereto it tends:</l>
      <l>Confer the times, perpend the history,</l>
      <l>The parties states, and eke their dolefull ends,</l>
      <l>With odde euents, that diuine iustice sends.</l>
      <l>For things forepast are presidents to vs,</l>
      <l>Whereby we may things present now discusse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Certes this world a Stage may well be call'd,</l>
      <l>Whereon is plai'd the part of eu'ry wight:</l>
      <l>Some, now aloft, anon with malice gal'd,</l>
      <l>Are from high state brought into dismall plight.</l>
      <l>Like counters are they, which stand now in sight</l>
      <l>For thousand or ten thousand, and anone</l>
      <l>Remoued, stand perhaps for lesse then one.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Newtonus,
Cestreshyrius.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>