<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>N., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4704_Bo1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03327</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13447</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4704</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>N., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Falles of vnfortunate princes : being a true chronicle historie of the vntimely death of such vnfortunate princes and men of note as haue happened since the first entrance of Brute into this iland vntill this our latter age : whereunto is added the famous life and deat of Queene Elizabeth, with a declaration of all the warres, battels and sea-fights, wherein at large is described the battell of 88 with the particular seruice of all such ships and men of note in that action</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Aspley, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 547+ pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="253" facs="136"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing hitherto continued the storie (gentle Reader) from the first entrance of <hi>Brute</hi> into this Iland, with the falles of such Princes, as were neuer before this time in one volume comprised, I now proceed with the rest, which take their beginning from the Conquest, whose pen-men being many and diuers, all diuerslie affected in the method of this their Mirror, I purpose only to follow the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded scope of that most honorable personage, who, by how much he did surpasse the rest in the eminence of his noble condition, by so much he hath exceeded them all in the excellencie of his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall stile, which with a golden pen he hath limmed out to poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in that worthy obiect of his minde, the Tragedie of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and in his preface then intituled Master <hi>Sackuils</hi> induction. This worthie President of learning, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to perfect all this storie himselfe from the Conquest, being called to a more serious expence of his time in the great State-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of his most royall Ladie and Soueraigne, left the dispose thereof to M. <hi>Baldwine,</hi> M. <hi>Ferrers</hi> and others, the composers of these Tragedies, who continuing their methode which was by way of dialogue or interlocution betwixt euery Tragedie, gaue it onely place before the Duke of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> complaint, which order I since hauing altered, haue placed the Induction in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, with euery Tragedie following according to succession and the iust computation of time, which before was not obserued; and lest any one thinke me enuious of others deserts, I haue sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed
<pb n="254" facs="137"/>
the names of all such as I could heare of, vnder such Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies as each one particularlie hath written; which at the request of the Printer, I haue briefely perused as the former. In which (friendly Reader) if I haue done amisse, I craue pardon for my ouersight, hoping if paines will in stead of penance pacifie thee, to yeeld thee satisfaction and content in my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions following, to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>