<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>R., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4728_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14894.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4728</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trades increase</title>
                 <author>Kayll, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I commend vnto you a <hi>Polidorus</hi> his Treasure; yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either murther or theft, but else as rich. So I confesse without leaue, neither may the Authour bee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if what I haue borrowed for my priuate vse, I haue payed to the seruice of the Common-wealth, in that what hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended at the instance of one, being written, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houefull o euery one.</p>
   <p>One <hi>Pithius,</hi> a crafty Sicilian, finding an honest Romane Gentleman, called <hi>Canius,</hi> Desirous of a pleasant Garden in the Iland, he inuited him to his; and conducted diuers poore Fishermen to attend that day his Bankes, with Boates and Nets; and to bring in plenty of fish, and to lay them at his feete. The Guest asking what that meant, was answered by the Hux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That it was the Royalty of that place, there was more fish thereabouts, then in any other streame of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuse. And as oft as he repaired thither, that seruice was due, and done vnto him. The poore Gentleman was taken with the Nets, and presently dealeth with the owner for the Garden, who suffering himselfe to be much improtuned, at the length was intreated to sell it full deerely: The day following, the buyer, dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="3"/>to shew the magnificence of his purchase, inuiteth diuers friends to accompany him thither, and missing the concourse and confluence of his expected homagers, the Fishermen <hi>(For there was neither Boate, Oare, Net, or Fin of fish to be seene)</hi> asketh his new neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours whether it were a holiday for Fishermen? The plaine folk answered, <hi>None they knew of;</hi> &amp; further wondred at the former resort, for they neuer saw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Boates or Fishermen there. In a word, hee was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sened. But it is not so in this fishing Proiect, to the which you are now inuited frankely and plainely: <hi>Nullae hic piscatorum ferae;</hi> we may alwaies fish here without feare of any <hi>Sicilian</hi> purchase, or scarcity of the Romane <hi>Macrobius</hi> his Table, where there was <hi>Piscis,</hi> but <hi>paucorū hominum.</hi> Here is fish, the King of fish, the meate and Marchandize of both remote and neighbour Nations. To perswade hereto, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour hath dealt by way of comparison, not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to derogate from other <hi>Trades,</hi> but to aduance this Mysterie, and indeed, to shew that they may all receiue true nourishment from this nursery. Let therefore no man take that with the left hand which is offered with the right. And though, by the opinion of some of vnderstanding in those faculties, there is a reasonable suruey giuen of our <hi>Sea-trades, State,</hi> and <hi>Breeding;</hi> and out of others iudgements, there is euen <hi>Candor animi</hi> in all particulars, without either suspicion of any personall taxation offered, or any States blot sus-spected: Yet I desire also to professe the Authours true and faire meaning herein, and to make good the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sights that may bee committed in the particular tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse, with that of the Poet, <hi>Vbi plurima nitent, Non
<pb facs="3"/>ego paucis offendor maculis.</hi> Of the subiect it selfe I will onely say thus much, That if <hi>Aurum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> hath beene alwaies welcome, hence you may receiue gold, pay the Kings duties, and doe your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey seruice; and so I leaue these businesses to their own abilities, and take my leaue of you with this conclusion of them.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Nisi peracta luduntur.</hi> I. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>