<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND HIS SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, the Lord Clyfton, Baron of Layton.</title>
           <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4777_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06950</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17376.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4777</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND HIS SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, the Lord Clyfton, Baron of Layton.</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Markhams maister-peece. Or, What doth a horse-man lacke : Containing all possible knowledge whatsoeuer which doth belong to any smith, farrier or horse-leech, touching the curing of all maner of diseases or sorrances in horses; drawne with great paine and most approued experience from the publique practise of all the forraine horse-marshals of Christendome, and from the priuate practise of all the best farriers of this kingdome. Being deuided into two bookes. The first containing all cures physicall. The second whatsoeuer belongeth to chirurgerie, with an addition of 130 most principall chapters, and 340 most excellent medicines, receits and secrets worthy euery mans knowledge, neuer written of, nor mentioned in any author before whatsoeuer. Together with the true nature, vse, and qualitie of euerie simple spoken of through the whole worke. Reade me, practise me, and admire me. Written by Geruase Markham gentleman</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 500, that is 510+ pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND HIS SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, the Lord Clyfton, Baron of Layton.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the tribute of poore mens labours (Right Honourable, and my most best Lord) be the al-witnesses of our most seruiceable loues: then I hope mine which comes to kisse your hand, will protest and vowe for me, that my zeale and duty towards you and your house, hath no date but in my last breath. And al be this worke, which hath beene my many yeares experience (for the rude and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med collection) may seeme too hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="3"/>
for your support: yet in as much as I know both your owne excellent and well approued knowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dge in the same art (and so best able to iudge either of my worth or vanitie) and your most noble affection to men of any vertue, I dare with better bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse present you with this my last sacrifice of writing, beseeching you in it to behold not only how my time is imployed, but how infinit my lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging is to bee numbred onely your creature.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors in all humble</hi> duty to command, Geruase Markham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>