<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Translator to the cap∣tious sort of Sycophants.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S478964_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08630</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18940</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S478964</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Translator to the cap∣tious sort of Sycophants.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The heroycall epistles of the learned poet Publius Ouidius Naso : in Englishe verse: set out and translated by George Turberuile Gent. with Aulus Sabinus aunsweres to certaine of the same</title>
                 <author>Ovid</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 161, 3 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="172"/>
   <pb facs="172"/>
   <head>¶ The Translator to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious sort of Sycophants.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe Ploughman hopes in recompence of toyle.</l>
      <l>And winters trauaile past, to reape the graine</l>
      <l>That he (goodman) hath sowen on his soyle,</l>
      <l>Wyth great encrease of crop and goodly gaine:</l>
      <l>And reason good why so he should in deede,</l>
      <l>For he thereon long earst bestowde his seede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The fearefull Fisherman that castes his Nette</l>
      <l>In hauen mouth, and layes his bayted hookes,</l>
      <l>Doth trust at length by happie hap to get</l>
      <l>Such store of fishe as may suffice the Cookes,</l>
      <l>And Caters eke, and bring him in the mucke</l>
      <l>That ventred life in hope of happie lucke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If Ploughman then and Fisher gape for gaynes,</l>
      <l>And hope assuredly to haue the same,</l>
      <l>To quite there troublous toyles, and dayly paynes</l>
      <l>Endurde ere they could bring their feates to frame:</l>
      <l>why should not such as climbe the craggie Mount</l>
      <l>Where Muses wonne, of earned hyre account?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And looke for laude at least at learned handes,</l>
      <l>That knowe the cares of vndertaken woorkes,</l>
      <l>And wote full well how hie Pernasus standes</l>
      <l>With stately steppes, where Poetes Lawrell lurkes:</l>
      <l>A haughtie hill that euerie wight must clime</l>
      <l>Ere he attaine with Poets pen to rime.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For though the thing but slender be in sight,</l>
      <l>And vaine to vewe of curious carping skull,</l>
      <pb facs="173"/>
      <l>In mother tongue a forraine speach to write:</l>
      <l>Yet he shall finde he hath a Crow to pull,</l>
      <l>That vndertakes with well agreeing File</l>
      <l>Of English verse, to rub the Romaine stile.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Deuises of the language diuers are,</l>
      <l>Well couched wordes, and feately forged phrase,</l>
      <l>Eche string in tune, no ragged ryme doth iarre,</l>
      <l>With figures fraught their bookes in euery place:</l>
      <l>So that it is a worke of prayse to cause</l>
      <l>A Romaine borne to speake with English iawes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which laude I leaue, and prayse to paynefull men</l>
      <l>That haue with nightly sweate of busie browe</l>
      <l>Set out their workes of fame with forwarde pen:</l>
      <l>For this my Muse I would accoumpt ynowe</l>
      <l>To scape the spitefull Zoyles chiding chaps,</l>
      <l>That (like a Curre) eche willing writer snaps.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>So I might go vntoucht of Momus traine,</l>
      <l>And neuer feele the force of enuious Hate,</l>
      <l>Sufficed me, well quitted were my payne,</l>
      <l>I might be thought a man of luckie fate.</l>
      <l>But, oh, it can not be, the best of all</l>
      <l>(That Homer hight) to nipping nayles was thrall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But let those Snakes, and beastly Vipers broode</l>
      <l>(I meane the spitefull Spider, Momus mate)</l>
      <l>When they haue done, recoumpt their gotten good,</l>
      <l>They gaine ywis but scorne and lothsome hate:</l>
      <l>Wherefore departe the racke thou Curre (I say)</l>
      <l>And let the lustie Courser champe the hay.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If thou thy selfe for kimpish idle life</l>
      <l>No leysure hast to take in hande the like,</l>
      <pb facs="173"/>
      <l>But kepste thy Couch: put vp that cankred knife</l>
      <l>Wherewith thou wonted art the good to strike:</l>
      <l>Let other presse in place to purchase fame,</l>
      <l>For vertues sake that woorke to winne a name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Discerne their deedes, when all their toyle is donne,</l>
      <l>Say thou thy worst, when they haue done their best:</l>
      <l>Condemne them not or ere thou hast begonne</l>
      <l>To vewe their workes, but ouerreade the rest:</l>
      <l>That done, let eche sustaine his earned meede,</l>
      <l>This were the way to purchase loue in deede.</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="174"/>
   <pb facs="174"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>