<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument of the Treatise following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4792_Fr3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07828</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18200.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4792</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument of the Treatise following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two treatises concerning regeneration, 1. Of repentance, 2. Of the diet of the soule : shewing, the one, how it ought to be sought after, and may be attained vnto. The other, how it being gotten, is to be preserued and continued</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas, of Berwick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 104, 8, 119, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="61"/>
   <head>The Argument of the Treatise following.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is not sufficient for the good estate of mans bodie that it be brought into the world, in the naturall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>on of it, which consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in the equall tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and iust proportion of the seueral parts of it, for that it being left here, would soone perish and come to noug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t: and therefore it must of necessitie be continually both nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished with meate and drinke, and also pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued from all hurtfull things, yea careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly restored to the former state of health, if by any inward or outward meanes it fall into sicknesse, or bee any way hurt, wounded, or distempered: no more will it serue for the good estate of the soule, that it be both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by repentance for regeneration, yea


<pb facs="62"/>
actually regenerated by the spirite of God: but it likewise must continually be tended, fed, and cherished, yea healed of all those ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies which by any meanes happen vnto it. This we call the right dieting of the soule, resembling the soule to the bodie, that both the doctrine may be plaine and easie, being illustrated &amp; declared by sensible &amp; fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar similitudes, and also, that the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all care and paines which we take about our bodies, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e ordering &amp; dieting of them, may alwaies be putting vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> minde of perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the same dutie vnto our soules, for the which we oght to be so much the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as eternall happinesse is better thē this short and miserable life.</p>
   <p>This spirituall diet hath two partes, conseruatiue, and restoratiue, the former continueth and keepeth in the soule that measure of grace and of holinesse, which it hath receiued from God, the other restoreth it when it is lost, and repaireth it being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied. Againe, conseruatiue diet hath two parts, nutritiue and preseruatiue: consisting, the one in the right vse of those things, by


<pb facs="62"/>
the which the soule is nourished, the other in the carefull auoyding of all things, which are hurtfull vnto it: spirituall nourishment consisteth in two t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ings, foode and exercise, whereof the one is the matter, the other the meanes, maner or forme of nutrition.</p>
   <p>Further, we are to consider how the soule hath resemblance to the state of the bodie, and how it being of it selfe simple and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, can be subiect to alterations, distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and diseases, which haue place in the bodie, by reason of the contrarietie of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties preuailing, or yeelding one to another: to wit, that as in the bodie heate and moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, so in the soule, holinesse &amp; sinfulnesse do continually fight togither, the one labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to consume and expell the other, the sinfulnesse of the flesh labouring to quench all the good motions of the spirit, and the spirit striuing to crucifie the flesh, with all the corrupt lusts thereof: Gal. <hi>5.17. The flesh lusteth against the spirit, and the spirite against the flesh: and these are contrary the one to the other.</hi> This is the composition &amp; temperature of the soule,


<pb facs="63"/>
hauing place onely in the state of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein the soule hath in it selfe both holinesse and sinfulnesse: but not in the state of innocencie, or yet since the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> in carnall men: when as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e soule being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither either holy or sinful, cannot be said to haue this composition or temperature.</p>
   <p>These points of doctrine may profitably be considered. But first we are to know, that the paines and care taken in dieting and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the soule, ought to bee continuall without any intermission, for that as the body being neglected for a small time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth weake and distempered, yea soone falleth into sicknesse and doth perish, so is it with the soule, the which being neglected but a litle, there will a decrease of holinesse be plainly felt, yea perhaps seene by others. The reason whereof is manifest: to wit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause both outward occasions and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and also t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e inward corruption of sin, neuer ceaseth from oppugning this holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: and therefore as the bodie must continually be repaired with nouris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ment, because it is continually consumed by our


<pb facs="63"/>
naturall heate, so must the soule by a good diet daily vsed, bee preserued. Thus the scripture doth euery where exhort vs to a continuall vse of all spirituall exercises, as namely of praier, Eph. <hi>6.18. Pray alwaies with all maner of praier and supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the spirit.</hi> And <hi>1.</hi> Thess. <hi>5.16. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce euermore, pray continually:</hi> not as if (as some haue fondly imagined) wee ought to giue our selues so wholly to spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall exercises, as that we neglect our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies &amp; this present life, as most men bestow all their time, care and labour, about their bodies, without any regarde had to their soules. For as God hath giuen vnto vs both bodies and soules, so it is his will that both be carefully preserued, and that both for the maintenance of this present life, we labour daily &amp; diligently in some lawfull calling, &amp; for the preseruing of the life of our souls we vse that spiritual diet which we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to declare. Yet as heauenly, spirituall, and eternall things are farre more excellent and more to be desired then earthly things, so we ought to haue greater care of the one


<pb facs="64"/>
then of the other, and so to frame the course of our life, that we entangle our selues in no mo worldly duties then are needfull. Thus the Apostle counselleth, <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>7.</hi> that the seruant should not neglect any duty which his maister enioyneth him, vnder pretence of seruing God but yet desire a free life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in it he may haue greater opportunitie and leisure to serue God: and like wise, that we should preferre a single life before mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which (vsually) bringeth with it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cares &amp; troubles. According to this rule they whō God hath blessed with riches and abundance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orldly things, ought to giue more time, care and labour to the seruice of God, thē they who are in pouertie, and want things needful: and to say with themselues, soule thou hast goods laide vp for many yeares, and therefore (not take thy ease and make thy selfe drunke with the superfluitie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orldly pleasures) but, take time as much as thou wilt to serue God, and to clense thy selfe from the filthinesse of sin, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the abhominable to God. But vsual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, as it were adding thirst to drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,


<pb facs="64"/>
the more they haue, the more they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to haue, and are more careful in seeking worldly things, then they who are in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test want.</p>
   <p>Besides, it is needful for the right dieting of the soule, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> know and consider the present state or constitution of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hether it be in infācie, or in ripe age, in the increase or decrease of holinesse, in strength or in faintnesse, in temptation or not: that so we may vse that diet which is most cōuenient, in regard of the present state of it. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise we cannot but erre in dieting it, yea euen in the carefull vse of the most holsome meates and soueraigne remedies. For as it is impossible to order the body aright, either in sicknesse or in health, without the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge of our complexion, age and strength, and vnlesse wee marke in what parts it is most weake or strong, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly choyse may be made both of meates in health, and of remedies in sicknesse, so the foundatiō of the right ordering of the soule consisteth in this, that we know our age and strength in Christ, whether we be ripe and


<pb facs="65"/>
strong men, able to digest solide meates, or but babes and weaklings, who must be fedde with milke: and also our infirmities, what sinnes we are most subiect vnto, that so we may auoyd all occasions of them.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>