<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull, and his dearely beloued in Chist, the Officers of the Queenes ma∣iesties Robes T. Paulfreyman, one of hir highnesse honorable Chap, wisheth the encrease of Gods mercy and grace, bothe to them and all theirs.</title>
           <author>Paulfreyman, T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4810_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08849</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19137.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4810</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull, and his dearely beloued in Chist, the Officers of the Queenes ma∣iesties Robes T. Paulfreyman, one of hir highnesse honorable Chap, wisheth the encrease of Gods mercy and grace, bothe to them and all theirs.</title>
                 <author>Paulfreyman, T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A paraphrase vppon the epistle of the holie apostle S. Paule to the Romanes : preserued through grace, and novv commended to the Church of God: wherein is more largely set forth &amp; plainly, the sense or true meaning of the apostle, to the better understanding and edifying of the vertuous and christian reader. Whereunto is also added certaine other workes of the godlie learned (as in the table appeareth) very apte [?] and necessary to be considered of in these dayes, not only amongst the ignorant and unlearned, for their godly [?] counsell and comfort, but also of others in sundrie respectes worthie [?] their well liking, and to further thereby the glorie of God [Seene?] and [allowed?] according to the order [?] appointed [?]</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 96 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right worshipfull, and his dearely beloued in Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ist,</hi> the Officers of the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Robes <hi>T. Paulfreyman,</hi> one of hir highnesse honorable Chap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, wisheth the encrease of Gods mercy and grace, bothe to them and all theirs.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>R. H. H. A. C. S.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T vvhat time (dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) it pleased the iuste and great of heauen, to chaunge by his iustice (for many sins) his cherefull countenaunce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this his Churche of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and to buckle hys bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves very heauily vppon it, to giue therevppon the fearefull frovvnes of hys vnsufferable and fierce furies: to shy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e the moste Chrystian state thereof, to alter therein the moste ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and true Religion, to afflicte vvithin it the professoure of his name, to holde them in moste cruell and bitter bondage, to suffer the burning of his sacred Scriptures (as also other vvorkes very notable and infinite, the trauels doubtlesse of the
<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oste godly, famouse, and great learned men, bothe of thys Countrey and elsevvhere, to the edifying mightily of Chrystes holy Churche) vvith other lyke horrible plagues, svviftely and faste ensuing: euen to the very hazarding and putting to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, the vvhole state of this moste Christian Kingdome, highly renoumed, and noble Region aforesaid: so clerely before lightned vvith the bright lyght of lyfe, so highly of God extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, so tenderly of him beloued, so diuersly blessed, so graciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly gouerned, so mercifully preserued, moste plenteously enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, adorned and beautified, vvith the singular good graces, gyftes, and great benefites of God, most bountifully and freely of him bestovved, and as vnthankfully of vs receiued, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more sharpe punishments therin by his iustice dyd fal, to the piteous amasing, terrifying, turmoyling, vexing, and moste greeuous afflicting bothe of the bodies and soules of men, of all ages, sexes, estates and degrees as their raging cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties then diuersly attempted and moste vvofully felt (vvelnigh vniuersally) vvitnesseth the same: vvhich before vvas truely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied by the good men of God: through vvhose diuine grace as by his trumpe of eternitie, sounded moste shirly foorth hys fatherly admonishments, as forerunners vnto vs for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of daungers, if our hearts then had ben vvarely and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prepared: vvho also them selues (vvith moste constante sayth and pacience) felte in that rage the iudgements of God by true tryall to the deathe, and confirmed their holy and sounde doctrine, euen vvith the effusion of their long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired and greedily thirsted bloude. In those dolefull dayes I say, it vvas my happe to attayne at a frendes hande, certayne vvritten copies of dyuers and sundry matters, that vvere, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many others in great number, fastened in their bandes, prepared before to the spoyle, and had their iudgemente to burne, although by Gods prouidence preuented to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and are novv by hys grace framed in their tyme, I trust to good purpose, as shall aptely to good menne appeare, and that not affectionately laboured I protest, or corruptly, but as beste beseemed a Christian frende sincerely and truely by good direction, according to the analogie and true sense of
<pb facs="5"/> the holy scriptures or vvoorde of God, and to further therevvith (as small povver hathe offered) his moste vvoorthie praise and glorie. Vnto vvhich moste happie ende, vvhen I had once passed them throughe, vvell vievved them, estemed the effecte of their matter, and perceiued yet vvith deliberation, their apparante rudenesse and great imperfection: especially, the Paraphrase vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Epistle of Saincte Paule to the Romaines: hovve vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvereably to the good grounde thereof it vvas left (by vvhome, or by vvhat meanes I knovve not) very barely and confusedly handled, in no poynte perfected, no order obserued, voide of good stile, euell Englished, and vvithoute the true rule or apte fourme of vvryting: I therefore finding good occasion, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming (vvith reuerence) vppon the vertue and pacience, of the learned and Christen reader (vnto vvhome I most gladly submit my selfe, and vvhose good fauoure heerein I moste humbly craue and desire) thought it not amisse (at times cōuenient, and as God vvould permit) for mine ovvne recreation, and for the auoiding also of other more vnprofitable exercises, to bestovve freely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them my diligence and simple trauel, and vvith earnest zeale so to pulishe them, as by their amiablenesse, invvarde beautie, and moste pearcing clerenes, they might dravv faste vnto them, the louely and moste Christian delightes of others. And vvhen I had (by the grace of God) accomplished therein my glad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and aftervvardes (as of duetie) commended them to the examination and iudgement of the moste godly learned, and so by order to passe from them vnto the Churche of God: I then deuised vvith my selfe, vvhere, or to vvhom (among many my friendes,) I mighte dispose these vvorkes, to their vvell lyking and friendely acceptation. And as (by the good vvyll of God) I had you (righte dearely beloued) firste in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, vvith vvhom also I thoughte I myghte bee bolde, and vvayed therevvith your vnfaygned profession to GOD, your constant zeale, and good conuersation in Christ: and hovv also by your meanes, vvorthy estimation, and christian good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, it might prosperously and very vvell passe foorth to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracement of others, and to further thereby the glory of God,
<pb facs="6"/> I refused then to reuoke, or to giue you vnkindely the slippe: but yeelded to the firste motion vvith moste glad consent, and doe novve as gladly vvith humblenesse, commend them togither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all your louing handes. Beseeching you all so to take in good par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, this my poore and slender gifte (in this vvise ordered and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vnto you) as you shall occasion me hereafter, the more to reioyce in your frendship, and to pray most hartely for you, that God may still graunt you the good conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his grace, for your helth, vvealth, and prosperitie bothe of body and soule in this life, and thence forthe (in Christe) the revvarde of eternall felicitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Youres to commaunde,</hi> T. Paulfreyman.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>