<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, desi∣rouse to know and to vnderstand the truth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4897_Fr2_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11927</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22241.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, desi∣rouse to know and to vnderstand the truth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three partes of Commentaries : containing the whole and perfect discourse of the ciuill warres of Fraunce, vnder the raignes of Henry the second, Frances the second, and of Charles the ninth. with [sic] an addition of the cruell murther of the Admirall Chastilion, and diuers other nobles, committed the 24. daye of August. Anno. 1572. Translated out of Latine into English by Thomas Timme minister. Seen and allowed</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Coldock (Coldoke), Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 271, 16, 267, 13, 160, 8, 161-306, 491-494 pages, 38 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="152"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse to know and to vnderstand the truth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T were to long, and peraduēture to loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some a thing vnto thee (Christian Reader) for vs to make rehearsall of those things which not vnaptly came to my minde at the writing out of these Tables of Commentaries: And although they should not be vtterly besides the purpose of this present Argument, yet if in so small a worke, I should wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into any long circuit of preface, I see it might bee obiected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that I pretende one thing and do another, which is a thing woorthy reprehention: as Horas in his verse noteth:</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Currente rota cur vrceus exit▪ <hi>that is,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The porter purposed to make a wyne measure,</l>
      <l>But in tourning of the wheele, is proued a water pitcher:</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Therefore, I will let them passe, if you be at leysure, and may vouchsafe to reade these fewe thinges. For nowe I haue here for thee (Gentle Reader) breefe Commentaries of the whole Ciuill warres of Fraunce, wherein I haue followed the order &amp; course of the matters rehearsed by vs in the former three bookes of Com mentaries. And if I shall begin to excuse my selfe, first for that I being a man euen without name, haue enterprised to begin the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie of so waighty matters, which had ben a fit Argument for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned writers: I see that strayght way, that may be obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me, which was obiected to <hi>Albinus</hi> the Romane, excusinge himself and asking pardon for writing a history in the Greke tong, wherein he was not very skilfull, (to wit) that he had rather aske pardon for his faulte, than to be without fault. But beit that I am in a faulte, whether it be rash nesse or temeritie (for I know that this my enterprise shall incurre the iudgements of diuers men) yet I truste, I shall not be accused of rashnesse before they haue red me, except it be of such, as by giuing their verdict of an vncertayne and vnknown matter, may be accused of temerity themselues. And as for the iudgement of those learned &amp; moderate men, which shall reade these our Commentaries, I do not greatly feare it, neyther will I thinke my labour wast, but rather count it for an excellent gayne vnlooked for, if I shall prouoke them to set them forth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the vtilitie of other mē. But least I should stay lōger thā I promised, in the defence of this extēporall writing, not lyke to liue aboue a day, lacking his <hi>Genius,</hi> I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>l only sai thus much: that if I haue offended for thy sake (gētle reader) I haue offended, that thou mightest not be destitute altogither of the discourse &amp; rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall of so great matters committed in Fraunce, for religions sake: And surely if euer any thing heretofore, or in our tyme were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be put in writing, these are worthy of the same: neither do I doubt but that thou shalt receyue frute by reading them.</p>
   <p>Here then thou mayst behold how many wayes God doth go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne and preserue his church, among the manifolde chaunges of
<pb facs="152"/>
worldly businesse: and how maruelously he prouideth entertainment for them in the seates of Monarches. The Gospell being spred abroad and planted in Germany, Switserland, England, &amp; in other places, France remained vtterly without so great a benefite, established by publique au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Magistrates. But it is a most delightsome thing to call to mynd by what meanes God did bring the gospel into France, &amp; by what maner of men, and how mightely God did work by weake vessels. For first the foundacion being layd by the helpe of poore men, which suffered sclaunder, proscriptiō, stripes, torments, burning, &amp; euery kind of slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at the length also when it pleased him, he ioyned vnto this Churche, men of greater account &amp; fame, euen noble men, Peeres, &amp; Princes: and those great difficulties, which could not but hinder the course of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, he toke away, &amp; layed open a broad entrance, to the propagation and enlarging of the same, that he might make it known, how far his power reacheth and extendeth it self to the preseruation of his Church, and that the same is contayned within no limites. The cace was so greatly chaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that whereas before the maliciouse enemies of the church, had the chief rule, and the authoritie of the Magistrates was armed against the same: now contraywyse, those maliciouse enemies were so restrayned &amp; holden vnder, that thei seemed to be brought on their kneese, the fame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of those matters were brought vnto them which fauoured the gospell, &amp; seemed to haue a speciall care to spread &amp; plant the same. But the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fell out far otherwyse: for he which seemed to haue most abilitie to promote &amp; further the cause of the gospeil, reiected the gospel &amp; became an vtter enemie to the same: so that he seemed most of al men to haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a wyde window to the ruyne therof. But how trimly did the Lorde disapoint Sathan &amp; Antichrist of their purpose: yet did he alwayes so mo derate the matter, that neither the church when it was expedient, might seeme to want mans help, neither might seeme wholy to be stayed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon. Greeuouse warres arose: God gaue vnto his seruants strong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of mans helpe, yet least they should depend thervpon, he weakned the same also, &amp; that so greatly, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> great daungers in diuers places ensued to the church, notwithstanding the end fell out for their safety.</p>
   <p>In the middest therefore of these confusions &amp; tumultes, God himselfe the Prince of Princes, shewed his singular prouidence &amp; care which hee hath effectually towardes mankind: but especially &amp; peculiarly, towards his church, to preserue and stablish the same mightely in the iniddest of al worldly troubles: neither by one meanes only, bnt by sundry meanes, as it hath seemed good to him in the diuers formes of rule &amp; gouernment, to assigne vnto his church an abyding place: as of old time in the gouerning of the primitiue Church immediatly after the Apostels, and in our tyme in Germany, Switserland, England, Scotland, and in other places, it hath appeared: and more of late in these our countrey of Fraunce, is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently seene: not that in this varietie we should ascribe any thing to the rule of fortune, but that the manifold and maruailouse efficacy of the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, might be considered, which doth singularly wateh ouer the safety of the Church. And if it may please thee to consider the second &amp; middell causes and reasons of the Instruments, which God vsed in the beginning of this worke; you shall see how cōtrary they be, and how va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable: On the one side the wicked and vnbridled iustes of men proue to
<pb facs="153"/>
worke mischief, doo appeare: a colour of religion is pretended to worke the ouerthrowe of Religion: the kinges name is vsurped when they go about to suppresse the King himself: and in the meane time, the gospeil is accused as a common enemy, and the subuersion of the same is conspy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. On y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> other side, God styrreth vp many men to preserue &amp; defend his church in those troubles, because the destruction of the same was chiefly desired. Ther appeareth in those mē as the history plainly sheweth, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of the safety of the church, of the Kings dignitie &amp; authoritie, &amp; of the publique peace: and yet in the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ution of that their laudable desire, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that they were not vtterly faultlesse. yet is the Church preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the middest of all these misorders: that as it is manifest, that men cannot be sayd to be the very authors &amp; keepers therof, so must we nedes confesse that God is the very author, preseruer, and keeper of the same. Therfore, the church doth not triumphe as hauing gotten the victory by mans ayde, neither doth it lye vtterly prostrat by the violence of worldly tumultes: which being fashoned like vnto her head, raigning in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> enemies, doth so stryue in continual conflictes in this world, because she certainly knoweth that the heauenly Iudge, hath prouided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> time when they shall fully triumph. The church hath heretofore ben ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised in many battails, &amp; how many are behind, God knoweth, bycause the time which is appointed for the last victory is vnknown: yet the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of the heauēly reward is most true, which y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> most valiant Chāpion hath pronounced with his own mouth saying, <hi>That through many tribulations we must enter into the kingdom of heauen.</hi> If the promise of God as touching y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> victory of his church were included within the limites of this world, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely it should triumphe in this world, by the vertue &amp; power of the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent &amp; euerlasting God: but that her triumph is appointed elswher, the often &amp; greuouse spoyles and calamities of the same declare.</p>
   <p>In the meane time let vs consider these things, &amp; contemplate wher &amp; in what partes of the world the tokens of that Catholike &amp; true church do appeare, &amp; let vs aduaunce the prouidence, wisdom, bountifulnes, and power of God in preseruing &amp; gouerning the same, least if the blind igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of men be reprehended, &amp; that worthely, because they see not God, who hath not left himself (as saith the Apost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e) without witnesse in this world: we also be much more worthy of blame, who see not the light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>yes▪ nor the Sunne beames glistering throughout the whole world, neyther do reuerence Iesus Christ diuersely triumphing by the mighty working of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>Truly, gentle reader, this is my counsaill &amp; purpose in writing these Commentaries, to giue thee occasion by preseruing the memory of these things, to contemplate &amp; reuerence the prouidence of God in the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his church, wherof we be members: and that we thereby, while the whole body is assaulted, enduring manfully our own particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts might w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all our mind, long for the reward of the heauenly victory. Moreouer, what soeuer in this litle work (wherin I haue traueled faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) belongeth vnto me, I dedicate the same wholy, liberaly, &amp; frankly to thee Christian Reader, neither shall it greeue mee too beare the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of diuers iudgements, so that thou by reading these s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>iender Cōmen taries, mayest be encouraged, and prepared to reade a iust history.</p>
   <closer>FARE WELL.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>