<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4897_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11927</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22241.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The three partes of Commentaries : containing the whole and perfect discourse of the ciuill warres of Fraunce, vnder the raignes of Henry the second, Frances the second, and of Charles the ninth. with [sic] an addition of the cruell murther of the Admirall Chastilion, and diuers other nobles, committed the 24. daye of August. Anno. 1572. Translated out of Latine into English by Thomas Timme minister. Seen and allowed</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Coldock (Coldoke), Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 271, 16, 267, 13, 160, 8, 161-306, 491-494 pages, 38 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Authors Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat a great businesse and much adoe there was of late yeares for Religion; &amp; that in the Kingdome of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> there is no man but he knoweth▪ yea all men sée the same to be such that it ought with diligence to be Cronicled for euer: and to be sent to the borderers of the vtmost part of the earth for all posterities. But he which hath taken this labour in hand of good will, desireth earnestly that it may generally take effect and turne to the profit of all men. For (so farre as I know) there is nothing extant to be read, but certaine writings which were put forth and set abrode, as the matter required, and certaine Commentaries in the French to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>gue: and if there be any thing, it is so obscurely written that the same of all men can not be vnderstoode.</p>
   <p>And truly there are certaine reasons which stayed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my men of great wisedome and experience in these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from that publique writing. For who, not knowing as yet what would come to passe, dare take vppon him to set foorth openly a whole Tragedie or Comedie, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest daunger to loose his labour, or at the least to séeme to lose it? Furthermore, who séeth not, that it is a thing at this time full of perill, and procuring enuie and displeasure? And beside all this, such laboure at this time séemeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most vnprofitable. For those matters are as yet freshe in memorie, and more sensibly felt of a great manie, than were to be wished, and are noysed abroade by others in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Nations. To conclude, this thing séemeth almost hurt full.</p>
   <p>For when as these controuersies haue ben stirred vp tho rough diuers opinions of religiō, which controuersies burst
<pb facs="4"/>
forth into so great perturbations and troubles, the rehersall now of these thinges, shall not only séeme pernicieus, but also vntimely and out of order. The which also séeme to bée other causes which haue discouraged learned men (who no doubt did diligently note and marke the reasons and falling out of those matters, which wonderfully hapned in these our dayes) from labouring to set forth this history. For either the hast is vnprofitable, or else the vntimely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth ridiculous, of this so spéedie &amp; vnseasonable labor</p>
   <p>Therfore least any man should thinke that it is our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, to write and sette foorthe a iust and true Historie of the state of the Churche of Fraunce: wée giue to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that it is neyther our purpose, nor yet agréeing to the time. Howbeit, hereafter more copions and plentifull woorkes of better learned menne, so soone as the troubles and lettes of these times bée taken awaye, will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade: and will also committe to those that shall come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a perfecte and full memoriall and Chronicle of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
   <p>Let this now bée our beginning and entrance, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine declaration of a greater worke: that we may shewe some part of that large and ample argument: and that we may reduce into these Commentaries a certaine Uiew of the seuerall times of our Churches, both that we may stirre vp such of greater learning and experience, as may happily hereafter take this matter in hand more fully to handle the same: and also that in the meane time wee may giue some fast of the greatest matters to Christian men, desirous to know the truth of this thing, and to men of forreine nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, bewayling our estate and condition.</p>
   <p>And in these thrée first Bookes of our Commentaries, we set forth vnto the reader, the first beginnings of the Church of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> béeing as yet but of tender yeares as it were, and in the fire, or at least wise, euen now by little and little cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of the fire.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Let the causes of the hatred and debate▪ by these very few things be considered, with the which the Bishop of Romes men so outragiously &amp; vniustly are inflamed against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faith full, &amp; against the cause of the faithfull. We must not looke here to haue a description of the faithfull and professours of Christ, in armes, (as our aduersaries doe nowe obiect vnto vs) but rather of the vnarmed &amp; naked members of Christ most cruelly afflicted, onely for this cause, bicause they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the true and pure doctrin of the Gospell now a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before the auncient customes &amp; traditions of men. The naked Church in time past was vexed, and the Gospell dyd run as it were through the sides of poore men, and broughte them to death: then Christians were accoūted as lyers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led heretikes, and by al maner of meanes vexed &amp; oppressed, then were they cast in prisons and in bonds, then were they whipped, then suffered they proscriptions and banishmēts, yea and cruell deathes, without fauour.</p>
   <p>But nowe when it pleased the omnipotent God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynte vnto his Church a more clears and beautiful estate, and to qualifie and quenche those fierce fyres, Sathan not forgetting hys olde subtilties and sleightes, deuiseth a new accusatiō, whispering into the eares of kings, that the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell will plucke their Scepters out of their handes: and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the faithfull throughout the whole kingdom of <hi>France</hi> defende their libertie graunted vnto them by the Kings E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictes, and by all lawfull causes, with force of armes, a new crime is nowe layde to their charge, namely Sedition, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and treason to the king and country: &amp; these crimes are obiected agaynste the godly, by those which (abusing the Kings name and authoritie to exercise their own tirannie) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>éeke moste of all the destruction of the Kings maiestie: and bicause they haue bene let of their purpose by the faithfull, therfore do they spewe out all the poyson of their hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them.</p>
   <p>By these beginnings it shall euidently appéere how obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb facs="5"/>
the Faithful haue bene alwayes to their Princes and Magistrates: that this thing béeyng layde as it were the foundation, it may plainly be séene who they be, which are the true authours of so many troubles as haue flowed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough this whole kingdome.</p>
   <p>God truely hath armed and fortified his Churche at thys daye with many externall helpes and fortresses: yet for all that, the cause is not chaunged: Christe is the selfe same Christe still, the Gospell is not chaunged, but it is the selfe same Gospell, whiche was vnreuerently handled and dealt withall in the persons of the Faithfull, by the sharpe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishementes of the wicked. The Faithfull are the same men still in obeying their Magistrates, and in reuerencing their Princes that they were before. But they are rebells whiche abusing the name and authoritie of Princes, and disloyally violating all Lawe persecute the Churche, go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to extinguish the Gospel, and as if they were Giants, furiously fight with God.</p>
   <p>And by the reading of these Commentaries, the Fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full shall finde many things which they maye applye vnto themselues, to stay and comfort themselues in the middest of these troubles.</p>
   <p>In these lamentable tymes, manye daungers of moste greuous calamities do compasse vs on euery side, many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and newe troubles do dayly burst forth also: But if we consider &amp; weigh the times paste, we shall in very déede haue a gesse nowe, what wil come to passe hereafter in our tyme. For séeing God hath afore time sette and placed hys Churche in a straunge and wonderfull order: We maye gather, that the same God being a perpetuall keper and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of his seruauntes, will applie his power and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to dispatche vs out of these our troubles: the whiche is a most firme and inuincible argument.</p>
   <p>Let vs call to remembrance the thicke mistes and darke cloudes of the former night: let vs sette before oure eyes in
<pb facs="5"/>
what state the Church was in the dayes of <hi>Francis,</hi> the first, <hi>Henry</hi> the second, and <hi>Francis</hi> the second. All thinges were then full of feare. Infinite kindes of punnishmentes, and paynes were layde vppon the Church, as banishmentes, proscriptions, and burninges: Then no man durst so much as name the Gospell, without he would be counted a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest heritike: Fewe men or none, and that of the meaner sort, when they were in their secret corners, durst not once mutter of the Gospell: men coulde not then enioy the libertie of the Gospell, except they woulde willinglye ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe themselues their countrey, and wander into foreine Nations.</p>
   <p>But who will not merueile herevppon at the issue and end of those afflictions? Looke what thinges were then harde of a fewe, did openly ringe in the eares of all men: Looke what things were reiected in some places, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly punished, were publikely receiued of the greatest part of men: yea there were many of the Nobles which sealed that doctrine with their bloud.</p>
   <p>By the deathes of Kyngs, the Gospell had passage, victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie was gotten, Triumphe was made, and within fewe dayes, the Gospell went through the greatest parte of the Kyngdome, by open sermons, by publique Disputations, where most men were assembled together, so that the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell had gotten many and singular witnesses.</p>
   <p>The places which had séene the tormenting fyres and ashes of the Faithfull before, sawe now great assemblies and multitudes of the Faythfull gathered together to heare the worde of God: and the Kynges Edictes which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together made for the hurt and destruction of the faythfull, were at the last, for all that the aduersaries could doe, made to preserue the faithfull.</p>
   <p>To be short, these Commentaries did bring to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce and consideration, such wonderfull and straunge matters (the like wherof wée our selues haue not
<pb facs="6"/>
safely séene) that by the prosperous and happye issue and ende of these perturbations, we oughte to conceyue a sure and vndoubted hope. The matter was then tryed by fyre: but now by force of armes: he which quenched the flamyng fires by the death and destruction of those whiche were fully purposed vtterly to ouerthrow and destroy the Churche, the same Lord of hostes &amp; graund Captain of battailes shall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and order these warres to the libertie and peace of his seruants. Therfore the examples of those things which wer done in time past, do plentifully shew, that whatsoeuer shall happen at the length (which in déede is not to be measured by humane reason) shall fall out for our health and welfare: and that bicause God will not leaue his worke vnperfected. Wherefore I truste it is euident by the consideration of the things which are set foorth in this Booke, what great profite shal come to those whom the boisterous waues of these tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests haue touched. And bicause this is not a priuate matter neither appertaineth to euery one man, but common to the whole Church of God dispersed throughout y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole world, we think also y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the manifest &amp; true knowlege of these thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is loked for of many mē of forein nations, &amp; that the first beginnings of those things in these our Commentaries shal not be read of them without some frute. Neither do we dout but that many when they haue gotten peace and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie after troubles, will behold our miseries, not as thoughe thei themselues were quite out of danger of the like, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moued with the féeling of our afflictions, will truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile our estate. For whose sake also we haue writtē these things in Latin, that they by some means at the least, may be generally vnderstoode of all those which séeke the glorye of God, and the preseruation of his Church▪</p>
   <p>Wherfore we trust if we be accused of rashnes, as though we had vnaduisedly set forth these things which should haue bin deferred till more conuenient and better occasions, wée haue to answere for our selues, and to make vs cleare from that faulte. For if in a matter commendable and deseruing
<pb facs="6"/>
praise, simple and small diligence ought not to be blamed, this may be a iuste defence for vs against learned and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent mē, namely, to wil is sufficiēt in matters of weight. It shal be no reproch or shame to vs at all, that there be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers of a learned &amp; perfect story. But this is the summe of our whole desire, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very truth of those things which were done in Fraunce for religion, might be knowne to all men, as, what is the goodnesse of the cause of the Faithfull and true churches, and what is the iniquitie and iniustice of their aduersaries.</p>
   <p>Let al mē know for a suretie that the Churches of France are not guiltie of sedition and rebellion, but are so called by the enimies of the truth and pure doctrine, for defending the libertie of the Gospell. Let all men know, that many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandes of faithfull Christians, being spoyled of their goodes, haue, like banished mē, forsaken their houses and countrey: let them knowe that by warre, and by other meanes, they haue become true martyrs, and by the fraude and deceyte of the Antichristian Guyses, are dayly martyred, who vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating and breaking the moste strayte lawe and faith of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, haue abused the kings name and authoritie to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise their tirannie and wickednesse. To be shorte, let al men know that Fraunce is falne into these ciuil wars through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wickednesse of aliens, not through the fault of the faithfull.</p>
   <p>Moreouer (gentle Reader, whiche desirest to be satisfyed in the truth) we testifie and affirme thus muche for our sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that we haue written all things truly, simply, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, without anye manner of parcialitie: not gathering any thing by rumours or reportes, but by certaine and vndoubted arguments: in so much that we are not afrayde to appeale to those that are yet alyue, as too eye witnesses, yea and to the very time it selfe. Farewell▪</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>