<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S492274_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B36534</idno>
           <idno type="STC">None</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S492274</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvayes for the ordering of souldiours in battelray, and setting of battayles, after diuers fashions, with their maner of marching : and also fugures [sic] of certayne newe plattes for fortification of townes: and more ouer, howe to make saltpeter, gunpouder, and diuers sortes of fireworkes or wilde fyre, with other thinges appertayning to the warres. Gathered &amp; set foorth by Peter VVhitehorne</title>
                 <author>Whithorne, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Williamson, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>49, 3 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Britons the auncient inhabitauntes of this Isle (for lacke of skillfull men of vvarre of their ovvne, being afraied of the Franki, &amp; Burgundi, vvhiche vvere certaine Barberous natiōs, vvho at the time ouer ran, spoiled, &amp; possessed Frāce) caused the Germaine people called Angly to come to ayde and defende them, by vvhose procurement the Angly vnder Vortiger their King, taking vpō the the same enterprise, after they had ones defended them, did then incontinente driue them out of this Islande, remaining here themselues to inhabite: and after their name called it England: euē as also of later daies, the like chaūce happened to the Greekes, by calling in the Turckes to helpe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their enemies. VVhich exāples, vvith innumerable like being vvell considered, do most manifestlie shevv, hovv daungerous &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius it is for a Prince and his Realme, to be driuen to truste to the seruice of straungers, for lacke of sufficient skillfull men of their ovvn for their defence. VVherfore sithens my intent in setting fourth this booke of Martial affaires, hath beene onely to the ende to declare my good vvill, to haue my naturall countriemen not to bee inferiour to anye in vvarlike knovvledge, but rather to excell in the same, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vvithout aide or helpe of any forein nation, vvee may alvvaies bee most renovvmed and famous, I shall beseeche all gentil readers, for this my labour done for their cōmodities, to iudge and reporte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of accordingly. And although my doinges herin, be not correspondēt to my desire, nor to the satisfactiō of euery mās minde (vvhich vvere impossible) yet my trust is, that some neuerthelesse by diligente rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therof, and imitating the example of Lucullus, (vvho chiefelye by studie of like bookes, in very shorte space, became one of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantest and vvorthiest vvariour of all the Romanes,] may if they list, take commoditie and profite, vvhereby the knovvledge in vvarres, may of such as neuer haue bene trayned in them, be the more easyly gotten and attayned. For vvhich cause, my indeuour and trauayle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken herein, for to profit this our common vveale, deserueth not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to be despised, seeing that the most verteous life, and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Alexander Seuerus Emperour of Rome, vvith manye other Princes, and common vveales, could not, being negligēt in this kinde
<pb facs="50"/> of studie and practis therof, saue or defende them selues, from moste shamefull endes, &amp; miserable deathes vvherin fortune vvas not to be blamed, but only their folly &amp; ignoraunce, for hauing neuer thought in time of tranquilitie and pease that it coulde chaunge into aduersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and trouble: the vvhich is a common faulte of men, not to make accompte in fayre vveather, of the tempest to come.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>