<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Tedder, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4937_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13565</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23859.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4937</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Tedder, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The recantations as they were seuerallie pronounced by VVylliam Tedder and Anthony Tyrrell (sometime two seminarie priests of the English Colledge in Rome and nowe by the great mercie of almightie God conuerted, vnto the profession of the Gospell of Iesus Christ) at Paules Crosse, the day and yeere as is mentioned in their seuerall tytles of theyr recantations : vvith an epistle dedicatorie vnto Her Maiestie and their seuerall præfaces vnto the reader, contayning the causes that mooued them to the same</title>
                 <author>Tedder, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Broome (Brome, Browne), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 47 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore you come to the reading of this my recantation, J thought good to aduertise you, first of the cause that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee to publishe it in print, which is the satisfaction of all my Countreymen. First, of them that were present at the pronouncing of the same, for though they did heare mee speake in that place where I did vtter it, yet hearde they not all that heere is sette down, for the shortnes of time cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed me to omitt that which I did. Secondly, I haue added something more then was in that copie: such are moste of the authorities noted in the margent, out of the Scriptures, and certaine verses, which heere I haue put downe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, I thought it not sufficient to haue pronounced it in one place: I know it had beene sufficient for the assembly there present: But, my desire is, that all her Maiesties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects whersoeuer, though they heard me not, shold haue if it please them, a copie of my Recantation in theyr hands. First to peruse for their satisfaction. Secondly to prayse God for myne effectuall conuersion.</p>
   <p>I am nowe to entreate the Christian Reader, not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider so much the stile wherein I haue written it, as the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection wherewith I did write it: and when you haue seene the same, I beseech you to pray God to continue me in that good worke, which his maiestie hath begun very gratiously in mee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your harty welwiller William Tedder.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>