<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE MAIOR, THE VVORSHIPFVLL THE ALDERMEN AND BVRGESSES, AND THE REST OF THE INHA∣BITANTS OF THE TOWNE AND PARISH OF BANBƲRY.</title>
           <author>Leigh, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4965_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15013</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25317.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4965</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE MAIOR, THE VVORSHIPFVLL THE ALDERMEN AND BVRGESSES, AND THE REST OF THE INHA∣BITANTS OF THE TOWNE AND PARISH OF BANBƲRY.</title>
                 <author>Leigh, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Prototypes, or, The primarie precedent presidents out of the booke of Genesis : shewing, the [brace] good and bad things [brace] they did and had practically applied to our information and reformation by that faithfull and painefull preacher of Gods word William Whately ... together with Mr. Whatelyes life and death ; published by Mr. Edward Leigh and Mr. Henry Scudder, who were appointed by the authour to peruse his manuscripts, and printed by his owne coppy</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Langham, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 267, 1, 182, 36 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE MAIOR, THE VVORSHIPFVLL THE ALDERMEN AND BVRGESSES, <hi>AND THE REST OF THE INHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BITANTS OF THE TOWNE AND PARISH OF BANBƲRY.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>Right Worshipfull,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I could not but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate my owne and your happinesse in the injoyment of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Pastours labours, so both I and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Christians do now condole your misery in the losse of the good Authour. The greater your happinesse was, the greater now is your misery, and I feare many
<pb facs="3"/>
of you prized not the blessing so much as you should have done, and that you knew not the greatnesse of the benefit so well by the fruition as now by the want of it. At <hi>Banbury</hi> even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you was your Pastour borne and bred, and there he lived and died. Ministers are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Incumbents, so was he being diligently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident in his place, they are stiled Lights, so was he, like a candle or lampe which spent himselfe to give light to others. He spent his means and strength amongst you, and as himselfe in his sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse said, <hi>He sought not yours but you.</hi> Of all the Ministers that ever I knew so experimentally, he was the most unblameable in his conversation. I had the happinesse to live almost a yeare with him in his house, neare foure yeares under his Ministry, and to be esteemed by him one of his faithfullest friends, I have cause to blesse GOD for him whilst I live, since it pleased him by his meanes, not onely to reveale many saving truthes unto mee, but also to set them on with such power, as I hope I shall never forget them. Oh, with what life and zeale would hee both preach and pray! and how strict and watchfull was hee in his whole life! being (as every good Minister should be) <hi>Blamelesse, Sober, Just, Holy, Temperate,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2. Tit. 1.8.</note>
      <hi>of good Behaviour, given to Hospitality, apt to teach, a lover</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <p>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. will beare both rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
         <p>2 Tim. 2.15.</p>
      </note>
      <hi>of good things and good men. Hee studied to approove himselfe unto GOD, a workeman that needed not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the word
<pb facs="3"/>
of Truth.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12 1 Pet. 5.3. Tit. 2.7. There are two singular virtues in a good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> He propounded to you the Examples of holy Writ, and was himselfe whilst he lived, an Example and Patterne of all good works, If that saying therefore of <hi>Austins</hi> be true, <hi>So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as a man shall edifie by a good Example,<note place="margin">
            <p n="1">1 It may profit a world of people. 1 Thes. 1.7, 8</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is lasting and may doe good for a long time after.</p>
            <p>1 Pet. 3.5, 6. M. <hi>Harris</hi> at <hi>Hanwell.</hi>
            </p>
         </note> for so many he shall receive a reward of a blessed life,</hi> than surely he hath now received a full reward for all the good hee did by his holy life, unto those with whom he conversed. In a word, hee was a most pious and accomplisht Divine for his ministeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all parts and paines (as one of his neare Friends said truely) hee might sooner bee envied than matcht and equalled; being in this like <hi>Saul,</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than his brethren by the head. He was well skilled in both the Originall tongues, being able to render the Text out of his <hi>Hebrew Bible</hi> or <hi>Greeke Testament</hi> to another in our mother tongue, as familiarly almost, as if it had bin En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish. For the Arts, he was a good <hi>Logician,</hi> as his exact <hi>Analysis</hi> of the <hi>ten Commandements</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, a good <hi>Philosopher,</hi> as his Sermons in manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script on the 104. <hi>Psalme</hi> doe witnesse, a good <hi>Rhetorician</hi> or <hi>Oratour,</hi> as his printed Treatises a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly testifie. Hee had words at will and could readily and aptly expresse himselfe in his Sermons, which gift of Elocution is requisite if not necessary for a compleate Divine.</p>
   <p>He had by long <note n="*" place="margin">He was a Preacher at <hi>Banbury</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thirty yeares.</note> Experience gotten the art of preaching, and he wrote a tract concerning that subject; hee had an excellent faculty in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterizing
<pb facs="4"/>
or fitly describing a vertue or vice, or any other thing, and though he had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-place-booke of his own, yet he could treat of any subject, I might also extoll his other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, and without danger of exceeding magnifie him for his strong naturall parts, his solid judgement and tenacious memorie, and commend some vertues wherein hee excelled to your imitation, as his Humility, Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnesse, Beneficence, Laboriousnesse and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence <note n="*" place="margin">Hee went over in his preaching the whole Booke of <hi>Iudges,</hi> both the <hi>Samuels,</hi> the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> to the 11. <hi>C.</hi> or therabout, all the <hi>Psal.</hi> to the 106. &amp; the whole <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Iob.</hi> besides al the principles of Religion often.</note> in his Calling, and then also shew how comfortably he died, being full of heavenly spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and godly Exhortations.</p>
   <p>Therefore I passe from himselfe to this <hi>Opus posthumum,</hi> this first worke of his which since his death came to light, <hi>viz.</hi> Sermons on all the Examples or Historicall part of <hi>Genesis,</hi> which Booke containeth a briefe and short Story of the things done from the beginning of the world to the death of <hi>Joseph,</hi> for the space as it is thought by some of 2309. yeares, by Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> of 2368. yeares. Examples are not unfitly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto looking-Glasses, wherein one may behold as well what to eschew, as what to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: So you should follow the <hi>Faith of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Obedience of Isaack,</hi> but shun their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dissembling; follow <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> in their <hi>Righteousnesse and Zeale,</hi> but shunne their <hi>drunkennesse and incest.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And because an <hi>Example</hi> of a Person living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb facs="4"/>
you may bee more prevalent with some then the Examples of others though singularly holy whose vertues they onely read of (as a Sermon delivered, <hi>Ʋiva voce,</hi> doth more affect then the same reade out of a Booke) So walke therefore as you had him for an Example, and bee you followers of him, as hee was of CHRIST, in the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before mentioned and all holy conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Remember him who had the rule over you,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note>
      <hi>who hath spoken unto you the Word of GOD, whose Faith follow</hi> and Charitie too; for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Whately</hi> was the most bountifull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster to the poore I thinke in <hi>England</hi> of his meanes, your Consciences will witnesse that hee hath often pressed and urged this Dutie upon you, and as hee was earnest in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading his Hearers to beneficence, so hee practised the same Himselfe, entertaining some poore widdowes or necessitous Persons weekely at the least at his Table, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the tenth of all his Estate that way, and see how GOD blessed him for the same, his Estate (as himselfe told mee) prospered the better after hee tooke that course, and in his sickenesse hee comforted himselfe with that Promise, <hi>Psalme</hi> 41.1, 3. <hi>Blessed is hee that considereth the poore, the LORD will deliver him in time of trouble. The LORD will strengthen him upon the bed of
<pb facs="5"/>
languishing.</hi> O follow him therefore who by Faith and Patience inherits the Promises, let his good Example and wholesome Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons provoke you to all holinesse, that you all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so may partake with him in that happinesse of which hee is now fully possessed,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true Christian Friend, <hi>Edward Leigh.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>