<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF Mr. WILLIAM WHATELY, LATE Minister of the Word at Banbury in the County of Oxford, written by Henry Scudder Mini∣ster of the Word at Collingborne-ducis, in the County of Wilts.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S4965_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15013</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25317.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S4965</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF Mr. WILLIAM WHATELY, LATE Minister of the Word at Banbury in the County of Oxford, written by Henry Scudder Mini∣ster of the Word at Collingborne-ducis, in the County of Wilts.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Prototypes, or, The primarie precedent presidents out of the booke of Genesis : shewing, the [brace] good and bad things [brace] they did and had practically applied to our information and reformation by that faithfull and painefull preacher of Gods word William Whately ... together with Mr. Whatelyes life and death ; published by Mr. Edward Leigh and Mr. Henry Scudder, who were appointed by the authour to peruse his manuscripts, and printed by his owne coppy</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Langham, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 267, 1, 182, 36 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography_of_author">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>WILLIAM WHATELY,</hi> LATE Minister of the Word at <hi>Banbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxford,</hi> written by <hi>Henry Scudder Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the Word at</hi> Collingborne-ducis, in the County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene a commendable use in the Church of God from the Primitive times downe to us; that the lives of some or other (especially of the more famous Ministers and lights therein) have beene written by men who best knew, and had learned what their lives and conversation was. This they did not onely to vindicate their names from the slanders of the wicked, who will speake evill of all that oppose their evill wayes, and also that the dead might bee duely honoured; but chiefly that the living by their good Examples might glorifie God for them and be edified.</p>
   <p>This writing and printing the lives of worthy men, is like the engravings with the point of a diamond, raising up for them an everlasting monument; upon which the light of their Faith and good workes is made to shine before men, that seeing their Faith and holinesse they may follow them; and may also praise God for his graces in them, and for the good which hath bin done by them, and so glorifie their Father which is in Heaven.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>I have beene earnestly intreated to write the Life and Death of M. <hi>William Whately,</hi> late Pastour of the Church of <hi>Banbury,</hi> I was made choice of the rather, because of that intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Friendship which was betweeene us, and because of our long acquaintance, being of the same time in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Vniversity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and of the same Colledge and Chamber and having the same Tutor; and afterward when wee were both placed in the Ministery wee lived sometime together in one house,<note place="margin">By marriage of sisters.</note> and a great while neare one another, and were also nearly allyed</p>
   <p>I know none that had like meanes to know him more thoroughly then I. I have therefore not unwillingly set pen to paper, and doe here in all plainenesse and sobriety of truth reckon up and report his life and death in a short summe, that those who will may read and make their use of it. For in many things hee may bee a lively patterne to us his Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in the Ministery of the Gospell of Christ; and the like in many things for the imitation of all that desire to live godly in Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>This M <hi>William Whately</hi> was borne at <hi>Banbury</hi> a burrough Town very well known in <hi>Oxfordsbure.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">M. <hi>Thomas</hi> and Mistres <hi>Ioyce Whately.</hi>
      </note>His Parents were both of them forward professours of the Gospell of Christ, and of the power of Godlinesse and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, according as it is now mainetained in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They were both of chiefe note and place in the Towne, his Father being oft Major, and a long time a stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Iustice of Peace in that Burrough. His Mother was a rare woman for naturall parts; but chiefly for Piety, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in her Calling, Frugality and Mercifullnesse to the poore. She was a right <hi>Lois</hi> or <hi>Eunice</hi> in breeding up this her Son (as shee did her other Children) in the Knowledge of the holy Scriptures from a child.</p>
   <p>His Parents trained him up in his yonger daies to learning, setti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g him to the best Schooles that were in those parts, where he profited in learning (as also hee did in the Vniversitie) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove most of his equalls in yeares. This hee did by reason of the Excellency of the naturall parts which God had given
<pb facs="7"/>
him, namely, a quicke apprehension, a cleare judgement and a most happy memory.</p>
   <p>His ripenesse in Grammer learning in Latine, Greeke and Hebrew was so earely that about the fourteenth yeare of his age, he was sent to Christs Colledge in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> where God provided him and me a <note n="*" place="margin">M <hi>Thomas Pot</hi>
      </note> Tutor, one of a thousand for Pietie, Learning, Diligence in reading unto, and in a most loving and wise care of governing and godly instructing of his pupils.</p>
   <p>In the Vniversity he was an hard Student and quickely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a good Logician and Philosopher, a strong disputant, and an excellent Orator. He delighted much in the study of Poetry and the Mathematiks.</p>
   <p>Hee was a constant hearer of M. Doctor <hi>Chaderton</hi> and of Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> who at that time were famous Preachers in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> And it was our Tutors manner to cause all his Pupills to come to Prayers into his Chamber every evening, and hee called all the under graduates to give account of what they had heard upon the Lords day, and when any of us were at a stand and <hi>non-plus,</hi> hee would say <hi>Whately,</hi> what say you? then hee would seldome faile, but repeate as readily, as if he had preached the Sermon himself. By this he did win our Tutors love, and our wonder at him; but (such was our pride) he gained our envy of him</p>
   <p>His Father (whether because he was not resolved what cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to breed him to, or for what other cause I know not) after that hee had with credit proceeded Bachelour of Arts, hee took him home, where he abode some good time, yet applying himselfe unto his studies.</p>
   <p>While hee remained at home with his Father hee married the Daughter of one Master <hi>George Hunt,</hi> the sonne of that tryed and prepared Martyr <hi>Iohn Hunt</hi> mentioned in the Book of Martyrs, who was condemned to be burnt for Religion, but was saved from the execution thereof by the death of Queene <hi>Mary.</hi> This Master <hi>George Hunt</hi> was bred up in the Famous f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee Schoole of the Marchant-Taylers in London, and afterward by the incouragement of Master D. <hi>Humfry</hi> (by
<pb facs="8"/>
occasion of a visit of that Schoole) and by the furtherance of M <hi>George</hi> and Mr. <hi>Iohn Kingsmells,</hi> and by the exhibitions of Bishop <hi>Pilkinton</hi> (all which for their honour sake I name) he was called unto, and mainetained in that worthy Foundation of good Learning, <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> till hee was Fellow of that House, where hee continued till hee had borne the offices of Deane of Arts and Deane of Divinity. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the meanes of those worthy Master <hi>Kingsmells,</hi> hee was preferred to the Church of <hi>Collingborn-ducis</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Wiles.</hi> where for the space of fifty and one yeares and five moneths he lived a sound and constant Preacher of the Word, and was of an unblameable and holy life, even untill the oyle of his radicall moysture was spent, and the candle of his life of it selfe went out, in a full and good old-age, after a long and joyous expectation, and longing for his blessed change, which was in the eighty and third yeare and fift moneth of his age.</p>
   <p>This Master <hi>George Hunt</hi> (after that by importunity hee had got this his sonne in law to make tryall of his ability to preach) he overperswaded him to intend the ministery. And thereupon he entred himselfe into <hi>Edmund Hall</hi> in the famous Vniversity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and tooke his Degree of Master of Arts.</p>
   <p>Not long after hee entred into the Ministery, and hee was presently called to be a Lecturer at <hi>Banbury</hi> which he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably performed above the space of foure yeares, and then was called to be Vicar of the same Church, which office hee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully discharged neare thirty years till he died.</p>
   <p>The abilities wherewith God had indued him for his work of the Ministery were more then ordinary. For hee was of a quicke understanding, of a cleare and deepe Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of a most firme memory, and of a lively spirit. Hee was naturally eloquent, a master of his words, having words at will. Hee had a most able body and sound lunges, and till some yeares before his death, he had a most strong and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible voice. And according as his matter in hand, and his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory needed, he was both a terrible <hi>Boanerges,</hi> a sonne of
<pb facs="8"/>
Thunder, and also a <hi>Barnabas,</hi> a sonne of sweet consolation. And which was the crowne of all, God gave him an heart to seek him and to aime at the saving of the soules of all that heard him. His speech and preaching was not with entising words of mans wisedome, but in demonstration of the spirit and of power. He was an <hi>Apollos</hi> not onely eloquent, but withall mighty in the Scriptures. He like some of the Ancient Fathers was as occasions fell out sometimes an every dayes Preacher. He preached ordinarily in his owne Church twise each Lords-Day, and catechized for above halfe an houre before evening Prayer, examining and instructing the youth, and once a weeke he preached the ordinary Lecture.</p>
   <p>Hee was much against all such preaching as was light, vaine, scenicall, impertinent, raw and indigested.</p>
   <p>His preaching was plaine, but as much according to the Scripture and also to the rules of Art, and of right Reason, as any that ever I heard or have heard of. In conference he hath told me what hee aimed at, and what use he made of the Arts, and what rules hee set to himselfe in the studying of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which was as followeth,</p>
   <p>That he might better understand his Text, hee made use of his Grammer learning in Greeke and Hebrew, in which tongues the Scripture is written. Also hee would use the helpe of <hi>Rhetoricke</hi> to discover to him what formes of speech in his Text was to be taken in their primary and proper signification, and what was elegantly cloathed and wrapped up in tropes and figures that hee might unfold them, and see their naked mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: Then well weighing and considering the context, hee would by the helpe of <hi>Logicke</hi> finde out the scope of the Holy Ghost in that Scripture. Hee would endeavour when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to enter upon the preaching of any Chapter, to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lise</hi> and take the Chapter into its severall branches and parts. Then he would if it were a doctrinall Text, note the Doctrine as it lay in the Text and so prosecute it. Or if the Text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted of illustrations or circumstances of some principall truth there prosecuted; hee would then gather from some notable part or branch of his Text, an apt Doctrine, or Divine Truth
<pb facs="9"/>
which should so immediately follow, that the Truth observed in the Text should be the argument or middle terme, wherby in a simple Sillogisme, he could conclude his Doctrine. Next, hee would seeke for apt proofes out of Scripture to confirme it. Fewer or more as hee thought best, which done, because o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arguments according to Scripture and right Reason are forcible to convince and confirme reasonable men in any truth, hee would find out Reasons of his Doctrine, but he aimed that they should bee strong Arguments, or middle termes by which hee might likewise Sillogistially conclude his said Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
   <p>Then according to the nature of the Doctrine, and the need and aptnesse of his Auditory; hee would as from an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble consequent of his Doctrine by way of Application, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme some profitable Truth, which yet by some might happily bee questioned, or else convince men of some errour, or reproove some vice, or exhort to some Dutie, or resolve some doubt, or case of conscience, or comfort such as needed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation. In all which sorts of Applications hee did make use of more or fewer of them as there might bee cause, and hee would bee carefull that his Doctrine should bee the Argument or middle terme whereby hee might sillogistically conclude the maine Proposition of any of his said uses: And if the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe or exhortation did need pressing home upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, then hee would study to enlarge his Speech, shewing motives to induce to such a duty; and allso disswasives from such a vice, taking his Arguments from dutie to God, decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or shamefullnesse, pleasure or paine, gaine or losse.</p>
   <p>And here again he would use the help of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> but all for the most part in a concealed way, without all affectation. And sometimes he would shew the effectuall meanes of attaining of the Grace and power to performe the duty to which he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And sometimes likewise he would shew the remedyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such or such a vice from which he disswaded, as may bee seene by his Sermons already extant. Also when hee thought it was needefull to discusse and handle any common place or head of Divinity, hee would doe it very judiciously, fully and most profitably.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>Though hee had but an ordinary study of books for such an accomplisht Divine, yet hee was one who had read very much. For hee would read most swiftly, yet not cursorily, for he could give an account of the substance and most remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able particulars of what hee had so read.</p>
   <p>Hee had allso allwayes when hee pleased the benefit of a Booke-sellers shop, which caused him to forbeare to buy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bookes.</p>
   <p>Though hee preached so often, yet what hee preached was before well studied and premeditated. Hee usually did pen his Sermons at large; and if before he preached, hee had but so much time as to read over what he had written, and to gather it up into short heades, hee was able if hee thought it fit to deliver it in publike well neare in the same words.</p>
   <p>It pleased God to put a seale to his Ministery in the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, confirming and building up of many thousand soules by his meanes in the whole course of his Ministery.</p>
   <p>Hee was a most diligent visitor of the sick people that were under his charge without respect of Persons, after that it came to his knowledge that they were sicke.</p>
   <p>He was a ready Peace-maker amongst his flocke that should happen to be at variance.</p>
   <p>He abounded in works of Mercie, hee was a truely liberall man, one that studyed liberall things; for hee would seeke out to finde objects of his mercy, rather then to stay till they were offered. Hee did set apart and expended for the space of many yeares for good uses the tenth part of his yearly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings in, both out of his temporall and ecclesiasticall meanes of maintenance.</p>
   <p>Hee had an heavenly gift in Prayer, both for aptnesse and Fullnesse of Confessions, Petitions, Supplications, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercessions and Prayses, as allso for readinesse and copious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of apt words, together with Fervency of Spirit to poure them out unto God in the name of Christ in the behalfe of himselfe, and of all those who in Prayer joyned with him.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>He had this singular abilitie that in his Prayer after Sermon, he could collect into a short Sum all which hee had delivered to his Hearers and make it the matter of his Prayer to God, to the end they might be inwardly taught of God, and become Beleevers and doers of what was taught them.</p>
   <p>Likewise when hee had read a <hi>Psalme</hi> or <hi>Chapter</hi> in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, hee was so well seene in the Text, and of so good a Judgement, and of so choice a memory that though the <hi>Chapter</hi> was part of the <hi>Ceremoniall Law,</hi> or in the bookes of <hi>Numbers, Chronicles,</hi> and hardest Prophecies, he in his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would discover the scope and meaning and chiefe notes of Observation, and their use, in such sort, that oft-times when I have heard him, I have much longed that I could call them all to minde; For I found the matter of his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be a better Commentary of that <hi>Chapter,</hi> with apt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations and applications for use, then I could finde in any Authour that I had read, who had vvritten there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
   <p>His manner was daily Morning and Evening to call his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily together, and to reade a <hi>Psalme</hi> or <hi>Chapter</hi> in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to pray with them and oft to catechize them; besides his constant Prayer Morning and Evening with his wife and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so constantly alone by himselfe.</p>
   <p>He did set a part private dayes of Humiliation for his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon speciall occasions, and oft times before their prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their due receiving of the Lords-Supper. At which times he did exceed himselfe in powring out his soule to GOD in most aboundant and most free Confessions of sinne, and expressions of Sorrow for sinne, with teares and with earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Petition for pardon and grace, and for the good of the Churches of God, but for our whole State and Church of <hi>England</hi> more specially and particularly.</p>
   <p>He was much in dayes of private Fasting and humbling himselfe before God alone, that hee might make and keepe his peace with God, and obtaine more Grace to keep more close to him, and to walke more evenly with him, and that hee might the better keepe under his body, and bring it
<pb facs="10"/>
into subjection (following the Example of the Apostle) least having preached to others hee himselfe should not live answerable to his Doctrine without reproofe, knowing that Ministers ought to be unreproveable. He was so much in this that it is thought by such as knew him best that it impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the health of his body, though it made much for the good of his soule.</p>
   <p>He was very able and very ready to conferre with, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve the doubts of those many who in love and desire of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation came unto him.</p>
   <p>He bare a tender love unto, and had a conscionable care of that great people over which God had made him over-seer. For, although his mainetenance from them was but small in comparison, and unkindnesses and discouragements many and his offers of greater preferment in the Church in respect of outward mainetenance were oft and importunate; yet he would not be perswaded to leave them. Yea though once for reasons which suddenly tooke him, he did promise to accept of another charge, yet within a while hee intreated mee to tell that Person to whom he had promised, that hee had better thought of it, and did desire to be released of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, and that out of Consideration of that great people which he should leave, saying, that if he should accept of that lesser charge, when he should come into the Church amongst them his heart would in yerning towards his other people, aske him what he did there.</p>
   <p>He was duely inquisitive after the affaires of Gods Church and people, and according as hee received true intelligence of their weale or woe, so hee had his sympathies and Fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with them in either of their conditions</p>
   <p>Hee was much grieved and troubled when hee saw that difference of opinions, and thereupon strangenesse, distract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions and rends to arise and bee made in the Church amongst Bretheren professing for the maine, and in fundamentalls the same Truthes. Hee signified so much to mee with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayling many times.</p>
   <p>Hee was judiciously charitable to any that should differ in
<pb facs="11"/>
some opinions from him, so long as he saw that they agreed with him in the maine and Fundamentall Points of Religion, and were diligent to enquire after the Truth, and saw allso that they did indeed shew the Power of Godlinesse in their lives. Hee could and did highly esteeme them, love them, and converse Christianly and familiarly with them, and that because (although hee thought they were in an errour, and hee would in private and publike endeavour to reclaime them) yet he was perswaded that their desire was to seeke Christ, and that they had an aime to know God aright, and to serve him in sincerity.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding all this good which according to the truth hath beene said of him; it must be remembred that hee was a man and not without his imperfections and frailties. For what man is he that liveth and sinneth not. And as it is also said, <hi>In many things we sin all.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is usuall with God that men of the greatest parts and gifts should be exercised with some or other inordinate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee mortified, and some strong temptations, to have some thorne in the flesh, or some or other messenger of Satan (as the Apostle had) to buffet them: Else they would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above measure to the sleighting, contemning, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning of their Bretheren, and other men would have too high an opinion of them, halfe deifying them, despising those vvho are no lesse holy, but not so excellently gifted as they.</p>
   <p>There was nothing which did more evidently discover truth of Gods grace in this man, then that which was occasioned by his slips and strong temptations; For these made him more watchfull over himselfe, then otherwise hee would have bin; It made him more humble and more to loath his originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and sinfull nature, and bewailingly to cry out with the Apostle, <hi>O miserable man that I am who shall deliver me from the body of this Death.</hi> And that because hee was (as other the deare servants of God are) most sensible of the captivitie and bondage which sin would strive to hold him under, sith that <hi>when he would doe well, evill was present with him,</hi> and made
<pb facs="11"/>
him sometimes to doe some things which in the bent of his soule he would not have done. This served to make him more humble in himselfe, more earnest in prayer to God and more pittifull towards others in whom this sinne remaineth and dwelleth (even after conversion) which (as the Apostle saith) is a weight and doth easily beset them, to hinder them in their Christian race. And this I am assured off, that hee would be the first espier of those faults of his when the world could not nor did take notice of them, having no peace in himselfe untill he had with all speed and earnestnesse, sought and regained par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and peace with God.</p>
   <p>He may be a patterne to all in receiving admonition from any that should in love mind him of his fault. Hee was glad when any of the righteous smote him and would take it well, not from his Superiours onely, but from his equalls and farre inferiours. Hee had learned with <hi>David</hi> to blesse God that sent them, and to blesse the advice, to follow it, and to blesse the party and thanke him that gave it. Hee would intreate such, as hee hath done me in particular, not to be wanting to him in this Christian office of Love; and hee would really shew more testimonies of his love to such afterwards then ever formerly; which is a sure argument of uprightnesse. A most reverend Divine who had knowne him from his infancy, and had often conversed with him, gave testimony of him to this effect unto me and others when lately he spake of him by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the mentioning of his sicknesse.</p>
   <p>His latter daies were his best daies; for in the judgement of those who could judge spiritually, hee grew exceedingly in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and in spirituall and heavenly mindednesse, his last works were his best works, arguing him to be of Gods grafting, and planted in the house of the Lord.</p>
   <p>Lastly, hee had a most happy and comfortable successe of his conflicts against sinne▪ For a good while before his sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and death he did with Comfort and Joy make knowne to his dearest friend that God had given him victory against his greatest corruptions vvhich had for a long time kept him in continuall exercise.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>About eight weekes before his death a great fit of inward and short coughing and extreame shortnesse of breath did cease upon him, in so much that those who came about him fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that hee would presently have departed. This fit bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, much weakenesse continued, yet hee preached di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, untill that his encreasing weakenesse did disable him.</p>
   <p>In the time of his sickenesse and weakenesse hee gave hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and wholesome counsell to his people, neighbours and friends that came to visit him: giving particular advise to his wife, children and servants respectively according to their place and condition as they oft came about him, thus hee did oft so long as hee was able to speake unto them.</p>
   <p>His Christian speeches that concerned all, tended to this, that they would be carefull to redeeme the time, and to bee much in reading, hearing and meditating of the Word of God. That they would be much in Prayer, much in brotherly love and communion of the Saints. And that they would be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to hold fast that which he had taught them out of the Word of Truth. And that while the light and meanes of Salvation was to be had, they should not spare paines nor cost to enjoy them. He was oft in his sickenesse upon the painefull racke or torture of inward snatchings and convulsions, which sometimes left him, but (three or foure dayes before his death) they returned and increased upon him; all which hee bare exceeding patiently. Hee was much in ejaculations and short prayers and lifting up his heart to God in the behalfe of the Church and State, and for himselfe allso, which hee was most frequent and earnest in, a little before his death. In the time when a brother of his (not onely in the common bonds of Christianity, but allso by alliance, and a brother in the Ministery) was praying with him and for him to this effect, that if his time was not determined or expired that God would be pleased to restore him for the good of his Church, or if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise that hee would put an end to his paine if he saw good; at the hearing thereof hee lift up his eyes stedfastly towards Heaven and allso one of his hands (hee being not able to lift
<pb facs="12"/>
up the other) and in the close of that prayer gave up the ghost, shutting downe his eyes himselfe, as if hee were fallen into a sweet sleepe. Hee lived much desired and died much lamented.</p>
   <p>Thus a great, a good and mercifull man, a chariot and horse-man of Israell is by Gods owne hand fallen and taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the evill to come, and is entred into peace, and rest in his bed of everlasting pleasures and joyes, enjoying the fruit of his Faith in Christ, and of his walking with God in upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Pretious in the sight of the Lord is the death of the Saints though the wicked regard it not, but are glad of their absence. But the living indeed they must, and they will lay it to heart, and will prepare and long for their owne dissolution, that they maybe more immediately gathered to Christ the Iudge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting and waiting for a blessed Resurrection of themselves and of all that die in the Faith of our Lord Jesus, to whom bee ascribed all Might, Majestie, Dominion and Glorie, both now and for ever more, Amen.</p>
   <p>This Man of God and faithfull Minister of Christ, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life upon Friday the 10. of <hi>May, Anno Domini,</hi> 1639. neare the end of the six and fiftieth yeare of his age.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>