<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5010_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20559</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6967.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bright star vvhich leadeth wise men to our Lord Iesus Christ : or A familiar and learned exposition on the ten Commandements: gathered from the mouth of a faithfull pastor: by a gracious young man, sometime scholler in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 92, 57, 57-59, 65-102 leaves, tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, the good prouidence of God hath vouchsafed thee benefit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, by the labours of a reuerent faithfull Pastor, which he meant only to his owne flocke at home. These fruitefull doctrines which in this booke are offered to thee, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from his mouth, but neither pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor perused by himselfe, nor publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with his consent or knowledge: for had he been willing that they should be exposed to open view, he would haue gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them with richer attire, and yet with modestie according to the Apostles rule, 1. Cor. 2. 1. Without affected excellencie of words or carnall wisdome. They were collected by a godly ingenious young man, whose diligent attention and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, deserne no small commendations: yet what hand or memorie can follow so
<pb facs="3"/> fast the fluent speech of an eloquent Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, as to set downe all in the same forme and elegancie wherein it is deliuered? Moreouer, at the printing diuers faultes haue escaped, both of Orthographie, poynting, and method in some places. But howsoeuer it is, a religious and well seasoned heart will finde and feele herein such comfort and light, as that light and slender defects will easilie be passed ouer. And let not God be defrauded of his due praise, who hath multiplied that food to feast so many, which of man was appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to feede so few. And here is that in some degree verified, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Sauiour foretold his Disciples, Luk. 12. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> What ye haue spoken in darkenesse shall be heard in light, and that which ye haue spoken in the eare in secret places, shall be heard on the houses. Well good reader, let this and such other wholesome writings kindle thy desire to the preaching of the word, that thou maist be more frequent in hearing, and iudicious in vnderstanding. Beware thou grow not conceited of a sufficiencie to be found in reading good bookes, and so begin to distaste the Ministerie: they
<pb facs="3"/> are not ordayned to kill our appetites to the word, but to sharpen them. And so I commend thee to the Lord, who of his mercy graunt thee wisdome, with good successe to thy euerlasting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, thorough Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, R. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>