<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The transzlatoure vnto the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1535</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5059_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10349</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2063.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5059</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The transzlatoure vnto the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Biblia : the Byble: that is, the holy Scrypture of the Olde and New Testament, faythfully translated in to Englyshe</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Cologne</pubPlace>
                    <date>1535</date>
                 <publisher>Cervicornus, Eucharius.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Nicholson (Nicolson, Nicolai, Nycolson), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, xc, cxx, lij, cij, lxxxi, that is lxxxii, cxiij, 1 leave, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="393"/>
   <head>The transzlatoure vnto the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese bokes (good reader) which be called Apocrypha, are not iudged amonge the doctours to be of like reputacion with the other scripture, as thou mayest perceaue by S. Ierome <hi>in epistola ad Paulinum.</hi> And the chefe cause therof is this: there be many places in them, that seme to be repugnaunt vnto the open and manyfest trueth in the other bokes of the byble. Neuertheles I haue not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them together to the intent that I wolde haue them despysed, or litle sett by, or that I shulde thinke them false, for I am not able to proue it: Yee I doute not verely, yf they were equally conferred with the other open scripture (tyme, place, and circumstaunce in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges considered) they shulde nether seme contrary, ner be vntruly &amp; peruersly aledged. Treuth it is: A mās face can not be sene so wel in a water, as in a fayre glasse: nether cā it be shewed so clearly in a water that is stered or moued, as in a styll water. These &amp; many other darck places of scripture haue bene sore stered and myxte with blynde and cuvetous opynions of men, which haue cast soch a myst afore the eyes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> symple, that as longe as they be not cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferred with the other places of scripture, they shall not seme other wyse to be vnderstonde, then as cuvetousnes expoundeth them. But who so euer thou be that readest scripture, let the holy goost be thy teacher, and let one text expounde another vnto the: As for soch drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, visions and darck sentences as be hyd from thy vnderstondinge, commytte them vnto God, and make no articles of them: But let the playne text be thy gyde, and the sprete of God (which is the author therof) shal lede the in all trueth.</p>
   <p>As for the prayer of Salomō (which thou findest not herin) y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prayer of Azarias, and the swete songe that he and his two felowes songe in the fyre: the first (namely the prayer of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomon) readest thou in the eight chapter of the thirde boke of the kynges, so that it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not to be <hi>Apocryphum</hi>: The other prayer and songe (namely of the thre children) haue I not founde amonge eny of the interpreters, but onely in the olde latyn texte, which reporteth it to be of Theodotios translacion. Neuertheles, both because of those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be weake and scrupu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lous, and for their sakes also that loue soch swete songes of thankesgeuinge: I haue not left them out: to the intent that the one shulde haue no cause to complayne, and that the other also might haue the more occasion to geue thankes vnto God in aduersite, as the thre chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dyd in the fyre. Grace be with the. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>