<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Peroration to the Reader.</title>
           <author>H., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5090_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03426</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13552.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5090</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Peroration to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>H., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Credo resurrectionem carnis : A tractate on the eleventh article of the Apostles Creed. By W.H. Esquire sometimes of Peter-house in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Hodson, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="188" facs="94"/>
   <head>A Peroration to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THus have I wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked about Sion, and viewed the bulwarks thereof: I have shewed the strength and munition of this Fort of Faith. In a plaine and short way <hi>(nec breuius potui nec apertius)</hi> I have meditated somewhat one this sweet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Article of our Creed.</p>
   <p>Expect more generous wine from old vine-trees; for resolutions of sacred
<pb n="189" facs="94"/> riddles and deepe mysteries of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, consult with such, whose ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trade is Divinity, with those cunning <hi>Bezaliels,</hi> which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually digging in the precious gemmes of the holy Scripture.</p>
   <p>And now having cast my Mite into the publike treasury, having made my thoughts legible, and sent them, <hi>in dias luminis a<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> This little Manuall <hi>(habent sua fata libelli)</hi> must either stand or fall, at the uncerteinty of my Readers Iudgment.</p>
   <p>I doe not embosome such a Mountebanoke opinion, as to set the garland on my owne worke, I dare not arrogate to my selfe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachnes motto (mihi soli de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo)</hi> and boast that I have spun
<pb n="290" facs="95"/> this thread out of mine owne bowels, No I will freely confesse (it were meere ingratitude should I not acknowledge it) <hi>Nihil egi sine Theseis,</hi> where I liked the water of other mens wells I have drunke deepe.</p>
   <p>I will therefore (with <hi>Lyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensis</hi>) rejoice in this, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver what I have learned, not what I invented, I have feld much wood out of other mens groves wherewith to build, but (as one spake in the like case) I have so hewed it, and squared it, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished it with my owne phrase and my own methode, that the Authors, though good Enditers, can hardly bring in evidence of theft against me.</p>
   <pb n="291" facs="95"/>
   <p>If this Enchiridion, or my <hi>vade Mecum,</hi> shall meete with a faire and candid interpretation from the Ingenuous, the file may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance bee drawne over it againe; Not that I hunt after the fume of vaine glory (what but an Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an eare will sucke-in such breath) but because our second thoughts are commonly more refined, and meditation like the wind gathers strength in proceeding.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. H.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>