<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY MOST WORTHY AND LEARNED FRIEND, EDWARD BENLOWES ESQVIRE.</title>
           <author>F., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5142_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00977</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11082.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5142</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY MOST WORTHY AND LEARNED FRIEND, EDWARD BENLOWES ESQVIRE.</title>
                 <author>F., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The purple island, or The Isle of Man : together with Piscatorie eclogs and other poeticall miscellanies· By P.F</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Phineas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cambridge University—Printers</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 181, 5, 130, 2 pages, 1 leave of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY MOST WORTHY AND LEARNED FRIEND, EDWARD BENLOWES ESQVIRE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S some <hi>Optick-glasses,</hi> if we look one way, increase the object; if the other, lessen the quantity: Such is an <hi>Eye</hi> that looks through <hi>Affection</hi>; It doubles any good, and extenuates what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse. Pardon me, <hi>Sir,</hi> for speaking plain truth; such is that eye whereby you have viewed these raw <hi>Essayes</hi> of my very unripe yeares, and almost childehood. How unseasonable are <hi>Blossomes</hi> in <hi>Autumne!</hi> (unlesse perhaps in this age, where are more flowers then fruit) I am entring upon my <hi>Winter,</hi> and yet these <hi>Blooms</hi> of my first <hi>Spring</hi> must now shew themselves to our <hi>ripe wits,</hi> which certainly will give them no other entertainment but derision. For my self, I cannot account that worthy of your <hi>Patronage,</hi> which comes forth so short of my <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
thereby meriting no other light then the fire. But since you please to have them see more <hi>Day</hi> then their credit can well endure, marvel not if they flie under your <hi>Shadow,</hi> to cover them from the piercing eye of this very curious (yet more censorious) age. In letting them abroad I desire onely to testifie, how much I preferre your desires before mine own, and how much I owe to <hi>You</hi> more then <hi>any other:</hi> This if they witnesse for me, it is all their service I require. <hi>Sir,</hi> I leave them to your <hi>tuition,</hi> and entreat you to <hi>love him</hi> who will contend with you in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to <hi>out-love you,</hi> and would be <hi>known</hi> to the world by no other <hi>Name,</hi> then</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true friend, P. <hi>F.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>Hilgay.
<date>
            <hi>May</hi> 1. 1633.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>