<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honoura∣ble and vertuous Ladie the Lady Frances, Countesse of Hertford, his very good Lady and Mistresse.</title>
           <author>Wolfe, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5176_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05792</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1599.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5176</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honoura∣ble and vertuous Ladie the Lady Frances, Countesse of Hertford, his very good Lady and Mistresse.</title>
                 <author>Wolfe, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Beautifull baybush to shrowd us from the sharp shovvers of sinne : containing many notable prayers and meditations, being very profitable for all true Christians that delight to laud the Lord</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 144, that is 288 pages, 16° in 8's</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>and vertuous Ladie the</hi> Lady Frances, Countesse of Hertford, his very good Lady and Mistresse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Christian mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie (right vertuous Ladie) mooued a Gentleman, the first authour hereof, not onely to conceale his name, but also to cease from setting foorth any thing in the praise of that, which in dutie deserueth to be commended of euery one: So Christian iustice and equitie,
<pb facs="5"/> which willeth vs to giue to euery thing his due, would not suffer me to let that passe without some commendation, whereunto I am notable sufficiently to giue any. But considering, that slightly to commend a thing were the next way to discōment it, except with all it were shrowded vnder the patronage of some great person, and thinking it vnmeet to let that go like an Orphan abroad, which had a father at home, I presumed to commit vnto your honourable patronage not a bare Lawrell, which of it selfe for the greenesse (when other be withered) may seeme to be accepted, but the same decked and adorned with
<pb facs="5"/> most spirituall and beautifull bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes. So that as I cannot thinke if your L. were presented with a materiall Lawrell (wherein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides naturall greenesse were but this necessarie vse, that it could defend you in your garden from the heat of the Sunne) but you would accept, if not of the gift yet of the good will of the giuer: So relying my selfe on your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed fauour and clemencie, I hope you will affoord some fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptation hereof: For herein is not that greenesse, which consisting of naturall qualities, must then wither vvhen all things haue their ending according to their nature, but the flourishing
<pb facs="6"/> greene promises of the conuenant of God, which (as God himselfe) last alwaies immutable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable: here are not the beautifull bushes of a materiall tree, which delight onely the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward sight, but a most familiar view of God himselfe in Christ euen to the delight of the soule, and the inward comfort of the spirit, which take pleasure onely in heauenly things, withstanding the inuasions and subtile practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Sathan, which daily stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth against them, to bring them to destruction. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, here you are not shrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the heat of the sunne, but shall find most coole shade
<pb facs="6"/> from the parching heat of sinne, from the which, God in this life shield &amp; defend you, &amp; in the life to come graunt you euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honors most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dutifull seruant. <hi>Iohn Wolfe.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>