<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5197_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73418</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25599</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Roger VViddringtons last reioynder to Mr. Thomas Fitz-herberts Reply concerning the oath of allegiance, and the Popes power to depose princes : vvherein all his arguments, taken from the lawes of God, in the old and new Testament, of nature, of nations, from the canon and ciuill law, and from the Popes breues, condemning the oath, and the cardinalls decree, forbidding two of Widdringtons bookes are answered: also many replies and instances of Cardinall Bellarmine in his Schulckenius, and of Leonard Lessius in his Singleton are confuted, and diuers cunning shifts of Cardinall Peron are discouered</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 645, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow dangerous and pernicious a thing it is <hi>(deare Contreymen)</hi> in any temporall Kingdome or Common-wealth to coyne, or willingly to vtter, and much more by fraud or violence to force the people to accept of counterfait money, any man of meane vnderstanding may easily perceiue. And true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no lesse dangerous and pernicious is it in the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Kingdome and <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.</note> which <hi>is the pillar and firmament of truth,</hi> to inuent, forge, or divulge, and which is farre worse, to thrust vpon the faithfull by fraud and violence false articles and positions for true and infallible <hi>Catholike faith,</hi> but especially in things which are greatly preiudiciall to the temporall <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie</hi> of Christian <hi>Princes,</hi> whom <hi>Christ</hi> our Sauiour, hath appointed to be <hi>Nurcing Fathers</hi> and <hi>Protectours</hi> of his Church:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isay 19.</hi> Concil. Trid. sess. <hi>25.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi> de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</note> for that thereby not onely Christian <hi>Princes</hi> are extreamely wronged, but also the Christian Religion is greatly scandalized, and the soules both of Princes and subiects are much endangered: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no lesse thanks doe they deserue at the hands of the Church of God, who should discouer a false and forged Catholike faith, and the first inuenters or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishers thereof, then doe they at the hands of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Kingdome, who should disclose false and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait
<pb facs="9"/>
money, and the first coiners or vtterers of the same.</p>
   <p n="2">2 And this is the very case betweene me and my Aduersaries in this controuersie concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> pretended authority to depose temporall Princes, and to dispose of all their temporalls. For I accuse them, and also in my iudgement clearely conuince them, that they haue, if not coined and forged, yet at least<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise not onely taught and divulged, and, which is worse, endeauoured by fraud and violence to thrust vpon Catholikes a false and forged Catholike faith, but also that they haue wrongfully defamed and slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered those Catholikes, and my selfe in particular, who doe plainely discouer their falshoods, and that they seeke both by deceitfull and violent meanes to hinder aswell the learned as the vnlearned people, that they shall not by the true touchstone and vndoubted rules of the Catholike faith, &amp; by reading those books which doe exactly and sincerely debate this question, examine in what a fraudulent manner they seeke to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour this their false and newly forged Catholike faith: wherein they doe most egregiously abuse all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Princes</hi> and people, most exceedingly scandalize Catholike Religon, and as much as lyeth in them, they make the <hi>Sea Apostolike</hi> odious and dreadfull both to Princes and people, and giue occasion of perpetuall discord betwixt the Kingdome and the Priesthood, whereby they prepare the way to <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and lay open a wide gap to Schisme, heresie, Atheisme, and infidelity.</p>
   <p n="3">3 For if vnder the pretence of aduancing the <hi>Popes</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
authority in so great preiudice of <hi>Regall</hi> Soueraignty, we once forsake the ancient and approoued rules, by which as by an assured touchstone the true Christian and Catholike faith, hath alwaies been discerned from the false and counterfeit, what vndoubted grounds, shal we haue to build our Catholike faith vpon, <hi>which</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">In the Creed of <hi>S. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>vnlesse euery one shall keepe entire, and inuiolate, without doubt he shall perish eternally?</hi> If Christian <hi>Princes</hi> &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple once perceiue, that the supreame Pastours of Gods Church doe both permit and applaud some learned men, who are otherwise potent in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> to impose by fraud and violence vpon the Church of Christ, in fauour of that authority which they pretend to haue ouer all temporals, a false and forged Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith for true, and to disgrace and slander all those who shall detect their forgeries, why may not the said Princes and people iustly suspect, as Fa. <hi>Lessius</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note n="d" place="margin">In his <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton part.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 74.</note>, that the Catholike faith and Religion is for a great part thereof a meere inuention of men, deuised of set purpose by Popes, Bishops, and Cleargie men in policie, that they may more securely dominiere, and vnder a shew of piety and Religion, dispose of all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals at their pleasure? And therefore how much these men are to answere at the day of iudgement, for so greatly wronging Christian Princes, for so mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly scandalizing Catholike Religion, for so much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering the soules of all sorts of people, and for so vniustly oppressing and slandering innocent and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Catholikes, who doe plainely discouer their fraud and falshoods, I cannot but tremble, when I
<pb facs="10"/>
seriously consider the same.</p>
   <p n="4">4. And if perhaps my <hi>Aduersaries</hi> will in their owne defence alledge, that one may be excused from all fault before God and man, who in zeale should teach any doctrine to be <hi>Catholike,</hi> which he sincerely in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science thinketh to bee truely Catholike, albeit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance in very deed it is not so; as also he that vttereth counterfait money not knowing it to bee counterfait, but sincerely thinking that it is good and lawfull coine, is not to be condemned before God or man: I <hi>answere,</hi> that all things done in zeale are not free from sinne, when the zeale is blinde, and grounded vpon an erroneous conscience, and culpable ignorance: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise we might excuse from all fault the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for crucifying our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and putting to death his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Luke 23.</note> for that <hi>they did it through ignorance,</hi> and <hi>thought thereby to doe seruice to God;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iohn 16.</note> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> for blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and persecuting the Christians, before his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion,<note place="margin">Acts 1.</note>
      <hi>because he did it being ignorant in incredulity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">5 And therefore <hi>first</hi> I wish them to remember that admonition,<note place="margin">Bell. lib <hi>2.</hi> de gemitu columbae cap <hi>9.</hi>
      </note> which Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> my chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Aduersary giueth to the Pastours and Prelates of the Church vpon occasion of relating the fearefull death of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, who greatly busied himselfe with the deposing of temporall <hi>Princes,</hi> and with the disposing of temporall kingdomes, whereby great warres, and much effusion of innocent blood, were caused in the Church of God (which perchance was one of the three causes for which the said Pope, as Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> rehearseth, had beene <hi>damned eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb facs="10"/>
if he had not repented at the houre of his death.</hi>) For first he deposed <hi>Philip,</hi> and set vp <hi>Otho,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth. Paris in vita Ioannis ad annū. <hi>1210.</hi> Page <hi>220.</hi>
      </note> then he deposed <hi>Otho,</hi> for seeking to recouer certaine townes and forts belonging to the Empire, which the said Pope in the time of <hi>Frederikes</hi> minority had taken into his owne possession: afterward he sought to thrust out of <hi>Italy</hi> the said <hi>Frederike</hi> the second,<note place="margin">Blondus decad. <hi>2.</hi> l b. <hi>6.</hi> Abbas Vrsperg. ad annū <hi>1212.</hi>
      </note> who before at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisgraue</hi> was crowned Emperour by the said Pope <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> his authority. I omit now to relate how here in <hi>England</hi> he carried himselfe, first in taking part with the Barons, and deposing King <hi>Iohn,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth Paris in vita Ioannis ad annū. <hi>1212.</hi> pag. <hi>223. And</hi> Stow <hi>in the life of King</hi> Iohn.</note> and (which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Car. <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> nor <hi>Suarez</hi> dare iustifie, who will not admit that the Pope may lawfully depose a King, and giue his Kingdome from the next heire; who is free from all fault, to another) in giuing the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and his posterity for euer, wherby he depriued the next lawful heire <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. being a childe, of his right, without any fault commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him: But after the Popes <hi>Legate</hi> had cunningly perswaded King <hi>Iohn,</hi> to resigne vp his Crowne and Kingdome to the Pope, then he tooke King <hi>Iohns</hi> part against the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Barons, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them not molest him, for that he was now become the Popes Vassall. But marke, I pray you, what Card. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> writeth of this Pope <hi>Innocent.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="6">6 <hi>About this time,</hi> saith he,<note place="margin">Surius ad <hi>16.</hi> Iunij.</note> relating <hi>Surius</hi> words in the life of S. <hi>Ludgard,</hi> Pope Innocent <hi>the third, after the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating of the</hi> Lateran Councell, <hi>departed this life, and forthwith he appeared visibly to</hi> Ludgard. <hi>But she seeing him compassed about with a great flame of fire, demāded who
<pb facs="11"/>
he was: He answered, that hee was</hi> Pope Innocent: <hi>And what is this, saith she with a pittifull grone, that the common Father of vs all is so cruelly tormented? Hee answered, For three causes am I so tormented, which also had most iustly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged me to euerlasting torments, if by the intercession of the most pious Mother of God, to whom I built a Monasterie, I had not repented at the last houre. And truely I haue escaped eternall death, but I shall be tormented with most grieuous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments vntill the day of Iudgement: But the Mother of mercie obtained for me of her Sonne, that I might come to thee to desire prayers: which when he had said, he presently va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished away. And</hi> Ludgard <hi>told his necessities to her Sisters, that they might relieue him: but she greatly pittying his case did afflict her selfe for his cause, with wonderfull punishment. Let the Reader know,</hi> saith <hi>Thomas Cantipratensis</hi> the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her life, (from whom <hi>Surius</hi> tooke the same) <hi>that those three causes are, by the reuealing of</hi> Ludgard, <hi>not vnknowne to vs, but for the reuerence of so great a</hi> Pope, <hi>we would not relate them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="7">7 <hi>Which example,</hi> saith <hi>Card.</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>is wont oftentimes to terrifie mee exceedingly, and to cause mee to tremble. For if so commendable a</hi> Pope, <hi>and who in the eies of men was accounted not onely honest and prudent, but also a Saint, and woorthy to bee imitated, did scape so narrowly hell fire, and is to bee punished vntill the day of Iudgement, with the most grieuous fire of Purgatory, what Prelate would not tremble? who would not examine most exactly the secrets of his conscience? For I doe easily perswade my selfe, that so great a</hi> Pope <hi>could not commit deadly sinnes, but being deceiued vnder the shew of good, by flatterrs, and
<pb facs="11"/>
those of his owne houshold, of whom it is said in the Gospell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth. 10</note> A mans enemyes are they of his owne howshold. <hi>Therefore let vs all learne by this so great an example, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine carefully our conscience, least perchance it be erroneous, albeit to vs it seeme to be right and sound.</hi> Thus Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> whose counsell in this point, I thinke it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, that all my Aduersaries with Cardinall <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> the chiefest of them, and my selfe should duely consider, least that the zeale, which all of vs pretend to haue, be blind, and not according to knowledge, and that our conscience, albeit to vs it seeme to bee right and sound, bee erroneous, and grounded vpon culpable ignorance. For my owne part, I haue exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined my conscience very carefully, and cannot find my selfe guilty of any fault, for examining this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie touching the lawfulnesse of the <hi>Oath,</hi> and the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depose <hi>Princes,</hi> and that I was not mooued thereunto for feare, flattery, hope of gaine, or any other worldly respect, but truely and sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God is my witnesse, for the loue, I beare to God, Religion, my Prince and Countrey, to finde out the Catholike truth, and being found, to embrace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, and follow it, and thereby according to our <hi>Sauiours</hi> commaundement, <hi>to render to God and Caesar that</hi> obedience, <hi>which doth belong to them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="8">8 <hi>Secondly,</hi> therfore I wish my Aduersaries to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what may in the iudgemēt of any prudent man, be thought of those men, who by fraud or violēce should seek to force vpon any one a great sum of gold, which he greatly suspecteth to be false and counterfaite, and
<pb facs="12"/>
therefore refuseth to accept thereof, before hee hath fully tryed whether it be true or forged coyne: and whether any fault be to be found in him, both for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring to haue the gold examined by the touchstone, and those waies by which true gold is discerned from counterfaite, before hee bee compelled to take it for good and currant; and also for giuing his reasons why hee thinketh the same to bee false and forged: And if they will not suffer him to make triall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or no, but will needes haue him to take it for good gold, when not onely himselfe, but also diuers other skilfull Gold-Smiths doe greatly suspect, yea and are fully perswaded, that it is naught and counterfaite, and if he refuse to accept thereof in that manner, they should seeke to disgrace him with the <hi>Prince</hi> and people, and to accuse him of disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the State, and who wilfully refuseth to accept and acknowledge the <hi>Kings</hi> coyne for lawfull, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther these men doe not great wrong to that party, and whether it may not be prudently thought, that they haue a guilty conscience, and that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues suspect the said gold, not to bee indeed so good and currant, as in words they would pretend.</p>
   <p n="9">9 Now the case betweene mee and my Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries is farre worse then this. For they haue sought by false and fraudulent meanes, not onely to impose vpon the whole Christian world, a false and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait Catholike faith, for truely Catholike, but to slander and defame all those Catholikes, and my selfe in particular, who, for the reasons wee haue often
<pb facs="12"/>
propounded, refuse to accept thereof for Catholike, vntill it be better prooued so to be, and to condemne vs of temerity, and disobedience to the <hi>Sea Apostolike,</hi> yea and of flat heresie; and they would make the world beleeue, that wee are not true Catholikes, but <hi>heretickes disguised and masked vnder the vizard of Catholikes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">For so saith M. <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi> nu. <hi>19.</hi>
      </note> And albeit we doe publikely professe our selues to be true Catholikes, and doe submit all our writings to the iudgement and censure of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romane</hi> Church, and doe sincerely and solemnly protest to recall and recant foorthwith our errour, if wee haue committed any, as soone as it shall be made knowne vnto vs, that wee haue written any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse, yet they feare not to affirme, contrary to all iustice and charity, that all this our profession, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and protestation, is but <hi>a false luster and glosse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">So saith <hi>Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert</hi> c. <hi>17</hi> nu. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>26.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>to cast vpon our counterfaite ware of purpose to deceiue,</hi> and that <hi>it proceedeth from no other ground, but from a deepe dissimulation, or rather an artificiall and execrable hypocrisie to delude and deceiue Catholikes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="10">10 Neither will they suffer vs to examine by the true grounds of Catholike Religion their newly inuented Catholike faith, and to yeeld our reasons, which doe fully perswade vs, that their faith, which they pretend to be Catholike, is not ancient and true, but a newly inuented, and a false and forged Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, but they haue caused his <hi>Holinesse</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne our bookes, which in our iudgement doe plainly discouer their forgeries, and to forbid all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, as well learned as vnlearned to read them,
<pb facs="13"/>
without signifying vnto vs any one thing in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar which we haue written amisse, although wee haue often and earnestly requested to know the same: but all that they say or write, wee must, <hi>forsooth,</hi> without any further examination approoue for good and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant doctrine, albeit wee haue most plainely conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them of manifest fraude and falshood, in almost euery one of their arguments and answeres, which they haue brought to prooue their doctrine, in this point of the <hi>Popes</hi> spirituall authority to depose <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and to inflict temporall punishments, to be truely Catholike. All which being duely considered, what infinite wrong they haue done vs, it is too too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, and albeit they pretend true zeale to Catholike Religion, and to the <hi>Sea Apostolike,</hi> yet for my own part I cannot see, but that any prudent man may iustly suppose their zeale to bee blind, and not according to knowledge, but grounded vpon culpable or wilfull ignorance, and that they themselues suspect their owne conscience to bee eroneous, and their cause to be naught, and therefore would not haue it to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sifted and examined.</p>
   <p n="11">11 For seing that the nature of truth, being like to pure and perfect gold, is such, that the more it is examined, the more cleere and perspicuous it doth still appeare, and contrariwise falshood the more it is sifted, the absurdity thereof still sheweth it selfe more manifest; if my Aduersaries are in their consciences perswaded, as in wordes they professe, that they haue truth on their side, and that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb facs="13"/>
of spirituall Pastours to <hi>excommunicate</hi> vpon iust cause Christian Princes, to <hi>binde and loose,</hi> and <hi>to dispence in Oathes</hi> in generall, which all Catholikes acknowledge to be included in their spirituall power, be denyed in the late <hi>Oath</hi> of allegiance, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, or that their authoritie to depose <hi>Princes,</hi> which all men confesse to bee denyed in the <hi>Oath,</hi> bee cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, out of controuersie, and a cleere point of Catholike faith (for which two causes chiefly they cry out against the <hi>Oath,</hi> and condemne it for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, as containing in it more then temporall allegiance, to wit, a manifest denyall of Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authority,) why are they so much afraide to haue the matter charitably and sincerely debated by learned men? Why will they not suffer those Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, especially who are learned, and to whom the charge of soules is committed, and are able to discerne betwixt truth and falshood, betwixt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith and opinion,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> and who ought <hi>to bee alwaies readie</hi> and prepared, <hi>to satisfie euerie one that asketh them a reason of that</hi> faith <hi>which is in them,</hi> to reade such bookes as doe sincerely and exactly handle this controuersie, and all the difficulties on both sides, and doe plainely declare, in what particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all Christians are bound by the law of <hi>Christ,</hi> according to the true and approoued grounds of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.</note>
      <hi>to render to God and Caesar that which is their due?</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="12">12 Why doe they so shamefully abuse his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> by misinforming him, that his <hi>power to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>
to <hi>binde and loose,</hi> and <hi>to absolue from Oathes in generall,</hi> is denyed in the <hi>Oath,</hi> and that his power to depose <hi>Princes,</hi> which indeed the <hi>Oath</hi> denyeth, is a point of faith, and thereupon by vrging him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the <hi>Oath,</hi> as <hi>containing in it many things flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to faith and saluation,</hi> and to forbid those bookes of Catholike Writers, that doe plainly discouer their forgeries, and euidently conuince, that no such spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power, as they pretend, is denyed in the <hi>Oath,</hi> and that his power to depose <hi>Princes,</hi> which the <hi>Oath</hi> denyeth, is not a point of faith, but hath euer since the time of <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> the seuenth (for before his age the practise thereof was not heard of,<note place="margin">Onuphrius. l. <hi>4.</hi> de varia creat. Romani Pont.</note> as <hi>Onuphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> witnesseth) it hath euer beene a great controuersie betwixt <hi>Popes,</hi> and Christian <hi>Princes,</hi> and those Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes who haue fauoured either part: and, which is more extrauagant, by vrging him to commaund vnder paine of Censures the <hi>Author</hi> of those bookes <hi>to purge himselfe foorthwith,</hi> and yet not to signifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him any one crime either in generall, or in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of which he should purge himselfe, although hee hath very often most humbly and instantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested to know the same?</p>
   <p n="13">13 Why doth not Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> my chiefest Aduersarie, being accused by mee to his <hi>Holinesse,</hi> in publike writings of manifest fraudes, falshoods, corruptions, and calumnies, cleare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe all this time of such fowle imputations, which cannot but greatly blemish his honour, and quite discredite his cause in the vnderstanding of any iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious
<pb facs="14"/>
man? if in his conscience hee thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to bee guiltlesse, and that I haue falsly accused him, why doth hee not answere and iustifie himselfe, and shew to the world that I haue belyed him, that also thereby I may see my errour, and aske him pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like forgiuenesse, and bee penitent for the same? If hee see that I am innocent, why doth hee not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store my credit, which hee hath wrongfully taken away, and in plaine tearmes confesse, that hee was deceiued and mistaken in this controuersie, and imitating the example of famous Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract all that hee hath written amisse, especially to the hurt and disgrace of innocent men? Can any man of iudgement imagine, that hee being now so neere his graue, would take such paines to write e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery yeere some one or other little Treatise of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which neuerthelesse will not excuse him before God, from restoring the good name of them whom hee hath falsly defamed) and that hee would bee so carelesse to purge himselfe of such shamelesse crimes, which cannot but leaue his memory tainted with perpetuall infamy, if with his credit hee could cleere himselfe? And therefore, if he did sincerely consider the admonition hee gaue to other Prelates, vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of <hi>Pope Innocents</hi> examples, to examine their conscience carefully, whether it bee sound or erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, hee might truely haue iust cause to bee sore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide, and greatly to suspect, that howsoeuer hee maketh an outward shew of zeale, sanctitie, and deuotion, hee hath within an erroneous and <hi>seared
<pb facs="15"/>
conscience,</hi> for which hee must shortly, before the tribunall of God render a strict account.</p>
   <p n="14">14 All which their proceedings being duely considered, whether they are not manifest signes, that in their owne consciences they suspect the iustice of their cause, and doe plainely see, that they are not able to make good their newly inuented Catholike faith, and yet will still goe on to maintaine by fraude and violence, what they cannot by reason and argument, wherein also how much they discredit themselues &amp; their cause, how mightily they scandalize Catholike Religion, and make the <hi>Sea Apostolike</hi> odious to <hi>Princes</hi> and subiects, how egregiously they wrong and slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der innocent Catholikes, and how greatly they endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger their owne soules and others, I leaue to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any prudent and pious man.</p>
   <p n="15">15 Wherefore my chiefe drift, <hi>good Reader,</hi> in this my answere to M. <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> is <hi>first,</hi> to keepe and maintaine entire and inuiolate the puritie of true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith and Religion, which is greatly defiled, not onely by impugning true and vndoubted articles of faith, but also by forging and defending false arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles for true. <hi>Secondly,</hi> to defend my innocency (which as long as I haue a pen to write, or a tongue to speake, I will, God willing, not bee afraide to maintaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any man whatsoeuer, that shall falsly accuse me and my doctrine of heresie) and to make knowne my sincere proceeding in handling this great and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous controuersie, which concerneth our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience due to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caesar,</hi> and the fraudulent and
<pb facs="15"/>
corrupt dealing of my Aduersaries, who by fraud and violence seeke to afflict, intangle, and disturbe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of scrupulous and vnlearned Catholikes, and to nourish in their hearts such dangerous speculations, which without manifest treason can neuer bee put in practise. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> to make manifest to all men that the doctrine for the Popes power to depose <hi>Princes</hi> is not certaine, vnquestionable, and a point of faith, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doubtfull, vncertaine, and at the most onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable: and consequently, that it cannot bee practised by the Pope, or any other whatsoeuer, without mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest iniury to the Prince, who is in lawfull possession of his Kingdome, of which the Pope vnder pretence onely of a probable power or title seeketh by his sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to depriue him; for that according to the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued rule of the law, and grounded vpon naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>In causa dubia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">De regulis Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in <hi>6.</hi> &amp; ff. de regulis Iuris regula, In pari causa.</note> siue incerta <hi>melior &amp; potior est condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio possidentis. In a doubtfull</hi> or disputable <hi>case the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the possessour is to bee preferred.</hi> And therefore, as well obserueth Fa. <hi>Lessius</hi> in his <hi>Singleton</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Par.</hi> 2. <hi>nu.</hi> 38.</note>, <hi>potestas, quae non omnino certa, sed probabilis, non potest esse fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>A power, which is not altogether certaine, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, cannot be a ground or foundation, whereby immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one may be punished, and be depriued of his right and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, but such a power must be most certaine, and not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> or disputable, &amp;c.</p>
   <p n="16">16 So that there is a great difference to be made, for as much as concerneth practise, betwixt a power onely probable, which tendeth to fauour, and is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to none, and which is penall and preiudiciall to a
<pb facs="16"/>
third person, who is depriued thereby of some thing which he lawfully possesseth. For it is most certaine, and approoued by all Diuines, that one may practise a probable power, to vse <hi>Lessius</hi> words, <hi>Quando agitur de fauore &amp; beneficio, &amp; nemo cogitur, nemo iure propinquo seu in re obtento spoliatur, sed potestas quae non omnino certa sed probabilis, non potest esse fundamentum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>When it is treated of a fauour and benefit, and no man is forced, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, no man is spoiled of his next right, or which hee posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth indeed, but a power which is not altogether certaine, but probable, cannot be a ground or foundation, whereby immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately one may be punished, or depriued of his right and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, &amp;c.</hi> And for this cause my Aduersaries, knowing right well that if they should once admit that this power of the Pope is onely probable, they must con-consequently grant, that it is <hi>merus titulus sine re,</hi> and can neuer bee lawfully put in practise by any Pope, Prince, or subiect whatsoeuer, haue so much laboured to conuince out of all lawes humane and diuine, that this power is not onely probable, but most certaine, and a cleare point of faith. But how shamefully they haue spent their labour in vaine, and what friuolous and fallacious arguments they haue brought vnder pretence of spirituall good, to make <hi>Soueraigne Princes</hi> (whom all the ancient Fathers with uniforme consent acknowledge to bee supreame on earth, and next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God in temporals) to bee in temporals subiect to the Pope, and that the more they striue to make their doctrine in this point to be certaine, and of faith, the more they shew it still to be lesse probable, and to bee
<pb facs="16"/>
inuented and maintained onely in fauour of the Pope without sufficient grounds, thou shalt see it, <hi>good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> in this Treatise made as cleare and manifest, as the light at noone-day.</p>
   <p n="17">17 Onely I must desire thy patience and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for my often repeating the selfe same things, which may seeme to some to bee both superfluous and tedious, but to me for satisfaction chiefly of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Reader, it seemed very necessary, especially, for that the chiefe state of the controuersie depends thereon, and yet my Aduersaries will scarse take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, yea, and are not ashamed to affirme, that I doe not teach any such things, although they haue beene by mee very often inculcated. As among other things, for example sake, albeit I haue in all my bookes so often repeated that distinction betwixt the <hi>directiue</hi> and <hi>coerciue</hi> power, betwixt <hi>commanding, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning,</hi> or <hi>imposing,</hi> and <hi>inflicting, punishing,</hi> or <hi>disposing,</hi> and that I doe so often and so expresly affirme, that spirituall Pastours haue by the institution of Christ authority to command, enioyne, and impose tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and coporall penalties, but to inflict them, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish temporally, and to dispose of temporall things, onely by the consent and grant of temporall Princes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 258.</note> yet Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his <hi>Schulckenius</hi> is not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to auerre, that <hi>Widdrington</hi> denieth the Pope <hi>to haue authority to command temporall</hi> Princes <hi>in temporals in order to spirituall good,</hi> and therevpon taxeth him of teaching flat heresie; and the most that M. <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> prooueth in this his <hi>Replie,</hi> is, as you shall see, that spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb facs="17"/>
Pastours may, for the necessitie of the Church, and the good of soules, command, enioyne, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose temporall and corporall afflictions, as fasting, almes deedes, vsing of haire-cloth, and the like, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no Catholike maketh doubt: And therefore I thought it necessarie to inculcate, as often as occasion should require the aforesaid distinction, it being the maine marke to which the greatest part of all my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries arguments, and of my answeres doe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally tend, and whereon the whole state of the Controuersie betwixt me and them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Popes power to depose <hi>Princes,</hi> and to dispose of all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, doth chiefly depend.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>