<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST WELCOME AND expected Pattern and Patron of Vertue and Goodnesse, the hopefull deserver of all the Costs and Honours which the Noble Fellowship and Brother-hood of Clothworkers and ample Love of the whole City, in full and generous Bounty be∣stow upon him, the Right Honourable and Judicious ROBERT PARKHVRST, Lord Major of the famous Ci∣ty of London.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5206_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73300</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23808</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5206</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST WELCOME AND expected Pattern and Patron of Vertue and Goodnesse, the hopefull deserver of all the Costs and Honours which the Noble Fellowship and Brother-hood of Clothworkers and ample Love of the whole City, in full and generous Bounty be∣stow upon him, the Right Honourable and Judicious ROBERT PARKHVRST, Lord Major of the famous Ci∣ty of London.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of fame and honour: or The noble accomplish'd solemnity : full of cost, art and state, at the inauguration and establishment of the true worthy and right nobly minded Robert Parkhurst, into the right honourable office of Lord Maior of London. The particularities of every invention in all the pageants, shewes and triumphs both by water and land, are here following fully set downe, being all performed by loves, liberall costs, and charges of the right worshipfull and worthy Brother-hood of the Cloth-workers the 29 of October 1634. Written by Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Gosson, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST WELCOME AND expected Pattern and Patron of Vertue and Goodnesse, the hopefull deserver of all the Costs and Honours which the Noble Fellowship and Brother-hood of <hi>Clothworkers</hi> and ample Love of the whole City, in full and generous Bounty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow upon him, the Right Honourable and Judicious <hi>ROBERT PARKHVRST,</hi> Lord <hi>Major</hi> of the famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>RIght Honourable Patron, to your state</l>
      <l>In duty I these <hi>Triumphs</hi> dedicate,</l>
      <l>Wherein your Worthy <hi>Brother-hood</hi> Approves</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Greatnesse</hi> and <hi>goodnes</hi> of their <hi>minds,</hi> and <hi>loves,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Their true affections and their liberall charge,</l>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <l>They have most bountifull exprest at large,</l>
      <l>And London in these Triumphs is renownd</l>
      <l>Above all cities in the worlds wide Round:</l>
      <l>For no Kings Deputy, or Magistrate</l>
      <l>Is with such pompous state inaugurate,</l>
      <l>As Londons Mayor is, which most plainly showes</l>
      <l>The Kings illustrious greatnesse whence it flowes;</l>
      <l>To whom then should my dedication run,</l>
      <l>But unto you, for whom these things were done?</l>
      <l>Your power is Londons watch-towre to espie,</l>
      <l>Dangers far off, and perills that are nigh:</l>
      <l>Your foresight must see much, and it is plaine,</l>
      <l>Millions of eyes will looke on you againe,</l>
      <l>For envy and detraction pries and stares</l>
      <l>T'assault true honour, and t'intrap in snares</l>
      <l>All that is good, for it is manifest,</l>
      <l>That envie alwaies feeds upon the best.</l>
      <l>This citie (the Kings Chamber) must be kept</l>
      <l>Cleane for his use, from foule pollution swept,</l>
      <l>And sure, that <hi>power</hi> that hath you thus advanc'd,</l>
      <l>To be thus honour'd, lov'd and countenanc'd,</l>
      <l>Will ever be your <hi>portion,</hi> and <hi>content,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And governe you in this your government.</l>
      <l>That you (at helme) a steddy course may steare</l>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <l>Twixt <hi>Justice,</hi> and blest <hi>Mercy,</hi> many a yeare</l>
      <l>Especially in this your greatest state,</l>
      <l>Let <hi>Hospitality</hi> still keepe your Gate;</l>
      <l>And <hi>Liberality,</hi> with <hi>welcome</hi> stand,</l>
      <l>To greet men with a free and open hand,</l>
      <l>Then Muses, Graces, Arts, the praise shall sing</l>
      <l>Of you (my Lord) Lieutenant to my King.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>