<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5209_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13648.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5209</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certayne sermons : appoynted by the Quenes Maiestie, to be declared and read, by all persones, vycars, and curates, euery Sonday and holy daye,in theyr churches: and by her Graces aduyse perused [and] ouersene, for the better vnderstandyng of the simple people. Newly imprynted in partes, accordynge as is mencioned in the booke of Commune prayers</title>
                 <author>Church of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 <publisher>Cawood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jugge, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsydering howe necessary it is, that the worde of GOD, which is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foode of the soule, and that moste excellent lyght that we muste walke by, in this our moste daungerous pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, should at all conuenient tymes be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto the people, that therby they may bothe learne theyr duetie towardes God, theyr Prynce, and theyr neighbours, accordyng to the mynde of the holy ghoste, expressed in the scriptures: And also to auoyde the manifolde enormities, whiche hearetofore by false doctrine, haue crepte into the Churche of God: and howe that all they whiche are appoynted ministers, haue not the gyft of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng, sufficiently to instruct the people, which is commytted vnto them, whereof great inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences myght ryse, and ignoraunce styll be mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, yf some honeste remedye be not speedely founde and prouyded. The Quenes moste excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. Maiestie, tenderynge the foule health of her louyng subiectes, and the quietynge of theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, in the chiefe and pryncypall poyntes of Christian Religion, and wyllyng also by the true settyng foorth, and pure declaryng of Gods word, which is the principall guyde and leader vnto all godlynesse and vertue, to expell and dryue aware, aswell all corrupt, vicious, and vngodly lyuyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, as also erronious and poysoned doctrines, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to superfficion and Idolatry: hath by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyse of her moste honourable comis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> her discharge in this behalfe, caused a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melies, which heretofore was sette <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>moste louynge Brother, a Prince of moste worthy memorye Edward the syxt, to be prynted a newe, wherein are conteyned certaine wholsome and godly exhortacions, to moue the people to honour and worshyppe almyghty God, and diligently to serue hym, euery one accordynge to theyr degree, state, and vocation. All whiche Homelies her Maiestie commaundeth and strayghtly chargeth all persons, vycars, curates, and all other hauyng spirituall cure, euery Sonday and holy day in the yere, at the ministryng of the holy communion, or if there be no Communion ministred that day, yet after the Gospell and Crede, in suche order and place as is appoynted in the booke of Common prayers, to reade and declare to theyr paryshyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners playnely and distinctly one of the sayde Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies in such order as they stande in the booke, except there be a Sermon according as it is inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the boke of her hyghnesse Iniunctions, and then for that cause onely, and for none other, the readyng of the sayde Homelye to be differred vnto the next Sonday or holy day folowyng. And whē the foresayde booke of Homelies is read ouer, her Maiesties pleasure is, that the same be repeated and read agayne, in such lyke sort, as was before prescrybed. Furthermore, her hyghnesse cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that notwithstandynge this order, the sayde Ecclesiasticall persons shall reade her Maiesties Iniunctions at such tymes and in suche order as is in the booke thereof appoynted. And that the Lordes prayer, the Articles of the fayth, and the ten commaundementes, be openly readde vnto the people, as in the sayde Iniunctions is specified,
<pb facs="3"/>that all her people of what degree or condicion so euer they be, maye learne howe to Inuocate and call vpon the name of Godde, knowe what duetie they owe both to God &amp; man: So that they maye pray, belieue, and worke accordyng to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whyle they shall lyue heare, and after this lyfe be with him that with his bloud hath bought vs all. To whom with the Father and the holy ghost, be al honor and glory for euer. AMEN.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>