<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVER END AND worthily honoured Father in God, IOHN by Diuine Pro∣uidence, L. Bishop of LONDON, Grace and Peace be multiplied, with all the complements of true Essentiall Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Marshall, Hamlett</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S521_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12788</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S521</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVER END AND worthily honoured Father in God, IOHN by Diuine Pro∣uidence, L. Bishop of LONDON, Grace and Peace be multiplied, with all the complements of true Essentiall Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Marshall, Hamlett</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and gracious sermon preached at Paules Crosse, by that famous and iudicious diuine, Iohn Spenser, D. of Diuinity, and late president of Corpus Chr: Coll: in Oxford. Published for the benefite of Christs vineyard, by H.M</title>
                 <author>Spenser, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rand, Samuel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 50 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVER END AND worthily honoured Father in <hi>God,</hi> IOHN <hi>by Diuine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,</hi> L. Bishop of LONDON, <hi>Grace and Peace be multiplied, with</hi> all the complements of true <hi>Essentiall Happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this Heauenly Sermon, (Right Reuerend and most worthy <hi>Moece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> of Learning) I may iustly compare to <hi>Iohn the Baptist,</hi> of whom Iesus giueth this commendation, that hee was a burning and a shining light, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.35. for hee was a
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Iohn</hi> indeede, a faithfull dispenser of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of God; in whom the grace of God was exceedingly resplendent, who burned with zeale &amp; loue towards Gods Vineyard; and was while he liued, such a shining light in the house of God, in respect of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, learning, piety and godlinesse, that he was reuerenced of all good men, admired of such as excell in iudicious learning; yea, all mē of what sort or condition soeuer, which knew him, did worthily afforde him the testimony of a milde and louing spirit. Oh, what admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable height of knowledge, and depth of iudgement dwelled within the lowly minde of this true humble man, great in all mens eyes except his owne! with what grauity, &amp; maiesty of speech did his tongue vtter hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly mysteries, which many a Christian eare hath heard, with vnspeakable ioy and comfort! Oh, how did he empty himselfe to fill others! how did hee waste and consume himselfe, to inlighten that flocke which was committed to his chargel yea, as it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true goodnes to communicate it selfe to others; so was it this good mans endeuor,
<pb facs="3"/>that as he was <hi>Lux illuminata,</hi> inlightned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with knowledge and grace from aboue, so he might be <hi>Lux illuminans,</hi> the instrument and seruant of God to inlighten others in the wayes of their peace, to the glory of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Christ, and the soules health of the lambs of his little flocke. For mine owne part I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it freely, that as I was to him vnder God most of al indebted for my liuelihood in this world: so for matter of learning &amp; light of knowledge (if I haue any) it was especially drawn from his fountain, &amp; deriued from the splendor of his goodnes; yea, while I liued as it were vnder his roofe (being his Minister for the space of fiue yeares) what gaine I got by attending his voyce, how much I haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by penning and obseruing his precious meditations, and what a blessing I haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from the haruest of his honest, religious, and vnblameable conuersation; those which knew mee before, and haue been acquainted with me since, can truly testifie to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that <hi>me mihi meliorem reddidit; quam accepit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherefore now to shew my thankfulnes in part, and the reuerend respect I deseruedly
<pb facs="4"/>bore him, I haue vndertaken (though vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all others) to publish such of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned labours as he left behind him: and which I am sure he rather penned for his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vse, then with any purpose to haue them printed eyther before or after his death: for though by all possible means this blessed mā was euer ready to manifest his good will to the benefite of the Church, and behoofe of posterity; yet was hee so lowly in his owne eyes, so cast downe in his owne conceite, and his labours of such little esteeme in his own sight, that he held nothing he did, worthy of the worlds view, though his paines were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so great in the composing thereof; yea this of mine owne knowledge I dare affirme, that such was his humility and modesty in that kind, that when he had taken extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paines, together with a most iudicious and complete Diuine in our Church, about the compiling of a learned and profitable worke now extant, yet would hee not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to put his hand to it, though hee had a speciall hand in it, and therfore it fell out, that <hi>tulitalter honores.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>Concerning this particular Sermon, which is his fathers <hi>postbumus,</hi> and presents it selfe in the first place to the world before the rest, which by Gods grace shall follow after, (though of it selfe it deserues allowance, and binds dependency vnto it) yet am I bolde to recommend the protection thereof to your Lordshippe, and to intitle it to your Honours name vpon due deliberation, and diuers iust causes; as first, in regard of the vnthankefulnes of this inconsiderate age of ours, which is more willing to entertaine euery idle Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet and vaine toy that fond inuention can excogitate, then to embrace such laudable enterprises which further the Kingdome of God, or perswade the truth of religiō among the sonnes of men: amongst which vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full monsters, some are such Atheists and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enemies of Gods truth, that they bark at them, <hi>sicut Cerberus in Stygio;</hi> some are such A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians, affecters of nouelty, that they will hisse at them, <hi>sicut anguis in herba,</hi> and looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>squint at euery occurrēt that fits not their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: and there is an <hi>ignauum pecus,</hi> which them selues stand idle in the market place al the day
<pb facs="5"/>long, and yet with forked tongues will they not spare to carpe at each monument of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in a preiudicate opinion reiect &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace their paines, who shall but crosse the path of their wicked delights; wherefore I much desired (my Honourable L.) that this worthy Sermon might find such an happy Patrone as your selfe, being assured, that pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vnder your Honourable name, it might be sheelded from the iniurie and enuy of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, superstitious and contentious persons, and might find with men of sound iudgemēt the freer acceptation, and with men of great place the grauer consideration, and with men of all sorts the better intertainment when it comes abroad. And further, though I know your Lordshippe delights not to haue your name diuulged in printed papers, yet I doubt not but you will bee pleased to patronize this poore Orphan, and suffer it willingly to passe vnder your Honors protection, and that for it own sake, being a discourse of Gods Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, a part whereof Almighty God hath made you an happy ouerseer: but especially for his fathers sake, whom while hee liued,
<pb facs="5"/>you loued as your owne life, and tendered as that which was neerest and dearest vnto you: oh, how did the loadstone of your loue euer draw him after your selfe! so that in the same Vniuersity you were Students together, in the same house you were seruants &amp; Chaplaines together, in the same city you were neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Preachers together: to the same colledges where you were first Students, you were aduanced together, and I doubt not, but in the same kingdome (though hee be gone first) through Gods mercy you shall shine as starres together: and therefore, seeing (good my Lord) he sleepeth, but you are waking, he is in heauen, and you on earth; what part or parcell of his writings can challenge as of right, protection frō any man that liues, saue only your self, who haue so truely loued him in his life, and so redoubled your affection vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in his, since his death, which his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, constant, and truly sorrowfull widdow with her fatherlesse children doe finde and freely confes, powring out incessāt praiers to almighty God for you and yours? And how can you want the blessings of heauen, which
<pb facs="6"/>haue the widdow and fatherlesse to intercede for you vpon earth? Oh giue mee leaue to say of your Lordship, concerning this, without suspition of flattery, as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> writes of <hi>Origen</hi> in his preface before his booke vpon the Canticles, <hi>In ceteris libris omnes alios vicerit, in Cantico Canticorum seipsum vicit:</hi> So in other of your paynfull works you goe beyond o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but in this worke of piety you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede your selfe. But not to trespasse too far vpon your Lordships patience, seing thus the God of mercy hath moued your heart, sincerely to affect the Author of this Sermon, and next vnder God to regard his widdow and fatherlesse children; let me presume to make this sute further vnto you, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of this the liuing Image of his soule, the first fruit of his published labours, that you being a Reuerend father of the church, would giue it your blessing before it goe abroad, yea that blessing which <hi>Iacob</hi> sent with his sonnes into <hi>Egypt, Gen.</hi> 43.14. God Almighty giue you mercy in the sight of the man; in the sight of the proud man, that you may make him humble; in the sight of the poore man,
<pb facs="6"/>that you may make him content; in the sight of the stubborne man, that you may make him yeeld; in the sight of the penitent man, that you may binde vp and powre wine and oyle into his wounds; in the sight of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren man, that you may make him fruitfull; in the sight of euery man, that you may touch their consciences, and winne their soules; but especially in the sight of our <hi>Ioseph,</hi> our <hi>Iesus,</hi> who euer so blesse your Lordship, that your waies may bee prosperous, your sorrowes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, your comforts manie, your vertues emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, your conscience quiet, your life holie, your death comfortable, your election sure, and your saluation certaine. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humbly deuoted, Hamlett Marshall.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>