<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY DEARE MOTHER Mrs. HELLEN PIERSON.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5223_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72251</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12897.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5223</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY DEARE MOTHER Mrs. HELLEN PIERSON.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The conditions of Christianity: or, The termes upon which Christ will be followed : A necessary consideration for them that otherwise would bee apt to take up religion upon trust, and only keep company with Christ a while for fashion sake. By Mr. Christopher Harvey, sometime minister of Gods word at Bunbury in Cheshire</title>
                 <author>Harvey, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 76 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY DEARE MOTHER M<seg rend="sup">rs.</seg> HELLEN PIERSON.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost deare, and most worthy to bee most deare, Mother, I remember a speech which diverse yeares a goe, fell from you, peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then but casually: when looking upon a booke that was Dedicated by a Sonne to his Mother, you said, you did hope one day to see the like from mee. It may bee your
<pb facs="3"/> words were then more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to your desire then your expectation: yet you see them in some sort ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled now. This only is the difference, that what he publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed was penned by himselfe, but that which I present you with, is no otherwise mine, than it was yours before, being part of the fruit of the labours of my reverend Father you former husband: which being by you, with the rest of his pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers, reserved for my use: is now at last come to my hand by the much lamented death of your late reverend Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Master <hi>Tho. Pierson</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Two such Husbands and Fathers few women and their sonnes have. I should esteeme it not a little happinesse, if I
<pb facs="3"/> might be a meanes to adde but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alfe that credit to their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, that you did comfort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o their lives. For the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the penne-man of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ittle Treatise, to expatiate in his praises would bee neither seemely for mee who am his sonne, nor seasonable now when already he hath had his rest in peace these foure and thirtie yeares &amp; upward, nor sutable to the proportion of so small a volume, unto which even this may seeme too large an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. For the Treatise it selfe, such as it is I received it from you, and returne it to you and thorough your hands commend it to the use of all them that desire to bee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, in an earnest, not in word and tongue only, but in
<pb facs="4"/> deed and truth. So humbly craving what I know, I have your daily prayers for blessings upon me and mine, I rest though much unworthy, yet most desirous to be still,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your every way observant and obedient Sonne, Christopher Harvey.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>