<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           <author>G., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5237_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72187</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12010.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5237</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 <author>G., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Heavens speedie hue and cry sent after lust and murther : Manifested upon the suddaine apprehending of Thomas Shearwood, and Elizabeth Evans, whose manner of lives, death, and free confessions, are heere expressed. Also some new additions, concerning the man that was tide to the gibbeit, with a discovery of those places where such kind of lude people haunt and resort unto, and by what signes and tokens you may discover them: disclosed by this Sherwood a little before his death. Who were executed the one upon the 14. and the other on the 17. of this moneth of April 1635. neere to the place where the facts were committed, and he now hangeth in chaines at Ring-Crosse. Written by H.G. their daily uisiter at the time of their imprisonment, and severall dayes of execution. Published by authority</title>
                 <author>Goodcole, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>I Haveresumed my Pen which I resolved in this Nature for
ever to be silent: But the Common good, and preservation
of my Countries welfare, incites me unto this officious ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
As one that standeth Centinell in the Night unto
whom Fidelity and Trust is reposed, and the safety of the whole
<hi>Army</hi> dependeth: (Even so am I) to discover the private and
suddaine approaching of the Enemies. Like a Watchman to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
all commers in and out, into the Gates of the City, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile
pernicious passengers, which dayes and nights uncessantly
passe through the Streets, and in the secret corners of the same
privily lurke, and watch an opportunity to <hi>cozen, rob,</hi> and
<hi>murther.</hi> I presume not to instruct the <hi>prudent</hi> and <hi>wise,</hi> that
were absurde and ridiculous: But the Levell of my intention is
to make the vulgar <hi>Ignorants</hi> so wise, as to walke warily and
circumspectly; which plaine path they may knowingly see, and
discerne by this sequent discovery of such notorious offenders,
that live upon the spoyles of such <hi>Passengers,</hi> and <hi>Travellers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorting
up unto <hi>London</hi> upon their necessary affaires. A new
kind of invented wickednesse, and fearefull mischiefe, but I
hope by Gods mercy, and the late exemplary Justice, strangled
in the birth, is the Narration of <hi>Country Tom,</hi> and <hi>Besse</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry,</hi>
so termed by those of their base disposition. A woman, Oh
shame unto her modest tender Sexe! to become a setter, or set on
such a brazen face, that upon a man unknowne unto her, shee
seazeth in the open Streets, and with her deceitfull smiles, and
salutes, so inchants, and incaptivates, and leads him unto <hi>slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
Like a decoy Ducke, shee is alone going abroad, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
returning, associated with multitudes homeward: The bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
shee strikes up, and goeth before, to a secret appointed
place, upon whom unawares, to the seduced person, attendeth
a mercilesse strong <hi>Theefe,</hi> and most barbarous cruell <hi>Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi>
that at once strikes and slayes: of whose cunning practices,
secret snares, and subtil wiles I labour to give all people a light
and true insight; <hi>God Almighty</hi> give it a blessing unto his good
pleasure and thy benefit, unto whom I am thy true professed
friend during the time of my mortality.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>