<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the faithfull Reader, Health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5293_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72547</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15514.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5293</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the faithfull Reader, Health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three godly treatises : 1. To comfort the sicke. 2. Against the feare of death. 3. Of the resurrection. Written in French by Mr. I.D. L'Espine, Peacher of the word of God in Angeers. And translated into English by S. Veghelman</title>
                 <author>L'Espine, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Bankworth, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 196, 2, 197-334 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="90"/>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Ecclesiasticus 18.</hi>
         </bibl>
         <p>Take physicke before sicknesse, and examine thy selfe before iudgment, and thou shalt finde pardon in the presence of God.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Reuelation 3.</hi>
         </bibl>
         <p>If thou doest not watch, I will come vnto thee as a theefe, and thou shalt not know at what houre I will come vnto thee.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Reuelation 16.</hi>
         </bibl>
         <p>Happy is hee that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, to the end that hee walke not naked, and that his shame bee not seene.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Matthew 24. Luke 12.</hi>
         </bibl>
         <p>Bee ready, for the sonne of man will come in an houre that you thinke not.</p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <pb n="165" facs="90"/>
   <head>To the faithfull <hi>Reader,</hi> Health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendly Reader, take in good part this present com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the which I haue here written for the good and profit of euery one that hath the feare of God, to make vse of it at his neede, when it shall please the Lord to call him; But be aduertised (that thou maist vse it well) that these three letters B.S.N. the first signifieth, brother to a man, the second sister to a woman, and the third, that you must name the partie by their proper name. For it ought not to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with names of worldly honour and dignity, but to oppose it selfe against Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="166" facs="91"/>
in the name of the Lord, it ought to be named by the proper name which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at the holy Sacrament of Baptisme. Which doing thou shalt obey vnto God, whom I beseech to be fauourable vnto thee, at the day of his comming. ({inverted ⁂})</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>