<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>NEITHER TO THE BEST, NOR yet to the worst; but to the common sort of WOMEN.</title>
           <author>Swetnam, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S529_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13240</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23534</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S529</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>NEITHER TO THE BEST, NOR yet to the worst; but to the common sort of WOMEN.</title>
                 <author>Swetnam, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The araignment of levvd, idle, froward, and vnconstant women : or the vanitie of them, choose you whether. With a commendation of wise, vertuous and honest women. Pleasant for married men, profitable for young men, and hurtfull to none</title>
                 <author>Swetnam, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Archer, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>NEITHER TO THE BEST, NOR yet to the worst; but to the common sort of WOMEN.</head>
   <p>MVsing with my selfe being idle, and hauing little ease to passe the time withal; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a great choller against some women, I mean more then one; And so in the ruffe of my fury, taking my pen in hand to beguile the time withall; indeed I might haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed my selfe to better vse, then in such an idle busines, and better it were to pocket vp a pelting iniury, then to intangle my selfe with such vermine: for this I know, that because wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are women, therefore many of them will doe that in an howre, which they many times will repent all their whole life time after; yet for any iniury which I haue reccyued of thē, the more I consider of it, the lesse I esteem of the same. Yet perhaps some may say vnto me, that I haue sought for honey, &amp; caught the Bee by the tayle, or that I haue bin bit or stung with some of these waspes, otherwise I could neuer haue beene expert in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying their qualities, for the mother would neuer haue sought her daughter in the Ouen, but that shee was there her selfe. Indeed I must confesse, I haue been a traueller this thirty &amp; odde yeeres, and many trauellers liue in disdaine of women; the reason is, for that their affections are so poysoned with the haynous euils of vnconstant women, which they happen to bee acquainted with in their trauels: for it doth so cloy their sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks,
<pb facs="5"/>
that they censure bardly of women euer afterwards: wronged men will not be tongue-tyed: therefore if you doe ill, you must not thinke to heare well; for although the world bee bad, yet it is not come to that passe, that men should beare with all the bad conditions that are in some women.</p>
   <p>I know I shall be bitten by many, because I touch many: but before I goe any further, let mee whisper one word in your eares, and that is this; whatsoeuer you thinke privately, I wish you to conceale it with silence, lest in starting up to find fault, you proue your selues guilty of these monstrous accusations, which are here following against some women: &amp; those which spurne, if they feele themselues touched, proue themselues stark fooles in bewraying their galled backs to the world: for this booke toucheth no sort of women, but such as when they heare it, will goe about to reproue it: for although in some part of this booke, I trip at your heeles, yet I will stay you by the hand, so that you shall not fall further then you are willing; although I deale with you after the manner of a shrow, which cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise ease her curst heart but by her vnhappy tongue: If I be too earnest, beare with me a little, for my meaning is not to speake much of those that are good, &amp; I shall speake too little of those that are naught; but yet I will not altogether condemn the bad; but hoping to better the good by the naughty examples of the bad: for there is no woman so good, but hath one idle part or other in her which may be amended; for the clearest Riuer that is, hath some durt in the bottome: Iewels are all precious, but yet they are not all of one price, nor all of one ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: gold is not all of one picture, no more are women all of one disposition; women are all necessary euills, and yet not all giuen to wickednesse, and yet many so bad, that in my conceit, if I should speake the worst that I know by some women, I should
<pb facs="5"/>
make their eares glow that heare mee, and my tongue would blister to report it: but it is a great discredite for a man to be accounted for a scold, for scolding is the maner of shromes; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had rather answere them with silence which find fault, then striue to win the Cucking-stoole frō them. Now me thinks I heare some curious Dames giue their rash iudgements, &amp; say that I hauing no wit, descant vpon womē which haue more wit then men. To answere you again, If I belie you, iudge me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; but if I speake the truth I shall be the better belieued an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time: and if I had wrote neuer so well, it is vnpossible to please all, and if neuer so ill, yet I shall please some. Let it bee well or ill, I looke for no prayse for my labor; I am weined from my mothers teat, and therfore neuer more to bee fed with her pap: wherefore say what you will, for I will follow my own vein in vnfolding euery pleat, and shewing euery wrinckle of a womans disposition, and yet I will not made so farre ouer the shooes, but that I may returne drie, nor so far in, but that I may easily escape out, and yet for all that, I must confesse my selfe to be in a fault, and that I haue offended you beyond sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, for it is hard to giue a sufficient recompence for a slaunder; and yet here after, if by no meanes I cannot obtaine your fauour to be one of your Pulpit-men, yet you cannot deny me to be one of your Parish; and therefore if you please but to place me in the body of the Church hereafter, you shall find my deuotion so great towards you, as he that kneeleth at the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell dore: for I wrote this booke with my hand, but not with my heart.</p>
   <p>Indeed, when I first began to write this booke, my wits were gone a wool-gathering, in so much that in a maner forgetting my selfe, and so in the rough of my fury, I vowed for euer to be an open enemy vnto women; but when my fury was a little
<pb facs="6"/>
past, I began to consider the blasphemy of this infamous booke against your sects; I then tooke my pen, and cut him in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty peeces, and had it not been for hurting my selfe, I would haue cut my own fingers which held my pen: and furthermore for penance, I do craue that my selfe may be a Iudge against my selfe; but yet assure your selues, of all euils I will choose the least; wherefore I choose rather to beare a fagot, then burn by the fagot; you may perceyue the wind is changed into another dore, and that I begin to be sea-sicke, and yet not past halfe a mile on the salt water, and that my mouth hath vttered that in my fury, which my heart neuer thought, and therefore I confesse that my tongue hath gone beyond my wits; for I do sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, that the sauce which I haue made, is too sharpe for your dyet, and the flowers which I haue gathered, are too strong for your noses: but if I had brought little dogs from <hi>Iceland,</hi> or fine glasses from <hi>Venice,</hi> then I am sure that you would either haue wooed me to haue them, or wished to see them. But I will here conclude this first Epistle, praying you with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to heare the rest: for if I offend you at the first, I will make you amends at the last: and so I leaue you to him, whose seate is in Heauen, and whose footestoole is the Earth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the way of Honesty,
Ioseph Swetnam.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>