<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the Ouerseers of the Church of ANGEERS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S5293_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72547</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15514.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S5293</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the Ouerseers of the Church of ANGEERS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three godly treatises : 1. To comfort the sicke. 2. Against the feare of death. 3. Of the resurrection. Written in French by Mr. I.D. L'Espine, Peacher of the word of God in Angeers. And translated into English by S. Veghelman</title>
                 <author>L'Espine, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Bankworth, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 196, 2, 197-334 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶To the Ouerseers of the Church of <hi>ANGEERS.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Esus Christ not without cause amongst those things which he commands vs to require of God in our praiers, doth enioyne vs to demaund that hee leade vs not into temptation: for, regarding on the one side the weaknes &amp; infirmity which is in vs, &amp; on the other the enuy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire which the diuell hath of our ruine, the diligence &amp; pursuit which he vseth to procure it, and finally the subtilties, meanes and practises that he holds to attaine thereunto, incessantly search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for to deuoure vs like vnto a roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lyon rauening after his prey: we haue great neede to stand vpon our gard, and to watch and pray for to preuent his ambuscadoes and surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, to the end we bee not caught in his nets. And for as much as the last assaultes which an enemie giues to those that are besieged, are
<pb facs="6"/>
ordinarily the hardest &amp; most furious, we must prepare betime, and prouide our selues (during our life) of those things which shall be necessary for vs at our death, for to arme our selues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the great assaults which then the diuell makes to cary vs away. knowing wel that if he faile at that time the place is lost for him, and that it behoues him shamefully to raise his siege, without hope to come thither any more. Now the weapons &amp; engins wherewith we should principally furnish our selues, are faith, and the word of God; faith by the which we apprehend the grace of God, and the iustice of Iesus Christ, for to serue vs for a buckler and target, to couer and defend vs from the flames of the enemy. And the word for to assault him vigorously, and to cast him on the ground, as did Iesus Christ. For there are but these two means by the which we are able to withstand or repulse his assaults, and carry away a full victory ouer him. Therfore is it (my brethren)
<pb facs="6"/>
that I haue gathered you out of the Scripture some notes, proper for to comfort &amp; strengthen you against the tentations, wherewith you may be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulted at the point of death. But I pray you not to stay till that howre, to take them, &amp; to arme your selues with them; doing as do the negligent Captaines, who stay to furnish the places which are committed vnto them, with things needfull for to keepe them, till they are compassed and enuironed with men of war, wherby it often hapneth, that fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themselues vnprouided of means needfull for to defend themselues, and so finding themselues astonied, they presently forsake them, &amp; easily yeeld vnto the enemy. But by the example of the Ant and the Bee, make your proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in due time and season, to the end that when the winter comes you may be wel prouided of all that shalbe need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full easily to passe &amp; sustaine the rigor thereof. Aboue all, I pray you to note in the treaty which I send you those pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="7"/>
which are therein alledged against rashnes and presumption. For they are the two principall tentations which the diuell ordinarily employeth for to ouerthrow vs: representing before our eyes, either the multitude &amp; greatnesse of our sins, for to cast vs headlong into a mistrust of the mercy of God: or our vertues and good works, for to raise vs vp vnto presumption and vaine confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence therin. These are the two ropes (saith <hi>S. Augustin</hi>) which this tormēter doth continually vse to strangle &amp; stifle men with, if they take not heed of him. But it shall be easie for you to preuent these dangers, calling often to minde that which is said in the scriptures, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the corruption &amp; vanity of men to humble them, and on the other side that which is also spoken of the great and infinite mercy and grace of God, to assure them of their saluatiō. I hope that with his helpe, my labour writing vnto you this little Treatise, and yours in the reading of it attentiuely, shal not be vnprofitable. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>