<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRAEFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S531_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23754</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S531</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRAEFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fearefull summer, or, Londons calamity, the countries courtesy, and both their misery / by Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PRAEFACE.</head>
   <p>IN this lamentable Time of generall Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, our hainous sinnes prouoking Gods just Indignation, this heauy visitation and mortality; I being atendant vpon the Queenes Ma<seg rend="sup">rie</seg> at Hampton Court and from thence within 2 miles of <hi>Oxford</hi> with her Barge (with much greife and remorse) did see and heare the miserable &amp; cold entertainment of many <hi>Londoners,</hi> which, for their preseruation fled and retired themselues from the Cittie into the Country. Whence I noted the peoples Charitie, and great amendment, for they had giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer one of the 7 deadly sinnes, which was <hi>Coueteus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> and in many places were so farre out of loue with a Citizens money, that they abhor'd and hated either to touch or receaue it; entertaining them with bitter wormewood welcome, (which Hearbe was in more request amongst many of them, then any of the heauenly <hi>Graces</hi> or Cardinall <hi>Vertues</hi>) yet the hearbe of <hi>Grace</hi> was in much estimation, although the name of it was a document that they had occasion to <hi>Rue</hi> the <hi>time</hi>; I farther perceiued that they were so farre from beleiuing or crediting any man, that they would or durst not trust their owne noses, but were doubtfull that that sence would conspire with the Plague to murther them, wherefore (like cunning Mariners, or
<pb facs="4"/>
mole-catchers,) they would craftily in their streetes and highwaies <hi>fetch the winde of any man,</hi> although they were ouer shoes and bootes, and sometimes tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled into a ditch for their labours. This was the time when a man with a nightcap at noone, would haue frighted a whole Parish out of their wits, when to call for <hi>Aquauitae</hi> (though it had beene but to make a drench for a sicke horse was enough to haue his house shut up. When <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon vs,</hi> made many of them tremble more then <hi>God Refuse, Renounce, Confound, or Damne.</hi> When a man trauailing in the habit of a Cityzen, was a meere <hi>bulbegger</hi>; when for a man to say, that he came from <hi>Hell</hi> would yeeld him better welcome, without money, then a man would giue to his owne father and mother that came from <hi>London.</hi> In this time of mans great miserie and small mercy, I tooke my pen in hand and wrote this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sueing discourse, I haue (as neere as I could) suited it, sadly according to the nature of the subject. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because that the bare and naked trueth was so cleare and ample, that I needed not to stuffe it out with friuolous fables or fantasticall fictions; with my soule, I thankfully acknowledge Gods great mercy exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded towards me (one of the most wretched and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) in that so many thousands of better life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation haue falne on my right hand and on my left, and round about me; yet hath his gratious protection beene my guard, for the which in my gratitude to my God, and to auoid the sinne of idlenes, I haue written what those that can may reade.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>