<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIHGT
Honorable and most vertuous
Lady, the La. Cicely Countesse of
DORSET.</title>
           <author>Abbot, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S555_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16906</idno>
           <idno type="STC">38.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S555</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIHGT
Honorable and most vertuous
Lady, the La. Cicely Countesse of
DORSET.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Westminster May 26. 1608. at the funerall solemnities of the Right Honorable Thomas Earle of Dorset, late L. High Treasurer of England. By George Abbot Doctor of Diuinitie and Deane of Winchester, on of his Lordships chapleines. Now published at the request of some honourable persons; very few things being added, which were then cut off by the shortnesse of the time</title>
                 <author>Abbot, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIHGT
Honorable and most vertuous
Lady, the La. Cicely Countesse of
DORSET.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are sundry reasons (right
Honourable) which haue moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
me to giue my consent that
this Sermon might be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed:
One is to testifie my duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
&amp; grateful respect towards
that noble personage now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased,
to whom when he was
liuing, I was so much bound for
so many yeeres together: Another is, to giue satisfaction to
diuers of speciall qualitie and note, who haue earnestly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated
me, that I will not denie this dutie to the dead, nor
such a kindnesse to them aliue, but that they may reade that
againe and againe, which they heard once with no discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment:
A third is, that the world may truly take notice
of many excellent vertues, wherewith God had indued this
honourable man: and that as well with resolued knowledge
to compose and settle his soule religiously towards heauen, as
with rare wisdome &amp; prudence otherwise, to digest and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch,
either publike businesse touching his Souereigne and
the State, or his owne priuat affaires. In the opening where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
as it should be vanitie to adde or amplifie any thing, so it
should be want of Christian dutie and regard, to conceale
that which is true: especially since the relation may satisfie
such as doubt, and the example may prouoke others to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
those good parts, which are not euery where to be found.
Now it being published, I haue as great reason to recommend
<pb facs="3"/>
it to your honourable patronage, since you are the Suruiuer
of that worthy couple, who for so long time were ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
in the bands of Christian wedlocke. And whom may
it more concerne, or vnto whom can it be more comfortable
than to your Ladiship, that there should be some memoriall
of his well-doing, whom you so deerly loued, and so respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
obserued, in the time of your conuersation together?
Besides, the reading of it, may peraduenture be a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer
vnto you of your owne mortalitie, when you heare of
his departure before you, who (as you supposed) might haue
ouer-liued you many yeeres. And lastly, the mention of that
which his Lordship hath left touching your selfe, may incite
you to go forward in those vertuous and Christian courses,
which hitherto you haue so singularly demonstrated, that
(besides the experience which his Lordship had, and testified
to the full) the world (which obserueth few good things,
vnlesse they be eminent) taketh great notice of them: and
therefore it neerly concerneth your Honor to persist therein:
and to endeuour yet dayly to increase those good graces; that
the end may counteruaile, yea exceed, both the progresse and
beginning. I doubt not but God who hath begun his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
worke in you, will accomplish it and make it perfect, so
blessing you all the dayes of your pilgrimage heere, that you
may liue to your children and childrens children an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
paterne of pietie, religion and vertue; and depart
from this earth in a full age, vnto the true and neuer ceasing
ioyes of his euerlasting Kingdome. Which he will alwayes
pray for, who is and long hath beene</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors very much bounden
<hi>GEORGE ABBOT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>