<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF The Author Alphonso.</title>
           <author>Stinnet, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S641_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18931</idno>
           <idno type="STC">535.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S641</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF The Author Alphonso.</title>
                 <author>Stinnet, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A breefe methode or way teachinge all sortes of Christian people, how to serue God in a moste perfect manner written first in Spanishe, by a religious man, named Alphonso ; and reduced owte of Latin into English in manner of a dialogue for the easier vnderstanding and capacities of the simpler sorte, by I.M</title>
                 <author>Alonso de Madrid</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>19, 73, that is 145, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF The Author Alphonso.</head>
   <p>SAinct <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith, that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the order &amp; manner how to woorke, greatly troubleth the qualitie of our meritt. Neither is it to be thought (as the same Author affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) that we haue full knowledge of a thinge which we know we ought to doe, vnlesse we know withall the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of proceedinge in the same.</p>
   <p>Whereupon it is manifest, that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth verie litle, if one know what is writen for seruing God, &amp; be ignorāt in what manner and order it is to be done. And albeit arte &amp; knowledge of euery good thinge, floweth from God the supremest artificer, &amp; many be illuminated by his goodnes, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented with benedictions of delighte &amp; sweetenes: yet for all that we must not omitt to doe what is in vs, to seke (as we are bounde) his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes &amp; will, &amp; other thinges which be necessary for doinge perfectly what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is pleasing vnto him. For which
<pb facs="6"/>purpose the breefe forme &amp; Methode which here we sett downe, will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, that we may know &amp; woorke those greate thinges, which the holy scriptures teach vs. The which to doe it is noe lesse needefull that some arte be sought owte, then for doinge any other thinge which we couert rightly to know or woorke. To fynde owte this arte, the holye Doctoures haue spente much tyme, &amp; haue lefte it wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at large in diuers volumes: of all which, we will gather a breefe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion or somme. But this short work being chiefly ordeyned for the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyses of the soule: it will seme som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes verye obscure to them which haue not bene exercysed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; operations of the powers of their soule. Yet we shall shewe after a while in the prosecution of the book this Methode to be so farre from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scuritie, that it bringeth greate lighte to all other bookes of lyke argument.</p>
   <p>Neither lett any thinke it superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or vayne, that we geue Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes whereby we may be helped to
<pb facs="7"/>serue God, when as all the Scripture witnessith such to be necessary. And S.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3</note>
      <hi>Paule</hi> saith, that we are helpers or coadiutors of God: but he either hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not rightly, or not sufficientlye, that helpeth not as much as he can &amp; oughte. Neither is it any other thing in vs that we helpe God, then that we moue our soule in all our workes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prescripte rule of this present arte, as sacred diuinitie at large declareth.</p>
   <p>The Philosopher in his Metaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicks affirmeth, that mankinde liue the by arte: in which place he semeth by this propertie to distinguish man from vnreasonable creatures, for that all these are moued onely by naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct without arte: but man is ruled by arte &amp; reason: Wherefore he may be said to serue God as it we are onely by naturall instinct, lyke to creatures voyde of reason, that is moued to serue him that way, by which he fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth greatest consolation &amp; sweetenes without regardinge by his vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge &amp; reason, whether there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="7"/>other manner, wherby he may be able, to serue God more excellently.</p>
   <p>Moreouer there is noe cause, why any should alledge the vnction of the holy Ghost, to teach vs in all things, &amp; therfore any art or Methode where by we may learne to serue God, is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>needeles: which sayinge is true, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supposinge that we our selues also be his coadiutors or helpers, endeuoringe to know &amp; woorke, as we are taughte in the sacred scriptures, &amp; in this arte which we are to geue. For the vncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy ghost, teachethe not them that are vnwillinge to learne, nor them that are idle, or make resis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
   <p>Furthermore leste the sweete yoke of our Lorde seme heauye to any, let vs consider that it is not a thing to be merueled at, if some dayes are to be spent, for getting so highe knowledg &amp; wisdom, as is heare conteyned and taught in this arte. For if in learninge Grammer or Logick (artes farr infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to this) one consume &amp; spende 3 or 4 yeares, yea all his lyfo, if he
<pb facs="8"/>will be perfecte in any of them: how much better is our lyfe bestowed (yea if it be wholly spente therein) for the perfect learning of this arte most high &amp; diuine of all other artes, which our supreame maister Iesus Christe, came to teach vs, with his so great toile &amp; payne.</p>
   <p>Moreover, he that beginnethe to learne this arte, must consider, that it will happen to him, as it is wonte to happen to infantes, who hauinge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect soules, yet want the vse of reason: and hauing in their bodyes handes &amp; fecte, yet can not goe or worke: but when they once begin to waxe and to moue their limmes, they goe, yet with great difficultie, &amp; with fallinge now &amp; then: but growing elder, &amp; vsinge daily Exercyse, they goe so freelye, that they can runne at their pleasures.</p>
   <p>The same hapneth in these Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, whyles one desyrethe purelye to serue god aster this Methode: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit our soules be perfect &amp; intyere, yet so mightely are we bounde &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed &amp; without strength to mooue
<pb facs="8"/>our selues in the perfecte way manifested in the holy gospell, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in this arte which we sett owte, that at the firste, we can not walke or goe at all, or if we be moued or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this, it is with such difficultie, that our goinge is well neare nothing. Yet notwithstanding let vs manfullye endeuour to doe what is here prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed so well as we can: for whiles we shall scarse dare, to hope to gett the perfection taught vs, we shall by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyse yea so runne by these high pathes that it may be said truly, our motions to be rather the motions of an Angell flying, then of a man walking on earth.</p>
   <p>None oughte to pretende any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse why he serueth not God after the manner we haue here sett downe, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting him self with the litterall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of som religious rule, or the commaundements of God, as suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente to saluation. For as the Apostle saith, Goddes will is that we be holy and perfect. Seinge therefore riches allready gotten, do not suffyce nor cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente the louers of the world, but all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="9"/>they wishe &amp; couet more, yea often contrary to Goddes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Neither in lyke māner ought we to be contente with these spirituall riches we haue allreadie: but labour to increase them dailye, &amp; augmente the rewarde we expecte, seinge God doth vehemently desyre that we so do. But if our appetite couet not this, for the profitt we may gert thereby, at the least it shoulde extende it selfe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre it, because we know it to be gods will that we be magnifyed &amp; enrych<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all thinges, as the children of so eternall &amp; glorious a Father in heauen, who admonisheth vs saying, <hi>Be you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because I your Lorde god &amp; Father am holy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This booke may be intituled, <hi>The Way, Arte, or Methode, of fitly seruing God:</hi> which may be deuyded into three partes. The first conteyneth certaine vniuersall documents, instructions, or rules, whereby we may be directed in all our actions. The seconde part cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth certaine particuler Exercyses, in which the seruant of God muste be
<pb facs="9"/>exercysed, that he may repaire the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and corruption which sinne haithe brought into his soule.</p>
   <p>The Third part treateth of the loue of god, and those thinges which he commaundeth to be loued, in which loue consistethe the fulfillinge of the Law, and of all our good. And let him marke that shall reade this, how much labour &amp; diligence he bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that desyreth to be conninge and furnished in some prophane arte, and how meete it is, that more diligence be vsed in this affayre.</p>
   <p>These considerations therfore had &amp; chefely relying vpon the assistance of our supreme maister Iesus Christ, our eternall God and Lorde, we will begin the foresaid arte &amp; Method.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>