<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Translator'S Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S714_Bo1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2854.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Translator'S Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first tome or volume of the Paraphrase of Erasmus vpon the newe testamente</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>cxxvii, 1, xcviij, cci, 1, cxxiii, 1, xc leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_preface">
   <pb n="j" facs="130"/>
   <opener>To the most excellent and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous princesse quene Catherine, wyfe to our moste gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious soueraigne Lorde, Henry the eyght, Kyng of England, Fraunce▪ and Irelande, defendour of the faythe, and of the Churche of Englād, and also of Irelande, in earthe supreme heade, Thomas Key, her dayly Oratoure, wisheth perpetuall felicitie.</opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mōge the innumerable benefites whiche we haue receiued of almighty God, most worthye and excellent Princesse, there is none in myne opiniō for the whiche we are more bounden vnto his merciful good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, then for that it hath pleased hym more clearely to illumine vs of this age with the knowledge of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly woorde, then our forefathers and elders. For who knoweth not how long this realme hath bene misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly seduced through ignoraunce of the Scriptures? Who, euen amonge the vplandishe, perceyueth not what intollerable abuses haue bene vnder pretence of true religion, and Godlynesse, mayntayned in this Churche of Englande, tyll suche tyme y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> God of his infinite mercy, sent vs a newe Iosias, by whose righteous administracion, and Godly policie, the light of Gods worde that so many yeares before was here extincte, began to shyne agayne: to the vtter extirpacion of false doctrine, the rote and chiefe cause of all such abusiōs? This Iosias is our mooste redoubted soueraigne Lorde Kyng Henry theyght, a Prince garnished with so many excellent gyftes of grace, nature, &amp; Fortune, that he is in very dede, &amp; therfore mooste worthely called, the perfite mirroure, &amp; pearle of all Christen Princes. To wade here in the prayse of his princely qualities, &amp; noble actes atchie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed to Gods honoure, and the publique weale of this realme, is not my purpose, for that I knowe it to be an enterpryse farre exceadyng the compasse of my symple learning, and barrayne eloquence: But onely to declare howe muche we are bounden, chiefly vnto God, and nexte vnto his moste excellent Maiestie, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we haue the Scriptures in our mother tōgue, &amp; are cured of our olde blindnesse by the medicine of veritie. For nowe hauing our spirituall iyes opened, and daily receyuing into the same the cleare light of Gods worde, we begyn to see, &amp; perfectly to knowe our onely sauiour Iesus Christ: whome to knowe is euerlasting lyfe and saluaciō. But so longe as the saide Scriptures were hyd, and kept from the knowledge of the people, fewe knewe Christ aryght: and none lesse then they, who appeared to be the chiefe professours of christian religion. For what els is it to knowe Christ, but to knowe and confesse that of him onely, and by hym cummeth oure saluacion? that by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>moure good dedes are acceptable vnto almyghty God the father? that by him the fathers wrathe is appeased? that by him we be enfraunchised from the captiuitie and thraldome of the deuell? and to be shorte, that by hym
<pb facs="131"/>
we are adopted and chosen to be the children of God, and enherytours of the kyngdome of heauen? Whoso knoweth Christ aryght, surely beleueth to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne saluaciō by him onely, who saythe: Cum vnto me all ye that do trauaile, and are charged, and I shall refresh you. The very office of Christ is to saue: &amp; therfore he was called by the high wisdome of God (Iesu) that is as muche to say, as a sauiour, because (so saythe the angell in Mathew) he shall saue the people from their sinnes: So that it appeareth hereby how greatly they are deceiued that thinke to be saued by any other waye or meane then by Christ, or that make thēselues quarter sauiours with him, ascribing any parte of their saluaciō vnto their owne workes and deseruinges. Nowe howe could Christ be knowen aright, that is to say, to be our onely sauioure and iustifier so long as the scriptures were shut vp, &amp; kept from the people: And <hi>Legenda aurea,</hi> with such like trūperye lay open for them to passe the time withall, and reade in stede of the byble? For this cause chiefly, and also for lacke of good preachers, to preache and teache the truthe, it came to passe, that he was almost cleane out of knowledge in this realme, insomuche that (during the tyme of this great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce and blyndes) many a thousand putte more confidence of soule he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>althe in workes that were but of mennes phantasying, as in pardons, in pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grymages, in kyssing of relyques, in offeryng to saintes, in halowed beades, in numberyng of prayers, in mumblyng vp of psalmes not vnderstand, in the merytes of those that called them selfes relygious, and in other lyke thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, disalowed by god, and his holy word, then in Christe thonly auctor, as is aforesayde, of mannes saluacion. But nowe that by the gracious permission of our sayde soueraigne Lorde, the scriptures are open for euery man to read soberly, and reuerently for his owne edifying in vertue and godly lyuing, it is right well knowen that the foresayd abusions were doctrines of Antichristes inuencion, and not of god: and that al such as teache any other waye or meane to attayne saluaciō, then by hym who sayth: I am the waye &amp; veritie, are false teachers, seducers, and liers. Nowe do the commaundementes of God no lenger giue place, as they were wonte to do, vnto mans tradiciōs. Now haue we learned what is our dutie to God, &amp; what obedēice we owe vnto our price, gods chief minister, and supreme head in earth of our churche &amp; cōgregacion. Now is idolatry, hipocrisy, and supersticion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eane plucked vp by the rootes, and true religion euery where planted. Nowe is false doctrine exiled, &amp; Gods worde truely setforthe and preached. Nowe hathe England cleane forsaken Antichrist of Rome, the greatest enemy of gods holy worde, with al his moste vngodly deuices, and diuilyshe inuenciōs. And all this came of the mere mercy and goodnes of almygty god towardes vs, who vndoubtedly for thasserciō of his holy word, and the delyueraūce of vs his people out of captiuitie, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and blydnes, hathe raysed vp in oure tymes thi Christen Iosias, and ioyned vnto the same by most lawful matrimony youre noble grace, a Lady, besydes other speciall gyftes, and singuler qualities, wholy geuen to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> study of vertue and godlynesse. Wherfore all England hathe iuste occasion to reioyce at this youre graces honorable aduauncement, yea rather hyghly to thanke god that our moste gracious soueraigne hathe matched himselfe with so ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous a Lady, in whome is the very expresse resemblance of all his maiesties excellent vertues, but specially of that his graces ardent zele, and deuocion in fauouryng and setting forthe of Gods word, the mother of all ioyful prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.
<pb n="ij" facs="131"/>
A manifest argument wherof besydes many other, is that your grace so muche desyreth to haue the Paraphrases of the renoumed clerke Erasmus of Roterdame vpon the new testament (a worke very fruitefull and necessary for the true vnderstandyng of this parte of holy scripture) tourned into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe: and for the xploiture and spedy accomplishement of this your graces most Godly desyre, hath (as is sayde) commaūded certein well learned persōs to translate the sayde worke, the paraphrase vpon S. Marke excepted, which the right worshypfull maister Owen (a man of muche lerning, &amp; no lesse ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie, and therfore worthyly Phisician to the kynges moste royall person) moued me, your graces pleasure fyrst knowē, to go in hād withall, affirming that I should do a thyng right acceptable vnto your hyghnes, if I would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently trauell therin. The whiche thing, being very desyrous to gratify your highnes, and with my pore seruice and diligence to further, as much as in me lay, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godly purpose of the same, I right gladly promised him to do, trusting rather vpon the benigne acceptacion of your gracious goddnes, then vpon the slendernesse of my wytte &amp; lerning farre vnable worthely to atchiue so weygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty an entreprise. For thauctour hereof was a man of incomparable elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quēce: and therfore it is not possible for a person scarcely of meane learning (as I am) to set out euery thing specially in our English tongue being very bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain of wordes and phrases (I will not saye barbarous withall) so lyuelye, &amp; with like grace as he wrote it fyrst in the Latine. Wherfore I mynded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng lesse then to contend with him in ornate speache, and eloquence: but haue done my diligent endeuour so to interprete the sayde worke, that it shoulde be bothe plaine and pleasaunte vnto the reader: and not onely that, but also to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the chiefest office of an interpretour, whiche is faythfully to translate, and expresse euery thing according to the true sence &amp; meaning of thauctoure. If I haue, most vertuous Prīcesse, any where fayled thus to do, it hath bene rather for lacke of learning, and better knowledge, then of any good will and diligence. To speake here any thyng eyther in praise of thauctour of this present worke, or of the worke selfe, in myne opinion shall not be nedefull, for that thauctour is so muche renoumed for his excellency in lerning, that my prayses can no more illustrate and set forthe his glory, then a candell (as the common prouerbe is) giue light vnto the sunne: and the great vtilitie of thother, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not so well be set out by any mans prayse and commendacion, as it shall eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare vnto them that wyll diligently reade and peruse it. If this my good wil and endeuour maye be acceptable vnto your highnes, as the great fame of your bountye, and gracious goodnes putteth me in comforte it shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, I wyll hereafter, god assisting me, employ my whole study and labours in suche wise, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the fruite thereof shalbe more worthy to be presented vnto your noble grace, then this rude translacion, the whiche I am bolde at this present throughe thaffiaūce of your natural gentlenesse to dedicate vnto the same. I beseche almighty God long to preserue our sayde soueraigne Lorde, your grace, and that moste confortable flower of all England, noble Prince Edward, in continuall honour, ioy, and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>