<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Translator'S Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S714_Bo1_5_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2854.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Translator'S Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first tome or volume of the Paraphrase of Erasmus vpon the newe testamente</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>cxxvii, 1, xcviij, cci, 1, cxxiii, 1, xc leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_preface">
   <pb n="i" facs="567"/>
   <opener>To the moste uertuous Ladie Quene Kateryne late wyfe to Kyng Henry the eyght of moste famous memorye deceassed, Nycolas Udall your graces most humble oratour, and seruaunt, wysheth perpetuall felicitee and ioye in Iesus Christ our lorde.</opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as nothyng doeth with lyke spede or with better effecte eyther open to the worlde or engraue in mennes heartes the knowelage of Goddes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and the rules of true christian doctrine, then deuout and godly tractises for the expoundyng and declaryng of holy scrypture: howe happie and blyssed are we, and howe greatly bounde to thanke God, that in these our tymes there dayly cum foorth so many and the same so fruictfull and Godly weorkes in our owne toung, to the ghostely coumfort and edifiyng of all deuout chrystian readers in the true fayeth and relygyon. For where in tymes past the studyous wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of bookes wer enforced with much highe suite and seruice to procure the fauoure and good wyll of prynces or other estates, to whome to dedicate such weorkes as thei wrote, to thentent that vnder the name and protection of such noble personages the sayd weorkes might be the better habled to the readers, and the better accepted of the people: nowe dooe Kynges, Quenes, prynces, and other piers (especyally here in Englande) of their owne mere mocions, and good zele, not only with their propense fauour, and with their benefycyall ayde, coumforte, and lyberalitee, helpe forewarde the good endeuour and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulytee of studious wryters, myndyng by their godly monumentes to edifie the feithfull congregacion: but also are dylygent and peynefull, bothe to put to theyr owne handes to the endictyng and pennyng of many holsome traicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses for that purpose, yea and ferther by their exaumple and prouocacion to set other in hande with wrytyng or translatyng, to the fructefull exercise of the learned, to the holsome enstruccion of Englyshe readers, and to the effectuall edifiyng of the simple ignoraunt multitude, if the same can bee content for their solle helthe to gyue eare and mynde thereto. And emong this sorte of publique benefactours, your excellent highnesse, Quene Kateryne, deserueth no lesse then next after our soueraygne lorde the kynges maiestee, whoe euen nowe already at the fyrst entreaunce of this his moste noble reigne, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the yeres of tendre minoritee, doth with the aduice and consent of the moste prudent and the same his moste dere vncle Edwarde duke of Somersette, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of his moste royall persone in the tyme of his mynorytee gouernoure, as also of all hys Maiestees realmes, dominyons, and subiectes Protector, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the assent and consent of the other his moste honourable, moste trusty, and moste feythfull Counsaillours, moste forewardly, moste earnestly, and with all possible diligence labour daye and nyght as well by moste holsō, lawes, as also by O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>elyes of moste pure doctryne, and by true preachers to refourme abuses, to sowe abrode the woorde of God, and to plante true rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon in all partes of his realmes and domynons, youre hyghnesse (I saye)
<pb facs="568"/>
next vnto these twoe, deserueth no lesse then to be estemed and called the chiefe patronesse: not onely for dyuers moste godly Psalmes and meditacions of your owne penning and settyng foorthe: but also for procuryng thys present weorke of Erasmus Paraphrases to be translated to the vse of the vnlearned multytude, whiche can go no ferther then the vnderstandyng or readyng of Englyshe. For in this Paraphrase of Erasmus is conteined in maner a whole librarie of deuout &amp; catholyke expositours vpon the whole new testamente, in which new testament is conteyned the plenteous richesse &amp; most precious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soures of Christes ghospell, that is, of the glad newes of Goddes fauour and mercy towardes mankynd. Which fauour and mercy of God whosoeuer doth feithfully &amp; syncerely enbrace, cannot but fauour and ferther the setting foorth of scripture in the vulgare language, that al folkes maye knowe it, and also of any other godly traictises whereby that same generall benefyte of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes mankynde, maye the more clerelye and certainly be perceiued. And to this effecte forasmuche as Desiderius Erasmus of Roterodam doeth especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally directe aswell these his Paraphrases vpon the newe testament, as also all other his right christian wrytinges, and that with as much indifferencie as is possible to be: I cannot but iudge, that whoso are prompte and hasty condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Erasmus, or eagre aduersaries vnto his doctrine: do vnder the name and colour of Erasmus rather vtter their stomake &amp; hatred againste Goddes woord and the grace of the ghospell, which Erasmus for his parte moste dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and moste simply laboureth to bryng to lyght. His doctryne (wyll some vneguall iudges saye) is scarcely sincere. If there shall no more insynceritee of doctrine appere in the wrytynges of them that so wyll say, then the comon cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the chrystian world doeth fynde and iudge in Erasmus: I doubte not but theyr weorkes shalbe of all good people approued, desyred, enbraced and folowed. Erasmus (wyl some such headie persones say) doth somewhere erre. It maye so be forasmuch as a man he is, and so estemeth hymself, and woulde his weorkes none other wyse to be reade or accepted then the wrytynges of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mortall men. But in case he should in some place saie now &amp; then a worde to much or to litel, or putte a wurse word for a more apte terme, or if he should in some place stoumble or swarue (whiche poincte of humayne frayltee the best doctours that wrote sence the apostles tyme hathe not escaped, nor Erasmus so standeth in his owne wylfull opynion, but that beeyng found and tryed a faulte, he woulde haue been as readye to retracte it, as euer any other godly &amp; catholike wryter hath ben:) yet were one lytle tryppe (after my poore iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) emong so many notable good workes for the enterpretacion of scryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and for the helpe of the symple, rather to bee borne withall, then so many good thinges to be either reiected or kept away from the hungry christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. it is, a colde charitee that can beare with nothing: and an eagre malice it is that for a trifle or a matier of nothing woulde haue the ignoraunt multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to lacke so much good edifying as may be taken of Erasmus, aswel in all hys other ryght deuoute and catholyke woorkes, as also moste specyally in these his paraphrases, in which he laboureth so to enlarge the processe and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the texte, as the sense therof may bothe euedentlye be gathered, &amp; may well hange together. Erasmus therfore lyke as he hathe by a paraphrasticall discourse playnly sette foorth the ghospelles of the fower Euangelistes afore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>so dooeth he now here expoune the seconde parte of Lukes ghospel, entitled y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Actes of the Apostles, whiche woorke Athanasius (at leste wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e if it were
<pb n="ii" facs="568"/>
Athanasius in dede, that wrote the litle traictise entitled of the bokes of bothe the olde and the newe testament. &amp;c.) testifieth, that Luke wrote out of Peturs mouthe▪ &amp; that Petur endicted vnto Luke what and how he should wryte thē, as Paule endicted to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Luke whan he wrote his ghospell. Whereof (as Erasmus in the preface to his paraphrase vpō Lukes ghospel recordeth) it is gathered and thought, that the sayde Actes wer wryten in Rome. But wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they were wryten, certes the worke was no lesse expediente &amp; necessarie to be wrytten, ne the paraphrase vpon the same any thyng lesse requisite to bee translated into Englysh, then the reste of the newe testament: firste for that it is a plain historical narracion &amp; a piece of the veray ghospel, in that it decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth aswell the ascencion of Christe from yearthe vp into heauen, as also hys sendyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oune of the holy ghoste from his heauenly father together with the spryngyng vp of the prymatiue churche, &amp; the fourme and ordre of preachyng that the Apostles than first begonne with: secondely because it was (as Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hymselfe testifieth) the last parte that he did of all the whole paraphrases vpon the testament, and by reason thereof (as I iudge) the moste absolute piece of worke and best dooen of the reste, by reason of his long exercise afore in this kynde of writing: and thyrdely because this piece of the new testament is no lesse profytable for the publishyng and furtheraunce of the ghospel, then Luke dyd deuise and entende it, ne to the poore younglynges in Christes dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline any thyng lesse auaillable. For here may we learne the beginninges of Christes churche, by whome and by what manier persones the feythe of Christe fyrste sprong vp, howe it proceded and grewe, howe it was persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and how by persecucyon it wexed stronger &amp; stronger. For as the Paulme tree the more weight and burdē is layed vpon it, the more it ariseth and shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth vpryght: so the ghospel the more persecucion that was inflycted vnto it, and the more rigour, wrong▪ reproche, cheynes, and aduersytee that was my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred vnto it, the more it grewe, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more it prospered, the better it wente fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and the more it floryshed. In the Actes is to be reade by what meanes and dryftes of humayne polycy the enemyes of Christes bloude and ghospell wrastled to suppresse the glorye of his crosse, &amp; howe the more that the wysedō of the world thought to euacuate the fruicte of Christes deathe and passion, the more dyd the humylytee of preachyng the Crosse, worke in the hartes of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> simple to contemne not onely the pleasures and flattery of the worlde, but also the persecucion &amp; tyranny therof, so that dayly encreased in euery place where the ghospell was preached, thousandes vpō thousandes to augmente y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> feith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full congregation. The Actes therefore were no lesse necessary to be transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then the rest of the paraphrases, which Actes I haue by occasiō of adding, digesting, and sorting the texte with the paraphrase throughly perused, and conferryng the same with the Latine I haue here and there dooen my good wyll and diligence to make the Englysh aunswerable to the Latyne booke, at lestwyse in sense: as by the same occasion I did also with Mathewe. In Iohn I haue in manier dooen nothing at all sauing only placed the texte, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the paraphrase, because I knew the translatours thereof, with whose erquysite dooynges I myght not without the cryme of great arrogancie and presumpcion be busy to entremedle. Moste humbly therfore beseching your highnesse moste gracious Ladie, in good parte to take my good zele and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and in case any thyng shall not suffyciently answere your mynde or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre,
<pb facs="569"/>
the same to impute rather to the lacke of facultee and knowlage, then to any default of good wil in me: I shal here without any ferther circūstaunce of woordes, commend and leue this whole worke to the diligent readyng and folowyng of all the deuout Englyshe congregacyon: and wyth moste hertye prayer beseche almyghty God long yeres to preserue and cōtynewe the prosperous estate of your highnesse, to thende that by your good help and meanes the deuout people that are willing and foreward to learne and to liue Christianlye, maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue many lyke godly weorkes and fruict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful traictises, to theyr continuall ghost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profite, coumfort, and edifying in the same our Lorde Iesus Christe, to whome with the father, and with the holy ghoste be al laude, honour, and glory, both in heauen and yearth for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>