<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The preface of Erasmus vnto his paraphrase vpon the Gospell of the Euangelist Matthew.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S714_Bo1_1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2854.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The preface of Erasmus vnto his paraphrase vpon the Gospell of the Euangelist Matthew.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first tome or volume of the Paraphrase of Erasmus vpon the newe testamente</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>cxxvii, 1, xcviij, cci, 1, cxxiii, 1, xc leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>¶The preface of Erasmus vnto his paraphrase vpon the Gospell of the Euangelist Matthew.</head>
   <opener>To the moste victorious Emperour Charles, the fift of that name Erasmus of Roterodame, gretyng.</opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eyng not ignoraunt, Charles Emperour most victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, howe muche godly feare and reuerence also, is of due congruence to be geuen, partely vnto all holye scriptures, whiche the holy fathers throughe the inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of God, haue left vnto vs, and especially vnto that part of scripture, whiche maketh an vpright and faythful relacion of suche thinges as the heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eyther wrought in facte, or spake in woordes, for the health and saluacion of the whole world, through his soone Iesus: and being ferther priuie to myne owne vnwurthynes, where not many yeares gone, I first attempted to set hand to making a parahrase vpon Paules Epistles, for the playner vnderstandyng of them (which thing to doe came vpon me at that time of a sodain pangue, euen of mine own mind) I did no lesse, then think myself to enterprise a veral bolde and presumpteous acte, and an acte (as the prouerbe sayeth) of a right daungerous hazarde, in so muche that after I had in one or twoo or three chapiters, taken a prouf, and assaye of the worke, how well it woulde doe, I was vttirly mynded to pulle downe my sayles againe, and to surcease from the course that I had afore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to take, vnlesse a wunderful consent of my frendes beyng men of ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, had perforce constrayned me to procede with that I had begon. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coulde I for their most earnest desires▪ be at any rest or quiet, vntil I had fully ended and finished all that euer there was of the Epistles Apostolical, whereas I had not taken in hand to medle, but only w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> those epistles whiche without all controuersie or doubte were wryten of thapostle Paule. It hath not at al tymes framed wel with me, ne come to good ende, when I haue ben ruled to doe thynges at the mocions &amp; instaunt pricking forward of frendes. But yet in this thing neuerthelesse I was not a litle proude of my selfe, that this my bolde auenturyng had come muche more happily to passe, then was loked for, as well for myne owne parte that was the maker, to whome it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased least enuie and grutche of men, of al the wurkes that euer I wrote: as also on the behalfe of all suche, as are studentes and suters to atteigne to the philosophye of the gospell, who doe euery man more then other, geue me thā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for that by meanes of myne industrious labour, they haue to the better knowlage of thapostolicall wisedome, eyther been moued and stirred vp, or els furthered. But whā I had cleane dispatched myself of this great charge and taske, I loked not that I shoulde at any tyme afterwarde, haue any more to doe with this kynde of writing, &amp; beholde the right reuerende father Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Cardinall of Sedune (by whose aduise and instigacion I had afore made vp all thepistles canonical) at what time I spake with him at Brurels, to welcome hym into the countrey, according to my duetie, after his returne from the counsell, whiche had than been holden at the citie of Wourmes, euē by and by at the first entring in talke with me, euen lyke a man that had deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vpon it afore, begynneth to exhorte me, that what I had afore doen vpon thapostolicall Epistles, the same I shoulde also doe vpon the gospel of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew.
<pb n="xviii" facs="18"/>
I on my partie anon made myne excuse by many thynges, firste that it was alreadye an acte bolde and ouerbolde, that I had attempted the same v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the writinges of thapostles: secondly that the Apostles in dede wer god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, yet neuerthelesse men they were, but the maiestie of Christ to be more great, then that it myght be lefull to auenture the doynge of suche a thynge in his wordes. And though the maiestie of the worke did not put of &amp; dryue one awaye, yet the nature of the argument or matter of the gospels to refuse the thyng, &amp; not to suffre one that should go about to make a Paraphrase: and not onely for that there are in the gospell persons of diuers and sundry sortes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome while the wordes and talke is so applied as to euery of them for his rate or degree maye best accorde, it commeth to passe that the wryters penne is kept shut within the enclosure of an excedyng streyght grate, because it is debarred from that libertie, whiche all other sortes of commentaries doe suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and receiue (for a paraphrase also is to be reputed as a kynde of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie.) Furthermore where as a good porcion of the gospell consisteth in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng report of this and that acte doynge, and that of a simple and a plain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port without any curiositie, one that shoulde in thys parte make a paraphrase shall seme nothyng els to doe, but at noontyde to light a candell, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe of the Grekes doeth call it. Nowe ferther, wheras the aunciente doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures and wryters doe in expoundyng the allegories, partly varie, not decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng it all after one waye: and partely so handle themselues, that to me they seme oft tymes to playe and dallie with it, nor myght expresse or bryng in the same allegories, but vnder the persones, eyther of Christ, orels of the euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list, it is euidente and well to be knowen in what narow streyghtes I should trauayle. I let passe and saye nothyng, that Christ in suche wyse spake cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thynges, as he woulde not haue the same to be vnderstanded at the time of the speakyng of them: of whiche sort this here ensuyng is one: Destroy ye this temple, and within thre dayes space I wyll buyld it vp agayne. And all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of bying a swearde: of the Phariseis leuen to be eschued. And truly in that same his talke, where he foresheweth the distruccion of the citie of Hierusalē and prophecieth of the ende of the world, and of affliccions long after to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue vnto the Apostles, Iesus doeth so intermedle and temper his talke, that me semeth his will and pleasure was to be darke and not vnderstanded, not onely to the Apostles, but also vnto vs all. There be also certayne places (as I thinke) almoste vnpossible to be expouned, of whiche sort one is, concernyng that sinne against the holy goste shall neuer be remitted: an other, concerning the day of iudgement, reserued to the knowlage of the father onely, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen euen to the very sonne selfe. In these places and suche lyke, yf one wryte commentaries, he maye at his pleasure without daunger reporte the sundrye opinions of sundrye expositours, he hath libertie frankly to confesse and acknowlege that he dothe not vnderstand the mening of the place. But one that maketh a paraphrase hath not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyke libertie nor power. Moreouer certayne thinges there be in suche sorte spoken, that they touche and concerne euen these verai times that now are, in which our tymes right many thinges there be, ferre disagreyng from the institucions &amp; ordinaunces of the Apost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And suche thynges although the Euangelistes foreknew them by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of prophecie, yet certes vnder the persones &amp; names of the Apostles, they can not be reported, but both coldely &amp; also cuttedly: There was yet also an
<pb facs="19"/>
other point that moued my minde, which was, that in case I should take and bestow this labour vpon Mathew only, there would by and by be some that would make instaunte &amp; earnest request for to haue the lyke doen vpon all the residue of the Euangelistes: whose wyl &amp; desire if I should folow, than muste it cum to passe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I must many tymes more then once make repeticion of one manier mattiers, that is to were, of all and euery matter in whiche the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes did amonge themselues accorde. Or, if on the othersyde I shoulde tye and linke together a certayne continuall processe of tellyng the thynges, &amp; so to make but one whole tale of them all together: than (forasmuche as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and to open all the places which in the Euangelistes seeme to disagre, is nothyng els but to be coumbreously entangled as it wer in a certayne mase) could I neuer haue been hable to do that is to be doen, for the clerenesse and light that a Paraphrase ought to haue. Whan with these &amp; verai many mo argumentes and reasons, I desired to be ridde of the charge that was layed vnto me to go in hande withall, wheras I thought my selfe to haue a good cause, and an excuse that might haue preuailed: yet did the sayed Matthewe vanquish me by his eloquence, he got the ouer hande of me by reason of hys autoritie wherby he might commaunde me, takyng on hymself the daungier and hasard of all the whole matier. Neyther durste I bee so bolde as any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to striue or strougle agaynst the aduise and councell of hym, whose coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailes your Maiestie customablie vseth in moste high and weighty affayres, not vnwyllyngly to folowe. And yet where as I had not euen plainly taken the matier vpon me, but had onely promysed that I woulde one daye assay yf happily the thyng would frame &amp; go forward: he than iourneiyng towardes Millayn, had made assured warantise vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Germaines in my behalf, that the worke should this instant winter season cum foorth: Wherupon I cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng backe my self againe vnto Basile, was in suche wise on eche side conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually called vpon of my maisters the Germaines, being crauers not of the lest importune sort, that because I would in any wise discharge both his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myse, &amp; myne own honestie to, I finished vp the weorke with litle more then a monethes labour. And God he graunte that bothe the cōmaundement of hym and the obedience of me, may be to all persons luckie and fortunate, and I trust it wyll so be if your maiestie will fauourablie acknowlage and accepte this slender gifte &amp; presente, to the same dedicated. But here perchaunce some man that knoweth you by none other title sauing onely by the name of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, wyl saye: What is a booke of suche an argumente or matier as thys for a prince secular, whiche it had been more mete and conuenient to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated vnto abbottes or bishops? for aunswer wherof, first me thinketh it a thyng aptlye geuen, whatsoeuer thyng beyng honest, is put vp to a Christen prince. And besides this, where as no prince is so secular, but that he hath a doe with the profession of the gospell, the Emperours are anoynted &amp; sacred for this very purpose, that they may eyther maynteyne or restore, or elles en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and sprede abrode the religion of the gospell. Ergo than (wil some man saye) the Emperour is not a teacher of the gospell, but the defendour of it. I graunte that: but in the meanwhyle mete it is, not to be ignoraunt what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thyng it is, for whiche one taketh armour to defende it. And forsoth whā I consider that herte and mynde of yours in suche wise to bee geuen vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and to godly deuocion, that to Bishops &amp; Abbottes it may towardes
<pb n="xix" facs="19"/>
the studie of godlinesse, bee aswell a rule, as also a spurre, me seemeth, I can not dedicate this gifte vnto any man, more conuenientlye, then to youre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie. So that the thyng whiche I myght aptly haue dedicated to any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten prince, and more aptlye to a Christen Emperoure: I doe moste aptly of all dedicate vnto you Charles. Muche lesse apte thynges doe they bringe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that geue you great gyftes of precious stones, that are gayson to bee found, of lustie fierce horses, of houndes, &amp; of riche hanginges, that come oute of farre straunge countreyes. And moreouer forasmuche as the Euangelistes haue writen the gospel vnto all folkes, no persone excepted: I do not see why it shoulde not of euery man bee read. And I haue so handled it, that it maye bee vnderstanded, euen of suche also, as are vnlettered. And surely it shall withe excellent good fruite be read, if euery bodye shall take it in his handes of the only mynde and entent, to bee made thereby a better man then he was afore: and not apply scripture of the gospell to his owne affeccions, but contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse refourme and correct his lyfe and his desyres, according to the rule and prescripcion therof. I haue in this present worke chiefly folowed Origenes, beyng singularly aboue others experte in diuinitie, and Chrisostome and Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, of the catholique writers most best allowed. That Lorde and Prince of heauen giue and graunte vnto you Charles, Emperour most emperiall, suche thinges to minde and to go about, as are of the principall beste sort, &amp; the same lord well prosper your endeuours in that behalf, to the ende that the moste noble Empier, whiche ye haue hitherto had without bloudshed of mā, ye maye semblably aswell enlarge and amplifie, as defende and maintayne. And this poinct in the meane while it maye please your merciful graciousnes frō tyme to tyme to haue in your remembraunce, that no warre there is vpon so iust &amp; lawfull causes taken in hande, nor with so good moderacion executed, that dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not after it an huige heape both of abominacions, and also of miseries: yea, and remembre also the greatest porcion of all the harmes, to light in fine, vpon persones bothe giltles and also vnworthy thesame.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Yeuen at Basile on <date>the Ides of Ianuarie, in the yere of our Lorde a thousande, fiue hundred, twentie and two.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>