<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface of Erasmus vnto his paraphrase vpon the ghospell of Luke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S714_Bo1_3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2854.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface of Erasmus vnto his paraphrase vpon the ghospell of Luke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first tome or volume of the Paraphrase of Erasmus vpon the newe testamente</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>cxxvii, 1, xcviij, cci, 1, cxxiii, 1, xc leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb n="vii" facs="236"/>
   <head>The preface of Erasmus vnto his paraphrase vpon the ghospell of Luke.</head>
   <opener>Unto the mooste puissaunt and most victorious Prince Henry the eight, king of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of the Catholike faith, Erasmus of Roterodame wisheth long health, with all honour and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous continuaunce.</opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oste regall and princely Kyng Henry, I sende vnto youre highnesse Luke the physician, not any other Luke then ye had of him heretofore, but thesame Luke speakyng some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more plainly and also more at large vnto the eares of suche as are vsed to good latine. Neyther do I suppose it any thyng nedefull for me here nowe in this matter, to spende laboure appeacyng and satisfiyng these kynde of people, which commonly allege vnto suche as I am, that it was a sentēce by right great learned mē, very wel taught, that in geuing of giftes or presētes menne ought to haue a speciall iye and regarde, that the thynges whiche we geue, bee apte for the parties that they are geuen vnto. I for my parte dyd this thyng not long sence, at what tyme I dedicated the Paraphrase vpon Matthewe vnto Charles the Emperour: yea and before my tyme also it hath of ryght excellent clerkes, by prescripcion of aunciente custome and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, been plainly declared, that any kynde of argumente what euer it bee, is rightly and well dedicated vnto prynces, whom though we know that they will neuer read it, yet is thus muche vtilitie and benefite gotten therby, that vnder the title of their names, the worke is the better ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>led to the fāsies of studious persons, according as Plinius finely wrote, certain thynges euen for suche onely respect to be reputed very precious, because they are dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for iewels in temples. But certes the waywardnesse of sum personnes towardes bokes, when they cum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> newely forth, is so greate, that they wyll bidde away with the bokes out of their sight, ere they take any assay or tast of the same. And by this meanes there perisheth aswel to the wryter y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> feute whiche he hoped to haue thereby, as also to the reader, his due profite &amp; v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie. And at suche mens hādes, one thing at least wise shal the title of noble princes obtein whan it is set in the first frount of any booke, that they wyll not geue sentence on it to be vtterly naught, that they wil not disdain it, that they wil not spet on it before they haue red it. Albeit euē otherwise also the godly zele and affeccion of sum prynces doeth make, that whoso sendeth the ghospell to any Kyng for a present, shall not seme to do against good reasō. For by men of right good credite, and suche as vse not to lye, it hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed vnto me, as well that Charles the Emperour, in case any vacāt tyme of leysure maye in so great vnquietnesse and troubleous state of the worlde bee gotten, doeth gladly bestowe thesame in readyng the ghospell boke: as also the moste renoumed Prince Ferdinando, brother to thesame Charles, muche and often to haue in his handes the Paraphrase vpon the ghospell of Saincte Iohn, whiche not very long agon I dedicated vnto hym: yea and
<pb facs="237"/>
furthermore that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right noble kyng of Denmarke Christie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, which thing maye to your highnes also be well knowen, hath bokes of christian religion often tymes in his handes, and that he with greate desyrefulnesse vseth to reade my paraphrase vpon the ghospel of Matthew. Why than shoulde the ghospel seme to be vnaptly sent vnto those whiche are handlers and louers of the ghospel, whiche ghospell certes is to be had and vsed in the hādes of all persones as many as remembre and thinke themselfes to be Christyans. Nowe although after the rate of worldely dealyng, suche a thyng is moste chiefely to bee geuen, as the partie hath nede of to whom it is sent, yet after the rule of the ghospell, whoso hath already, to hym muste nedes be geuen, that he may haue plentie. Wherfore me thought I should do but as myght best stande with congruence, to sende this Euangelical physicion vnto your highnesse, for asmuche as thesame is so farre from disdainyng holy scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, that (as your owne writinges dooe testifye,) ye haue aboue the meane rate profited in the same, so that yf a man geue vnto your grace any thing to holy scripture apperteinyng, he shall not seme so muche to geue a gifte, as to make amendes and recompence for a pleasure receyued. Moreouer if this be a thyng specially aboue others in all haste prouided for, that in the kinges &amp; Emperours courtes there may from tyme to tyme be physicions ready and prest at hande (beyng men exactly learned and of approued fidelitie) to take charge that the princes be dye be preserued and kept in health: howe muche more doeth it stande with congruence, that Luke the physicion should there be reslaunte, who doeth not with scammony or ellebour preserue the health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful state of the body, but doth with an heauenly pocion deliuer the soule frō diseases that violently hale men to death euerlastyng, that is to were, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowyng of the truthe, mistrustfulnesse &amp; vnbelefe towardes God, the loue of this worlde, ambicion, auarice, riottous excesse, hatred, enuye, and suche others? For these diseases is all the life of mortall men subiect vnto, &amp; dayly in daunger of falling into them, as Iohn thapostle sayeth, where he beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that all the whole worlde is set in naughtinesse, neyther any thing els to reigne therin, but cōcupiscence of the flesh, concupiscence of the iyes, &amp; pryde of the lyfe. And in so muche the more peril and hasard of the said diseases do the princes stand, as they are more then others made wantons &amp; derelynges of fortune, and haue lybertie withoute checke or controllemente to fullfyll their owne sensuall lustes and appetites. But nowe me seemeth I shall not spende my labour in vayne but to good purpose, if I shal in a fewe wordes commend and sette Foorth vnto your highnesse, first Luke himself being the physiciō, and then the pociō or medicine that he bringeth with hym, albeit I put no doubtes but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as well the one as the other is already (as in dede they ought to be) vnto your godly ze'e and deuocion in most best wyse accepted. Forsoth this same is that excellent man Luke an Antiochian by the coūtrey &amp; nacion that he was borne in. And Antioche is a citie whiche was in old tyme of so great fame and power, that so muche parte of al the countrey of Syria as reacheth vnto Cicilie &amp; butteth vpō it, had the name geuen it thereof; And the sayed Antioche was in this behalf more happie and fortunate then verye Rome it self, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Peter y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apostle had his first see here in this citie of Antioche and that Paule, and Barnabas dyd in the same citie receiue their dignitie of the charge and funcciō Apostolical. Now to our present purpose this Luke
<pb n="viii" facs="237"/>
was of familiar acquaintaunce and comiersacion with all the Apostles, but most specially a folower and disciple of Paule, and also a companion of his in all his peregrinaciō, neuer separated nor deuided from his coumpany. By linyng in coumpany with the Apostles, he wrote his ghospell: and by the thynges whiche Paule wrought and did, Luke beyng a presente witnesse of theim, he wrote the booke whiche he entytled, <hi>the actes of the apostles.</hi> And that hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie of the Actes, he continued vntill the second yere of Paul abydyng at Rome, that is to say, vntill the fowerth yere of Nero, the Emperour there. Wherof men gather a consecture that the boke was writtē in the same citie. and fully agreed it is amonge the learned men,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. viii.</note> that this same verye Luke it is, of whom Paul the Apostle doeth so often tymes make mencion: as for e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aumple, in his second epistle to the Corinthians, where he thus saith: We haue sēt with him our brother, whose lande is in the gospel throughout all the congregacions. Again, where he writeth to the Collosstās, he sayth: dere Lukes the physicion greteth you.<note place="margin">Colloss. iii. i. Tim. iiii.</note> And agayne in the secound epystle to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe: For Demas hath forsaken me, louing this presēt world, &amp; is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto. Thessalonica: Crescens, is gone into Galacia: Titus into Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia: onely Lukas is with me. Yea and this point moreouer is leaft to vs by auncyent writers, that as often as Paul calleth it by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of his gospell, (as he doeth to Timothe,<note place="margin">ii. Tim. ii.</note> where he saieth: Remembre that Iesus Christ of the seede of Dauid arose again from death accordyng to my gospell. &amp;c.) he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>neth of the ghospel of Luke, because that like as Marke wrote the histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the gospell at Peters woorde, by his settying on, so dyd Luke at the word and biddyng of Paule. Hierome is of the opinion and iudgement, that Luke was more expert in the greke tongue then the other were, and by reasoasō therof wrote the discourse and processe of the story after a more e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and gromidely sort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> then the others dyd, that is to were, takyng his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce at the first concepcion of Iohn the Baptist, and makyng relacion of verye muche ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter touchyng the natiuitie, and concernyng the babehoode, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ea and certayne poyntes furthermore concernyng the childhood of Iesus, making also rehersall of many parables and miracles whiche the other euā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes for loue of briefnes had let passe he any thing spoken of. And where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s not one of all the others went any wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t ferther then the tyme of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lorde Iesus beyng assumpted into heauen, this man alone did in an other seconde boke make a further continuaciō of the story concerning the churche, howe it first sprang vp, and how it grewe more and more to sprede and shew it self. Thus muche moreouer the wryters affyrme: that lyke as Matthew wrote his ghospell, and Peter his epistles, chyefely vnto the Iewes: so dyd Luke wryte his gospell most specially to the Gentiles, as one that was a disciple of Paules, which Paul as he was the teacher of Gētiles, so did he write all his epistles vnto Gentiles, except the only one epistle to the Hebrues, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eaufou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> &amp; writer wherof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t hath euermore been doubted whether it were Paule or not. He wrote his ghospel after Marke, but yet before that Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e his, by reason wherof beyng but a disciple, he is set before Iohn who was an Apostle. And to conclude, it is written that a long lyued manne he was, whiche thyng was in a physicion, euen as of congruence it ought to be. for he folowed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coūsa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le of Paul, which wrote: It is good not to touche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: he liued a single man fower score and fower yeres.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="238"/>The bones of him after he was dead, wer remoued and conueied out of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia, to Constantinople, together with the bones of Andrewe the apostle, in the twētieth yere of Cōstancius. Ye haue nowe a phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>icion for the soule of a physicion for the body, a man by his familiaritie of conuersacion, with the Apostles habled, and by mo testimonies then one of Paul the apostle, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and praysed, and by the wholle consent of all the faythfull congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaciōs allowed. For where the gospels of many were reiected and refused, Luke was by the consent of al the congregacions voices receyued, to make vp that same holy and mistical quaternitie, which Moses in old tyme limy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, whan he expoūded vnto vs the fower-studdes or riuers welling vp out of one spryng in paradise, whiche studdes do water al the earth vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall: and the whiche quaternitie the Prophet Ezechiell afterward saw, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>̄ he playnly set out vnto vs (as it had been in a picture) the fower mystycall beastes &amp; the fower wheles in one. Nowe if it be so thought good, let vs in fewe wordes, sumwhat speake of the pocion or medicine that he hath geuen vs. He had been wonte out of Hyprocrates to take medicines wherewith to remedie diseases of the body, but this medicine of the ghospel, wherwith to cure and heale our soules, he toke of the Apostles, whiche had both seen and heard Christ, yea or rather of the veray holy ghost himself.</p>
   <p>There was among the physicions of olde time, a certain kind of medicine of passyng great efficacie &amp; vertue, whiche medicine they called in Greke <hi>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> that is to say, Gods handes, lyke as there is nowe a confeccion that is called <hi>manus Christi.</hi> But yet was there neuer any medicine inuented by the Phisicions, that was able to remedie al diseases of the body, though they make neuer so muche vauntes and boast of that same which they call, <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> a medicine (as they affirme) effectual and of muche vertue, but knowen to us man. Once the sicknes of olde age geueth place to no phisike. But this same medicine of the ghospel is in very true dede, the <hi>manus Christi</hi>▪ whiche thorough syncere faith doeth once for altogether take away all diseases of the soules, &amp; geueth immortalitie: which thing apperteineth onely vnto god to do. And certes it was a thyng not vnfearly ne vnskilfully spoken in the prouerbes of the Grekes, that woordes and talke is the physicion of a mynde beyng dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eased and sicke: yea and sum there hath been, which beleued that the diseases of the body also myght be driuen away with certayne hartie wordes aduy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly spoken, hauyng a certain magical vertue &amp; efficacie in them. The Lord Ies{us} was a phisiciō, who while he liued here on earth, did with his wordes put awaye diseases of the bodies, were they neuer so sore, or of neuer so lōg continuance rooted in them. Yea and with his wordes he raysed dead folkes to lyfe agayne. For his woord was no woord of magike: but the almighty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful word of the omnipotēt father. The same Christ did also with his word driue awaye diseases of the soules, whan he sayd: Sonne thy synnes are forgeuen the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and in an other place: Goe thy wayes, thy fayth hath made the whole. And in cōsideracion hereof the prophecy had afore promised y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Christ should be a physicion. For it sayeth in the booke of Sapience: For neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearbe ne any supplyng plaister hath healed them, but thy word, o Lord, whiche healeth all thynges. Thissame verily is that true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicious speake of, as afore sayd. Also the mystical psalme hath this sentence. He sent his woord, and he healed them from their vtter peryshynges. The
<pb n="ix" facs="238"/>
liuelye woorde of the father is Christe. He had sent Moses and the prophetes: and by them was the nacion of the Iewes taken in cure to be loked vnto, but they were not clene healed. Onelye the woorde of the father was of sufficiente vertue and efficacie to heale the diseases of man, and not onelye the lighte dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, but also the mortall and deadly sickenesses. For it is a marke whereby to know that it speaketh of deadly sickenesses, whan the prophete addeth, from theyr vtter perishynges. At suche tyme as the stomacke is so clene fallen awaye that it abhorreth and refuseth all kynde of meate, than groweth the sicke partie to wardes his death, and of suche manier a disease was all the whole vniuersall worlde sicke, before the cumming of the heauenly phisician. Whiche thing had the psalmiste a litle tofore spoken: Their solle abhorred all kynde of meate, they were drawen nere, euen to the gates of death. There had bene manye soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry dren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hes tempered by the philosophiers, as for exaumple, by the secte of Pythagoras, by the Academikes, by the Stoikes, by the Epicureans, and by the Perepatetikes, promisyng perfect healthe of the myndes, yea and heauens blisse too. Moses tempered many pocions, prescrybyng and appoyntyng soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ceremonies of religion and of seruyng▪ god: the prophetes also made muche and many temperynges to thesame ende and purpose: but by reason of disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses growyng strong and preuayling, the phisicke and medicines auailed not, ne dyd any other good, sauing that it encreased the diseases, and bewrayed the same that it might appere. The stomacke of the soule beeyng corrupte with naughtie desyres, as it had beene with euell and hurtefull humoures, dyd on the one syde turne theyr face awaye from the moral preceptes and lessons of the philosophiers composed with greate labour and studye: and on the other syde by the ordinaunces and prescripcions of Moses▪ they were made the more su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persticious, but nothyng the better men. As for the bittur chydyng whiche the prophetes ministred, had no good relice ne taste in theyr mouthes, and therfore was there no credyte geuen to theyr promises. Whiche thyng the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen whan he sawe, because he woulde not haue any thyng to perishe of all that he had created: sente foorth his woorde who should with an heauenly medicine delyuer all people from all diseases of theyr soules, onelye requiryng of vs to acknowleage our disease, and put assured trust and confidence in the phisician. And lyke as the louyng &amp; frendely phisiciās, if at any time they cannot styll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne to bee euermore present with theyr pacientes, doe commonly vse to leaue some boxe or receypt of phisicke with them, whereby the parties that are sicke maye be theyr owne phisicians, if the case shoulde so require: so the lorde Iesus when he returned into heauen, leafte vnto vs by his Apostles a medicinable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuarie of the gospell, bothe easye and readie for euery bodye that wyll take it, but of great vertue and effecte, if a man receyue it as it ought to be: and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to take it to ones profite and benefite, the chiefe thyng that worketh it, is his assured trust and affiaunce in the phisician.</p>
   <p>Neither is it enough to haue taken a stendre taste or assaye thereof, but it muste be receiued and conueyghed into the veraye bowels, that as soone as it is receyued within the stomacke, the vertue therof maye haue full course to renne euery waye throughout all the veynes. At suche tyme and neuer till than it begynneth to roumble and shake all the partie from toppe to toe with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of his former life: but after this great troublyng and confusion, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ensueth greate tranquillitie of mynde and quiet of the conscience. The
<pb facs="239"/>
phisicians of the bodyes, haue practicioners, and poticaries that dooe ministre theyr arte vnder them: and theimselues are the prescribers and appoyneters what it is that must bee geuen to the sicke: Christ alone it is and none els, that hath prescribed the medicine of euerlastyng saluacion. The Apostles, and their successours the bishops, are no more but ministers, they temper in due propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, they fyne and beate to powder, they laye to the places diseased, not receip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of theyr owne, but of Christes. They baptise in water, but Christe it is that washeth the soule cleane: they teache the thynges whiche he taught and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto theim, but Christes owne selfe it is, whiche maketh that theyr wordes maye take effecte. The corporall phisicians dooe often tymes varie aswell in their iudicials of the diseases, as also in appoyntyng medicines for thesame: yea and many tymes in stede of medicines they appoynte thynges that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray poyson to the sickenes, accordyng to the saying of the greke Poete.</p>
   <p>Many of the medicines be good that are wrought,</p>
   <p>And many of theim again are sterke staryng nought.</p>
   <p>But of the phisicke and medicine Euangelicall, there is but onely one receip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, whiche ought of no mortall creature to bee either corrupted or altered. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to conclude, it is confect of no mo but one simple, so that althoughe they, whose parte and duetie it were to be ministers of the same, woulde bee slacke to dooe theyr office, euery man maye take it and ministre vnto hymselfe, so that he haue a mynde feithfully trustyng, a mynde syncere, and desirous of health. For euen that same chiefe and head phisician of all, who alone and none but he is of power hable to heale all the whole manne, did at some seasons geue health by hymselfe in his owne persone, and many tymes also by the ministerie of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles and disciples. Now ferthermore all the whole facultie and arte of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, hath two markes that it principally shoteth at: the one that it maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer the bodye from diseases, and from suche thynges as doe brede diseases, &amp; this parte is by the phisicans terme, called <hi>therapeutica,</hi> that is to saye, the arte of curyng or healyng diseases: secondelye theyr arte is to preserue and continue the healthfull state of the bodye, and to encreace the strength: and this parte of phisicke they place in the ordreing of the diete.</p>
   <p>For the phisicians dooe not euermore sere with hote yrons, or cutte, they doe not euermore geue pocions of scammonie to consume and waste the fleashe as men in manier sleaghyng and martiring the bodye, to kepe it in lyfe: but some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes they ministre suche thynges as maye make the herte lyghte and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rie, yea and also they geue the bodye sustinaunce at large: So there is firste of all ministred vnto vs the pocion of faith, whiche troubleth the soule and conscience with repentaunce, and emptying vs, dooeth discharge and vnlade vs of oure synne. Than immediatly therupon is geuen an electuarie of consolacion, of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortyng and of more perfeict doctrine. For if a phisician, as soone as he hath made the bodye emptie by purgacion, should soodaynely geue vp the sicke pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and leat hym alone, it is an hazarde and ieopardie leste whan it is desty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all the strength, some power and rage of a greater sickenesse maye take it, as for example, the paulsey, the generall taking or dissolucion of all the lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and senewes, wherupon men lye bedred, or a consumpcion. So after that repentaunce hath cast downe our combe, and hath well shaken our disease, whā baptisme hath scoured or pourged vs and made vs emptie and voyde from al synnes, there bee suche thinges ministred, and geuen to vs, as maye holsomlye
<pb n="x" facs="239"/>
replenishe the soule agayne beeyng now well clensed and made voyde. Wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes is voyded out, and tentilnesse and mekenesse is in stede thereof infused. Enuie is sucked out, and taking of all thynges to the best, put in for it. Picling and pollyng is voyded out, and in place therof succedeth liberalitie. The fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent desyre of makyng warre, is consumed awaye, and the earnest zele of peace cometh in for it. The loue of sensuall pleasures of the fleshe is expelled, and in their stede entreth the loue of thynges celestiall. Wyll ye heare what is the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ammonie euangelicall? <hi>Dooe ye penaunce. The axe is nowe alreadie sette at the roote of the tree. And euerie tree that bringeth not foorth good fruicte is cutte vp.</hi> And Paule in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier: <hi>Mortifie your membres whiche are vpon yearth: whoorehuntyng, vncleannesse, wanton lust, euill concupiscence, and auarice.</hi> And within fewe woordes after it foloweth: <hi>spoysyng your selues of the olde man with all his actes.</hi> He hathe now voyded out the ill humoures, how doeth he fill vp the emptie place agayne? <hi>Dooe vpon youre selues,</hi> (sayth he) <hi>as the saintes &amp; the elected of God, the bowels of mercie, bounteousnesse, submission, humilitie, pacience, suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng one another, and forgeuyng your selues emong you if any persone haue a querele agaynste an other, lyke as the Lorde also hathe giuen to you. And aboue all these thynges haue ye charitie, whiche is the bande of perfeccion, and seat the peace of Christe reioyce in your heartes.</hi> Suche mannier an house swap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> cleane with broomes and replenished on euery syde with suche or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes▪ the eiuell spirite shall not eftsones entre vpon, whan he returneth with seuen wurse then himselfe. Thus than the Euangelicall medicine hath wyne of it owne, wherewith to scoure the mattier of oure woundes that they smarte agayne. <hi>Auaunt, come behynde me Satan, thou sauourest not tho thynges whiche are of god, but whiche are of men.</hi> Now see the suppleyng oyle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thesame <hi>Haue ye a perfecte trust and confidence, for I haue ouercommed the worlde. A heare of heade shall not perishe. Be ye not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>earde litle flocke, for yours is the kyngdome of heauen.</hi> Paule hathe meate, wherewith he coumforteth and cherisheth suche as are but newlye conuerted to Christe, that they maye not fal agayne into diseases, forasmuche as they are yet weake: he hath also sounde and substanciall meate that maye kepe theim in perfeicte strength, growyng forewarde from daye to daye vnto the measure of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Christe. Those persones had gathered perfeict strengthe, of whome it is thus wrytten in the actes of the Apostles: <hi>They went reioycyng oute of the sight of the counsell, in that they had been reputed worthie to suffre reproche for the name of Iesus.</hi> That man also had gathered perfeicte strength whiche layed: <hi>I can dooe all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in hym that maketh me strong.</hi> And for this consideracion the Lorde Iesus in the ghospell exhorteth menne to the eatyng of the breade that was come from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the eatyng whereof geueth immortalitie. He exhorteth men to the eatyng of his fleshe, and to the drinking of his bloude, meanyng vndoubtedlye of his doctrine, whiche beyng as breade to the soule, dooeth make thesame lustie and strong and (as effectuall strong wyne) doeth inebricate men and bryng them in a godly kynde of drounkennesse, euen to the contempte of this worlde, in lyke maner as fleashe hath sound nourishemente for the bodye, and lyke as bloude hath a vertue and effecte vnto lyfe. And though all the scripture of god haue a medicinable vertue and power in it: yet hath it none a more effectuall electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye or receipt then that pertaineth to the ghospel. One and thesame spirite it is, that is in all the Scriptures of God, but yet in the ghospell especiallye his pleasure was, that the thyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ould remaine, wherin he might speciallye shewe foorth his owne power, because there shoulde appere some difference betwene the seruauntes and the maister, betwene the puddels or litle gutters, and the
<pb facs="240"/>
spryng or fountaine. And truely it is a labour well bestowed, to considre how great a thyng the vertue of this medicine is. Euerie common weale is (as ye woulde saye) a certayne body. The pestilent diseases and sickenesses of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, are euil maniers. Againste whiche diseases such men as haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled others in wysedome, haue in soondrye regions or deyned and set lawes, as it were certayne medicines and remedies for thesame, as for exaumple, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Atheniens, Solon made lawes: emong the Lacedemonians, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus: emong the people of Crete, Minos: emong the Romaynes the tenne Commissioners called in theyr toungue, <hi>Decemuiti.</hi> Yet not one of all these men, was hable to bryng to passe, that other nacions also would enbrace and receiue the lawes that he had made. No neither dyd any of them so muche as attempte such a thyng, leste besides spendyng of labour in vayne, he shoulde also haue wonne an opinion of a shamelesse acte in his so doyng. Solon was fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to liue tenne yeares a banished man for thrustyng his lawes into the citie of Athens alone to be vsed there. Plato a man so well learned and so eloquent, coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bryng the people of Athens in mynde to receyue his lawes. And yet is there no doubtes to bee made, but that euerye one of theim perswaded theimselues, that the lawes whiche they hadde made were true, and that they wisshed (yf it myght possibly haue been brought to passe) that all the world should haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced and receyued thesame. No nor the lawes of Moses neither were ipr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d abrode or receyued any ferther then within onely one nacion, although in dede the Pharisets did with great highe suyt hunte to wynne and geat vnto them a fewe proselites, that is to saye, foreyns and aliens wonne to their religion. Fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, not the violent autoritie of the Emperours neither, was hable by vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or compulsion to obteyne, that theyr lawes might haue weight and force with all nacions. And the thyng whiche all the sayed persones by the lawes that they made did endeuour to bryng about, thesame did also the Philosophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers attempt by theyr morall rules and lessons, with great iudgement, and with incomparable diligence and labour wryten and published. Of al which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse, not one hath there been so eloquente or so well learned, that he hath been hable to bryng any one nacion in the mynde that he woulde haue theim in, so werishe and vneffectuall was the vertue of the medicine of phisicke which they broughte. Onelye the trueth Euangelicall dyd in processe of a fewe yeares possesse, perswade, and ouercome all nacions of the worlde full and wholle, drawyng vnto it the Grekes, and the barbarous peoples, the learned and the vnlearned, the inferiour common people, and kynges and all. So pith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hy and so effectuall was the electuarie of this trueth, that so many thousandes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forsakyng the lawes of their owne countreyes, renouncyng the religiō that theyr forefathers had vsed▪ leauyng aswell the sensuall pleasures and vices, whiche from their cradels they had been accustomed vnto: they enbraced a new and a forein doctrine, and out of diuerse toungues, and ordinaunces of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie sorte, they did consente to the receyuyng of a certaine lowe and basse philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie: especiallye at suche a tyme as neuer was there any of the lyke sorte fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished nor armed either with the maintenaunce and supportacion of learnyng and eloquence, or with the power and autoritie of princes: and at suche a time ferthermore whā al the worlde with al the strengthe that it had, fought against the trueth of the ghospel beeyng vnarmed and naked: yet neuerthelesse it could
<pb n="xi" facs="240"/>
not possiblye bryng to passe, but that the sayed trueth after that it firste <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntred possession vpon the countrey of Grece, inuaded also the citie of Rome, and the veraye courte of Ner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, and foorthwith spred it self abrode throughout all and singular the prouincies of the Empire of Rome, euen vntill the Isles called Gades, lying in the ferthest parte beyonde Spaigne, and vnto the Indians, vnto the peoples of Afrike, and the Scithians, and the Isle of Britannia now called Englande, beyng a countrey vttrelye diuided and cutte of from all the rest of the worlde. These nacions and peoples dyd verye muche differ one from another in theyr languages, lawes, rytes, vsages, ordeynaunces, Goddes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and facions: and anon beeyng from suche great discorde broughte to a generall vniformitie, they begonne to syng all one song, extollyng with laudes and prayses Iesus Christe the onely lorde and salueour of the worlde. And all this while, the spoylyng of their goodes, their banishementes, emprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonynges, tormentes, deathes, were none other thing but good procedyng and goyng forewarde of the ghospell. What persone hath there euer been founde, that hath been content to suffre death for the lawes of Solon, or the morall preceptes of Zeno? But for the simple and playne doctryne of Christ, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousandes of men, both olde &amp; young, how many thousandes of matrones and vyrgins, haue willyngly offered and holden out their neckes to bee chopte of? And yet how muche more wondrefull, and more abhorryng from commune reason, are the thinges whiche the ghospell teacheth, then whiche the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes, that is to saie the straunge opinions of the philosophiers, dooe teache? And the sayd philosophiers doctryne not one of the princes did euer make anye a dooe to destroye or suppresse, and yet of it owne accorde it vanyshed awaye, lyke as did also theyr lawes, and the arte magicall, and the rites of sacryfices. For what creature dooeth at this daye sacrifyce vnto the Gods of the Heathen, or slaygheth beastes in sacrifice as the Iewes did? What persone dooeth now knowe of Zoroastes? What man setteth an heare by the misticall riddels of Pythagoras? Who readeth the lyfe of Apollonius Tyaneus any otherwyse then as a certayne dreame? Yea or rather who vouchesalueth to reade it at al? For where Aristotell is at these dayes of greate name and fame in the scholes, leat hym neuer thanke his owne f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cte therefore, but the Christians. For euen he had perished too, yf there had not been made a medley of Christe and hym to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in our schooles of diuinitie. Against the philosophie Euangelical, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, yet but tendre and euen but newly spryngyng vp, the worlde arose at the first chop with all his force and power, by meane of the Iewes, vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texte and coulour of religion fightyng agaynst the fountaine of all religion, by meane of the philosophiers beeyng hable muche to doe in all kyndes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng by meane of the Sophisters beyng felowes vnpossible to bee ouercōmed in stiffenesse of holdyng argumentacions, by meane of the rhetoricians beyng meruaylous in the force of eloquence, by the tyrannes beeyng armed with all sortes of shewyng crueltie, by meane of kynges, lieutenauntes, magistrates, by suche as were cunnynng in magike and sorcerie, and perfecte in the sleyght of castyng mystes ouer mennes iyes and other senses, and by meane of eiuyll spirites beeyng the lordes of this worlde. All suche tumultuous buisynesse, as these, (as a sea of eiuils swellyng vp and ouerflowyng,) dydde the power of the trueth Euangelicall receiue, endure, breake throughe, and vtterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. For at the lighte of the ghospell whan it came, it was reason that all
<pb facs="241"/>
counterfaictes of worldly power should clene vanishe a waye. Up shot that same ghospell and shewed it selfe beeyng plaine and lowe, whiche all men w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> great a doe endeuoured to ouertrede and kepe downe. The bokes of suche persones, as with singular high witte, with woondrefull learnyng, and with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite eloquence wrote agaynst the ghospel, vanished awaye of theyr owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde as it had been certayne dreames, insomuche that they are not at this day remaynyng to bee had neyther, excepte if any fragmentes or small pieces haue been saued of the Christians, by reason of wrytyng agaynst them in confuting them. The kynges and princes dooe nowe bough downe, to honoure the thyng which to fore they wēt about to destroie: the power of magike is vanished awai and gone: the euill spirites are cast out that they howle and rore agayn: philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophie hath confessed her ignoraunce: and geuyng ouer the foolishe wisedome of the world, it hath enbraced the wysedome of the crosse: the rethoricians write oracions in the prayse of Iesus Christ: the poetes do hisse the olde goddes out of place, and in the lieu and place of Goddes innumerable, all their song and composyng is nowe of Iesus Christe alone. Thissame so great a chaunge of the world, begoonne within a fewe yeares after Christ was putte to death, to be made generall and common through al the whole worlde, and withoute any maintenaunce or supportacion of mā, it encreaced from tyme to tyme still more and more, vntyll the piece of leauen beeyng miengled in three pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>kes of meale did▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>auen and turne al the whole batche, and vntill the graine of mustard seed beeyng digged into the yearth, did ferre and wyde spleygh his boughes abrode ouer Asia, ouer Afrike, and Europe. And ouer and besydes all this, those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones who layed theyr battrey agaynst the trueth Euangelical to cast it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owne and to destroye it, not onely had diuerse and sondry kyndes of terroures, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with euen very manly stomakes also might haue been quayled, that is to we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e open cōmaundementes by proclamacion, consistories &amp; places of iudgemente, forfaityng of al theyr goodes to the princes, attaindres and depriuacions, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishementes, priesons, tormentes of burnyng plates, scourgyng with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oddis, axes wherwith to choppe of theyr heades, ieobettes, fiers to burne them, wylde beastes to cast them to, that thei might be deuoured, deathes: but also they had diuerse and soondrye allurementes, wherewith an herte though it wer right cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent might bee corrupted. Ceasar would saye to some one of them: Rencague thou and forsake Christ, and be thou the chiefe emong all my piers, and except thou so do, all thy gooddes shall be forfayte to my behoufe. I wyll shewe all extremitie of rigour towarde thy wyfe and children, and thyselfe for thyne own part shalt bee cast to wylde beastes in a denne. Who did in suche cases as these perswade so many thousandes, and bryng them in mynde with reioycyng to take it whan theyr promocions and dignities were taken from them, whan theyr gooddes were spoyled, that whan they sawe those parties haled with all violence to huige tormentes and execucion of death, who nexte after God were moste derely beloued vnto them, they should geue thankes to God: and finally that themselues whan they might easly haue escaped, and whan they might haue enioyed suche high commodities, should of theyr owne voluntary wylles off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e themselues to bee cruelly martyred? No power of humayne elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence could this haue dooen: but the godlye power of the trueth was hable, whiche laye hidden in the graine of mustardsede. Neither did the philosophiers doctrine lacke alluremente. The Stoykes promised libertie and fredome, true
<pb n="xii" facs="241"/>
rychesse, health, reigne, &amp; other thynges magnificent and royall to be spoken. The Epicureans made highe woordes and promises of pleasure to the cares of men. The Peripatetikes dyd couple the good giftes of the bodye with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. But the doctrine of the ghospell as it did not drawe any body vnto it with any worldly terrours: so on the contrary parte, how fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re was it from hauyng any thyng commendable in outwarde shewe to see to, naye rather howe many thynges did it conteine vttrely vncredible? It telleth newes of one Iesus nail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the crosse, who had by his death deliuered mankynde, and this Iesus to be bothe god and man, borne of a virgin, and one that had returned agayne from death to life, and was nowe sitting at the right hande of God the father, and thesame Iesus to had been a man that had taught suche persones to bee in blissed case, as for the profession of his name did mourne and warle, did suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre thirst or hungre, were put to affliccion, wer euill spoken of, or were putte to death: and that all men shall in time to come arise to life agayn, and that the godly sorte at that daye (thesame veray Iesus beeyng their iudge,) shall haue immortalitie to their lotte, &amp; the wicked shall haue the peines of hell for euer without ende to endure. What philosopher durst haue entreprised to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poune suche thynges as these so ferre contrarye to all mennes opinion or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, and thynges so vntouthsome for menne to bee fond on, or to make anye great countenaunce vnto? Yet all these thynges neuerthelesse dyd the law talke of, the ghospell dyd in suche wyse perswade, that suche an one is taken for mad and cleane out of his wittes, as dooeth not beleue it: and that so manye thousandes of people will sooner forsake their life, then the profession of the trueth Euāgelical. And by what maner felowes at last dyd so great a chaunge of the worlde firste come vp? by meane of a fewe disciples beeyng menne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen, men of lowe degree, men of pouertie, &amp; vnlearned. To what purpose is it to speake of the rest, whan Peter the chiefe of them was a fisher, and of no ferther knowlage but his bare mother toungue, Paule a leather sewer, and not one of them all, a man of rychesse, or a man of power, or a ientle man? And either nothyng at all had they of this worldes, or in case thei had aforetymes had, they clene forsooke it. And by what wayes was it possible for suche men to bryng so great a matier to passe? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erres they brought a medicine in a vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e boxe but it was through godly vertue, a medicine of great power and efficacie. The talke euangelicall is of a playne homely sorte, and of no eloquent compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syng, whiche in case a manne examine and trye by the storie of Thucidides in greke, or of Titus Liuius in latine, he shall fynde a lacke of many thynges, &amp; with many poyntes shall he be offended. What a noumbre of thynges dooe the Euangelistes leat passe, howe manye thynges dooe they touche with three woordes and no more▪ in how many places dooeth the ordre disagree, and in how many places dooe they appere to be one contrarie vnto another? It was possible that suche thinges should haue turned awaye the mynde of the reader from the readyng of it, and should haue caused it neuer to be beleued. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwyse they that haue written stories of worldly affaires, how carefull are they wherof to make the first begynnyng of the matter, what labour &amp; diligence do they bestowe, that thei maye not tell anye thyng otherwyse then is semyng, that they maye not tell any thyng vnlykely, that they maye not tell any thyng not standyng together, or any thynges contrary vnto reason?</p>
   <p>Than ferther with what euidence dooe they laye the thyng playne before
<pb facs="242"/>
mennes iyes, with what swete pleasaunt knackes and conceiptes do they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente and reteine the readers mynde, that no pointe of tediousnesse maye come stealyng vpon hym? But the monumentes of all this sorte of wryters hauyng been composed with great labour and studie, are a great porcion of them lost, and those that remayne are reade neither of all persones, and yet withoute ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng any credite vnto them. For what persone is there so light of belefe, that he wyll auouche and waraunt, that in all Titus Liuius there is no poynte cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned of telling an vntrueth? But so many thousandes of people there haue been found, whiche would with better will tenne times suffre death, then to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte or graunte any one false clause to bee conteined in the writinges of the gospell. Haue we not than of these premisses an euidēt marke whereby to know the matter not to be of worldly auctoritee or wisedome, but of the vertue and power of God? There is a secrete vertue and efficacie lying hidden in the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, whiche whan it was once poured into the body, spred it selfe abrode ouer all the vniuersall nacions of the worlde, as if it were by resemblaunce, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the membres. We haue nowe the cause, why the veritie euangelicall did within so fewe yeares by men of lowe degree, sprede it selfe abrode all the world ouer, whan thesame worlde rebelled against it with all kyndes of extreme cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And now maie it come in some mannes mynde greatly to meruaile by what reason it hath come to passe that in those later seasons, whan the worlde had Christian princes, Bishops, men of learnyng, welthie and riche persones, and endued with great authoritie, the dicion of Christe is so shrounken together in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a narowe roume. For the cause of this matier beeyng well knowen, a remedie might perhappes the sooner be founde. But I hauyng a good while sence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottē my self, do passe the limites &amp; boūdes of a preface. I therefore returne now to our phisicion Luke, whome lyke as I doubte not to be right acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your grace: so woulde I by my good wyll haue hym by meane of thesame your grace, to be made the more acceptable vnto all people. The wyse Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticus speaketh in this manier: Honour thou the phisicion for necessities sake. How muche more than ought condigne honour to be shewed to this phisicion, who hath ientilly geuen vs so effectuall a receipt of phisicke, whiche is to euery creature necessary, except if any suche persone there bee, whiche is withoute all faulte and hath no nede to waxe a better man than he was? And certes it will also bee effectuall, if we beeyng vttrely wery of our diseases and infirmities, shall oftentymes byte of this medicine, if we shall continuallye chawe it, if we shall conueye it to passe into our stomake and into the botome of oure herte, if we shall not vomite vp agayne that hath been taken therof, but shall kepe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same still in the stomake of oure soule, vntill it cast a brode the vertue that it hath, the chaunge vs altogether into it selfe. This poynte by experience haue I founde in myne owneselfe, that litle fruite there commeth of the gospell, if a man reade it but sluggishely, and superficially renne it ouer. But in case a mā do with diligent and exquisite meditacion kepe hymself occupied therin, he shal fele a certaine vertue and pith suche as he shall not fele the lyke in any other bookes. Nowe to preuente makyng of myne aunswer vnto the suspicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynges of menne, for that I haue dedicated euery particular paraphrase of the ghospels seuerally to particular princes, it is veray chaunce and not anye ambicion or sekyng on my behalfe. For the same thyng hath fortuned vnto me in this matier, that fortuned in the epistles Apostolicall. Whan I wrote the
<pb n="xiii" facs="242"/>
paraphrase vpon Matthewe, I loked for nothyng lesse, then that Iohn should bee earnestly required, and immediatly after hym this Lukas. But nowe to thentente there shall not any glasewyndoore or gappe bee seen emong the Euā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes, I wyll adde Marke also vnto the other three: albeit he that dedicateth sondrie ghospels to sondrie men, maie seme to do neuer a whit more contrarie to reason, then did Sayncte Hierome, who dedicated, yea euen the lesser Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, vnto seuerall persones. I haue elswhere geuen aduertisemente, and do now eftsons geue warning vnto the reader, that he esteme no more auctoritie to be in any paraphrase of myne, then he woulde geue to the commentaries of other wryters. For I do not for any suche purpose wryte paraphrases, because I would shake or strike the gospell out of mennes handes, but to thentente it maye be read the more commodiouslye to a mannes mynde, and with the more fruite, lyke as meates are sauced to the ende they maye be taken with the better will and the more delectacion. Yea and of one ferther poynte also must I here warne a reader that is somewhat grosse of vnderstanding, whiche is, that it bee not myne owne woordes that I do any where speake in the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase, leste the thyng whiche vnder the persone of the Euangeliste is humbly and truely spoken, maye seme to bee arrogauntlye spoken vnder myne owne persone. The lord Iesus geue his spirite vnto you, moste noble kyng, to the ende that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your proteccion beeyng a true Christian Prince in dede, the veritie of the gospell maye from daye to daye more and more reigne and flourishe.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Yeuen at Basill <date>the .xxiii. daye of August in the yeare of our Lorde M.D.xxiii.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>