<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1540</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S718_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16087</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2968</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Epistles and Gospelles with a brief postil vpon the same from after Easter tyll Aduent, which is the somer parte : set forth for the singuler cōmoditie of all good Christen men and namely of prestes and curates. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1540</date>
                 <publisher>Bankes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Clerke, Anthony</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, lxx leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>Rycharde Tauerner clerke of the Signet to oure so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lorde the kynge wyssheth to the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten reader al grace from God aboue and increase of knowledge in his worde</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>FOrasmuche as (good christen reader) at thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent<note place="margin">Mat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> IX.</note> tyme according to our Lordes word, the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uest is greate and plenteouse, but the labourers are <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ewe: I meane as thus, that the people be very desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous &amp; gready to receyue gods word, yf they had plē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of sobre modeste &amp; sincere teachers, wheras nowe for skacetie of such in some places they be destitute &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cattered a brode euen as shepe lacking feythful she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdes: I was instantly required, to thintent y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Lord of the haruest myght by thys meane thrust forth his labourers in to his harueste, to peruse and recognize this brefe postel which was deliuerid me of certayne godly persons for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> purpose &amp; intente. which thinge to my lytel power and as the shortnes of tyme wolde serue, I haue done. And such sermons or homylyes as semed to want, I haue supplyed partely w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> myne owne industrye, &amp; partlye w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the helpe of other sober men whych be better lernyd then I my selfe. Now, yf ye &amp; namely you pristes &amp; curates shall vse thys syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler helpe and benifyte, whych is here offered vnto you, well and to the edificatiō of Christes churche, ye shal gyue occasis̄ that other fruteful workes may be hereafter at the cōmaūdemēt of the kynges maiestie or of his most honorable counsel set forth and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed vnto you. But yf, on the contrary part, after the<note place="margin">X<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Luk. Mat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> xxvi.</note> exemple of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnprofitable seruaūt spokē of in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ye wol not fynde in your hartes charitably &amp; pru dently to occupye this talent that here is frankely de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered
<pb facs="2"/>
 vnto you, but wyll eyther wrappe it vp in a fayre napkyn or els vnreuerently handle it to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and not to the edification of others: he ye then sure, that not only no mo such benefytes shalbe bestowed vpon you, but also all that whyche ye haue already, shalbe taken from you &amp; that not vnworthy ly. Yea &amp; fynally accordynge to our Lordes owne sē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ye shalbe caste as seruantes vnprofytable int vtter darkenes, where shalbe wepynge &amp; gnashyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of teeth. But there is good hope that ye woll other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse demene your selues, namely nowe syth ye be so beningly inuited, inioyned, &amp; cōtinually called vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to execute youre office in thys behalfe by oure hygh shepeherde vnder Christ &amp; supreme heade oure most dradde soueraigne lorde the kinges maiestie whom, I doubte not, but ye woll gladly obeye, I meane to fede more often your flocke cōmytted to your charge not with rashe, erronyouse, heretical or fabulouse ser mons, but with sobre, discret, catholike and Godly in structions such as be here described vnto you or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter yf better ye can deuyse. In whych thynge doyng; ye shall vndoubtedly not onely declare youre selues obedient to your supreme heade Gods minister, but also ye shall discharge youre conscience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God of the due ministratiō where vnto ye be called. To whome be gyuen all prayse and glorye worlde wythout ende.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <pb facs="3"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>