<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my louing and be∣loued Friends and Neighbours, the Parishioners of S. Matthews Friday street, increase of Grace in the knowledge of Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Burton, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S734_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17301</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4143</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my louing and be∣loued Friends and Neighbours, the Parishioners of S. Matthews Friday street, increase of Grace in the knowledge of Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Grounds of Christian religion : laid downe briefly and plainely by way of question and answer / by H.B</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bird, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="24"/>
   <head>To my louing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Friends and Neighbours, the Parishioners of S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Friday street, increase of Grace in the knowledge of Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost louing neighbors, though late, yet now at length I present you with a Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, small in bulke, but for the substance weighty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the summe of those doctrines which you haue heard me deliuer in the course of my ministeriall charge; so as both you may more properly challenge an interest here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in then others: and my selfe may more boldly presume of an acceptance at your hands, of whose patience and loue towards my poore ministry I haue had so plentifull proofe. The Preacher saith, The words of the wise are as goads, and as nayles faste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the masters of assemblies, which are giuen by one shepheard. I therefore haue collected these short notes to be as nayles to
<pb facs="25"/>
fasten the maine doctrines (which you haue heard, and here may see) vpon your belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hearts, and as goades, to quicken vp your willing <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> affections to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of holinesse in the feare of God. And because it is the duty of faithfull parents to propagate and conuey the knowledge of Christ vnto their children and families, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did: I therefore commend these grounds to your Christian care, to the end you may the more easily instruct your fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in them, that you with yours being built vpon the rocke of truth, may be established in the beliefe and loue of the same against the windes of errour, and waues of heresie, till you arriue on the hauen of eternal rest, which is in Iesus Christ: which that you may doe, it shall be the daily prayer, and dutifull indeauour of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>your vnworthy, but faithfull and louing Pastor, <hi>Henry Burton.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="25"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>