<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
L A
decorative header
</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S750_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72262</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13018.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S750</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
L A
decorative header
</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bloudy new-yeares gift, or A true declaration of the most cruell and bloudy murther, of maister Robert Heath, in his owne house at high Holbourne, being the signe of the fire-brand : which murther was committed by Rowland Cramphorne, seruant and tapster to the said Heath: on new-yearesday last past in the morning, 1609. Whereunto is annexed, sundry exploits of Tendance, otherwise called Double diligence, seruant vnto Derricke the hangman, who with his consort (Olde dublets) was executed at Tyborne, in Ianuary last past 1609</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <distributor>Barrenger (Barringer), William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Sutton, Bartholomew</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
         <head>L A</head>
         <figDesc>decorative header</figDesc>
      </figure>
   </head>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the relation (gentle reader) of the ensuing discourse, I haue bin so dilligent and carefull, that I haue rather failed to write so much as I might, then any way I come short of truth and sinceritie. I heard the offenders tryall and conuiction, at the Sessions house, and according to the enstructions, there deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in euidence, haue briefely set downe the whole summe in effect, though not so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly (perhaps) as a better iudgemenr could haue done. I stand free (I trust from partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, or sinister construction) being no way waged for the one, or fearefully doubting of the other. And in the opening of such cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal cases, concerning persons of no
<pb facs="3"/>higher qualitie. I am of the minde, that any writer (keeping himself within the boundes and limits of truth) hath freedome of his pen, and good ground for his publication; Because such examples remaining to poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, do expresse the care and industry of precedent times, in punishing such sinnes, and serue as mirrours or spectacles, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to auoid the like monstrous enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
   <p>I haue heard an infinite number of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, concerning this present murder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and strange constructions, vppon as strange obseruations. I was neuer so giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected, as rashly to beleeue, or leane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soluedly to any, but what I both saw and heard, in the honourable Court of Iustice, and in the best maner I could, I haue follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the course of direct information, such as from the worthy paines of the Coroner, his empanelled Enquest, and the Iustices that had the examination of the cause, was eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, plainely, and iustly deliuered.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, with that olde grammaticall rule, <hi>Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I knit vp this short preface, desiring that the punishment of this mans offence may so serue in example, as the like bloudy sinne, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in, or neere this famous Citie, may neuer heerafter (by any one) be committed.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>