<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREAMBLE before the Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S756_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5848</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S756</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREAMBLE before the Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mirror of martyrs : In a short vievv lively expressing the force of their faith, the feruency of their loue, the wisedome of their sayings, the patience of their suffrings, &amp;c. With their prayers and preparation for their last farevvell. Whereunto is added two godly letters written by M. Bradford, full of sweet consolation for such as are afflicted in conscience</title>
                 <author>Foxe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 216, 8 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A <hi>PREAMBLE</hi> before the Booke.</head>
   <p>HAppy, happy, yea thrise, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastingly happy is that Soule which by Faith feeles it selfe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fasted vnto Christ! Thogh it meet with a prosperous estate in this world, it easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly swels not: and if it meet with th'adverse things of the world, it easily quailes not. For it hath the word of Christ, and the Spirit of
<pb facs="5"/>
Christ residing and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in it. Shee is not to learne in whome shee hath beleeued: neither can she ever be finally forced from beleeving. Bring her to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and prooue whether of the two, <hi>Christ</hi> or <hi>Belial</hi> she will embrace; offer her Gold to forgoe CHRIST shee greatly contemns it: Let the mighty terrify with threats, shee feares not their feare, nor is carefull vpon the perill of life, to giue them a direct answere: she regards not whippings; she dreads not rackings: vpon honorable conditions shee esteems the prison a Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; fetters of jron, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of fine Gold: the darkest dungeon, a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
<pb facs="5"/>
dwelling; rather then shee will violate the chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of her faith to CHRIST her onely Spouse, she will willingly endure headding and hanging; yea burning and broyling: In a word, nothing can be able to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate this sweet soule from that loue of GOD to her; which is in CHRIST Iesus her Lord. Now the jmage of such a soule who desires to see, and by sight thereof to be transformed inro the same jmage: Let him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a spirituall eye prie into this <hi>Mirrour</hi> of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> following: Where he shall behold their Faith victorious, their Hope liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their peace passing al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, their Ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable
<pb facs="6"/>
and glorious: their Speach alwaies graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, their prayers full of Fervor, their liues full of Beautie, their ends full of Honor: <hi>This Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor shalbe to all the Saints.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>