<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the High and Mighty King, CHARLES King of Great Britaine.</title>
           <author>Delamain, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S763_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6543</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the High and Mighty King, CHARLES King of Great Britaine.</title>
                 <author>Delamain, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Grammelogia or, the mathematicall ring : Extracted from the logarythmes, and projected circular: now published in the inlargement thereof unto any magnitude fit for use: shewing any reasonable capacity that hath not arithmeticke, how to resolve and worke, all ordinary operations of arithmeticke: and those that are most difficult with greatest facilitie, the extraction of rootes, the valuation of leases, &amp;c. the measuring of plaines and solids, with the resolution of plaine and sphericall triangles applied to the practicall parts of geometrie, horologographie, geographie, fortification, navigation, astronomie, &amp;c. And that onely by an ocular inspection, and a circular motion, invented and first published, by R. Delamain, teacher, and student of the mathematicks</title>
                 <author>Delamain, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 18, 17-22, 53-68, 30 pages, 4 plates (3 folded), illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the High and Mighty King, CHARLES King of Great Britaine.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Dread Soveraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad</hi> not your gracious favour given <hi>life</hi> unto my first <hi>birth,</hi> I should not have dar'd thus boldly to rush into your <hi>sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred presence,</hi> but onely in humble confidence I am incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, that, as your <hi>gracious Majestie</hi> pleased to accept of my imperfect endevours, the same <hi>blessed eye</hi> will not now reject that <hi>worke</hi> brought to its fuller growth and perfection. <hi>It</hi> was the great <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> of that <hi>Noble Lo. Nepeir Baron of Marcheston</hi> his ever-worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admired discovery of the <hi>Logarythmes</hi> in cutting off the toylesome working by <hi>Sines, Tangenis, Secants, &amp;c.</hi> My paines formerly was conversant about to bring them likewise into a shorter way for <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call uses,</hi> by an <hi>instrumentall Projection</hi> of these numbers in <hi>Circles,</hi> of which I composed my <hi>Mathematicall Ring.</hi> Every thing hath his beginning, and curious <hi>Arts</hi> seldome come to the height at the first; It was my promise then to inlarge the <hi>invention</hi> by a way of <hi>decuplating the Circles,</hi> which I now present unto your <hi>sacred Majestie</hi> as the <hi>quintessence</hi> and <hi>excellencie</hi> there of, whereby <hi>Mathematicall operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> which tend to ordinary and usuall <hi>affaires</hi> and such of a higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are performed accuratly, without tedious <hi>extraction of Roots,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating by naturall <hi>Sines, Tangents, secants,</hi> or the <hi>Tables of Logaryth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> themselves, and that by an inspection of the <hi>eye</hi> alone and a <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motion.</hi> It is now againe your <hi>gracious acceptance</hi> and the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke good,</hi> which my life &amp; paines are studious of: the one I hope will acknowledge, the other defend these mine <hi>honest labours</hi> which some endevour to <hi>rob</hi> me of. I have no better thing as yet to expresse a <hi>loyall subjects</hi> heart, and affections by: but onely my <hi>selfe,</hi> which with my poore <hi>endeavours</hi> in all humble submission I cast downe at your <hi>sacred feete,</hi> accounting it my cheefest Happinesse to be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Majesties most humble, true, and Loyall Subject,</hi> Rich. Delamain</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>