<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S763_Ba3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6543</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Grammelogia or, the mathematicall ring : Extracted from the logarythmes, and projected circular: now published in the inlargement thereof unto any magnitude fit for use: shewing any reasonable capacity that hath not arithmeticke, how to resolve and worke, all ordinary operations of arithmeticke: and those that are most difficult with greatest facilitie, the extraction of rootes, the valuation of leases, &amp;c. the measuring of plaines and solids, with the resolution of plaine and sphericall triangles applied to the practicall parts of geometrie, horologographie, geographie, fortification, navigation, astronomie, &amp;c. And that onely by an ocular inspection, and a circular motion, invented and first published, by R. Delamain, teacher, and student of the mathematicks</title>
                 <author>Delamain, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 18, 17-22, 53-68, 30 pages, 4 plates (3 folded), illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="57"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>Courteous Reader</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto the <hi>world</hi> hath beene abused as well as my <hi>selfe,</hi> with a false <hi>Rumor</hi> (raised by some rude ignorant <hi>tongue</hi>) that my <hi>Invention</hi> both of <hi>Ring</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant</hi> was got, or borrowed, or stollen (even as they please to miscall it) from another <hi>Man,</hi> by the sight of a <hi>Letter,</hi> by some private <hi>Conference</hi> by — J know not what meanes (nor they neither) but onely by their malicious phancy: which how true, how just it is, that the <hi>world</hi> and my <hi>selfe</hi> may have our <hi>right,</hi> and they the <hi>shame,</hi> by this following just defence and future event, J hope thou mayest fully be enformed. I did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take this course, but sought <hi>peace</hi> and my <hi>right</hi> by a private and <hi>friendly way;</hi> but failing of it my good intentions <hi>scorned</hi> and <hi>slighted;</hi> J desire all may now <hi>Iudge</hi> who is in fault; and let this ensuing discourse be my <hi>Plea.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>