<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To euery vnpar , Grace and Truth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S768_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20358</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6773</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S768</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To euery vnpar , Grace and Truth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discription of what God hath predestinated concerning man : in his [brace] creation, transgression, &amp; regeneration : as also an answere to Iohn Robinson, touching baptisme</title>
                 <author>Murton, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To euery vnpar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE are not ignorant of the great oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions that are in the world at this day, about the most righteous <hi>Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of GOD, and the true consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, and that among the Wise and Learned; of which number wee account not our selues, neither are accounted of others, but are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to bee accounted of the lower sort, <hi>Euen of the foolish, weake, vile, dispised, and those that are not:</hi> Yet hauing receiued something of the Lord in this thing, and perceiuing that many thousands are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the difference, and are violently carryed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by tradition, then by sound knowledge, to detest the Truth, and imbrace the error, wee among others holde our selues bound to make knowne what wee haue receiued, to the end all may weigh it in the ballance of Gods Sanctuary, try it by the true touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, and measure it with the Golden reede. It is a thing not carelesly to bee minded, but seriously to be considered of and searched into, <hi>If any will be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and goe on in their blinde zeale according to tradition, let them be ignorant, and remember that If the Truth be hid it is hid to them that perish</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.</note>. There can be no hurt by try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our wayes, for as true tryall will burne vp the chaffe of falshood, so will it refine the way of <hi>Truth</hi> as Gold tryed in the fire seauen times, in which we must take heed, <hi>Wee presume not aboue what is written</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.</note>, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adde too, nor diminish the perfect Law of the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the Scriptures</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 2: 18.19.</note>, <hi>Secret thinges belong to the Lord our God, thinges reuealed belong to vs</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.29.</note>.</p>
   <p>But some man will say vnto vs, what shall wee neede tryall of this thing againe? the Counsell of <hi>Dort</hi> hath sufficiently tryed it, and haue passed their sentence to establish <hi>Caluins</hi> Doctrine, and to reject the contrary, but to such wee will answer, by asking
<pb facs="3"/>
question, was not the Counsell of <hi>Dort</hi> subiect to erre? If yea: Then is it safe for men to build their <hi>Faith</hi> vpon their sentence? their answer, is yea, for not onely so they haue Decreed, but also that whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer teacheth contrary, shall be persecuted: Ah hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy case! will men teach they are subiect to erre, and yet decree Persecution for them that cannot beleeue their Decrees? Well, yet thus f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rre wee are sure they will grant they may erre; and whether they haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or no, let that bee scanned by Gods worde, and iudged by euery mans Conscience. It is a maine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie between the <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> whether the Church and Counsels may erre: the <hi>Papists</hi> affirme they cannot, and so constraineth all to beleeue as the Church beleeues. The <hi>Protestants</hi> affirme the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is no Church, no Counsell, no man, but they are subiect to erre, and therefore ought to be no further beleeued, then euery mans Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can iudge them to accord with the meaning of God in the Scriptures; which being true (as it is most true) then why may not the Counsell of <hi>Dort</hi> haue erred in its sentence in these thinges?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sa 29.14. Math. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5.26. Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.48.49. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Cor. 1.19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>6. &amp;c.</note>If any say it was <hi>Learned,</hi> wee answer. <hi>God vsually hid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his secrets from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Learned, and reuealeth them to Babes. And destroyes the wisdome of the wise, &amp; casts away the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the prudent, &amp; makes the wisdome of the wise foolishnes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If any say the assembly was great; wee answer: greater Counsels by much, euen vniuersall Counsels haue grosely erred, who is ignorant of this? How did the Counsels of <hi>Ephesus, Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>sia, Trident, Lateren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers erre, where the vniuersall Learned of the world were assembled? whose numbers, and errors were too many to relate: but to be short in this thing, we may truely conclude with the wordes of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> who saith*,<note place="margin">ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 346</note>
      <hi>Hee neuer saw any Counsell haue a good end;</hi> For what is the end of them but cruelty and persecution? that when they haue decreed what they thinke good,
<pb facs="3"/>
then they procure the <hi>Magistrates</hi> sword to impose their Decrees vpon mens Consciencs: And why any Church should call Counsels to make Decrees in cause of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, but <hi>Rome</hi> it cannot be defended. The Counsell at <hi>Ierusalem</hi> will not warrant them; that assembly could not erre, who dare say so, besides that Mother of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes <hi>(Rome)</hi> of whom wee may say with the <hi>Prophet, Thou hadst an Whores forehead, thou wouldst not be ashamed</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 3.3</note>.</p>
   <p>Men are couered with the Spirit of slumber, that call Counsels to make Decrees to bee imposed vpon mens Consciences, and yet hold that the Counsels may erre. And for the <hi>Armenians,</hi> (as they are called) wee are not truely enformed of their opinions; but for their tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous courses wee much detest, the ground of their, and their aduersaries proceeding, being that deuillish perswasion, that it is lawfull to persecute, yea to kill one another for difference in Religion: the Lord giue them to see their sinne on both sides. Against which opinion and practise, that Noble and worthy Prince the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> hath written in these wordes: <hi>And not withstanding, the successe of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>se latter times, wherein sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry opinions, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e beene hatched, about the subiect of Religion, may make one clearely discerne with his eye, and (as it were) touch with his finger, that acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rding to the veritie of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a Maxime heretofore held and maintayned by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, Doctors of the Church, that mens Consciences ought in no sort to bee violated, vrged, or constrayned; and whensoeuer men haue attempted any thing by this violent course, whether openly, or by secret meanes, the issue hath beene pernicious, and the cause of great and wonderfull innouations, in the principallest and mightiest Kingdomes and Countries of all Christendome, &amp;c.</hi> And further his Maiesty saith: <hi>So that once more wee d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> protest before God, and the whole world, that from this time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, wee are firmely resolued, not to persec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te or molest, or suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to be persecuted or molested any person whosoeuer, for matter of Religion, no not they, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rofesse themselues to bee of the</hi> Romane <hi>Church, neither to trouble or disturbe them in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise
<pb facs="4"/>
of their Religion, So they liue conformably to the Lawes of the States, &amp;c.</hi> Whose wordes and practise, the King of Kings grant, that the Gouernors of the earth, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly our most dread Soueraigne, who hath himselfe written much to the same effect, may consider of, and doe accordingly; as blessed bee our God, all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes that wee know, or can heare of, practiseth the same; except <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In this writing we haue obserued this order, to set down such affirmations as the contrary minded haue written and spoken in these thinges. 1. Touching <hi>Predestination,</hi> 2. Of <hi>Election,</hi> 3. Of <hi>Falling away,</hi> 4. Of <hi>Free-will,</hi> 5. Of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall sinne,</hi> and lastly, Of the entrance into <hi>Christ,</hi> one depending vpon another, and so haue answered them from point to point, by way of <hi>Dialogue.</hi> There affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thou mayst see to be most fearefull; one, and that a <hi>Principall</hi> one<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Knox</hi> in his printed Booke aga. an aduersa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of Gods <hi>Pred.</hi> as hee calleth him. <hi>pag. 255.</hi>
      </note>, saith; <hi>Gods</hi> Predestination <hi>was the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall or first cause of</hi> Adams <hi>fall, yea of all the wickednes that euer hath beene, is, or shall be committed, yea in plaine wordes, that</hi> God <hi>is not onely the principall cause of all thinges, but also the very</hi> Author, <hi>appointing all thinges to the one part and to the other by his Counsell;</hi> and <hi>That whatsoeuer the</hi> Ethnicks <hi>ascribed to Fortune; the same wee ought</hi> (saith he) <hi>to ascribe to the Prouidence of God,</hi> which how large a blasphemie it is, will appeare to euery tender Conscience.</p>
   <p>Againe they say, <hi>That God hath Elected the lesser part of Man-kinde, euen some particuler persons, without any Condition, who cannot but bee saued by any meanes;</hi> And againe, <hi>That God hath Reprobated the greater part of man-kinde without all cause of desert, who cannot but bee Damned by any manner of meanes,</hi> Christ <hi>not dying for them:</hi> Which Doctrine, how it impeacheth not onely the Iustice of <hi>God,</hi> mercy of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> and protestations of <hi>God</hi> to the contrary in the Scriptures, but also the sufficiencie, and merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riousnes of <hi>Christs</hi> most precious Death and sufferings, and laying the imputation of Mans damnation not on his owne sinne and vnbeleefe, but on God and <hi>Christ,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
shall by this that followeth manifestly appeare.</p>
   <p>The cheife maintayners of this Destination (as wee see by experience) are the <hi>Caluinists,</hi> or <hi>Puritanes</hi> as they are called, one of their chiefe <hi>Prophets</hi> further affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Knox</hi> the said Booke <hi>pag 317.</hi> with <hi>312.</hi>
      </note>, <hi>That the wicked are not onely left by Gods suffering, but compelled to sinne by power, &amp;c,</hi> Wherein you plainely see their opinion, not onely that men cannot chuse, but doe what wickednes and mischiefe they doe, but also they are compelled with the power force and compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Gods <hi>Predestination.</hi> to commit all those wicked crimes, for which they are either executed with the Temporall sword, or damned with euerlasting torment.</p>
   <p>Consider wee beseech you not the persons of men be they neuer so <hi>high,</hi> neuer so <hi>wise,</hi> neuer so <hi>many,</hi> but mark the opinion it selfe, euen in thy Conscience and in the sight of <hi>God</hi> whether any thing can be more repugnant to the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or more defacing his <hi>Iustice,</hi> then to say, That <hi>God</hi> punisheth <hi>Man</hi> with the torments of <hi>Hell</hi> in euerlasting <hi>Fire,</hi> for doing those thinges, which hee himselfe hath <hi>Predestinated, Ordayned, Decreed, determined, appointed, willed and compelled him to doe, and that a man cannot chuse, but of necessity m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st doe, by the force and compulsion of his</hi> Predestnation; Which being true, then what is our <hi>Life</hi> but a meere <hi>Destiny,</hi> all our dooings <hi>Gods</hi> ordinances, and all our Imaginations branches of his <hi>Predestination.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let no man deceiue you with vaine wordes, wherein they would seeme to temper the matter with more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent speaking of it, (as they say) seeing they plainly holde these principles, and when they see their time speake plainely thereof themselues, as you may well perceiue by that which hath already, and shal yet more largely in this writing following be rehearsed. If it be a truth, why should it not plainely be spoken? If it bee a truth <hi>that Traytors bee Predestinated of God to conspire the destruction of their Princes, and Rebels Predestinated of God to rebell against their Soueraignes.</hi> If (we say) it be a truth, that God hath so Predestinated them, and that they
<pb facs="5"/>
must of necessitie, and cannot chuse but commit such wickednes; why should it not be plainely spoken? Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept men should be ashamed to speake the Truth. But in what Scripture is it written?</p>
   <p>The greatest shew they haue is collected from <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. from whence they conceiue, <hi>That God hated</hi> Esau, <hi>and so all wicked men before they were borne, and hath Decreed all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r actions which they doe, whilest they liue vpon the earth,</hi> for which cause, we haue explained the whole <hi>Chap.</hi> Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they doe most wofully peruert it. For proofe whereof wee haue the Apostle <hi>Peters</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 3.15. &amp;c.</note> approbation of vs against them, who writ after <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistles that spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of these things, which we desire may be carefully obserued, and then a way most easie will be made for <hi>Pauls</hi> meaning in all his Epistles concerning this thing.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>That God hateth wicked men,</hi> we confesse the Scriptures plenteously witnes, but wheresoeuer it is said that <hi>God</hi> hated any, there will we manifestly proue, that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>God</hi> first, and that their wicked euill deseruing went before his hatred,<note place="margin">Rō. 5.10. 2 Chr. 36 15.16.</note> For he is so <hi>Gracious and mercifull that he loueth his en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mies. So slowe to wrath or hatred that hee stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth with them by his Word and Spirit, vntill there be no remedy,</hi> When there is no remedy to reclaime them, but that in Iustice his wrath must needs breake forth, <hi>Yet doth he lament for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 23.37.</note> in these wordes. <hi>Jerusalem, Ierusalem, &amp;c. how oft would I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e gathered thy Children, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Oh that thou hadst knowne the Day of thy visitation; but now it is hid from thine eyes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 81.13. Vers. 15.</note> And <hi>Oh that my people had harkened to mee, and</hi> Israell <hi>had walked in my wayes, &amp;c. And the haters of the Lord should haue bene subiect to him, and their time should haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> for euer.</hi> And many the like.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus haue wee giuen you a taste of that which followeth, besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching you: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> and Iudge without partiality, and the God of Wisdom giue you wisdome in all thinges.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, <hi>ready to doe you any good, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> seruants of</hi> Christ, <hi>fals<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>y</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Ana-baptists.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>