<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE, MOST CHRISTIAN AND WORTHY KING, IAMES, by the grace of God King of England, Scotland, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. All prosperitie and true happinesse in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Downame, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S779_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20740</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7120</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S779</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE, MOST CHRISTIAN AND WORTHY KING, IAMES, by the grace of God King of England, Scotland, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. All prosperitie and true happinesse in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Downame, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise concerning Antichrist : diuided into two bookes, the former, prouing that the Pope is Antichrist: the latter, maintaining the same assertion, against all the obiections of Robert Bellarmine, Iesuit and cardinall of the Church of Rome. By George Douuname, Doctor of Diuinitie, and lately reader of the diuinity lecture in Paules</title>
                 <author>Downame, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Read, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 142, 2, 192 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH <hi>AND MIGHTIE, MOST</hi> CHRISTIAN AND WORTHY KING, IAMES, by the grace of God King of England, <hi>Scotland, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the</hi> faith, &amp;c. All prosperitie and true happinesse in this life, and eternall felicitie in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE blessed dispensation of Gods most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prouidence towards this land; (for which his holy name is alwayes to be praised in his church) in bringing your Highnesse vnto this kingdome, in the beginning of this seuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth century after Christ, seemeth to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, that the happy reformation of the church, restitution of the Gospell, consumption of Antichrist, decay of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon <hi>happily begun in the last centenary, shall in this age or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury receiue a notable confirmation and increase, if not a perfect consummation. For howsoeuer whiles the darkenesse of Popery ouer spred the Christian world, not onely the inhabitants of the earth were made drunke with the goulden cup of the whore of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons <note place="margin">Apoc. 17. 2, &amp; 18. 3.</note>
      <hi>fornications, but the Kings also and Princes of the earth hauing drunke of the same cup, committed spirituall whoredome</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apo. 17. 13</note>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>with her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> power to support <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> when as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> enlighten the world with the bright beames of his glorious Gospell, then Antichrist began to consume, and</hi> Babylon <hi>to decay: the Preachers discouering Antichrist, the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. 1. &amp; 14. 6. 3.</note>
      <hi>out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and the Princes which before had assisted Antichrist, setting themselues against him. This great worke of God in the full consumption of Antichrist and confusion of</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>the Ministers of God, that is to say, Princes and Preachers, are</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note>
      <hi>to accomplish and bring to passe. The Preachers, by preaching the euerlasting Gospell; at the sound whereof</hi> Babylon <hi>falleth, as once</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 6. 7. 8.</note>
      <hi>the walles of</hi> Iericho <hi>at the noise of the Trumpets sounded by the Priests: and by the ministerie whereof as it were the spirit of the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note>
      <hi>Lords mouth, Antichrist falleth into a consumption, as</hi> Dagon <note place="margin">2. Thes. 2. 8</note>
      <hi>once did fall before the Arke. Th Princes, partly by their godly example, going out and in before the people in the sincere profession</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.</note>
      <hi>of the truth, and detestation of popery; partly by their authoritie, prouiding faithfull Ministers, countenancing their Ministerie, oppugning Antichrist in his religion and in his members, berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the whore of</hi> Babylon <hi>the Popes concubine of her meanes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apo. 17. 16</note>
      <hi>and lastly sacking her and consuming her with fire. For which cause as I thought it my duety (being called to read a Lecture in diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) when I perceiued the Papists within these few yeares (I know not vpon what other hopes then of raising their fortunes out of the ruines of this whole Island) growne more insolent then in former times, to make the best opposition I could against them, and to that end handled this maine controuersie concerning Antichrist (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon all Popery dependeth) both</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>proouing the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue,</hi> viz. <hi>that the Pope is Antichrist, and also</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouing the negatiue against the obiections of</hi> Bellarmine <hi>the Goliath of the Papists: so being now at the instance of many well</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>disposed persons, to publish this treatise, I haue thought good to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the same to your Maiestie, as the chiefe patron and defender of the faith and Gospell of Christ (vpon earth) against Antichrist and his adherents. For hereby not onely your royall courage may be stirred vp, and your godly resolution in oppugning Antichrist (according to the prophecies of the scripture, foretelling the dutie of Christian Princes in this behalfe) more and more confirmed: but also it may most euidently appeare to all men, that vpon most iust and weighty considerations, you and your people renounce all communion with the Pope and church of Rome, and by all good meanes doe set our selues against them. For if the Pope be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ (which is prooued in this Booke) &amp; consequently the church of Rome, the whore of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and synagogue of Antichrist: the papists, (who call themselues Catholicks, and vs Heretiques) the limmes of Antichrist; the religion and doctrine of popery, the mysterie of iniquitie and meere Antichristianisme: it followeth necessarily, that Christian princes are not to tolerate either the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of papists or their persons within their dominions. The reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deu. 13. 1. 5</note>
      <hi>of papistry being a Catholick Apostasie from God, consisting not onely in respect of the worship, of manifold superstion and most grosse idolatrie; but also in respect of the doctrine, of many hundred Antichristian errours and doctrines of diuels. The persons of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick-papists, being Catholick heretiques and reuolters frō God, members of Antichrist, palpable idolatours; many of them (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Seminarie priests and Iesuites) perswaders of others to ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and apostasie from God. Not to speake of the treason against Christian Princes which is enclosed in the bowels of popery, and bosomes of papists. For they teach that all Christian Princes who acknowledge not the Pope for their supreame head and Lord, (as no true Christians doe) are Schismaticks at the least, and</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>consequently that the Pope hath authoritie to depose them, and to absolue their subiects from their allegiance: and that the Pope when he proceedeth to the sentence of excommunication and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of them (as he did against your sister of blessed memorie Queene</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>and doth, so oft as he dareth, against others) he doth not erre in his definitiue sentence. And therefore (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they pretend to the contrarie) it is certaine, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the marked slaues of Antichrist, wholy deuoted to his will, are also willing and ready (when meanes and opportunitie faile not) to put in execution his Antichristian censures, and diuellish de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signements. In consideration whereof, Christian Princes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are not onely bound to come out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and to renounce</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 4.</note>
      <hi>all communion with the Pope and Church of Rome, but also they are to rewarde the where of</hi> Babylon, <hi>as she hath rewarded vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 6.</note>
      <hi>yea</hi> to repay her double: <hi>and not onely to</hi> hate her, but also to make her desolate and naked, to eate her flesh and consume <note place="margin">Apo. 17. 16.</note> her with fire. <hi>And hereof Christian Princes are to be assured, that as those which ioyne with the Pope in persecuting the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, doe fight vnder the banner of Antichrist the beast, against Christ the Lambe: so they in oppugning the Pope and Church of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apo. 19. 19</note>
      <hi>Rome, doe fight the battailes of Christ against Antichrist. And consequently are to promise to themselues vndoubted victorie: they fighting vnder the banner of the Lambe, who shall be sure to ouercome, seeing he</hi> is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings: <note place="margin">Apo. 17. 14.</note> and those also that are with him, <hi>though esteemed of Antichrist</hi>
      <note place="margin">Qui monet vt facias, quod iam facis, ipse monendo Laudat, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>atu comprobat acta su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>and his adherents, as Schismaticks and Heretiques, yet are they</hi> called, elect, and faithfull. <hi>Encourage therefore your selfe most Christian King (as we doubt not but you doe) to maintaine for euer the truth of Christ, against the falshood of Antichrist. And doubt you not both of happy successe and victorie in this life, and of</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>an immortall crowne of glory in the life to come. The God of all mercy and power, who in his vnspeakeable bountie towards vs, hath placed your Highnesse ouer vs in peace, make both you and vs truely thankfull to his maiestie for this inestimable benefit: and establish your Highnesse and your Royall posteritie in the throne of this Kingdome, to the glory of his great name, aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Kingdome, propagation of the Gospell, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Popery, consolation of all true Christians, and your owne euerlasting comfort.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties <hi>most humble</hi> and <hi>dutifull subiect</hi> GEORGE DOVVNAME.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>