<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable his very good. Lord, the L. HARING∣TON, Baron of EXTON; and to the right Noble and Vertuous the LADIE HARINGTON his wife, &amp; my singular good LADIE, Grace, Mercy and Peace.</title>
           <author>Draxe, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S782_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20802</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7182</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S782</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable his very good. Lord, the L. HARING∣TON, Baron of EXTON; and to the right Noble and Vertuous the LADIE HARINGTON his wife, &amp; my singular good LADIE, Grace, Mercy and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Draxe, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian armorie : wherein is contained all manner of spirituall munition, fit for secure Christians to arme themselues withall against Satans assaults, and all other kind of crosses, temptations, troubles, and afflictions: contrived in two bookes, and handled pithil and plainly by way of questions and answers: by Thomas Draxe, bachelar in diuinitie. Hereunto is adioined a table of all the principall heads and branches comprised in each chapter of the whole treatise</title>
                 <author>Draxe, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Stepneth (Stepney), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 182, 8, 34, 33-165, 19 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="95"/>
   <pb facs="95"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable his very good. Lord, the L. <hi>HARING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON,</hi> Baron of EXTON; and to the right Noble and Vertuous the LADIE HARINGTON his wife, &amp; my singular good <hi>LADIE,</hi> Grace, Mercy and Peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer booke treated of such publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate troubles, vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, losses and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that are common to Gods children with the wicked; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing (according to my measure) sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, and set downe such plaine
<pb facs="96"/>
and compendious rules, directions, and consolations, as may seeme most fit and necessary; I haue in this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Booke propounded in order those doubts, distresses, griefes, scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, trials and afflictions, which did specially and properly concerne Gods Saints and seruants: (for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the troubles of the righteous, and the better Christian the more tried and afflicted) &amp; I haue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all expressed and drawn out of Gods booke such certaine resolutions, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted conclusions, and choice comforts, as (I hope) will giue good satisfaction and contentment to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Christian. And hoping that through Gods blessing this small worke may doe much good, I haue beene willing to make it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and for many iust and waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reasons me mouing, doe deuote and consecrate it to your Honours. For, first, your Honours being <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> in Gods house, and goodly
<pb facs="96"/>
      <hi>Cedars</hi> in the <hi>Lebanon</hi> of his Church militant, beare your parts in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and therefore the comforts do appertaine vnto you; you share in the conflicts, and why not in the conquests?</p>
   <p>Secondly, this my discourse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a subiect and matter of religion and learning, who haue greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in it, then such a noble <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> &amp; honourable <hi>Sunamite,</hi> who both doe so much fauour, further, and wish well to learning and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse?</p>
   <p>Thirdly, in whom doe might and meekenesse, honour and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, greatnesse and gratiousnes, more happily concur, then in your Honours?</p>
   <p>Lastly, hauing receiued so many great and vndeserued fauours from your Honours, as the Roote, and from your noble ofspring, as the blessed branches; I could finde no
<pb facs="97"/>
better meanes to manifest my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dutie, and to testifie my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart, then by dedicating, and commending these my labours to your patronages.</p>
   <p>Vouchsafe therefore not onely to peruse my meditations, but also to approue them; that the Author may receiue the greater encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt, &amp; the fragrant perfume of your fauourable disposition, may more amply enlarge, and make knowne it selfe. But fearing to bee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue and tedious, and assuring my selfe of your Honourable accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I doe here most heartily sue and supplicate to God the Father of our Lord Iesus Christ, to blesse the bright <hi>Morning Starre,</hi> that <hi>Princely charge</hi> vnder your careful tuition, and herein to respect and reward your faithfull seruice, and watchfull attendance, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in goodnesse all your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="97"/>
shewed to his Church and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drē, to continue you long in health, to encrease you in all grace and honour, and to replenish your hearts with all hope and comfort.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all dutie, most affectionate, <hi>THOMAS DRAXE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>