<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S784_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20858</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7236</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S784</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The considerations of Drexelius upon eternitie : Translated by Ralph Winterton fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge 1632</title>
                 <author>Drexel, Jeremias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cambridge University—Printers.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 358, 2 pages, 9 plates, illustrations, 24°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any man more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in censuring what is done for a common good, rather then studious himself to promote it, should question me for medling in another mans profession: I might answer him in his own kinde by way of question, as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedemus</hi> in <hi>Terence</hi> answered <hi>Chremes</hi> finding fault with him, <hi>Tantúmne abs re tua est otii tibi, Aliena ut cures, eáque nihil quae ad te attinent?</hi> Hast thou so much lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as to meddle with that, which nothing concerns thee?</p>
   <p>But to satisfie thee (Courteous Reader) who intendest, I know, with the <hi>Bee</hi> to gather <hi>Hony</hi> out of this <hi>Garden</hi> of <hi>Eternitie,</hi> and not <hi>Poyson</hi> with the <hi>Spider:</hi> I hold it fit to acquaint thee with the true
<pb facs="8"/>
occasion that moved me to translate this Book. No <hi>Divine</hi> I am indeed, neither yet can I be if I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so fain: I would I were but worthy the name of a <hi>Physician!</hi> But howsoever, being destinated by the statutes of my private <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> to the studie of <hi>Physick,</hi> in the first place I thought good to spend some time in <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> as being a necessarie instrument and help in my <hi>Profession:</hi> In which I made some progresse, passing from <hi>Numeration, Addition, Subtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Multiplication, Division, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, To the Golden Rule,</hi> or <hi>the Rule of Three, The Rule of Falshood, The Rules of Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>the Rules of Societie,</hi> and the rest. But the knowledge of this cost me so deare, that I was forced to leave the studie of it: For many nights together I was constrained against my will to practise <hi>Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> oftener then I would, telling the Clock, and could take but little rest. Whereupon I resolved with my self to leave the <hi>Arithmetick School,</hi> and so I went unto the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
and <hi>Musick Schools,</hi> imploring at one and the same time the help of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and the <hi>Muses.</hi> For at that time I turned the first book of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his <hi>Aphorismes</hi> into Greek verses, hoping to procure rest by <hi>Physick</hi> and the <hi>Musick</hi> of <hi>Poeticall Numbers;</hi> by which I found some rest indeed (And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore since I have well-nigh finished at spare houres the other six books, which, if God permit, may ere long see light.) But though I found some rest, yet I did not sleep so soundly as at other times. So I left the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and the <hi>Muses,</hi> and betook my self into the <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> to learn of <hi>David</hi> divine <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> which consisteth in the due numbring of the dayes of this short life, by comparing them with the yeares of <hi>Eternitie:</hi> And so I fell upon translating this book of <hi>Eternitie.</hi> And this I found by day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience to be the best <hi>Hypno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticon</hi> that ever I used; For it brought me to my rest better then if I had taken <hi>Diacodion.</hi> Thus I found the old saying true, <hi>Where
<pb facs="9"/>
Philosophie ends, there Physick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; and where Physick ends, there Divinitie begins;</hi> which I interpret thus, (as I found it true by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) <hi>When Philosophie by Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had done me harm, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick could do me little good, I found perfect help in Divinitie.</hi> And having found so much good by this book my self, I could not be so envious as not impart it unto others for a <hi>Soveraigne Medicine, to</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure quiet sleep. Neither is it good for that onely, but (Farre unlike to other Medicines, which are onely good for some one disease, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into unskilfull hands often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time do more harm then good) It is a <hi>Medicine</hi> fitting <hi>All Ages, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, Conditions, Places, Parts, Diseases Spirituall and Corporall</hi> whatsoever: It is a <hi>Medicine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servative, Curative, Restaurative:</hi> It is an <hi>Antidote</hi> against the <hi>poyson</hi> of sinne: It is <hi>Dictamnum</hi> to drive out the fierie <hi>darts</hi> of <hi>Satan:</hi> It is <hi>Catholicon</hi> to purge out all ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. It is better then <hi>Exhilarans Galeni,</hi> to cheare the Heart oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="9"/>
with <hi>Melancholie:</hi> It is an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copon</hi> for all wearinesse, an <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynon</hi> for all pains, a <hi>Panchreston</hi> Profitable for all things, or <hi>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>good.</hi> It is <hi>Panacea, Hearts-ease, All-heal.</hi> It is <hi>a rich Treasurie for</hi> Englishmen, <hi>A storehouse for the diseased,</hi> and <hi>The ready way to long life,</hi> even to blessed <hi>Eternitie.</hi> Let no man now challenge me for usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping another mans office, or tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing upon <hi>Divines;</hi> I cannot see but <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Physicians</hi> may well agree together: Both are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied about curing of <hi>diseases</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Spirituall</hi> or <hi>Corporall:</hi> And here is a <hi>Medicine</hi> for both. <hi>Take</hi> it and use it, Christian Reader; And thou shalt finde by thine own experience that it hath all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues above mentioned. So I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thee to the <hi>Physician</hi> both of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> and heartily desire thy <hi>Temporall</hi> and <hi>Eternall</hi> Health and Welfare.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ralph Winterton.</signed>
      <dateline>From Kings Coll.
<date>
            <hi>June</hi> 1. 1632.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>