<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND MY singular good Lord and Master, HENRY, Lord Morley, and Mount-eagle, Baron of Rye.</title>
           <author>Court, Andrew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S786_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21002</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7373</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S786</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND MY singular good Lord and Master, HENRY, Lord Morley, and Mount-eagle, Baron of Rye.</title>
                 <author>Court, Andrew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bvckler against adversitie: or A treatise of constancie. Written in French by the Right Honourable the Lord Dv Vair, keeper of the great seale of France. And now done into English by Andrevv Covrt</title>
                 <author>Du Vair, Guillaume</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 165, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND MY singular good Lord and Master, HENRY, Lord <hi>Morley,</hi> and <hi>Mount-eagle,</hi> Baron of <hi>Rye.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince your Lordship hath bin pleased to make me the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deseruing Obiect of many of your Fauors, thereby to demonstrate vnto the world the truly Noblenesse of your owne dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, in fauouring such weake Deserts, as durst not presume so much as to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the honour of your Lordships fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aspect; I could doe no lesse, then in a thankfull remembrance thereof, by this poore Testimonie of my bounden seruice, expresse the desire I haue to manifest vnto your Lordship my thankefull heart; and withall, seeke for safegard vnder your Lordships Protection: Hoping thereby,
<pb facs="4"/>that the Beames of your gracious Aspect will disperse these Gusts of Calumniation, and Gulfes of Enuy, which will striue to swallow this poore strange Barke, ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>English</hi> Rigging. Vnto which, if your Lordship will be pleased but to adde the Colours of your owne Honor, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be knowne to whom shee belongs; I make no question, but by that meanes shee will be securely wafted along through these Tempests, vnto the Hauen of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigne Acceptation; And there will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine euer at your Lordships command, as dayly will also</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humble and obedient Seruant, <hi>ANDREVV COVRT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>