<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>C., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S786_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21002</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7373</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S786</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>C., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bvckler against adversitie: or A treatise of constancie. Written in French by the Right Honourable the Lord Dv Vair, keeper of the great seale of France. And now done into English by Andrevv Covrt</title>
                 <author>Du Vair, Guillaume</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 165, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I haue long beene in Quest for some worthy peece to present vnto your view: at last by good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, I haue lighted vpon one, cut by the curious hand of France; which in its proper colours deserues all commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. If my vnproper colours haue any wayes discounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced it, I hope you will not blame the peece, though you haue colour for it. I am confident, those who are iudicious, well know how hard and difficult a thing it is for a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to attaine vnto the perfection of the English tongue; and what labour hee must bestow to seeke and sift, begge and borrow proper words and phrases to expresse himselfe. Therefore for such errours as I haue committed, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume they will grant mee their pardons, and take neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse this little Essay of mine in good part. Which if I can obtaine, I will repriue many an houre from my other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to doe them seruice in this kinde.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>