<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CAP∣TIOVS AND MALI∣cious Detractors.</title>
           <author>A., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S839_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73755</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5529</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S839</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CAP∣TIOVS AND MALI∣cious Detractors.</title>
                 <author>A., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fasciculus florum. Or A handfull of flowers : gathered out of the seuerall bookes of the Right Honorable Sir Edward Coke Knight, and one of the Kings Maiesties most honorable councellours of estate. Per Tho: Ashe, Graijens</title>
                 <author>Coke, Edward, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="anti-dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE <hi>CAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIOVS AND MALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Detractors.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether it commeth to passe for want of wit, or proceeds from fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Fortune, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell: but this I know by wofull experience, through the whole course of my life, that my hap hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hard, in most things that I haue taken in hand, or at any time
<pb facs="6"/> enterprised: wherefore I am now iustly occasioned, to commit to writing <hi>in perpetuam rei memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> the saying of the Philosopher, which heretofore in words, hath beene with me alwaies most fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, <hi>Nihil agere semper infaelicis est optimum.</hi> Otherwise how could it be that in this my poore Epistle my simple and plaine meaning should be so mistaken? and my dutifull and alwaies most faithfull seruice towards my <hi>Patron,</hi> and <hi>Maecaenas,</hi> should be so traduced and slaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? When, as the eyes of seruants haue waited vpon their Masters, and as the eyes of a mayden haue looked vnto the hands of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse; euen so haue I waighted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in simplicity and singlenes of heart: which may well appeare
<pb facs="6"/> by those my labours past and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, as also by my paines taken in and about the generall Table to all his bookes, in my vnfortunate Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle promised, and shortly likewise in Print to be published: But what should I thinke, or what might I say? but that their mistaking of this my good and plaine meaning pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from two sorts of people, either from them which of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance cannot, or from another sort, who out of their malicious heart (which are the worser sort, <hi>Nam quod scire debes et non vis, Non pro ignorantia, sed pro contèmptu haberi debet,</hi>) will not vnderstand a speech allegorically deliuered. I may iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cry out, <hi>O tempora! o mores!</hi> for that which in former times in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hath beene tollerated, in this
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/> captious age is turned into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary sence, sound fault with all, and reproued. For (besides holy writ, which is with allegoricall speeches repleat and filled) let me be bould, to put you in mind of one president elsewhere borrowed, instead of many. You may read in the booke of Martyres <hi>fol.</hi> 2013. of one writing vnto that worthy professor and Preacher of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in those daies, Master <hi>Philpot,</hi> vseth these allegoricall speeches: Oh good Master <hi>Philpot,</hi> which art a principall Pot indeed, filled with most precious licour: Oh Pot most happy, of the highest Potter or day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to honor, &amp;c. Oh Pot, thrice happy in whom, &amp;c. Which speech in those times was not onely by the best learned well approued, but by
<pb facs="8"/> the Reuerend man Master <hi>Fox</hi> in his Booke of Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to euerlasting memory left, and recommended. Wherefore to stop your malignant mouthes, and stay your detracting tongues, be not angry with mee, sith you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with speeches allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; if I retort vpon you a speech prouerbiall. You seem to resemble those which will be, <hi>aliorum medici ipsi vlcerib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s scatentes: Plutarch.</hi> And finally, to giue full satisfaction to all others (besides your selues) of my single &amp; plaine meaning in that my Epistle thus mistaken: I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test before God, I am, and alwaies haue beene far from any intent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly, or obliquely to scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize that Right Honorable and well deseruing Knight. And let me
<pb facs="9"/> be bould to tell you, that are posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with a malignant heart towards him, or thinke amisse of me; That he for his part, may be compared to the Camamile, the more it is trampled vpon, the better and sweeter sent and sauour it sendeth forth to the cheering of the senses. So the more you enuy his vertues, the more wil they flourish vnto the worlds end, and neither you nor I, if we all were so minded, could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molish or diminish the least iot of his worth. And as for my selfe I am an <hi>Ashe,</hi> so deepely rooted in the soyle of sincerity and plaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that I feare not your <hi>Aquilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> biasts: for albeit they may peraduenture shake my leaues, yet they shall not be able to peirce my barke, much lesse loosen the tree
<pb facs="9"/> at the roote. <hi>Non metuo pulicis sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulos, fucique susurros.</hi> And thus I leaue you abruptly, because you haue dealt with mee somewhat dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courteously, and yet in hope that you will stay your further slaunder, I bid you farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>