<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Christian Readers, I doe here dedicate and direct this my Booke vnto all you that are the elect children of God, desiring through Iesus Christ, your health in the Lord.</title>
           <author>Andrewes, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S90287_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07162</idno>
           <idno type="STC">589.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S90287</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Christian Readers, I doe here dedicate and direct this my Booke vnto all you that are the elect children of God, desiring through Iesus Christ, your health in the Lord.</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Andrewes repentance, sounding alarum, to returne from his sins vnto Almightie God : Perfectly guiding all those that hope to bee saued, in the direct way of repentance, whereby they may attaine eternall life: newly made in the autumne or declining of his age. Serò sed seriò Wherein is contained, not only what repentance is, and the necessity thereof; but also (for the better satisfying of the doubtfull,) here is so plaine a resolution, concerning the assurance of the penitent mans saluation, and that so directly penned, with proofes of holy Scripture, according vnto the Word of God; that I hope there is not the least doubt to be made of it by anyman, (if there be neuer so little of Gods grace in him,) but vpon his true repentance, he may be assured of his saluation, and certainly know whether hee shall bee saued or damned</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wright, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>(unpaged), 12°⁸.⁴</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Christian Readers, I doe here dedicate and direct this my Booke vnto all you that are the elect children of God, desiring through Iesus Christ, your health in the Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Christian Readers, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises or Bookes of this kinde we haue too few; but of lasciuious too many: and whereas I haue formerly published vnto the view of the world, many small books, for the setting forth of Gods glorie, the discharge of my conscience, and the benefit of you the children of God, in the which I desired not the praise of men, seeing it is but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, neither did I looke for preferment, the world is so corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed: for I here openly protest, I feare none but God, whose truth I teach, and hate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but sinne, which is the destruction of the soule; neither doe I care for my life, so it were lost in the defence of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>And now seeing that my former bookes are so vendible, and so well liking vnto the children of God, that in short time there haue beene diuers impressions printed, I haue therefore now set forth another booke, entituled <hi>Andrewes Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> which I made and composed for mine owne priuate vse, intending to engrosse it to my selfe.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>And although it came forth last, which should haue beene first, yet notwithstanding, whereas it is <hi>serò,</hi> yet it is <hi>serio.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And being made in the autumne, or declining of mine age, yet I doubt not by the helpe of God, but it will continue the whole time of my life: hoping you will grace me with your fauourable suspence, vntill my deeds proue my doctrine. And withall, I most entirely desire you, and euery one of you, (euen for my Sauiour Iesus Christ his sake) that shall gather any spirituall comfort to cure your soules out of these my labours, to pray vnto our Lord Iesus Christ for me, to giue me his grace to returne vnto him by speedy repentance, and therein to guide me with his Word, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me by his holy Spirit, that what I either preach or write, I may both in life and doctrine expresse, and performe the same vnto my liues end, that whilest I endeuour to raise others, I may raise my selfe, from all my sinnes, vnto the glorie of Gods holy name and the saluation of my owne soule. And so doe for mee an earnest repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant sinner, euen as you your selues, towards your selues, expect from Iesus Christ. <hi>Valete in Christo.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours towards you, as I would you should be for me,</hi> Iohn Andrewes <hi>Preacher of Gods Word.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>