<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT GODLY, WOR∣SHIPFVLL, AND VIGILANT PASTOR IN Christs Kirke, Iohne Erskin of Dun, especiall planter and builder of the Reformed within the boundes of An∣gus, Merns, Stermonth, and Gowrie: Iames Anderson, Minister at Collace, his most humble, and obedient in Christ, wisheth grace and peace from God the Fa∣ther, with increase of spirituall gifts, and health of bodie, through Iesus Christ our Sauiour. Amen.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S90283_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07160</idno>
           <idno type="STC">572.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S90283</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT GODLY, WOR∣SHIPFVLL, AND VIGILANT PASTOR IN Christs Kirke, Iohne Erskin of Dun, especiall planter and builder of the Reformed within the boundes of An∣gus, Merns, Stermonth, and Gowrie: Iames Anderson, Minister at Collace, his most humble, and obedient in Christ, wisheth grace and peace from God the Fa∣ther, with increase of spirituall gifts, and health of bodie, through Iesus Christ our Sauiour. Amen.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ane godly treatis, callit the first and second cumming of Christ. In verse</title>
                 <author>Anderson, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>(unpaged), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT GODLY, WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, AND VIGILANT PASTOR IN Christs Kirke, <hi>Iohne Erskin</hi> of <hi>Dun,</hi> especiall planter and builder of the Reformed within the boundes of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, Merns, Stermonth,</hi> and <hi>Gowrie: Iames Anderson,</hi> Minister at <hi>Collace,</hi> his most humble, and obedient in Christ, wisheth grace and peace from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with increase of spirituall gifts, and health of bodie, through Iesus Christ our Sauiour. Amen.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>RIght ancient Professour of the Trueth,</l>
      <l>Long time before it came to cōmon sight:</l>
      <l>Which perilous time thou passedst not with sleuth.</l>
      <l>But hardily didst hazard day and night,</l>
      <l>To bring the Trueth to libertie and light.</l>
      <l>Life, Land, and geare, thou set them all apart,</l>
      <l>Of that true Treasure so joyfull was thine heart.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thine house was harbour to all that profest,</l>
      <l>Thy geare was common to them in time of need:</l>
      <l>Aboue all other thou loued thy brethren best:</l>
      <l>As thy own flesh thou didst them cloath &amp; feed:</l>
      <l>Not naked loue in word, but loue indeed:</l>
      <l>VVhich loue the Lord forget not to restore;</l>
      <l>The more thou gaue, hee gaue thee aye the more.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And whē it pleasde Christ Iesus King of grace,</l>
      <l>To bring his Trueth to light and libertie,</l>
      <l>And by the same, proud Papistes to deface,</l>
      <l>And them ouerthrow, with their Idolatrie:</l>
      <l>Then did hee call thee to this dignitie,</l>
      <pb facs="2"/>
      <l>To plant his Kirke in <hi>Gowrie, Mernes,</hi> and <hi>Angus,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>VVhich prudently thou hast planted among vs:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And hast the same oft watered with his word,</l>
      <l>Perswading euer to perseuerance:</l>
      <l>And not to faint for feare of Fire or Sword:</l>
      <l>But bee enarmed with Faith and patience,</l>
      <l>Builded on Christ, that Rocke of sure defence,</l>
      <l>Thus thou ceast not, but traueilledst faithfully,</l>
      <l>Till infirme age perforce constrained thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yea, though thou be now warded, as it were,</l>
      <l>Frō tedious trauels, which thou wast wōt to tak,</l>
      <l>And mayst not from thy Chamber journey farre:</l>
      <l>Yet in thy cure thou art not slow nor flacke:</l>
      <l>But as the Bee that doeth collect and make,</l>
      <l>Her wholsome honey of many Herbes &amp; Flowers,</l>
      <l>So thou thy Sermons of sundry sweet Scriptures:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhich thou doest forme into most comly writ,</l>
      <l>For speciall profit to thy Posteritie:</l>
      <l>Thy louable labours therein ere and late,</l>
      <l>VVhen thou art dead, shall liue eternally,</l>
      <l>And keepe thy Name in blessed memorie:</l>
      <l>That as in youth thy tong taught Christs word,</l>
      <l>So in thine age thy penne did preach that Lord.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I Can not dite as thou hast done deserue,</l>
      <l>In Kirke &amp; Court, Countrey and Commonweale:</l>
      <l>Carefull the Kirke in peace for to preserue:</l>
      <l>In Court thy counsell was stout, &amp; true as steele:</l>
      <l>Thy policie decores the Countrey well,</l>
      <l>In planting Trees, and building places faire,</l>
      <l>VVith costly Brigs ouer waters plaine repaire.</l>
   </lg>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
      <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>