<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S90323_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21281</idno>
           <idno type="STC">762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S90323</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The problemes of Aristotle, with other philosophers and phisitions : Wherein are contayned diuers questions, with their answers, touching the estate of mans bodie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London ; Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>EVery man dooth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (gentle reader) at an Eclipse of the Sunne or of the Moone, and gazeth at a Blazing Starre, and beholdeth with admiration, an exquisit picture, drawne with the pensill of a skilfull hand, yea all nouelties doe please, be they neuer so small. But if they be once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, bee they neuer so great wonders, no man vouchsafeth to giue them the looking on. But then as <hi>Seneca</hi> doth say: <hi>Non est AEthiopia inter suos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> color.</hi> The selfe same doth happen in man, and in the wonderfull workmanship of his bodie, and vnspeakeable excellencie of his soule: for if we regarde his excellencie, he doth surpasse all creatures vnder Heauen; and therefore the Aegyptians being rauished with the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of mans dignitie and perfection, doubted not to call him a terrestriall god, a
<pb facs="3"/>
celestiall creature, a messenger of the god Lord and Master of things belowe, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friend vnto those who liue aboue, miracle of nature, and as <hi>Seneca</hi> doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him, Natures darling.</p>
   <p>It is said, that after that <hi>Phidias</hi> a most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous caruer had made <hi>Mineruas</hi> shielde, he engraued his own portraiture so liuely, &amp; deepely in the same, that it could neuer be taken out againe, without the defacing of the whole worke. So God himselse a farre more excellent workeman then <hi>Phidias,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had made the vniuersall world, and all creatures therein, for a token of his skill, drew it a new in a small compas, as an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of all his workes, to wit, when he made man, who is a Microcosme or little worlde, and in him printed his owne image and similitude, so liuely, that no power what soeuer is able to blot it out. This image and similitude is the soule and vnderstanding, which he would neuer haue printed in man, vnlesse he had first made him a bodie of a substance fit and apt to receiue that impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and vnlesse also he had so skilfully fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, that it should be worthie to receiue so great an ornament, as the vnderstanding
<pb facs="3"/>
is. And therefore the body of man is made of a complexion most pure and delicate, and in shape comely and beautifull, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, all these perfections which man hath in himselfe, few or none take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the studie of himselfe, or is carefull to know the substance, state, condition, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vse of the parts of his owne bodie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be the honor of nature, and more to be adm red then the strangest and rarest wonder that euer happened. The cause of this is no other, but because mans nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in noueltie, and neglecteth to search out the causes of those things which are common.</p>
   <p>I haue therefore thought good, to giue thee in a knowne tongue, this little booke, written by the deepest of all Philosophers who teacheth the vse of all the parts of mans body, their nature, quality, property and vse, which may bring thee in reading of it, if reade it thou wilt no lesse delite then profit, nor no lesse profit then delight.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell</salute>
      <signed>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
            <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>