<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S909_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06674</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17128</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S909</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations and deuout discourses vpon the B. Sacrament composed by Ch. M</title>
                 <author>M, Ch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--East Ham</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 14, 190 pages, 8° in 4's</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>o the Reader.</head>
   <p>THE nature of man is desirous of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie, chaunge, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> &amp; varietie. Noe bed is so soft, of which in tyme we are not wearie; no Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick so delightfull, which by oftē repetition, becommeth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: noe dish so daintie which if it come often to the table is not loathed: and nothing but the cleare vision and fruition of God doth alwaies content.</p>
   <p>The reason of this is the suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of God his goodnes &amp; the insufficiēcie of that which is good in his creatures. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For God is <hi> Sūmum bonum,</hi> cheefest and infinite Good
<pb facs="12"/>in which is no defect, and so being seen clearlie, &amp; perfectli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, as he is of the Blessed in heauē, who see him <hi>face to face,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies delight, neuer glutte the Blessed, or make them desirous of chaunge. But all creatures, and create Goods, as they content and delight for a tyme, by reason that they are good in their kind, so in tyme they discontent, and make vs wearie of them, because in that they are finite, they are also defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. VVhence it is that as sick men cannot lye long on one side or in one posture, but doe turn &amp; chaunge often, so wee are neuer long content with any one create thing, seeme it at first neuer so pleasing, but after wee haue had a tast of it, wee are wearie of it, and desire to chaunge, though some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes for worse.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And this is the cause why after
<pb facs="12"/>many spirituall bookes set out heretofore by others, I haue not feared to set out myne, though they bee of the same subiect that other former bookes were, seeing that, though myne treat of the same matter, yet they doe it in a diuers manner, and so for varietie may please. I knew well that many had written <hi>paraphrases</hi> vpon the Psalme <hi>Miserere</hi> and vpon all the Psalmes: and yet in the yeare 1635 laduētured to set out mine also, hoping that when deuout persōs are wearie of still reading others <hi>Paraphrases,</hi> they wold for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie be content to read mine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, and I was not deceiued.</p>
   <p>And although I was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that many Authours haue written meditations vpon the B. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Sacrament, and the sacred passion of Christ yet for the aforesaid reason, I now diuulge my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb facs="13"/>vpon the same subiects, hoping that after often reading of those former bookes, some out of desire of chaunge wilbe content to read mine though inferiour.</p>
   <p>And therfore to accommodate my self to humain infirmitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to which euen spirituall exercises, in time grow wearisome, in these my meditations vpon the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, I haue so disposed, that euerie meditation, hath a diuers particular subiect, that so the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie at least may allure the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and that the Communicant or Receiuer may come with a better spirituall appetite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notion to receiue in this Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, his Sauiour &amp; his sacred bodie and bloud, I propose him in diuers manners, as in manner, of a Feast maker, a boūtifull house keeper, a Freind, a Pastour, a phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician,
<pb facs="13"/>a spouse, a Father, and the like, that this varietie may delight and cause the Receiuer to come to this Holie Sacrament without any tediousnes, yea with greater spirituall appetite.</p>
   <p>And so I hope my meditations will not be vngratefull, because in them there is varietie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie also from the meditations, which others haue set forth. others may haue somethīg, which I haue not, and I may haue some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which they haue not; they may haue their manner, and I may haue myne; they may haue their inuentions, I may haue myne; and so both theirs and myne may be pleasing. For as the same meate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerslie cooked, may be as pleasing as diuers meates, soe the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter handled by diuers diuerslie may by reason of this varietie, prooue no lesse pleasing then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="14"/>matters, and subiectes.</p>
   <p>Otherwise, if because that some haue written of a subiect, others who succeed thē, must not touch that matter, all modern Authours must absteine from writing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause nothing can be now sayd, which was not in substance sayd before. For as <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> said in his time, so much more may wee now say in our time:
<note place="margin">Eccles. 1</note>
      <hi>nothing vnder the Sunne is new, neither is any man able to saye: behold this is new; for that it hath alreadie gone before in the ages that were before.</hi> And so wee See that there are diuers commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries vpon the same booke of scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, diuers sermons on the same holy day &amp; text, diuers bookes of the same part of Philosophie &amp; diuinitie.</p>
   <p>This being premised for my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> I will breeflie aduertise the Reader that Meditation is not
<pb facs="14"/>whatsoeuer speculation or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course vpon God or his diuine perfections, or the mysteries of our faith, for, this speculation being only to discouer the truth, is not worthie the name of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, which is a kind of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal prayer: but meditation doth speculate the aforesaid obiectes, &amp; discourseth on them to mooue some affection, as loue, ioye, feare, sorrow, according to the natures of the mysteries or obiectes, on which wee meditate. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
   </p>
   <p>In this exercise of meditation (as the contemplatiues doe well obserue) there are three wayes to perfection. The one is <hi>Purgatiue,</hi> when by meditation wee stirr vp in vs a feare of God &amp; his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and sorrow for our sinnes or hatred of them, by which our soules are purged from all filth of sinne. The second way is <hi>illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue,</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>when by meditation our understanding is so illuminated, as it seeth the excellencie of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as of obedience, humilitie, pouertie of spirit, chastitie and the like, and seing the beautie of it, induceth the will to loue it, and louing it, to practise and to get it. The third way is <hi>Vnitiue,</hi> when by meditation of God his Diuine perfections we stirre vp in our heartes a loue of God, a compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in his Goodnes or mercie, or other his perfectiōs, and diuine attributes &amp; by this way our soules are vnited to God. The first way is of beginners, the secōd of those that profit in the way of vertue, the third of them that are perfect.</p>
   <p>In my <hi>Paraphrasis</hi> and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Psalme <hi>Miserere,</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I haue speciallie shewed the <hi>Purgatiue</hi> way, inducing the sinner to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and sorrow for his sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="15"/>by which sorrow the soule is purged frō sinne. In my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the Passion, I propose the <hi>illuminatiue</hi> waye, because Christ in his Passion hath set vs exāples of all vertues. In my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatiōs vpon the B. Sacrament I teach the <hi>vnitiue</hi> way, that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by it selfe vniting vs reallie to Christ, and the consideration of it stirring vp loue towards God for such a benefit, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> by which we are vnited vnto him; although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in euerie one of these my treatises, I shew all the aforesayd three wayes.</p>
   <p>But because Christ instituted this B. Sacrament before his Passion, and was immolated my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticallie before he was sacrificed on the Crosse reallie: I first pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent thee (Gentle Reader) with my Meditations on the B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and after them I will make
<pb facs="16"/>thee partaker of those of the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion which shall follow these for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. God graunt that both thou and I, in them may find out and follow the aforesayd three wayes to perfection; that wee may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the perfection of vertue and grace in this life, and soe to the perfection of glorie (which is our last and greatest perfection) in the next.</p>
   <pb facs="16"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>