<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S91274_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07431</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S91274</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two treatises : 1. The holy exercise of a true fast, described out of Gods word. Written by T. C. The substance of the Lordes supper. Written by T. W [ilcox.]</title>
                 <author>T. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 99, 11, 88, 16, 135, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="57"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the motion and request of sundrie my deare friendes in the Lord, I haue thought good to putte dovvne tvvo Prayers at the latter ende of this Treatise, not thereby min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either to tie any person to the vse of them onely, for they may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their seuerall necessi ies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue some other of their ovvne, or practise some better forme already set dovvne, by men of greater giftes, and feeling: nor yet, so to busie their mindes, and to occupie their heades, as that they should be imployed in these, vvhen the publike Prayers and exercises of the Church, performed by the Ministers are in hand (for be it farre frō vs, vvhen the Minister Gods mouth speaketh from the Lord to vs or vvhen he as our mouth speaketh to the Lord for vs, to haue either our heartes
<pb facs="58"/> or our mouthes occupied about any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, than the reuerent hearing and consenting vnto, of such thinges as he vttereth) but that ayding the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of our breathren, such as haue not the gifte to conceiue Prayer, might haue a forme to exercise them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in, both before they repaire to the publike exercises of the Church, and after the celebration of those reuerent my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, shall he finished.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>