<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHILDREN AND youth of Long-Ditton, Kingston vp∣on Thames, and East Molsey: Grace be vnto you and peace, from him which was, and which is, &amp; which is to come.</title>
           <author>Byfield, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S91269_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07429</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4237.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S91269</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHILDREN AND youth of Long-Ditton, Kingston vp∣on Thames, and East Molsey: Grace be vnto you and peace, from him which was, and which is, &amp; which is to come.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A candle lighted at the lampe of sacred scriptvres. Or A catechisme conteining all truths fundamentall, and none but fundamentalls. By Richard Bifield, Minister of Gods word, and Pastor in Long Duton.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>[52] p. ;  8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE CHILDREN AND youth of</hi> Long-Ditton, Kingston <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Thames, <hi>and East</hi> Molsey: <hi>Grace</hi> be vnto you and peace, from him which was, and which is, &amp; which is to come.</head>
   <p>LIttle children and youth, I am debter to you als<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, and am taught by <hi>Iohn,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh,</hi> 2 12, 13.</note> the Disciple whom our Saviour loved: to pay this debt by writing. I Dedicate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this little booke to you ioyntly: where in▪ you my little babes, may see the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in forgiuing your sinnes for Christs name sake; and may learne euen in the milke to know, and knowing to call God Father. Wherein likewise you young men, may, as out of the Lords armory, haue weapons ready fitted to your hand &amp; vse, wherewith ye shall overcome that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one. And if ye receiue by faith this doctrine, and let it abide in you, to loue it to obey it, you shall encrease your strength; and the better with stand future assaults, in all of them, being more then Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
   <p>For, in the first part, yee haue orderly framed in words of Stripture, the whole body of divinitie, which we are to beleeue
<pb facs="3"/> concern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g the Gospell of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Iesus Christ, after a familiar way of Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>chising: no one matter of opinion mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, but onely fundamentall truthes; layd downe so that all Heresies-now being, or formerly rooted, or that may hereafter spring vp, as tares amongst the wheate, are cut off; not by humaine wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t and Schoole distincti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ns: but by divine word &amp; holy writ. here you haue much, yea all in a little, yet without obscurity. Here ye have that faith which ever was held &amp; professed vniversally in the Church: as will be manifest to the iudicious that are acquaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d with Scripture, with Councels with the authen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Creeds, with the pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like confessions of christian m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n &amp; Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. The truth I dare boldly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themselues being iudges. In a word: yee haue here the heads of Doctrine, which in euery particular in the audience of the Congregation of <hi>Kingston</hi> vpon <hi>Thames,</hi> was with feare and trembling <hi>(being</hi> part of full three years laboures their) discoursed off at larg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; shewing in all and every point, the Harmony of both Testaments, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiyng of difficulties and knots in them, by way of explication, the wiles of Satha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and the flesh, begui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing vs of the fruite of such
<pb facs="3"/> knowledge and beleife in deeds, while our mouthes professed the same in words, the conclusions profitable and famous which depend upon such prime truthes. And last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Instr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ctions, consolations and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes which these doctrines afford us, for the reformation of heart and life.</p>
   <p>In the second part, I present you with the rules of holy life, whereby you are taught as the truth is in Iesus, <hi>to put off con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the the former conversation, the old man which is corrupt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the deceitfull lusts, and being renewed in the spirit of your minde, to put on the new man, which after God is created in righteovsnes and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse.</hi> Here I haue diuided the precepts of the Gospell: from those of the Law, to avoyd confusion: that they are distinct is a thing not hitherto heeded, yet (as to them will appeare that consider it without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice) most certaine. The words of Christ haue as much force to bind, as the words of the Decalogue or ten commandements.</p>
   <p>Likewise the voyce of Repentance, is no voyce of the Law; and so of the rest. That I haue cast them into ten, is not out of any superstition of the number: nor any conceit of mine that there are iust ten, but onely to
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/> help memory; they also fitly arising to that number, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or ought I see, the whole comprehended. I haue in the margent set two different marks upon certaine answers or phrases in those answers, by which I would haue you to take notice of your estate before God. If those or any one of those graces or priviledges bee manifest vpon your hearts wrought by the word, which are signed with this signe <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>being that Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall mark, Ezek.</hi> 9. 4.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> they proue you actually the children of God. If the sinnes or kind of offending be yet found in you which is marked with that marke <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>the first letter in the word</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zim <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>l.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>signify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing scorn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> you are unregenerated and wicked sinners, and remaine s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch till you wash them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by true repentance, and Faith in the Lord Iesus.</p>
   <p>Take these &amp; digest them thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yea eate them up; as reached forth to you from God, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gh by the unworthy hands of a meane Labourer in Gods V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: whose pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r is, that you may increase in wisdome and stature, and in favour with God and man.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Richard Bifield.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>