<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL VERTVOVS Nobilitie, reuerend Clergie, and well affected Gentrie, ROBEKT CARLYLE wisheth grace, mer∣cie, and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S91360_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B01023</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4650</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S91360</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL VERTVOVS Nobilitie, reuerend Clergie, and well affected Gentrie, ROBEKT CARLYLE wisheth grace, mer∣cie, and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Britaines glorie, or An allegoricall dreame : with the exposition thereof. Containing the heathens infidelitie the Turkes blasphemie the Popes hypocrisie Amsterdams varietie the Church of Englands verity in religion. And in our Church of England, the Kings excellency. His issues integritie. The nobles and gentries constancie. The councell and iudges fidelities. The preachers puritie. The bishops sinceritie. Conceiued and written by Robert Carlyle gent. for the loue and honour of his king and countrie</title>
                 <author>Carliell, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 42 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL VERTVOVS Nobilitie, reuerend Clergie, and well affected Gentrie, ROBEKT CARLYLE wisheth grace, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and peace in <hi>Christ Iesus.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Noble, Religious and worthie persons, the Title Page demonstrateth vnto you, that the plot of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke hath a generall scope, and is erected vpon all your seuerall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, so that for the interest which you may challenge in this structure, I will entitle you with the Dedication: For in so much as God hath giuen you the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of knowledge, Religion, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, you are also coheires of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation thereof: And because this building is thus magnificently beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="3"/>with excellent Statues, no lesse per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons then your selues, adorned with all the golden and pretious robes of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Saints: meruaile not that I giue it a glorious name; for if the Arke of God was called <hi>The glory of Israel</hi> being a type onely, 1. <hi>Sam</hi> 4.21. Then the Gospell of Christ Iesus, the foundation of this frame, shall make it glorious eternally. I haue beene curious in the workemanship of this Edifice, and carefull lest my blunt edged Chissell, in the caruing of your pictures, and inscription of your Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies, should blemish your personages, or dash out one letter of your fame: If I haue done well I shall be glad for my Countries sake; If I haue committed any one error I disdaine not to haue it amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this worke by such as are better experienced then my selfe. Meane time I desire my loue and good will may be louingly accepted. And so I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most deuoted <hi>R. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>