<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To al that wish Ieru∣shalems prosperitie, the grace of God be mul∣tiplied.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S91453_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07515</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5336.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S91453</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To al that wish Ieru∣shalems prosperitie, the grace of God be mul∣tiplied.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A description of new Ierushalem being the substaunce of two sermons deliuered at Paules Crosse : Containing, a briefe discouery and conuiction of certayne doctrines held of Romanists and Brownists against the Catholike and Apostolike faith. By Henoch Clapham</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 113, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To al that wish Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shalems prosperitie, the grace of God be <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued, if euer, now fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayer is highly necessary: as for the whole catholike Church, so (of our partes) more specially for our owne particular Church, a member of the vniuersall. As I am not a little acquainted with forraine Churches their corruptions (but the lesse contagious, because they be in further part of the catholik body remoued from vs) so, not to dissemble our own (alas, alas) hovv is our Sauiors speech fulfilled vpon vs? Faith (faithfully professed) hard to bee found, when vnder color of Reformation, people feare not to complot Deformation: euerie fantasticke spirite attempting what is good in his owne eyes and priuate iudgement, as though there were no King in Israel, no God in heauen. For Charitie, the most of vs haue exiled her. Faith iustifieth alone, say we: tis true: but adde with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, <hi>That faith which worketh by Loue:</hi> euen by Loue termed the <hi>Bond of Perfection,</hi> and
<pb facs="5"/> the <hi>Fulfilling of the Law:</hi> for neuer shall that Tree bee approoued which bringeth not foorth good fruit. Trees are not planted for liuing to themselues, but for benefiting others also. The diuel once sought to leade vs so to gaze on the merit of workes, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all we should examine howe wee stood in the faith: now he labors to cause vs so to admire Faith, as wee should forget (I had almost said, forsweare) good works. Thus Satan is euer in extremities: but the people of God must know, that as GOD hath blessedly ioyned true faith and good workes togither: so, none can but by the instinct of Satan attempt to put them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder. If we so beleeue, and so walke, then God shall not be weary of doing vs good, nor we haue occasion to feare the threates of Belial.</p>
   <p>As all euilles are contagion, so falshood in doctrine is Leauen for infecting many: and a Canker for corroding like a viper. For, from whence proceede euill workes, but from euill Beliefe, false perswasion of God and his proceedings? The late Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manistes will that their Pope may erre in <hi>Fact,</hi> but not in <hi>Faith.</hi> A blinde assertion: for no erroneous fact, but it proceeds from erroneous Faith. As for example: <hi>Peter</hi> denieth his maister, a foule Fact. From
<pb facs="5"/> whence proceeded this, but from a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion, that it should be good for him <hi>then</hi> to do <hi>so?</hi> The like may be said of any fact. So that we may conclude rather, A man may erre in faith, yet not in fact (for hee may stay to act his error) but neuer erre in fact, but first the diuell hath sowen errour in his faith. And heereof it commeth that Romanists on the one hand; &amp; Brownists, Anabaptists, Arrians, &amp;c. on the other hand, they besiege our Church with spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall artillery: euery Sect thinking they therein doe God very good seruice, and their Fact passing commendable: whereas (alas) such proceeding is but the fruite (to thinke the best) of errour in Faith, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in iudgement.</p>
   <p>It is then a duty of Gods Ministers, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially owing to the people, namely, to hold out the word of trueth for enlightning the senses. And because <hi>Illumination</hi> without <hi>Sanctification</hi> doth make a man but a <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> an Iscariot, a diuell: herewith they are to pray much, that GOD would sanctifie such light and knowledge to true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
   <p>Amongest the residue of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, I (the least of many) do labour in this worke daily. Though I haue no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="6"/> flocke to attend on by peculiar calling: yet am I called to the worke of Christ, for ministration of worde and Sacrament to God his sheepe, in this catholike sheepfold. A calling had at home, and not vnsubscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto by forraine Churches. Before thine eyes I haue heere lighted a candle, describing new Ierushalem, the praise of the whole earth. This is not done so parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as might be wished, but as the time could affoorde. <hi>Moses</hi> (from mount <hi>Neboes</hi> toppe termed <hi>Pisgah</hi>) he seeth <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Israels</hi> distinct lotts: but <hi>Ioshuah</hi> (the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of these mansions) hee sawe it more thorowly. If that I haue done may occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion any other to do better, my lot is good. Meane time accept of this <hi>Description of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rushalem,</hi> as of a light, directing to a <hi>Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Babel:</hi> that (if God thinke good) I may heereafter publish. Which if, some things heere omitted, may there be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obserued.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Southwark</hi> by <hi>London,</hi>
         <date>1601</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>