<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S91610_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07555</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6326</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S91610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The art of vvar, and Englands traynings : plainely demonstrating the dutie of a priuate sovldier; with the office of each seuerall officer belonging to a foot-company: and the martiall lawes of the field. As also, the office and charge belonging to the command of a colonell; the exercise of trayning or drilling: with diuers other necessary and profitable disciplined notes and observations. By Edw. Davies Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Davies, Edward, gentleman</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 121, that is 221, 1 page, 1 folded leaf, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He exercise of training hath beene much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and chiefly in the Marches of <hi>Wales,</hi> till now of late that it hath pleased God, and the Kings grace, to send vs that thrice wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Earle of <hi>North-hampton,</hi> Lord Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, established in the principality of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Councell in the Marches of <hi>Wales</hi> &amp;c. For it hath pleased his Excellencie in times conuenient to call together the Traine-men; and his Lordship was honourably, and dutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, and conueied from Shire to Shire by his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Lieutenants of the Shire; and also all the Knights and best Gentlemen in the Countrey. The Military men being as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled together, it pleased his Lordship to take great paines in ordering, directing, and exercising both Horse and Foote most brauely to behold; and his Lordshippe taking speciall view both of Horse and Foote, where his Lordship apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding debilitie and error to be committed amongst them, his Lordship giueth the Captaines a streight charge, by no meanes, not to neglect their exercise of training vnder paine, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Likewise, to make it more apparant to the view of the world of his Lo: affection towards the exercise of Marciall disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, his Lo: hath now of late called together, not only his Lo: owne Gentlemen, but also all the Clarkes belonging to the Councell in the Marches of <hi>Wales;</hi> and his Lordship being well prouided of an able Leader, which is one of his Lo: Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who in times conuenient doth exercise the said Company.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>Moreouer, I ought not to omit to relate his Honours due commendations, as also his speciall care of the <hi>KINGS</hi> Maiesties seruice, to maintaine not onely all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall discipline, but also to lead his Ho: Successors to the marke of an honourable subiect; and to performe the same his Lordship is alwaies prouided of <hi>18.</hi> goodly and braue young Horses, the which are daily trained in all points of warre (at <hi>Luddlow</hi> Castle-yard) by one of his Gent: of the Horse, who is an expert and sufficient Rider, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Also it is my part to say somewhat herein of the worthy Rulers, and Gouernours of the <hi>Low-countries</hi> the schoole of Warre; his Excellencie <hi>Graue Mauris</hi> hath inuented and set out diuers Postures belonging to the orders both of Pike and Musket, very necessary and profitable for the exercise of armes, the which are maintained and practised by the thrice worthy Commanders, Coronell <hi>Cissell,</hi> and Coronell <hi>Veare;</hi> and is directly followed by all other valiant Leaders: the which Postures and Orders are practised in the Artillery-yard, and also in the Military-yard, by worthy Captaines, well experienced in the Martiall discipline, and also they are well prouided of sufficient Officers.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>There came a little Pamphlet to my hands wherin I found, and made vse of certaine Orders of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cising Muskettieres: The said booke was dedicated vnto that worthy Commander Coronell CISSELL, who did much practise the said Orders:</hi> Viz. <hi>also that the said vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume was set out by that worthy Leader Captaine WAIMOVTH, who is worthy of great commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for his good worke.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>