<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the fayghtfull.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S91796_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07588</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7376.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S91796</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the fayghtfull.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A litell dialogue off the consolator co [m] fortynge the churche in hyr afflictions : taken out off the 129. psalme. Composed in fre [n] che by M. Peter du Val. And translated into Englyshe by Robert Pownoll. Anno 1556. Me [n] s [is] Iunij</title>
                 <author>DuVal, P. (Pierre)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lambrecht, Joos</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_faithful">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the fayghtfull.</head>
   <p>FOR as myche as in all ages, the Lorde God (and that by his secret &amp; iuste iudgment, and for certaine causes expressed vnto vs in his holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures) hathe alwayes exposed and gyven ouer his people, to the ragynge rygoure, &amp; violēt affliction off the wycked: so that wordly wysdom blynded, dothe esteme the condition &amp; state of the fayghtful mos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te vnfortunate. Beynge subiecte to so ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny myseres, cōtemned of men, destituted off ryches, afflicted by pouertye, assau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted off tyrrantes, banyshed out off theyre owne coūtryes, theyre goodes confysked, some tyme imprisoned, oftentymes mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered, drowned, buryed quycke, hedded, bornte, hanged, &amp; extemed no more then the fylthynes off the worlde, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cowrynge off al thynges. And on the o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther syde seynge the wycked (gyuen ouer to all vngodlynes) prosper in felicite, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ounde in wealthe, increace in ryches, continewe in healthe, lusty in body, mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in power, hauynge the worlde at they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re wyll, in shuche sorte that theyre condi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion in respect off the other, ys to be desy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red: so that this tēptation dothe not a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell
<pb facs="2"/>
troble the simple mynded, who cōsy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no thynge but that which they see pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sently before theyre eyes. Wherfor to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vēt shuche a mased bashfulnes as now oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupyethe the myndes off a great manye of simple well dyspoced people: and some what to elivate and styre vp theyre decly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned spiretes. I haue thought good to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medye the same by some lytell cōsolation: the which amongest the offices off chari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dothe not pocesse the last place, &amp; ought never to be farre dystant from the feloshi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe off the fayghtfull. For as callamites and troubles shall never fayle them this worlde: even so behouethe it them to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all wayes in theyre hande, in theyre mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the, and in theyre herte, godly cōsolatiō and cōforte, which at this present ys most necessary vnto the chyldryne off God, yff euer it were requysite: seynge that tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations do now aboūde with out measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re more then in tymes paste. For in thesse dayes whether so euer the fayghtfull go, or torne them selves: eyther the fyres are redy kendled to consume them, or the pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons &amp; dongions are open to ressayve thē, or els theyre howses &amp; goodes are sealed vp by the feales off vniuste iustices to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueryshe them, or els they fleinge hyther
<pb facs="3"/>
&amp; thyther as poore slaves &amp; vacabondes, destitute bothe off mony &amp; fryndds do suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer infinite miseres &amp; pouertyes, and are compelled to supporte a thowsand oppro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres &amp; iniures, as people forsaken &amp; vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vnworthy off all goodnes. With out omittynge, that they are compassed abou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te with an innumerable multitude off ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uersaries: amongest whom on the one sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de are thosse great and ferefull giantes with theire rable of grevous greshoppers, to wytt, the Pope, his Lardenales, Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chebishopes, Byshoppes, Myters, Cros<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses, Croissyers, thounderynge &amp; rorynge with theyre titeles, Sāctissimi, Colēdis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simi, Reuerendissimi, Obseruandissimi: and about thē are theyre Prothenotares Archedeacons, Chanones, Curates and Prestes, with an infinite nōber of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes &amp; fryers: all to gyther animated &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flambed to warre agaynste the hūble her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, &amp; ferynge God. On the other syde are armed the Ceasars inuictissimi, the Rynges illustrissimi, the Princes fortis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simi, with al theire nobilitey: vnder whō the earthe tremblethe, &amp; the worlde qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe. On the other syde are the graue Presedentes, the prudent Counsaylors, the facounde Aduocates, and eloquēt La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyers,
<pb facs="3"/>
with theyre cruell bandes: amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest whom, some do set vp the galowes, some other do prepare the fagotes, other some haue in theyre handes, Gyvers, Fet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, Manacles, and all other kynde of tortures redy to put them in practysse.</p>
   <p>On the other syde, are the worshupfull master Doctore, the reuerēde Bachelors, the venerable Rectors, the lerned Regen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, the wysse Masters, and all shuche o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, redy fornyshed with theyre wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pōs. What cā preuaylle agaynst so myghty an arme? Cā thosse that take part with Iesus Christ, which seme to be so feable? Seynge that the most part off them are people poore off spirete, simple as doves, shepe affocision, with out ryches, voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de off fryndes, extemed apostates, dyspy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced craftesmen, handy laborers, vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, exposed to all dangers, condēned as vnprofytable, expelled, whypped, banys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hed scaffolded, weryed, travayled, nyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, deiected, imprisoned, stocked, fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and destituted off all defence, excepte off that tow edged sworde, which ys the worde off God: Agaynst whom, in the meane tyme, the aduersaryes do conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, consulte conspire, coniure: do wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them selfes, battell them selfes, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyfye
<pb facs="4"/>
them selfes, do imagen, enterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, attēpte, do sowe abrod lyinge letters, sklanderous reportes, vntrew tales, ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>genynge vayne thynges, they thounder, they tempeste, they roar, and attempt al possible meanes, to ruinate and dystroye them: They on the other syde, wepynge, fastynge, praynge blyshynge, dissemblyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge theyre sorrowe, coverynge theyre hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vynes, sacreficynge vnto God theyre tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, abydynge in this worlde no thynge but blowes, strypes, contumeles, tormē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, paynes, greffes, molestations and mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>seryes. Yff then shuche be not consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and cōforted by the holy scryptures, wherin only ys all refuge, Ioye &amp; delecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: how can they cōtinewe without los<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se of corrage? What man off warre ys the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re be he nev{er} so valiante, whosse enymes semynge inuisible, and seynge hym selfe sodenly inclosed with them, that ys not forth with abashed &amp; dismayed, vnlesse he be boldened with a sure perswasion of notable &amp; honorable victorye? And cōtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rywysse what ys he so feable and faynte herted that seynge before his eyes his vic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torious captayne skyrmyshynge with his enymes, brekynge theyre araye, beatynge downe the mightiest, ouertrowynge the
<pb facs="4"/>
valienteste and, and levynge the reste effe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minated, discorraged, weryed, and all moste dyscomfited, that wyll not pull vp his stomake and boldly thruste hym selfe into the battayll, and specially hauynge a sure promys off his Capitayne to be crowned with triumphe after the fygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. And doth not this frute off perseuerā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce prosede from the pleasant tre off conso<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation? who all wayes promyseth, a ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full issewe after sorrowe, calmnes after tempeste, lyght after darknes, swetnes af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter sowrnes, perpetuall peace after a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment off vnquietnes, infinite glorye after a lytell payne? The father off all mercye and God off all consolation,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte the vs in all oure tribulatiōs, graūt that we may be able to cōforte them that are in any manner off trouble, with the same comforte where with we oure selues are conforted off hym: and as the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons off Christe are plentious in vs, and in al that are his, that even so every one off vs may be plentious in consolation by Christe. For this cause then, as the mos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te leste warryoure, I haue wyllyngly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated my selfe, to incorrage to the vttermost off my power my followe sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioures that now do sustayne the wayght
<pb facs="5"/>
and bronte off the batayll. And as in a battayll all are nat appoynted to fyght &amp; strycke, but some to sounde the trompet, some the drome and some to playe vpon the phiffe, therby to encorrage the soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oures: even so I can do no les, &amp; all other that there vnto are called with me, but to noyse the phiffe, to vse the pen, to plaie with my fyngers vpon the Davideicall harpe, to sounde the prophetical trompet and to stryke vp the Euangelicall drome, therby to anymate and corrag to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayll the hertes off the worthy warryors and valiante soldiours off Iesus Christe: exteminge on my parte to haue muche pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyted, yff with the sounde off this lytell phiffe, I may any thynge confort the fain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te herted, anymate the weake corraged, &amp; strenghten thosse that by feablenes do ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halte with the tyme, or straye a sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, to thende they may be restored vnto theyre former vigoure and boldnes agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: for even for them chefly do I present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sounde it: trustynge to ressayve double Ioye there by, yff in any thynge it may profyte them: Knowyng the most valiant and strongest soldiours, at the sondrye noyses off trompetes and dromes sounded vplōge ago to haue all redy wonderfully
<pb facs="5"/>
put theyre enymes to the foyle: off whō,<note place="margin">As off, Crā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ridlye, Hop{per}, Bradforthe, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Pot, Tayler, Farrer, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dmaker, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, vvith many other vvorthy vvarriours.</note> some hauynge trauarsed the batail, by fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, by watter, by sworde &amp; divers other tormentes which they haue suffred in pas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>syng thorowe: haue now preuaylled ouer theyre enymes, &amp; do were the triūphant crowne off glorye. The other as yet beyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge in the greatest thronge off the batayll, do most valiātly and corragiously sustay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the violent assautes of thosse Elephan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Lyons, Beares, Tigers, Bores, Wolfes, Dogges, Bulles, and all other shuch cruell kynde off beastes, in whosse assautes they are sufficiētly anymated to penetrate the breache of theyre aduersary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. To thende then that I do not rone at an vncertayne thynge,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> nor fyght as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne that beatethe the ayre? I haue put my felfe into the arraye with the fayghtfull Champions off Iesus Christe, for to soū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the alarom agaynst his enymyes: And all though this my phiffe do make no gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at noyse, for that it ys but lytell: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the les he that wyll gyve attētyve ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vnto the same (in myn opinion) shall fynde the same replete with sufficient har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monye, and not yll agreynge with the trō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petes, clarious and dromes that hath byn sounded all redy, all thought his tune be
<pb facs="6"/>
not so hyghe. I am ryght well assured that it shall playe no thynge out off the tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne off Godes worde, which thynge cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sethe me to iudge that it shalbe the better harde. Besydes that, the tow persons set forthe in this dialogue are ryght worthy that we shoulde gyve them audience: For the one ys the Churche or Congregation off Christe, and the other ys the Consola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor or the comfortor. I saye notablye the Churche off Christe, the Cōgregation off the fayghtfull where so ever they be, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte to God eternal lyffe: and not the Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deicall Synagoge, nor the Mahometical broude, nor all the papisticall Rable, nor yet none off the hereticall Sectaryes: all the which haue no parte in this churche, founded vpon the doctryne off the Apost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and Prophetes: The which Churche ys introduced in this dialogue, as sorrow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, mornynge, troubled, and discōfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by cause off the oppressions, persecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, calamites, afflictions and tormen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes wherewith the wycked vngodly tyrā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and persecutors do moleste hyr: &amp; that only by cause that she sustaynethe, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dethe, mayntaynethe &amp; supportethe the quarrell off hyr God: off whom she feare the to be forsaken, abandoned and cōtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="6"/>
as some tyme it semethe that she ys, by cause of hyr synnes. And therfor most aptly ys there also introduced a Consola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor for the other Collocutor, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to his name dothe consolate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, and fortifye hyr: allegynge vnto hyr manye worthy sentences &amp; notable places off the holy scriptures, which do assure hyr off the assistāce &amp; healpe off hyr God, off his good wyll, and diuine prouidence towardes hyr: promysynge a most short &amp; perfyte delyurance off hyr Crosse, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyne off hyr enymee, and a croune off in credible glorye: wher with finally she con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentethe hyr felfe, and dependethe vpō the same with great confidence. I doute not that any wyll saye, they are tow persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ill appropriated: for in myn opinion it ys not possible to accomodate and copell to gyther for this present tyme, tow per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons more apte and proper. What thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ys there in the worlde more afflicted, then the Churche off Christe? And what thynge ys more worthy all cōsolation thē she? Truly there ys not one off all thosse that notte them selfes to be hyr fryndes, that dothe comforte hyr: But rather thos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se that wonte to boste thēselves to be hyr cheffe fryndes and familiers haue vtterly
<pb facs="7"/>
contemned and dispyced hyr. where are the goodly consolations that, that gentyll gallāt the Pope (who bostethe hym selfe to be hyr hedde) with all his Clargye, (who preache thē selves to be hyr pillers) that they do minister vnto hyr? Are not thesse theye that ffyrst off all crye out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste hyr, and vpon hyr, to the fyre, to the fyre? What supporte fyndethe she off the kynges and prices of this worlde, that so muche afflicte hyr on euery syde (exsep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te off a very fewe) who not withstandin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ought to be hyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orses? But how shoulde they comforte this so poore afflic Churche, which they esteme as the of cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge off the worlde, whē as by most cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell warres and blouddy battailles they do so miserablye devoure theyre owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per subiectes? We muste then searche so<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me other Consolator and comfortor, thē thesse before named. But in searchynge we shall not fynde the trew Consolator a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where els, but where as she ys, to wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te,<note place="margin">prou. 30.</note> in God only, who all wayes dothe cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>solate the humble and afflicted, in gyvyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge them eternall consolation by his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, the which ys asure defence &amp; buckler, vnto all thosse that truste in the same: frō thēs thē we must ressayve hyr. For which
<pb facs="7"/>
cause I haue holpen my selfe with the .129 psalme off Dauid, which semethe vnto me very fytt for the purpose. For in the same, the state off the Churche, of hyr per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>secutions and afflictions, and off hyr per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>persecutors, with the Issew and ende as well off hyr that ys persecuted, as off hyr persecutors, ys so fully dystrybed. that with mythe a do there can be founde any one place more fytt for this purpose, all though that through out all the Psaul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this songe be often repeted. And I woulde to God that all thosse that synge the psalmes takynge pleasure in the voyce may in shuche sorte taste the wordes and sence off the same, that they may ressayve as muche consolation in theyre soules by the depe consyderation theroff as they gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve melodye to theyr eares by theyr voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, the which with out the sence ys all to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther vnprofytable. I wyll confesse fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I haue more serched in this Psal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, that which seruethe to the purpose off the dialogue, to comforte the fayght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and weake, then any exquysyte or sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll interpretation, that may be gathered and borowed out off the bokes off shuche as haue wrytten vpō the Psaulter. But me thynkes that I here al redy some that
<pb facs="8"/>
saye with Nathanaell? Can there come a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny good thynge out off Nazarethe? To whom I wyll answere: Come and se. A lytel vessell somtyme contaynethe good ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quoure. And it ys not so myche to be pas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed on, what the vessell ys, nor whens it comethe, so the lyquoure be good that ys drawen out off it. Fynally, this lytell, beynge ressayved and accepted in good par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and that it dothe engender some good appetyte in the harte off thosse that with saffe to taste the same: It shal occasiō me to take pleasure to prepare some other dishe no lesse delectable to the taste then this ys: But the vometyng vp off this, wyll cause me to cease from the reste, for it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re but lost laboure and exspēces yll imploi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to prepare meate, and no man to haue any appetyte to eate it. And yet this my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyl I saye, that he ys very yll cōplexi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oned, and hathe vtterly lost his stomake and taste, that cannot digeste &amp; savor this lytell morsell off meate, seynge that it ys all to gyther cōposed &amp; prepared off hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly cōfections, in the which chefly cōsist<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ethe the lyffe off man, who lyvethe not by brede only, but by every worde that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedethe out off the mouthe off God, off the which it ys sayed that it ys lyke the rai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="8"/>
&amp; snowe which cometh downe frō hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and retornethe not thyther agayne,<note place="margin">Esa. 55.</note> but watereth the eat the and makethe it frutfull &amp; grene, that it may gyve corne vnto the sower, and brede vnto hym that eateth: Even so the worde of God dothe not retorne to hym in vayne, but dothe ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cōplyshe his wyll, &amp; prosper in the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges where vnto he sendethe it. Those thē are to muche simple, that followynge the hoūgrey fooles, do imploye theyre mony in that which ys no brede, &amp; theyre labour about the thynge that dothe not satisfye and wyll not gyve eare vnto the lorde to eate the thynge that ys good,<note place="margin">Sapi. 7.</note> to thende theyre soul may haue pleasure in his plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiousnes. The lorde gyve vs his wysdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, in the which ys the spiret off vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge, which ys holy, intere, plenty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, subtyll, courtoys, discrete, quycke, vndefyled, playne, swete, lovynge the thynge that ys good, sharpe, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byddeth not to do well, gentyll, kynde, stedfaste, sure, fre, hauynge all vertues, syrcomspecte in all thynges, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendethe all spiretes off vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge, beyng pure &amp; sharpe. </p>
   <closer>So be it.</closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>