<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S918_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07920</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18290</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S918</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pidax Petreia, or, The discoverie of S. Peters well, at Peter-head, in Scotland : being in latitude 57.d.43.m. and in longitude 22.d.40.m. Shewing the admirable vertues thereof, against many deplorable diseases. By A.M. student in Medicine</title>
                 <author>Mure, Andrew, m.d</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro, Heirs of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>GOD by his wise, mighty, and wonderfull provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in such fashion governeth the world, that hee doth furnish every nation, with what hee knows to bee most necessary and convenient for them. This our nation of North Britaine, in all former ages, was esteemed and known to be as wise and valiant in minde, so health full in body; while now that by intemperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, the gut, gravell, the diseases of the splene, the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chondriak melancholy, with many other terrible uncouth, cruel and monstruous maladies are come in ready to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and destroy us, if God of his great mercy, had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to this nation that excellent spring, and water of health, which I thus discovered, being at London, with that hopefull gentleman <hi>Iames Scot,</hi> son to my <hi>L.</hi> of
<hi>Scots-tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet,</hi> who was he avily troubled with a disease, which the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est and greatest Physicians in that place, called a
<hi>Carnositie in the urinall passage,</hi> (though it proved in end to be a very hard one, and turned in a stone) the which to cure, they applyed many good and laudable medicaments, without prevailing any thing against his disease. At length despairing of health: he is sent to the waters of Tunbridge, as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>s last refuge. With whom amongst others I went: where, by the use of these waters, his paine was mitigate and aboundance of slimy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors voyded: from thence he went to Paris, where he was cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ordained to go to the Well of Spaw in Germany, and from thence to Knesbrough in England: by the use of all which waters, he is come to be expert, and to have full know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of the nature and vertues of such minerall waters.</p>
   <p>In the mean time of these voyages, my study was of that
<pb facs="3"/>kinde of fountains: remembring from my childhood, in some kinde, the affinity of the taste of the Well of Peter-head, with that which I did finde in thole Wells, whereof now I have spoken, I resolved to come and try the vertues and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of that Well. Which first the inhabitants of that town of Peter-head manifested to me, by their relation of its curing of sore eyes, loosing of the belly, if bound, &amp; stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the immoderate course thereof, serving to them for a cup of preparation before dinner, with many other such like experiences: as one, which I think not amisse to insert in this place of an old, ancient, grave man of 76. years experience, yet living, who diverse and often times hath told me, that he himself being usually troubled with sand and stones in the kidneys, used many kindes of drogues, to free him from this fearfull and consuming desease: at last being vehemently vexed with paine, took some 5. or 6. draughts of this water, after which, there burst out with his urine, great quantitie of sand and stones. Which water thus he did drink 8 dayes altogether, every morning, with the like effects, and hath never been troubled hithertils, with so vehement paine.</p>
   <p>Another in that same town, who voyded his stomach of a stone, bigger then a tennis ball <hi>per anum,</hi> and I think it was, the great antipathie which this water hath against stones or sand, in all places of the body, that made him so evacuate such a monstrous thing as this.</p>
   <p>Yet not content to know the truth hereof, and that the vertues of this water were great by some experiences: I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to dive in the deepest of this fountaine, by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary tryals of such waters: as the drawing of the tincture of a nutgall, which it will do in the twinckling of an eye, with many other pretty little tryals of that sort: as in all of them it proved excellent.</p>
   <p>Neither yet confident of my own tryals, I carryed the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this source, to the source and fountain, from whence my first knowledge in medicine did slow: and from whom, many in this nation have received the most part of their <pb facs="4"/>knowledge, both divine and Philosophicall, which water was keept half year, then tried and found neither changed in taste nor smell, as yet it remaineth in that same state after two years: and by his advise, information, and ordinance I caused pur this clear, pure wholesome water in a vessell, which after a little boyling, was coagulate in a red or brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish tincture. (like that of Plin. chap. 2. lib. 3, <hi>Tungria, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas Galliae, fontem habet insignem, plurimis bullis stillantem, ferruginei saporis, quod ipsum non nisi in fine potus intelligitur. Purgat hic corpora, tertianas febres discutit, calculorumque vitia. Eadem aqua igni admota, turbida fit, ac postremo ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bescit.</hi>) In the bottome of which vessel, after evaporation remained a red kinde of matter, like unto <hi>colcothar,</hi> which was calcined, pulverised, and dissolved with common water: the water being separate from the sediment by inclination, and evaporate there remained in the bottome a perfect vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, of a greenish colour, and of taste sharp and sweet: the vitriol by concoction within the earth, having turned its cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosive acrimonie, in a good sweet aciditie, <hi>ideo aquae therma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les omnes, qua solutam vitrioli materiam fixam, eamque coctā &amp; subdulcem, sine suo humido complectuntur, caeteris omnibus praestant: quod materia illa fixa vitrioli, humido radicali fixo auri &amp; argenti respondeat, cui infinitas occultas virtutes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esse tota credidit antiquitas. inquit Fabet. Cap.</hi> 17.
<hi>Pallad. spag.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The sediment which remained after separation of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by inclination, being again tried in the fire, proved to be a confused masse of not perfectly cancocted mettals.</p>
   <p>But none can speak more by experience, of the goodnesse and vertue of this fountaine, then the gentleman, I have named, and another gentleman of good worth, <hi>M. Thomas Aikinhead,</hi> Commissar of Edinburgh, who in August last, <hi>An.</hi> 1635. did find in this Well, as much worth, as they found in any of the forementioned exotick Wells, having tryed both. And not only those, but many other gentlemen of good respect can testifie these things to be true, which in this booke, I have written, concerning the medicinall vertues of this <pb facs="4"/>fountaine: which, good reader, I hope you may patiently read, and thank God; if, diseased, you reap any benefit from hence.</p>
   <p>Neither had I intention to have published this treatise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conscious of my own weaknesse, if I had not been ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and encouraged thereto by a letter, which I receaved from my learned Master, whom I shall reverence, with a filial respect so long as breath shall delay to expire.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>