<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Instructions to the Commssi∣oners for the dioces of Norwiche.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S92399_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00014</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10288</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S92399</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Instructions to the Commssi∣oners for the dioces of Norwiche.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Articles to be enquired of within the dioces of Norwiche, in the metropoliticall visitation of the moste Reuerend father in God, Matthew, by the prouidence of God, Archebyshop of Canterbury : Primate of all Englande, and Metropolitane, in the yeare of our Lorde God, M. D. LXVII</title>
                 <author>Church of England, Province of Canterbury, Archbishop (1559-1575 : Parker)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe, Reyner (Reginald)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="instructions_for_commissioners">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <div type="part">
      <head>Instructions to the Commssi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the dioces of Norwiche.</head>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIrste, that you doe with all diligence trauell to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the state of the clergye vnto one vniforme or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their ministration and preaching: and that w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> out any parciall respect you will put in dew execution the Queenes maiesties Ecclesiasticall lawes, Statutes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, and her highnes other commandements gyuen and published in that behalf.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Item, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in all places in your cyrcuite, you giue in charge not only vnto the curates and ministers, but also vnto the Churchwardens of euery church &amp; chappell, that they do not admitte and suffer anye person to preache or minister in their seuerall church or chappell, before they shall first see their seuerall licences vnder seale in due forme, vnder the payne that may follow thereof.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Item, you shall take diligent heede, that no fees but due &amp; of old accustomed, be exacted or taken of any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people by any registrer, clerke, somner, or anye other youre mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters or attendantes.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Item, for the better certainty &amp; knowledge of all duties and fees vnto suche as shuld pay the same, you shall note the certaine some thereof with one of your handes at the leaste in some parte of euery Instrument or writinge that shall passe your seale or graunt.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Item, that you foresee y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> no greater price be taken for the Articles which you shall inquire of, together bound with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Aduertisements then iiij.d. &amp; for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> table of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> degrees ij.d.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Item, when you haue fynished your visitation &amp; cyrcuite, (the charges of your vyage being borne and discharged) if any part of the dew procurations by you receaued of the clergy, do remaine vnspent, all the same you shal distribute to the moste poore and needye of the clergye that bee resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and keepe hospitalitye vpon theire benefices in the sayde dioces.</p>
   </div>
   <closer>God saue the Queene.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>