<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the christen reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S92562_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07679</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11211.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S92562</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the christen reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Fountayne or Well of lyfe : out of the whyche doth sprynge mooste swete consolations, ryghte necessarye for troubled conscyences to thyntente that they shal not despayre in aduersitie and trouble. Newly corrected and amended</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lobley (Loblee), Michael</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 10 cm (16°)</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the christen reader.</head>
   <p>BEholde here (christen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) the very lyuynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, the celestial treasure of gods promyses, out of whych do sprynge moost frutful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solacons for the, when so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> thou wylte resorte vnto it in thyne aduersitie wyth a thur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty stomake. For here be cōpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diously gathered togyther, the thinges that peraduēture thou myghtest seke after in the By<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble a greate whyle. And here thou mayste sone fynde wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythe thou shalte be able, not onely to cure thyne owne woū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des but also to reconforte thy neyghbour beynge fallen in to any aduersitie. And morouer to make strōge and encoura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the feblenes of mannes con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, wyth these most dele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le scriptures of the great mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of God. For al consolacyon
<pb facs="2"/> or cōforte of man, shall sauour but lyke in the, after that thou hast ones tasted of this. Thy phisicion, thy wyfe, thy paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and frendes do promise y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> nothyng but bodely helth and put the in hope of lenger lyfe, but the worde of god doth put the in hope of the lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stynge, and causehth the to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stayne the hand? of god wyth all pacyence, and to witstande the feare of death with a bolde courage, euen as it were with a stronge bulwarke, wherfore moost gentle reoder, I beseche the to take in wrath this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke such as it is, beinge bestow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed only to thy vse, and leuynge al contagyous waters &amp; styn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge fylthy pudels that may infecte thy mynde wyth errour heresye and sedycyon: Drynke largely out of thys vncorrupt and pure wel of our sauiours
<pb facs="3"/> the knowlege of his hygh me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, And in the meane tyme con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>syder how thou art bounde to eschew those ii. euyls, wherof the prophet Ieremy doth spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in thys wyse▪ My people<note place="margin">Hiere. 2</note> haue commytted. ii. euyls they haue forsaken me that am the well of the water of lyfe, and haue dygged out broken c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes that can holde no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but rather preace thou boldely to the throne<note place="margin">Hiere. 5.</note> of hys grace, that thou mayst obtaine mercy and fynde grace in tyme of nede. Vale.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>