<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the English Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S926_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the English Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The benefit that Christians receiue by Iesus Christ crucified. Translated out of French into English, by A.G</title>
                 <author>Benedetto, da Mantova</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the English Reader.</head>
   <p>THou hast here deliuered to thee, good Reader, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
treatise, first written in the Italian tongue, and
printed at Venice: after that, translated intoo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
French language, and printed at Lions, and now<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
translated &amp; printed for thee to reade in the Englishe
tongue. Enquire not of the Author, he is vnknowen,
and to know him, would doe thee but little good. Reade
the booke deuoutly, regard the matter of it attentiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
it may doe thee much good in these euil dayes. This
may be counted among the greatest euils with which
this age is infected, that they, which are called christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
are miserably diuided about Christ. And yet in
trueth (as the Apostle saith vnto vs,)<note place="margin">2. Cor.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> there is but one
God, which is the father, of whom are all things, and
we in him: &amp; our Lord Iesus Christ, by whom are all
things, and we by him. To discourse on this diuision
and the cause thereof, woulde be to some pleasing, to
some it would be displeasing. For what one truth can
please mindes so diuersly diuided? would God it could
please al to become one in that one Christ, whose name
we all doe carrie. In this little booke is that benefit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
which commeth by Christ crucified to the Christians,
truely and comfortably handled: which benefit if all
Christians did truely vnderstand and faithfully em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace,
this diuision would vanishe away, and in Christ
the Christians should become one. To this ende reade
this booke, and much good in Christ may it doe to all
them which doe reade it.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>