<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Iohn Brooke to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S92644_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11620.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S92644</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Iohn Brooke to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and cleare confession of the Christian fayth : Containing an hundreth articles, after the order of the creede of the Apostles. Made and declared by Iohn Gardiner. Translated out of French into English by Iohn Brooke of Asshe, next Sandwitch. An. 1577</title>
                 <author>Garnier, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 48, 4 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>
      <hi>¶ Iohn Brooke</hi> to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His litle Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> (gentle Reader) may seeme vnto thee a thing of small value and lesse importance, if thou make thy estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof by the small outwarde showe and feeling: But if in this litle and light worke to the eye, be enclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded great and waighty matter, if in this briefe and short Treatise be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and sufficiently set forth long and manifold causes, how much the more then is it to be imbraced and estemed. I promyse thee nothing, but for gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mrecye, offer thee my good wyll and trauaile, I red it in French, written by master Iohn Gardiner: and finding it pithy, profitable and necessary to bee red of all Christians, for thine onelye commodity and comfort I haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated him into thy mother tongue. If
<pb facs="12"/> in this translation thou finde any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, let my zeale &amp; good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towardes thee, counteruaile or rather preuaile to gaine thy friendly acceptaunce, and do not therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the thing or the Authour, who vndoubtedly needeth no supporter or defender, but bringeth with him mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and defence sufficient. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture (I say) the reading as I did at the firste, if thou finde him worthye, make it a Iewell vnto thee, beare him daily in thy hand, or button him nere thy hart in thy bosō, he is neither hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy nor cūbrous, nor wil be vnto thee very chargeable. Gods holy spirite be thy guide in reading and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, to the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>