<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Gilgate, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S92695_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07699</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11895.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S92695</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gilgate, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine reasons, proouing the separation, commonly called Brownists, to be schismatiques : By William Gilgate, Minister of the Word of God</title>
                 <author>Gilgate, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing some yeares since suffered shipwracke in the gulfe of Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by Gods gracious hand ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene lifted out, and saued from drowning in these waues, I thinke it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to discry to others the danger and escape of those passages to and from Amsterdam. I left these Arguments of mine with Master <hi>Henry Ainsworth,</hi> Preacher to the same English at Amsterdam, calling themselues the Separation, commonly called <hi>Brownists;</hi> that hee and his might see, how I not rashly, but for iust cause left them. Sithence that, I haue beene inwardly moued to publish them in print, that they also who still sticke in that pit, may at length perceiue on what a sandy foundation the Separation is built; and forsaking the same with mee and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, may labour to build themselues vpon the Rocke Christ, so as the gates of Hell may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile against them, to plucke them from the one
<pb facs="3"/> Body, whereof hee is the one onely Head. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they perswade themselues, that their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of separation is the same that the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe warrant, I haue set downe their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons grounded on two chiefe places of the same, very firmely, as they imagine: but I haue shewed that they wrest them, as many other alleaged to that end, for the proofe of that which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. My reasons shewing their Separation to be a Schisme, I haue set downe briefly. This I haue done, not of hatred to any of their persons, or any truth of Christ, which they hold with the true Churches of God; but of sincere loue toward them; that they might acknowledge and forsake this worke of the flesh, Schisme I meane, which among other excludeth men from the Kingdome of God; which I pray God to bestow vpon all his there and euery where. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>William Gilgate.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>