<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S92705_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00084</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11925.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S92705</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods acre of land : Manured dressed and maintained; by six devines Ch: G. Will: P. M. Ro Do: Play. A. Dene. M. D</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <distributor>Langley, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 112 pages, °</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Christian READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EE that doth publish a matter to the iudgement of many, the same requireth to bee done, not lightly, but deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; considering it is a subiect to sundry censures, and in reading and iudging all are not <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Lectores.</hi> In regard wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (good Christian Reader) I
<pb facs="8"/> haue published my paines to thy profit, and presented thy liking of it, to thy looking ouer, hauing (as nigh as I may) not onely cut off all such occasions, as might cause cavillation, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so ministred such matter as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes our consolation: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee not pollished pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely, for the expectation of the curious; yet it is finished plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the information of the simple. Now it may bee there be many that will vse obiectiōs against the Triple forme of this Treatise, because no art hath reduced althings (and rightly) to <hi>Dicotomies.</hi> True; but wisedome may contriue much
<pb facs="8"/> compendiously, and yet profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie: besides although I haue framed it as an easie entrance for the erudition of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, I haue not excluded what may further bee added by the consideration of the learned, &amp; abiect much more might bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted in many places for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie, yet much lesse I feare mee is obserued of the most part for their vtilitie. Some will require a more direct placing of thinges in their order; <hi>Certes</hi> that is well placed, that is well applied: And those that doe more respect the manner of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, then the matter it selfe, may bee noted in the number of
<pb facs="9"/> those, who would haue the Psalmes of <hi>DAVID</hi> to proceede, and not to follow the Booke of <hi>IOB;</hi> making a scripulous question without cause, when wee all know they are both included in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and containe comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter for our saluation. Some will not like so many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers sortes of sundry things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest together in one heape, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will require more prospy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitie, some one thing, some another: Insomuch that hee that expecteth to please the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of all people, must either refraine from open Publication of any thing, or referre himselfe
<pb facs="9"/> to their generall dispositions in iudgement: And this is the common successe of acceptance; many will commend it, most will mislike it, few will follow it. But as my meaning was to profit the simple, by the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of it; so I shall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the godly to a good liking of it: and as for the froward, I will not refell their foolish questions in disputation about it, knowing what the <hi>Apostle Paul</hi> saith, that foolish and vnlearned questions, ingender strife.</p>
   <p>So wishing all to measure by the meete they would receiue themselues, and so to report
<pb facs="10"/> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>pect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> pris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I both submit myselfe to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, so it be pertinent; and commit euery one to his owne liking, so it be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</p>
   <p>Vale.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>