<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ALARME To all Christian Princes and States of the Religion.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S92792_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07711</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12531.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S92792</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ALARME To all Christian Princes and States of the Religion.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An alarme to all Christian princes and states of the religion : Written immediately vpon the first newes of the death of the King of Sweden of famous memory, and euer will be to all posterity, and to eternity</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>AN ALARME To all Christian Princes and States of the Religion.</head>
   <head type="sub">WRITTEN Immediatly vpon the first newes of the death<note n="*" place="margin">1632.</note> of the King of Sweden of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and euer will be to all poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to eternity.</head>
   <p>Which I haue concealed till now, hauing a great reluctation within my self, and doubtfull whether to publish it at all or <hi>no.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.3 <hi>Amos.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.53.
<hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12</note>
      <hi>No</hi> answereth the echo, <hi>for this time is euill: It is an euill time</hi> answereth the Prophet. <hi>The very power of darkenes: this is your houre, &amp; the power of darkenes,</hi> answereth the Lord Iesus, <hi>for we wrestle not,</hi> our reluctation is not,
<hi>against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against powers &amp;c:</hi> answereth the Apostle. The whole legion of deuils, for they are many: <hi>We are many,</hi> answereth the deuill himself, with a hollow echo from hell. But too many for one poore worme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mark.</hi> 5.9</note> such a one as I am, <hi>a worme and no man,</hi> to wrestle withall: the Lord Iesus help me. Yet considering whom I serue, euen this Lord Iesus: and what an other Apostle answereth: <hi>He that knoweth to doe good and doth it not, to him it is sin.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17 <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.25</note> And conceiuing it a part of my <hi>talent</hi> committed to me of Gods grace,
<hi>not to be concealed, not to be hid,</hi> whereof one day I must giue account: and for no other reason: written I say immediatlie after the sorowfull <pb facs="2"/>
      <pb facs="2"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>newes came of the death of that renowmed King: and directed (and I hope in God it is also from him, and so will be taken, and not of any presumption at all from me) to all those Princes and States, now vpon so great consultations and treaties, wherevpon dependeth the whole State of Gods Church: all the reformed Churches of Christendome, now in quaestion vpon the death of that famous King whether to stand or fall, high time therefore for all <hi>either now to speake, or for euer hereafter to hold their peace.</hi> Wherein I make no doubt but <hi>Sathan</hi> will also act his part to the vtmost, (this his last part) by his Embassadors, and secret Agents from all parts,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.1.</note>
      <hi>and stand at the right hand of our high Priest Joshua to resist him:</hi> that he and his Kingdome may stand, and our high Priest
<hi>Ioshua</hi> (that is <hi>Jesus</hi>) &amp; his Kingdome fall: I haue therfore aduentured in the name of this <hi>Iesus: (Jesus, Jesus, Jesus:</hi> which were the last words that great King vttered immediatly before he gaue battell: <hi>help me to fight this day to the honour of thy name. If I die I die) Let vs goe and die with him.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Esthe.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.16.</note> Why liue we after him? who died not for himself but for vs, and for others, (as did
<hi>Iesus,</hi>) and for the name of the Lord <hi>Iesus.</hi> I say in the name of this <hi>Jesus,</hi> our <hi>Joshua,</hi> who died both for him, and for vs all, (all humane respects, either of feare or fauour, set apart) I haue adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to publish it. <hi>My name shrowded vnder his name Iesus: &amp; who dare speak against it this name Jesus?</hi> Hoping this <hi>Sathan</hi> who now <hi>thinketh he standeth,</hi> and presumteously taketh place <hi>at the right hand</hi> of our
<hi>Ioshua</hi> (this <hi>Jesus</hi>) shall fall shorthlie, and finally, <hi>the God of peace shall tread downe Sathan vnder your feet shortly,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Luk.</hi>
10.18</note> as in that his diuine vision: <hi>I saw Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than fall downe lyke lightening from heauen,</hi> Amen, Amen, and let the whole Church of Christ applaud herevnto, and say, Amen and Amen.</p>
   <div type="citations">
      <head>IHS, IHS, IHS.</head>
      <q>
         <p>
            <hi>Helpt me to fight this day to the honour of thy name,</hi> against this <hi>Sathan:</hi> this <hi>Legioen of Deuils:</hi> for we wrestle not against flesh and blood, but against principallities, against powers, &amp; against the worldly gouernours the Princes of the darknes of this world, against Spirituall wickednesses which are in the high places,</p>
         <bibl>Ephes. 6.12.</bibl>
      </q>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>