<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An explanation of certaine wordes being quareld withall, by some, for that in this translation they be otherwyse wrytten, then either the vnlettered people or some partes of the Country sound, or speake them.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S93923_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16435</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S93923</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An explanation of certaine wordes being quareld withall, by some, for that in this translation they be otherwyse wrytten, then either the vnlettered people or some partes of the Country sound, or speake them.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lliver gvveddi gyffredin a gwenidogaeth y Sacramentae, ac eraill gynneddfeu a' ceremoniae yn eccles loecr : viewed, perused and allowed by the bishops, accordyng to the act stablished for the translation of the Bibles and thys booke into the Brytyshe tonge</title>
                 <author>Church of England</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, cxliii, 1, lxxxiiii leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction_to_Welsh">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>An explanation of certaine wordes being quarel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d withall, by some, for that in this translation they be otherwyse wrytten, then either the vnlettered people or some partes of the Country sound, or speake them.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
      </hi> Signifieng if, or whether, for o.</p>
   <p>A being Matine, or a <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ice <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>pletiue not vsed to them of Southwales.</p>
   <p>Anival for enivel.</p>
   <p>Any for oni.</p>
   <p>Anid for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nid, or o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d.</p>
   <p>Ancompte for anhyinhic.</p>
   <list>
      <item>awd in the end of a word, for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d, odd, or oedd, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</item>
      <item>awdd in the end of a word, for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d, odd, or oedd, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</item>
      <item>awl in the end of a word, for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d, odd, or oedd, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</item>
   </list>
   <p>As for ays or vs.</p>
   <p>Bwystvil (which rather would be wryt<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> Bestvil) for the corruptlye pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ounced gwys<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>▪</p>
   <p>C for K (because the Printers haue not so many as the Welsh requireth) and in some wordes for g.</p>
   <p>Cent, in one place, for cant.</p>
   <p>Dew, for Duw in Northwales speach, and for Dyw, as they of Southwales speake it.</p>
   <p>Ef, for the Northern &amp; efo, or 'fo.</p>
   <p>F, sometime for ff.</p>
   <p>F, for v.</p>
   <p>Et, for i, or y, to them of Southwales.</p>
   <p>Eich, for ych.</p>
   <p>Gestwng, for gistwng, or gostwng.</p>
   <p>Hanwynt, hanynt, hanaddynt, for the corrupt honynt.</p>
   <p>Ioan for Ieuan, Iouan, Ievan, Ifan or Iwon: euen for that it is so diuersly soūded in diuers parts of the coūtry
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <note place="margin">Iardanis.</note>Iorddanen, for Irddonen.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Iudaeus</note>Iuddew, for Iddew.</p>
   <p>Megis, for the Southern meis.</p>
   <p>Monyth for mynydd: so they pronounce it at Sanct Dauids.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ego vnus▪ hoc est ego ipse. <hi>Aliquis quidam</hi>
      </note>Myvn for myhun or vyhun.</p>
   <p>Nebun, for neb, or ryw vn.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Proterea</note>O bleit, or o blait, for o blegit.</p>
   <p>P sometime remaining not turned into b, m, or ph.</p>
   <p>Pemp for pymp or pump.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Quomodo</note>P' odd vsed <hi>per syncopen</hi> in Southwales for pa vodd.</p>
   <p>Popul for pobyl, pobl, or the Southern pybyl or gwerin Pleit, for plait, or plaid.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Hoc est</note>'Sef per <hi>aphaeresin,</hi> for ysef, or sef.</p>
   <p>Tangneddyf for tangnevedd or heddwch.</p>
   <p>Tragyvyth for tragywydd, or tragowydd: to keepe his orthographie, for it is compounded of tra cy &amp; vyth: for hereby is it also more effectuall in signification.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Domus.</note>Tuy, for the Northern ty.</p>
   <p>V, for f.</p>
   <p>Vcain, for vgain, ygain or igen.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Amicus meus</note>Vy car for vyncar or vynghar: wherein n is receyued without good cause.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Deus meus</note>Vy Dew for vynuw, or vynyw, wherein D is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, euen for the more significatiue expressing of the grace of the woord.</p>
   <p>Vy popul for vymhobl, to saue the word theles maimed</p>
   <p>Vy-troct for vynrhoed that the signification maye be more apparent to the straunge Reader.</p>
   <p>Wy, or hwy, for wynt or hwynt: which be here also vsed when they come before a vowel.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Qui, quae quod. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>quis.</hi>
      </note>Y being relatiue, or a kinde of expletiue, for a, vnto the North Wales Readers.</p>
   <p>Yd for hyd.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>Yddy duy, for y ew, or y'w dy in Northwales.<note place="margin">To hys house. <hi>Illis.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>Yddwynt for yddynt, or vddunt.</p>
   <p>Yr ei for y rrei, or y rrai.</p>
   <p>Ysy, or 'sy <hi>per synaloepham</hi> for ysy or sy:<note place="margin">Est.</note> and comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a vowel beginning an other woord <hi>propter euphonian</hi> ys ydd, for y sydd.</p>
   <p>Ys ef, or 'sef.<note place="margin">Hoc est.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Ys, is verye often vsed in the translation to expresse the emphatical energie or notable vehemence, where the Latine hath <hi>&amp;</hi> or <hi>etiam,</hi> and the English yea, or euen.</p>
   <p>And besyde these there is very little alteration either of the commun writing, or of straungenes of woordes, which be not opened by referryng to the lyke marke in the margent, as the word is marked in the text: as thus Dew <note n="*" place="margin">y gyd a chwi</note> cenych <note n="‡" place="margin">bawp</note> oll. And as for some of the faults that es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped in printing, the meanely learned Reader may espie them and correct: as where three odd or three ill come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or else when a letter is mys set, or one letter for another, or a syllable doth want, or is superfluous: euen as the Northern orthographie is to the Southern tong: which onely in pronounciation would be reformed. The rest of the faultes may the welwilling learned easily find out him selfe and helpe to correct as occasion serueth.</p>
   <p>But let euery such one as shal reade the Seruice to the people, marke well the three pointes or stayes in reading,<note place="margin">NOTA</note> being these,:. Wherat namely in reading the Psalmes, except he stay and rest accordingly, he shall wonderfullye confound the matter, and astonish the hearers. And for an example hereof, the sixt verse of the .xxx. Psalme may serue full well. The verse that I meane is this.</p>
   <p>Can na phery [anyd] enhyd bach yn ei lit: ac yn ei ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennydd y mae bywyt: wylofain [a all] aros echwydd, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyd [e ddaw] gorvoledd y borae.</p>
   <p>Which verse being distinctly read, is very comfortable to the hearers soule: otherwyse it is a verye <hi>Chaos,</hi> or as it were, a commixtion of heauen and hell together.</p>
   <p>As for these two halfe circles () who is it but know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth that they betokē a <hi>Parenthesin,</hi> or a clause inserted, which
<pb facs="7"/>
might be left out, and the sentence perfect, yea and for the most part more plaine and sensible to vnderstand.</p>
   <div type="section">
      <head>❧<hi>To vnderstand these other new markes not vsed in</hi> thys tongue before thys tyme, whyche are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed thus' - [ ] and for the most part thus [ ].</head>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Of this marke</note>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His kynde of marke' ouer the top of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters signifieth a vowel or a consonant cut of euen vnder the place where it is: as thus, v'enait, for vy enait: Herod a' Philatus, for Herod ac Pilatus.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnion</note>This marke - is borowed of the Hebrues, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of them <hi>Makkaph,</hi> which signifieth an vnion properly with them, or knitting of two wordes vnder one accent, and with vs, as thus, y-my, y-ty, ydd-aw. But here it is also vsed sometime (for learuing sake) to vnite or knit, as were in one, two or three or moe wordes together, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the signification of one Hebrue or Greeke woorde. And some other time to separate a compound woord for the more euident or effectuall vnderstanding thereof.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">Of</note>This marke [comming onely at the beginning of a word, signifieth that the first peece thereof is added for the playner vnderstanding of the text, and the same not had inche Hebrue.<note place="margin">Of</note> The lyke is ment when] onelye is ioyned to the latter end of any word.<note place="margin">Of</note> But if both these [ ] do inclose any word or woordes, they signifie that all the words therin inclosed be not had in the Hebrue or Greke, letter, but of very necessitie (as if ye marke, ye may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) to make the sence perfect, so inserted. And therfore thus marked, that Gods own word may remayn sincere and vnviolate from generation to generation.</p>
      <p>And this much for the better expedition of the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom Gods holy sprite perfectly prosper. Amen.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>