<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS KIND, AND TRVE FRIEND: EDWARD BLVNT.</title>
           <author>Thorpe, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94045_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00389</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16883.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94045</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS KIND, AND TRVE FRIEND: EDWARD BLVNT.</title>
                 <author>Thorpe, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lvcans first booke : translated line for line, by Chr. Marlovv</title>
                 <author>Lucan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flasket, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Linley, Paul.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS KIND, AND TRVE FRIEND: EDWARD BLVNT.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Lount:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I purpose to be blūt with you, &amp; out of my dulnesse to encounter you with a <hi>Dedication</hi> in the memory of that pure Elementall wit <hi>Chr. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low;</hi> whose ghoast or <hi>Genius</hi> is to be seene walke the <hi>Churchyard</hi> in (at the least) three or foure sheets. Me thinks you should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently looke wilde now, and growe humorously frantique vpon the tast of it. Well, least you should, let mee tell you. This spirit was sometime a familiar of your own, <hi>Lucans first booke translated;</hi> which (in regard of your old right in it) J haue rais'd in the circle of your Patronage. But stay now <hi>Edward</hi> (if J mistake not) you are to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date your selfe with some fewe instructions, touching the property of a Patron, that you are not yet possest of; and to study them for your better grace as our Gallants do fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shions. First you must be proud and thinke you haue merit inough in you, though you are ne're so emptie; then when I bring you the booke take physicke, and keepe state, assigne me a time by your man to come againe, and afore the day be sure to haue chang'd your lodging; in the meane time sleepe little, and sweat with the inuention of some pittiful dry iest or two which you may happen to vtter, with some litle (or not at al) marking of your friends when you haue found a place for them to come in at: or if by chance some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing has dropt from you worth the taking vp weary all
<pb facs="3"/>that come to you with the often repetition of it; Censure scornefully inough, and somewhat like a trauailer; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend nothing least you discredit your (that which you would seeme to haue) iudgement. These things if you can mould your selfe to them <hi>Ned</hi> I make no question but they will not become you. One speciall vertue in our Patrons of these daies J haue promist my selfe you shall fit excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, which is to giue nothing; Yes, thy loue J will chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge as my peculiar Obiect both in this, and (J hope) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie more succeeding offices: Farewell, J affect not the world should measure my thoughts to thee by a scale of this Nature: Leaue to thinke good of me when J fall from thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all rites of perfect friendship, THOM. THORPE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>