<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR his Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94173_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00431</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17845</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94173</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR his Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The divine pourtrait. Or, a true and liuely representation of the blessed sacrament of the Lords Supper : with our due preparation how to receiue the same worthily. Delivered in a sermon, at the reformed church of Paris (on Easter day last:) by Monsieur Iohn Mestrezat, minister of the Word of God there: vpon these words of our Savious, This is my Body. Englished by John Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Mestrezat, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Baker, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>66, 6, 5-147, that is 172 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR his Preface to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was with a holy admiration, and a religious and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified zeale, that the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Prophet King <hi>David</hi> (contemplating on the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Gods creatures, and meditating on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence and dignitie which hee gaue man over them) Cryed out,
<note place="margin">Psal. 8.4.</note>
      <hi>O Lord, our God, how excellent is thy <pb facs="13"/>name in all the world, And what is man, that thou art so mindefull of him, and the Sonne of man that thou vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitest him.</hi> If <hi>David</hi> (who was a liuely <hi>Type</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>) were rapt into this spirituall extasie of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and ioy, when he considered of Gods power and providence, in the workes of his creation; How much more infinitly and thankfully should wee poore miserable sinners, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with true admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and admire with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ioy, at the vnspeakable and incomprehensible love of God towards mankinde;
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.8. Col. 1.14.</note> In giving vp his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> to death; yea, to the shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <pb facs="13"/>death of the <hi>Crosse</hi> for our redemption, and that he was so gracious a God, and so mercifull and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent a Father to vs, that he suffered his blessed <hi>Sonne</hi> to dye for vs,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note>
      <hi>That hee might redeeme vs from all iniquitie, and purge vs, to be a peculiar people to himselfe.</hi> For, wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched sinners that we are; In <hi>Paradise,</hi> where our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gained their life, there (by their wilfull disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and transgression) they lost their righteousnes and we in them; because the foule staine and Leprosie of that their originall sin, hath successively and actually, made vs, their vnfortunate seede and posteritie, guilty both of Death and Hell; and <pb facs="14"/>there iustly adiudged <hi>to haue our Portions with the Devill and his Angels.</hi> But notwithstanding all this; God (yet) hath beene as mercifull to vs, as we have bene sinnefull to him; for although wee were lost in <hi>Adam,</hi> by
<hi>Nature,</hi> yet we are againe, both found and saved in <hi>Iesus Christ by grace;</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.6.</note>
      <hi>Who hath given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a ransome for all men;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai 53.4,5</note>
      <hi>Hath borne our infirmities, and carried away our sinnes and sorrows, by suffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to bee wounded for our transgressions, and broken for our iniquities.</hi> So that it is the present ioy of our hearts, and the future happinesse of our soules,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.4,5.</note>
      <hi>That God, who is rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <note place="margin">Eph 2.4,5</note>
      <hi>(through the great loue wherewith he loved vs) when we were dead by our sins, hath quickned vs together in Iesus Christ, by whose grace we are saved.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And to the ende that all true <hi>Christians</hi> should not despaire of <hi>Christs</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses vnto them nor so much give themselues over, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the reprobate sense and pleasures of sinne, or to the sugred insinuations and trecherous temptations of Satan, as any way to doubt of their salvation in the <hi>Lord:</hi> Why, this our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Lord &amp; Master, <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> (the great Shepheard of his Flocke, and <hi>Saviour</hi> of his people) who by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporating his Divinitie <pb facs="15"/>with his humanitie) was wholly composed of loue &amp; mercy toward them. Hee, I say, a litle before his bloody, yet blessed death and passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Crosse) was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously pleased, to honour and sanctifie his Apostles, and, in them vs, who are of the true seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> with the holy Sacrament of his most blessed Supper, as a diuine pledge, and a firme &amp; authenticall confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his inestimable loue towards vs, and of his watchful care and vigilancy for our saluation; I meane for the full perfecting and accomplishing of our glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in Heaven with God his father:
<note place="margin">Rom 6.4.</note>
      <hi>That sin might haue no more domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <pb facs="15"/>over ver vs; because we are now no longer vnder the Law, but vnder Grace;</hi> but that by the worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and holy partaking thereof <hi>(In the imitation of Christ and his blessed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles)</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. 2.6.</note>
      <hi>wee might be raysed vp together with him in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is therefore not our owne merits, but onely Gods mercies, not our own workes which are sinfull, but onely the blessed death and passion of Christ Iesus which is sacred, that must be, both the triumph, and glory of a Christian: And I confesse with ioy, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Consolation, that this holy Sacrament of his <pb facs="16"/>most blessed Supper (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bread of his body was broken, and the wine of his blood powred out and shed, for the sinnes of all mankind) is the perfect pledge, the sacred seale, the full ransome, and the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest mysterie of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in Iesus Christ: And that as wee are abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely cleansed and washed from our originall sinne, by the water of Baptisme, when wee enter into the State of Grace, in the Church militant heere on earth; That so by the blood of this Paschall Lambe, Christ Iesus (in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his blessed Supper) our sinnes are wholly defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and washed away and <pb facs="16"/>consequently, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee shall enter into the state of glory, in the Church triumphant in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; So that fighting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the banner of Christ his Crosse, and being spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually armed with these two sacred Sacraments, we may boldly beleeue, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently assure our selues, that neither Sathan, nor hell shall have power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile against vs.</p>
   <p>And here (Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) before I proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this my Preface to thee; I give thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, That I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, with what a great world of different opinions and controversies this our little world of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <pb facs="17"/>is perplexed and troubled with, about this blessed Sacrament of the Lords Supper, betwixt the Protestant, and the Papist, &amp; especially about Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation, the Reall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and communicating in one kind: In so much that an infinite number (yea too great a number) of pens, pulpits, and presses, are pittifully (because vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably) oppressed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: and that Christs blessed body in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (without pietie, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or charity) is daily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacerated and torne in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with these contentions, whereas his owne Coate, (or vesture) was without peece or seame; So that our <pb facs="17"/>silly soules may well feare drowning, when the barke of our weake faith (masted and rigged with curiositie) sayleth in so dangerous and turbulent an Ocean, that hath neither bottome nor shoare; and which is daily and hourly tossed, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be split, and dashed in peeces, either with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering waves of levity and inconstancy, or with the boysterous winds of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensd malice, or scandalous and erronious virulency: without looking vp to the true day-Starre of their hope, Iesus Christ; or to the Sunne of their saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God; or without ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring or thinking, safely to arrive, and cast anchor <pb facs="18"/>in the Cape of good hope; Heaven. O that the spirit of Pietie, should (without piety) thus bee conuerted, and transformed into the spirit of Contention. And as for mee (who am the meanest, and most vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of all Gods Seruants and Children) bingeniously confesse and acknowledge; that in some few languages I have read so many of these intemperate Contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies, and vntimely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, that I am wearie of reading them; And yet so, That I rather pitie, then maligne, first their Authors for their sakes, and then them for their Authors sakes; and my witnesse is in heaven &amp; in mine own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, <pb facs="18"/>that with my heart &amp; soule I wish, that all these vnspirituall quarells might be composed in peace and amitie, and that these vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate disputes and lynes might terminate in one, and the same Centre, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and that their learned Authors, (having their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity vanquished with the honour and glory of God) as Christian mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, might bee insepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fast knit and vnited to their Head, and grand Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Iesus Christ: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause contention is not the way to heaven, and that God was found in the still and quiet, and not in the whirle and tempestuous winds; As also that where <pb facs="19"/>the great Lamps of learning and lights of the Church, contend &amp; fight about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, that there assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly the weake ones, and the more illiterat Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doe infinitly suffer in this quarell: That therefore (in the name and feare of God) they would please to take vp, and embrace this saying of the blessed Apostle
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note>
      <hi>Follow peace with all men, and also holynesse, without which no man shall see God:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the same purpose,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.15</note>
      <hi>Let vs fellow the truth in loue, and in all things grow vp in him, who is the Head, (to wit) Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To call our religion in questiō, is to doubt therof, and to halt betweene two <pb facs="19"/>opinions in matters of saith is <hi>(with the Luke-warme La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicean)</hi> to be of neither: I know wee are commanded by the Apostle, <hi>To make our election sure, and taught by the Prophet,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hosh. 4.14.</note>
      <hi>That the people who doe not vnderstand shall fall.</hi> I likewise know, that curiositie in matters of Faith and Religion is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and that for being too curious in prying into the sacred secrets of God, it is a fatall Rocke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on some excellent iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have suffered Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke wilfully, and a world of weake wits igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly. That Gods vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed mysteries and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses are as secret, as sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and as occult, and <pb facs="20"/>abstruse, as they are divine, and that wee are positively told, and taught by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<note place="margin">Isa. 40.28.</note>
      <hi>That there is no searching out of Gods vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing;</hi> VVherefore as I envy no man for his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; so (I prayse and blesse my Redeemer) I am not so wretchedly instructed in piety, as to deny mine to the world: much lesse to dare to desemble it to God: It shall suffice mee; that I had rather beleeue the truth, then quarell with it, and farre sooner (and with more alacritie and promptitude) to embrace and follow it, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or contest against it.</p>
   <p>As therefore wee cannot beleeue in God, before wee <pb facs="20"/>first know him; So wee cannot perfectly know this Sacrament of his blessed Supper, except we first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in it, and in the pure truth, and naked vertue and integritie thereof. I am not therefore of the vnion or communion of those vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catholique Romanists, who are carnall, and not spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eaters of this blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and who tye their implicite faith onely to the bare letter, not to the true sense, and to the sight, not to the figure or commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which this heavenly mysterie infoldeth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; VVho can dispense with their consciences (yea with their soules) rather to eat their God, then to obey <pb facs="21"/>him; and daily to teare his blessed body in peeces with them teach, as they doe hourly with their sinnes; and who rely on their own poore &amp; wretched merits, rather then on Christs rich promises, or on the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable treasor of his blessed death and passion, premised and prefigured vnto vs, in the bread and wine of his sacred Supper: But for my part; I really and confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue, that Christs owne words, <hi>Take, eat, and drinke this in remembrance of me;</hi> doth make this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to bee a mysticall, not a corporall, a spirituall, and not a carnall sacrifice.</p>
   <p>But to leave Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie <pb facs="21"/>and contention, to those who love them, (in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this divine doctrine of this Sacrament of the Lords Supper) and to come to that which more neerly and narrowly concearnes our edification to Christ, and sanctification by Christ; I ioyfully affirme, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verre, That it hath bene a great part and degree of my earthly selicity, to have heard many excellent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and seene, and read many comfortable Tracts vpon this sacred Supper of the Lord, aswell on this side, as beyond the seas; and preached and written, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well by the Samts of God abroad, as by our owne English Saints and Seruants <pb facs="22"/>of the Lord here at hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> who have most painful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and industriously travell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> heerein, with much tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> glory to God, with infini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> prayse and honour to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> selues; and with a world o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> consolation and happines<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> to their Christian Auditor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and Readers; have piously chalked them out the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and safe way to Heaven, and most divinely pointed and shewed them the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous path-way, and glorious narrow way to God.</p>
   <p>And now (by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and mercy) mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting very lately with a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of that heavenly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, preached (on Easter day last) to the famous and flourishing assembly of the <pb facs="22"/>Protestants in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mned Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> (at <hi>Charenton</hi>) vpon these words of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (in the blessed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his last Supper)
<hi>This is my body:</hi> By the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reverend Seruant of the Lord,
<hi>Monsieur Iohn Mestrezat,</hi> the first Pastor and minister of that great, and godly congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the worthy Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor of that famous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, <hi>Monsr. P. Du. Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,</hi> the great light of his time, and Ornament of his Church. I say, I no sooner seriously perused and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously considered it; but finding it to bee pend in an elegant &amp; excellent phrase, and digested and cast into <pb facs="23"/>a most spirituall order a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> method; at last (after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> short parlie with my soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and a little reluctation wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> my resolutions) God n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> only suggested, but cōma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded me to teach it to spea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> English, and especially fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> these two reasons, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>siderations.</p>
   <p n="1">I. That the translatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thereof, infinitly tended t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Gods honour and glory, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> being a perfect and a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mising way to draw many soules to God, aswell by their seeing and knowing of it, as by practising and putting into execution, that sacred discipline, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which it containes.</p>
   <p n="2">II For that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Preacher of it, is <pb facs="23"/>so worthy a Minister of Gods word, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wished and counselled his beloved <hi>titus</hi> to bee, (to wit)
<note place="margin">Titus. 2.7.</note>
      <hi>That his life is a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and example of good workes, and of vncorrupt doctrine, gravitie, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie;</hi> for to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (as also to all others, who know him, or his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and abilities) he is so learned, and of so meeke, and Saint-like a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation, that it is a dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table question, whether his doctrine doe more crowne, and grace his life, or his life his doctrine: And that thorefore it might well stand with Gods pleasure (as it doth referre, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to his honour) that <pb facs="24"/>the reading heereof might refresh, and profit some Christians heere in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as well as the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof hath done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in <hi>France.</hi> As also, that as (at my residence in <hi>Paris</hi>) I have taken singular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and comfort to have often heard him preach, so consequently that others might doe the like here, by visibly reading, or tacitly seeing, and hearing him preach in this his Sermon, <hi>(or Divine Pourtrait)</hi> which so lively (yea so tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at life) representeth the Sacrament of the Lords blessed Supper vnto vs, I being as confident of this truth, as of this presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That as in most of <pb facs="24"/>his Sermons hee excelleth and surpasseth others, so in this; that hee hath infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly both surpassed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celd himselfe.</p>
   <p>And although <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> I have formerly in this my Preface, expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and signified to thee, that this little, (yet most excellent) Sermon of his doth most sweetly shew thee, the sure, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way to heaven and to God, and with a happines (peraduenture) beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, hath most fully performed, and most diuine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acted thee that part, (whereunto I will referre and commend thee in the Lord) Yet because I am an humble Seruant to Christ <pb facs="25"/>(both in my desires and affections) aswell as I am the shaddow, and Echo of my Author in this my translation: Therefore I trust in the goodnesse of God, and hope in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of mine owne heart, that I shall rather right thee, then any way wrong him, in presuming poorly to gleane after his rich har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest, by aduenturing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and give thee a word or two of spirituall aduice and directions of mine owne, vpon the receiuing of this blessed Sacrament of the Lords Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I commend this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Pourtrait</hi> thereof to thee, thee to it, and you both vnto God.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="25"/>When therefore thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soluest
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.8.</note>
      <hi>to draw neere vnto God, that God may draw neer vnto thee,</hi> by receiving and partaking of this his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sacrament, Thou must (in the innocency of thy heart, and the purity of thy soule)
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note>
      <hi>first humble thy selfe vnder the mighty hand of God, that hee may exalt thee.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iam. 4.10.</note>
      <hi>And cast thy selfe downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, that hee may lift thee vp.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.34.</note>
      <hi>Thou must awake to live righteously, and resolue to sinne no more;</hi> but hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to become a new man, and a new Christian:
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.24.</note>
      <hi>for they that are Christs, have crucified the flesh with the lusts thereof. Thou must set thy affections on things which are above, and not on things <pb facs="26"/>which are on the Earth.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note>
      <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> thy conuersation must bee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> heaven, from whence tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> must expect thy Sauiour, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the Lord Iesus Christ;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. 5.25,</note>
      <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> if thou live in the spirit, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> must also walke in the spirit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 4.4,</note>
      <hi>Thou must tremble, but n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> sinne, and thou must examin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> thy selfe vpon thy bed:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 68.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> God will try thee, as siluer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> tryed:</hi> Thou must not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceive thy selfe,
<note place="margin">Galat. 6.7.</note>
      <hi>for God wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> not bee mocked.</hi> Thou mus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> not be hot in thy sinnes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> cold and frozen in thy de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>votion and piety toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> God, neither must thou seeme now to bee that in thy humility and zeale, which thou art not: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Hypocrisie towards God, proves treacherie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <pb facs="26"/>our owne soules: But runne thou a Contrary Course with thy heart and soule, at thy receiving of this great act of thy Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this blessed Sacrament; for bee thou the death of thy sinnes, and then God will assuredly be the life of thy Soule.</p>
   <p>As for those who either vnworthily receiue, or carelesly deferre, or wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemne the receiving of this blessed Sacrament, they doe assuredly spin out the webbe of their owne damnation, and so being dead in the Lethargie of their owne securitie and prophanesse, they hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wincked ride post to Hell: Consider and remember <pb facs="27"/>with thy selfe,
<note place="margin">Ioel. 1.15.</note>
      <hi>That the day of the Lord is at hand.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10</note>
      <hi>And that death and destruction comes from the Lord, as a Thiefe in the night:</hi> That death (the grimme Pursi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and Sergeant of the Lord) d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th neither spare nor pardon any sexe or age, but with his fatall Dart, and Mace (without respect or difference) aresteth as well the King as the begger, the Priest as the people, and the young as the old.</p>
   <p>Wee must not therefore put farre from vs the evill day,
<note place="margin">Amos. 6.3,4,5.</note>
      <hi>nor stretch our selues on our beds of Ivorie, nor sing to the sound of the Violl,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Prophet meanes all excesse of riot, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth all degree of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scene <pb facs="27"/>pleasures, and beastly voluptuousnesse: For if we love God, we must honour him, and if we will honour him, wee must loue him,
<note place="margin">Amos 6.3,4,5.</note>
      <hi>And not wearie him with our sinnes, nor presse him downe with their burthen, as a Cart is with Sheafes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Consider wee againe, That as there is but one way forvs to come into the world, so that there are a thousand waies to go out of it. That we are subiect to as many diseases as sinnes; yea, and that diseases doe as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and as insensibly steale into our bodyes, as sinnes doe into our soules; That wee are never neerer death, then when we think our selues farthest from it, <pb facs="28"/>and that when we suppose our selues to be strongest in <hi>Nature,</hi> wee commonly are then weakest in <hi>Grace:</hi> As also, that a theeuish
<hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postume,</hi> a poore <hi>Apoplexie,</hi> a Cut-throat Squinancy, or a fierce and furious visitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Pestilence,</hi> doth many times (in a moment of time) violently snatch vs away from the world, and the world from vs, yea, and which is more to be admired, though no lesse to bee pittied, That some times, in the very twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an Eye, we are choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a Fly, a Kernell of an apple, a crumm of bread, or a small Fish bone; Or else have our braynes dashd out with a fall, either from <pb facs="28"/>a Horse, or a staire. O (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) how seriously ought we to ponder in our hearts, and how maturely and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously to consider in our soules, how extreame dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is for vs, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crastinate, and deferre: and (consequently) how infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely necessary, &amp; expediēt it is for vs frequently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this blessed Sacramēt of the Lords Supper.</p>
   <p>Consider wee further,
<note place="margin">Iam 4.14.</note>
      <hi>That wee cannot tell what shall betyde vs to morrow, for that our life is but a Ʋapour, that appeareth for a smal time, and then vanisheth away.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.24</note>
      <hi>That all flesh is grasse, and all the glory of man, is as the flower of grasse, and that the grasse withereth, &amp; the flower <pb facs="29"/>thereof falleth away,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note>
      <hi>That we haue no abiding Citie heere, but must therefore seeke one to come, which is aboue: That as the tree falleth it lyes.</hi> That there is no sorrowing for our sins in the grave, and that after our death, there is no place nor hope left vs for a second repentance:
<note place="margin">Heb. 10 31</note>
      <hi>And that it is a feare full thing to fall into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Armed in this manner with a lively faith towards God, and with periect love and Charity towards our neighbour, and having freed and cleared those sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full spots of our hearts, and reformed and cleansed those foule affections and imperfections of our soules <pb facs="29"/>by our (vnfeigned) godly repentance and sorow; And having now assumed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp a firme resolution, <hi>ever hereafter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph. 5.10.</note>
      <hi>to approve and doe that which is pleasing to the Lord;</hi> And contracted a solemne Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and our souls,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.11.</note>
      <hi>never any more to have any fellowship with the workes of darkenesse, but reprove them,</hi> and not henceforth to dare to looke back (with affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) on our forepast, deerest and darling sinnes, but with infinite hatred &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of them. Then, I say, let vs follow the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Apostle.
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note>
      <hi>Let vs goe vp boldly to the Throne of Grace, that wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive mercy.</hi> Let vs goe <pb facs="30"/>boldly to this table; to this pretious banket of the Lords blessed Supper, and eat that sacred bread of his body, and drinke that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wine of his blood, in a strong Confidence and Cōmemoration, <hi>That Christ dyed for vs on the Altar of the Crosse,</hi> and for the free reconciliation, and full satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and redemption of our sinnes.</p>
   <p>And having thus filled our hearts with sacred Ioy, and replenished our soules with spirituall and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gladnesse, by receining of this most blessed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we must then have an infinite watchfull eye over our hearts, and place a most strong and religious guard <pb facs="30"/>over our soules, that wee doe not hencefoorth once presume to hearken to sin, or so much as give way, or dare to consent to looke, or listen after the treacherous lures and temptations of the world, the flesh or the devill; and so to fall backe into a spirituall relapse of sinne, which is ten thousand times worse, and infinitly more dangerous and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then that of any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall disease whatsoever, For it is a wofull, yea a wretched misery, which leaues vs no hope of better fortunes, nor place for worse,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22</note>
      <hi>If with the Dogge wee returne to our owne vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and with the Sow, that wee againe wallow in the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <pb facs="31"/>mire of our former beast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sinnes and transgressions,</hi> For then our end will bee farre worse then our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
<note place="margin">Hos 4.7.</note>
      <hi>Then God will change our glory into shame, And then wee shall make our selues guilty of the body and blood of Christ,</hi> (which without his all saving grace and mercy) is the high way to endlesse perdition, and the true way to eternall damnation. No, No, farre be such vngodly and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious thoughts from our hearts, and such vnspiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all treason against God from our soules; And let vs (who are the seed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham</hi> by nature, and the Sonnes of God by Grace)
<note place="margin">Hos. 10.12</note>
      <hi>still breake vp the fallow <pb facs="31"/>ground of our hearts with a holy repentance and sorrow for our sinnes,</hi> and with a constant and inuiolable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution never to sinne more; and as (therefore) we have received Christ Jesus by faith,

<note place="margin">Collos. 2.6.</note>
      <hi>So let vs walke in him,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Thes. 1.11,</note>
      <hi>and walke worthy of him, who now calles vs to his Kingdome of glory,</hi> and, which is more, who in a spirituall Contract,
<note place="margin">Hos. 2.19.</note>
      <hi>hath vnited and maried vs to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in righteousnesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In which regard and consideration, because wee are so highly beloued of God, and so infinitly hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the name of Christians (wherein wee ought more to insult, and triumph, then in all things
<pb facs="32"/>else which are vnder Christ) Let vs, I say, forsake the stincking garlicke and vnions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> (I meane our old beastly sinnes and transgressions) and for ever hencefoorth smell to the sweet Roses and Lilies of Heaven, (the delectable love, and promises of our Saviour Christ Iesus vnto vs) which are so sweetly watred with his pretious blood, and so odoriferously perfumed, not with fraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant odors, or costly spices of <hi>Arabia,</hi> but with the rich myrrh of Gods sacred mercy, and with the sweet and pretious frankincense of his divine fauour and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving countenande towards vs.
<note place="margin">Psal. 134.2</note>
      <hi>Let vs (I say) lift vp our <pb facs="32"/>hands to his holy Sanctuary, &amp; prayse the Lord,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ier. 31.3.</note>
      <hi>for that he loves vs with an everlasting love,</hi> and that (by the blessed death and passion of his Sonne Christ)
<note place="margin">Psal. 68.20</note>
      <hi>hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our God, and the God that saveth vs,</hi> The which, If we religiously &amp; constantly performe;
<note place="margin">Ier. 31.12.</note>
      <hi>Then our soules shall bee as a watred Garden, and wee shall know no more sorrow:</hi> Then wee shall be as the
<note place="margin">Hos. 14.6.</note>
      <hi>Dew vnto Israel, and God will make vs grow as Lilies, &amp; will fasten our roots as the trees of Lebanon;</hi> Then
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18</note>
      <hi>wee shall see God face to face in his Kingdome of glory,</hi> and there (both) live and raigne with him eternally,
<note place="margin">1 Tim 4.8.</note>
      <hi>And then hee will crowne vs with a Crowne of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <pb facs="33"/>which hee hath reserued and layd vp for his elect, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Seruants.</hi> Of which blessed number, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, O God, who art our Creator and Reedee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, (for thy promise sake, for thy <hi>Sions</hi> sake, and for thy <hi>Sonne, Christ Iesus</hi> his sake) to make vs: <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy Christian Friend, IOHN REYNOLDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>