<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Prologue of the Auctour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94248_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00452</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18225.6</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94248</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Prologue of the Auctour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>This is the glasse of helth : A great treasure for pore men, necessary and nedefull for euery person to loke in, yt wyll kepe theyr body from syckenesses, and dyseases: and it sheweth how the planettes reygne euery houre of the daye [and] the nyght, with the natures [and] exposicions of the. xii. sygnes deuyded by the. xii. monethes of the yere. And after foloweth of all the euyll and daungerous dayes of the yere. And sheweth the remedyes for dyuers infyrmyties and dyseases, that hurteth the body of man</title>
                 <author>Moulton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The Prologue of the Auctour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do you well to wytte, that this Boke profyteth greatly to euery Surgyon, for to knowe in what sygne, or what degree of the syg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the sonne and the Moone syt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth euerye daye / In any of the .xii. sygnes / And not onely it is profytable to Surgyons, but also to Phesycyons, and Barboures, and to all that vse to gyue medycynes, or Laxaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, or to vse any Passyons, or cuttynge, or Lettynge of Blode / For as the sonne passeth thoroughe all the .xii. sygnes, by the space of a yere, abydynge in a sygne .xxx. dayes / ryghte so doth the Moone passe thoroughe all the .xii sygnes, that in .xxx. dayes abydynge in a syg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne .lx. houres, and as the Moone amonge all planettes is nexte the Earth in course. So he hath most effecte of workynge, in these earthly thynges, after the dysposycion of the Nature of the sygnes that he hath his course in? And therfore it is full good and necessary truely to knowe the state, the course, &amp; the nature of the Moone. For therby a man may knowe, whan it is good to begyn many dyuers thynges, &amp; whan it is not good / And also what wether moste lykely is to falle, after the nature of the sygnes, whether drye, or moyste, hote, or colde
<pb facs="2"/> there shall folowe after the Nature of the syg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne that he is in / In dyuers coniunctions of Planettes, that is ioyned therwith / And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore naturally in order, I purpose me to decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, shortly in the thyrde Chapiter, the nature &amp; the state of euery sygne that he passeth by.</p>
   <p>Thus endeth the Porlogue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>