<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The French Au∣thors Aduertise∣ment to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94239_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14844</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18155</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94239</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The French Au∣thors Aduertise∣ment to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Six excellent treatises of life and death, collected (and published in French) by Philip Mornay, Sieur du Plessis: and now (first) translated into English</title>
                 <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>540 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The French Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the Argument of this discourse, it tēdeth principally to the abating of that hope, and presumption, which wee vsually haue, to obtain, in this life, that which neuer was enioyed here since the transgression of our first Parēts, nor neuer shall be; as it is very well inferred, especially in the first Discourse, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription
<pb facs="4"/>of man, frō his beginning, while he leaues this world. As for this word Fortune, the which ye shal here meet withall, in diuers passages, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, out of the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Custome and Vse, or rather, indeed, out of the necessity of our tōgue; the which, in stead of quite abolishing, doth too stiffely retaine the vse hereof: because those things which commonly happen, without it being known why, or wherfore, vnto men; they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by our Ancestors,
<pb facs="4"/>according to the heathen phrase, to Fortune. And, to conclude: wheras <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> who were called Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, are brought in, speaking by way of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, after the first Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, let not this be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, of any want we had of more Authentike Authors, that is to say, amōgst the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, vpon this argumēt (seeing we haue in like maner produced two in this second edition, which are Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and S. <hi>Ambrose):</hi> but this was
<pb facs="5"/>onely thought a better meanes to awake vs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, by the crie of these strāge witnesses, who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting only, but out of their naturall iudgement, and some knowledge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience which they had of the vanities of man; it seems, they would fain hail vs along to some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Port, and Retrait, than themselues haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for them, or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed vnto others by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>