<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94464_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07965</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18507.51A</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94464</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A continuation of more nevves from the Palatinate, the 13. of Iune 1622 : Relating the surprising of the Landtgrave of Ermstadt, with the skirmish betweene count Mansfield and Mounsieur Tillye in the returne. Together with the expedition of the Duke of Brunswick: and the reason of the preparations of Bethlem Gabor against the Emperour. In the end is added a comparison of two souldiers letters concerning former occurrences; and some newes from other places</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 22, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E had rather a great deale (gentle reader) present you with the happy newes of the Articles of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene Christian Princes, and that they would once listen to the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent aduice of our <hi>English Salomon</hi> who labours to make all Countreys happy like his owne, that in his dayes there might bee abundance of peace. But since God is yet pleased for the
<pb facs="4"/> sinnes of Christendome to set euerie mans Sword against his Brother; Wee therefore knowing all men desirous of newes, be it either good or bad, haue purposed (so farre as the power of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie shall licence vs) to publish the weekely occurrences which come to our hands: Our chiefe intention being to stay the vncertaine reports of partiall newes-mongers, who tell euery thing as themselues would haue it; And in this Continuation, though wee cannot hope to make euery reader beleeue what we write, yet neuerthelesse we will not publish any thing, but either from a sure hand, or some relation, seconded and confirmed by others: What we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in doubtfull termes, wee will not report peremptorily, but you shall haue it as we receiue it, neither will we print
<pb facs="4"/> euery report. And although to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse truth, we wish well, yet that we are not partiall, you may perceiue by our relating this skirmish betweene Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>Tilly.</hi> Wee write a continuation, that you may see by the proceedings, that there is good dependancy betweene the relations, wherein we purpose to keepe nere to the Lawes of Historie, to guesse at the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the actions by the most apparant presumptions, and to set downe the true names and distances of places, and times, that you may perceiue, there is probability in the seuerall Atchieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And thus much we care not to divulge, for wee feare not that any pamphletter of newes, wil take the like paines: And where wee erre in the termes of Warre, we desire all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="5"/> Souldiers to vnderstand it their way. This we thought good to tell you of: That you may vnderstand what you buy, and thus wee bid you fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>