<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the righte reuerende Father in GOD, and his singular good Lord Ihon Watson, by the grace of God Bishop of Winchester, and Prelate of the right honourable order of the Garter. I. H. wisheth healthe and peace, and long life in Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Hester, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94592_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00482</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19181.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94592</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the righte reuerende Father in GOD, and his singular good Lord Ihon Watson, by the grace of God Bishop of Winchester, and Prelate of the right honourable order of the Garter. I. H. wisheth healthe and peace, and long life in Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Hester, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first part of the key of philosophie : Wherein is contained moste ex-excellent [sic] secretes of phisicke and philosophie, deuided into twoo bookes. In the firste is shewed the true and perfect order to distill, or drawe forthe the oiles, of all maner of gummes, spices, seedes, rootes, and herbes, with their perfect taste, smell, [and] vertues. In the seconde is shewed the true and perfect order to prepare, calcine, sublime, and dissolue all maner of mineralles, and how ye shall drawe forthe their oiles and saltes, whiche are moste wonderfull in their operations, for the health of mannes bodie. First written in the Germaine tongue by the moste learned Theophrastus Paraselsus, and now published in the Englishe tongue by Ihon Hester practitioner in the arte of distillation</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the righte reuerende <hi>Father in GOD, and his singular</hi>
      </hi> good Lord Ihon Watson, by the grace of God Bishop of Winchester, and Prelate of the right honourable order of the Garter. I. H. wisheth healthe and peace, and long life in Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Retie and pithie is the tale (my good lorde) that Plato tells in his Protagoras, and somewhat appliable to my prsent purpose, and therefore not absurd for me to sett doune, to the better preferment of my pretence. Emong other his excellent inuentions (as he is in all his thinges moste like hymself still verie diuine) he she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth
<pb facs="4"/> how Joue looking doune frō Heauen with a pitifull regarde, vpon the harde and vntowarde condition of men, seeyng the son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie calamities, and infinite mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that they were subiect vnto, while yet they liued sauage like beastes amongst beastes, euery man leadyng his life after the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of his owne lust: tooke order straight with his winged messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Mercurie, to descende doune with expedition, with trauell to collecte and gather together the dispersed multitude, that so vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they might bothe bee stronger to defende them selues from the bruite beastes their common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie:
<pb facs="4"/> &amp; lincked as it were in a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die pollique, each presented as wel with the daily viewe of his owne want, as the continuall showe of like lacke in others, might with ioynt assent and consent (as dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by necessitie) endeuor to driue necessitie from themselues. For the spedier accomplishyng whereof, he had in charge to establishe a law, that if any amongest them weare founde vnfurnished with Iustice, and voide of shame fastnesse: the same should bee accompted as an vnprofitable Droane among la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouryng Bees, and should suffer punishement accordyngly. A wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie tale, and fit so worthie a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher.
<pb facs="5"/> By the which he liuely de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuered in generall tearmes, that whiche wee daiely finde in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culare proof: to weete, no common wealth, nor societie to continewe long happie where the members &amp; partes therof either for loue of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, or feare of shame are not like affectioned eche other. Now least J should seeme to allowe of this tale in speeche, and to dislike it in practise, J haue presumed by this bare translation, to testifie my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse in furtheryng her that fosters me. And yet is not my trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slatiō so bare (my good lorde) but that it carrieth in it more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to the readers, then perhapps
<pb facs="5"/> thei shall finde in the first writer: For beside that J haue culled out their choise thynges, J haue from the same choise proined, and cut of their superfluities, I haue supplied their defectes, J haue laied open their obscuritie, and I haue shado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed their defaultes, neither yet arrogating to my self, nor deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng from them, but as Dies diem docet, so Experimentū experiendo confirmatur. VVhat my trauaile herein shall profite, J knowe not: but sure J am my trouble in the triall of them hath been great, my expēces large, my proofs painfull, and nothing at all herein pleasant saue onely a little knowledge that
<pb facs="6"/> I haue gott, aboue the capacitie of the common sort, a thing sure that I value farre aboue the price that it coste me. VVhich knowledge in deede such is my grosnesse, or such the subtilnesse of the matter it self that I cā easilyer by demōstration shew it, then by declaration teach it: and therefore dare I not vnder credite warrant perspicuitie to all mē, but to those that are Filij ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. I promise more then I founde, and yet founde J more then thei hauing would willingly lose: to the residue I maie saie, that as hennes sit, but hatche not chickens in one daie: so men read, but learne not artes in one daie. To you my good
<pb facs="6"/> Lord, whose countenance herein I craue for protection, whose iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and skill I appeale to for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, I must needes confesse thei are not written (although loth to haue them masterlesse like their master, J am ouer bolde, to shroude them vnder your winges) to you J saie thei are not written, except ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden with the deepe &amp; graue mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of higher and more heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Philosophie, it maie please you for delight, now and then to looke doune into the plentifull and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant storehouse of Nature, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter no doubt<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that all your whole life time <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ue been singularly delighted <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>as most plainly do
<pb facs="7"/> declare the singularitie, that you haue happely attained vnto in all and euery the partes of her, no lesse to your great cōtent at home, then to your like cōmendation abroad: which because I can neither praise to your desarte, nor in praisyng please your desire, I leaue to speake farther of: only desiring your good lordship with your wonted clemē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to accept of this small testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my great good will, assuring your self, that emongst the greate number of your well willers, there is no one more dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then your pore</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Jhon Hester.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>