<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94666_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00537</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19605.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94666</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exhortation vnto the gouernours, and people of hir Maiesties countrie of Wales : to labour earnestly, to haue the preaching of the gospell planted among them. There is in the ends something that was not in the former impression</title>
                 <author>Penry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="41" facs="23"/>
   <p>THus I haue set downe the exhortation, word for word, as it was in the former impressiō, without the altering or deminishing of any one thing, (three marginall notes added) sauing the faults escaped in the printing. And hauing heere and there diffused my reasons against the dumb ministers, which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue are not so easilie to bee gathered out of the same, because the most part of them were brought in for other purposes; I thought good in this place, to set them downe syllogistically, to the end it maye appear vnto the church of God, vpon what grounds I denie them to be ministers. But here first the state of the question is to be made knowen,<note place="margin">The slate of the question is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be anie minister at all, good or bad vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome the Lord neuer said go and preach. Mat. 28.18.19. I denye such a one to be any.</note> which is not whether our readers be such, as haue the names, &amp; supplie the places of ministers, (for he that will not graunt this, denieth heat to be in the fire) but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, by the vnlawfull consent of our corrupt prelats, stealing the names, &amp; intruding themselues vppon the places of ministers, that is, hauing a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt outward calling, be ministers indeede. So that for the better vnderstanding of this controuersie, I graunt, that in our Churche in those daies of hir ruines, there bee two sortes of ministers. First, a minister <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> onely in name, which is not a minister indeed. Secondly, a minister both in name and deede: which also is double. First, a minister, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> that is, hauing not only vpon him the name of a minister, but also in him these thinges which are agreeable vnto the name, and giue the essence and being therevnto. Secondly, a minister, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> which both carrieth the name, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the essence thereof, and laboureth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form indeed whatsoeuer belōgeth vnto his calling, onely this minister is the good minister. As for the ministers <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> if they bee not <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="42" facs="24"/>they are all of them euill ministers. Of the whiche crue, are all those attainted with the faults spoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.4.7.</note> in the worde; whome although by the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of the Church, they should bee compelled to leaue, either theyr faultes, or their ministerie: yet I dare not deny to be ministers, as long as the church tollerateth them, vnlesse their offences bee such, as presently there ensueth<note n="b" place="margin">2. King. 23.9. Ezeb. 44.10.</note> a nullitie of their ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie before the Lord. Those who are onely ministers in name (of which sorte by the reasons following, I prooue all our readers to bee) are not ministers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, and therefore can by no meanes be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ministers. Especiallie, seeing as good and as able ministers altogether as they are, might in ciuill pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie bee established among the sauadge Caniballs, who feed vpon mens flesh, though they should ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther suffer any to come amongest them, that might teache them true religion, nor resorte them selues where the same were professed. For our Liturgie booke of Articles, manner of ordaining of Bishops and Priests, articles agreed vpon by the cleargie, in the conuocation house, might bee translated vnto their toong; &amp; they by a Lord-Archbishop or Bishop, Caniball, might bee mad Deacons or foule Priests, to were a surplice, a cloake with sleeues, a truncke gowne, a cap and tipper, and I thinke bell and babell (ornaments fit inogh for such deformed coxcombs) to read a Gospell, church women, bid fasting dayes, and holy-daies, profane the Sacramentes, praye at the buriall of the dead, pronounce a cursse against sinners vppon Ash-wendsday, and at no time els, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a new Sacrament of the crosse, in the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of baptisme, visit the sicke with a wafer cake, and a wine-bottell, read Homilies, pray for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie of theeues, pyrates, murtherers, yea, a Pope
<pb n="43" facs="24"/>Cardinall, Arch-bishop, Lord-bishop, or any other enemie of God, &amp; his Church, if he trauaile by land or by water, and brieflie to performe whatsoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie reader within wales, by his outwarde calling is bound to do. Now any reasonable man would denie these to be ministers: howbeit they emoyed the names and roomes agreeable vnto that function. And I pray you, what difference should there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene these and our readers, in regard of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie? In their persons I graunt some might bee shewed, but that can be nothing to make their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie disagree. And this out of all controuersie is most true, that no ministerie can be where true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not, no ministerie can be out of the church, as we see the ministerie of our readers may. For the Apostle inseperablie ioyneth the gathering' toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the saints with the<note n="a" place="margin">Ephes. 4.22.</note> worke of the ministerie.</p>
   <p>Where also the importunacie of the distinction that they are euill, that they are maimed ministers, &amp; therfore ministers is esier answered then propoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by granting thē to be euill &amp; may med ministers indeed, but so euil and so maimed, as they are flatly none, &amp; so making 2. kinds of euill ministers, the one so euil &amp; so maimed as they are none at al, the other in deede euill and maymed, but so as they want not the life, whereby a minister is a minister. A Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion entering into a campe of discomfited and wounded men, shoulde finde them all (it maye bee) wounded and maimed in most miserable sorte; but some so maimed, as they were not men, but deade corpses. The same is to be said of our foiled and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ministerie in this Lande, wherein all, from the highest to the lowest (some few excepted which kepe vs from beeing like Sodome and Gomoraah (shalbe found mangled by Sathan (sorrowfull and desperate
<pb n="44" facs="25"/>sight:) in their verie essential parts, but some so mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that they are as dead as the doore naile. Now that all our readers want the very life, essence, and beeing whereby a minister is a minister, that is, are not ministers in deed. I proue by these two reasons, and haue prooued in the booke by the reasons that shall ensue. Whosoeuer wanteth that life, which is either prescribed or included in the word, to be the life of a minister good or bad, hee hath not so much as the life of a badde minister, much lesse of a good. But our readers want both that life, which is prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed or included in the worde to be the life of a good minister, and that which is the life of a bad minister. Therefore our readers haue not so much as the life of a bad minister, much lesse of a good; The propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition is most manifest. For whence learne we, what giueth life and beeing vnto a minister, but out of the woorde? The proose of the assumption is thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. First, there is no essence of that minister, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as good or as a bad minister, set downe to the worde, whereof there is at all no mencion made in worde. The truth hereof Appius Caecus might see. Doth the worde shewe what life and beeing hee can haue, whome it denieth to be at all? But our readers are not mentioned in the word as publik ministers; Because the word neuer dremt of that minister, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome it is not sayd: go<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 28.19</note> and teach. Therefore, there is no essence or life of our readers mentioned, off in the worde, either as good, or as bad ministers. Secondly, there is no essence or life of that minister, either as a good or as a badde minister, set downe in the word, which is but the ordinance of the church, by the ordinance of the church, I mean euery mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery &amp; minister, which is not read of in the word, howsoeuer the outward calling be ioyned vnto it. I
<pb n="45" facs="25"/>know that the very outward calling of a minister, is not the ordinance of the church, but the inuiolable prescript ordinance of God, in the deliuery wherof, the church is but an instrument, &amp; I can proue our readers to be neither the ordinance of God, nor of the church in that sence, whereby the ordinance of the church is takē for the outward calling acording to the word; To the assumption. But our readers to make the most of them, are no more then the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the church. Therfore there is no essence or life of our readers set downe in the worde, either as good or bad ministers. The assumption euerye man will graunt; the proposition is most firme; Because that euerie minister<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.4.11.28. &amp; 4.7. &amp; 9.16.17. 2 Cor: 4.6. Math: 21.25. &amp; 11.11. Rom. 12.6. Ephe: 4.11. Collosir. 25.</note> good or<note n="b" place="margin">Phil: 1.15.16. 1. Cor: 3.3.15. Mat: 7.22. 1. Cor. 9.27.</note> bad, is the ordinance of God, in such sort, as to whome-soeuer the Lorde hath not committed<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.4. Iohns ministerie was from God, therfore much more euery mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stery more euery mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery in the king done vnder the gospell. Math. 21.26. &amp; 11.11</note> the dispensation of his will, well he may haue the outward calling of a minister, he is in deede no more then the ordinaunce of the Church, and so wanteth the verie life of a minister. For it is not the approbation of the Church by the outward calling, that can giue life vnto that miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie which is not heard off in the worde. Because the outwarde calling giueth not the life or beeing vnto a minister, but the birth. So that to make a minister, therebe two things required. First, a being or life, which the Lord onely can giue. Secondlye, a birth, which the Church as an instrument of the ordinance of God, is to bestow vpon him by his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling. These two things are so essentially to be required in a minister, that whosoeuer wanteth either of them, he cannot possibly be a minister. For where is that man that consisteth onelye of a soule, or onelye of a bodye? where is that man that neuer had life? Or what was is his name that neuer was borne? whervpon it ensueth, that neither he which
<pb n="46" facs="26"/>wanteth either of these two partes, muste not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to intermeddle with those actions, which are by the ordinance of God, necessarilie tied (as the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes are) vnto him that hath both the life and the birth of a minister, nor I aduenture to goe vnto him for those things, which he hath no commission to deliuer. Be a man therefore neuer so godly, neuer so learned, endued with neuer so liuelye faculties of the ministerie, yet he is no minister in deed, vnlesse he haue the ordinaunce of his God vpon him by his outward calling. The preaching of the word being a gift, and not depending vpon the very ordination is not so tied to the person of a minister: but that he which hath not the outwarde calling, may offer the trial of his gifts vnto the church in the publik place, his spirite hauing before bene subiect vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> that is, such as haue iudgement to discerne of his gifts. On the other side, beit that a man haue the outward calling of the church: yet in deede he is no minister, vnlesse the Lord hath giuen him the life of a minister, by committing the woorde of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation vnto his hands. By this I haue set down two maine questions which trouble many that fear God in these daies are decided. First, because the outward calling is essentially required in a minister, it is therefore thought of some to be that, which gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the life vnto a minister. As though a childe hath not life in the wombe before it be born, or that his birth be any thing to giue him life: I graunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that a woman cannot glorie of the fruit of her body, vntill it come to the byrth, for the bignes of the woombe may proceede of some Tympany. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlye, in asmuch as the manner of the essentiall birth of a minister, is prescribed in the worde, which prescript cannot without sinne be altered by any, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="47" facs="26"/>in taking vpon them the ministery, or in impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the same vpon others, some are seelilie carried away to thinke them, to be no ministers which haue not their birth in euerye point according vnto this prescription. The reason is no better, then if I should denie him to be a true and a liuing childe, whome I cannot denie to haue the life &amp; the birth of a child, because hee issued out at his birth by the waye hee should not:<note place="margin">Tranq. in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i. Caes.</note> if C. Iulins had beene taken out at hys mothers side, shoulde it therefore bee needlesse to warne him to take heede of the Ides of March? ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd.</p>
   <p>The second reason against these vntimely births, I thus frame; Whatsoeuer ministerie and minister, was then vnknowen in the Church, when all those callings flowrished therein, which were in any age, or time appointed by the Lord to be in the ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; that ministerie and minister hath not so much as the essence of a ministerye or minister, good or bad; Euerie one knoweth this, who knoweth Paule to haue sette downe, that the Lord<note n="a" place="margin">Ephes. 4.12.</note> ordained not a transitorie ministerie, but suche as was to continue vntill his second comming. And more then extream follie were it to thinke him, to set downe a being for that minister whom he neuer ment to ordain. But our readers &amp; their ministery were thē vnknown in the Church, whē al these callings flowrished therin, which the Lord in any age or time ordained for the ministerie, I meane in the<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 12.3.7. 1. cor 12 28. ephes. 4.12.13.</note> Apostles time. Therfore our readers and their ministerie, haue not so much as the essence of a ministerie or ministers good or bad. Our of these two reasons arise two proper dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, between the magistracy &amp; the ministerie. First, there may be a lawfull magistracie and magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate according to the woord, whose name and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="48" facs="27"/>was neuer heard of before in the worlde, much lesse read in the word, so can there not be a ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or minister.<note place="margin">Tit. Liui. lib. 3. Cicero in 2. Cat</note> L. Quintius Cincinatus is made Dictator. L. Tarquinius maister of the horse. L. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimius, the counsel must see that the cōmon-wealth be not endaungered by any faction, the same place both before &amp; after sustained many among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. In our time the care of the publike peace in all the Germaine empire, was committed to Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus a Schiuendi.<note place="margin">Iohn. Funccinus</note> All these were new kindes of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracies at their first institution, yet lawfull. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond difference is, that the life and office of a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster is prescibed in the word, contained in his gifts, and seuered from his, outwarde calling. But the life of the magistracie, is neither prescribed in the worde, (for so there coulde bee no magistrates out of the Church, nor any in the Church, but such as are prescribed in the worde, which were verie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious to thinke) or contained in the gifts of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grstracie, not yet seperated from his outwarde cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For the verie outward calling is it, that giueth life vnto the magistracie, though the person sustay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, want gifts to discharge the same. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son heereof is euident, because the magistracie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an humane constitution<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> as the holy ghost saith, is appropriated vnto his possession vpon whomsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man bestoweth the same, if hee bee capable to possesse (though vnfit to execute) what is allotted vnto him. So cannot the ministerie bee, vnlesse hee vpon whome the Church imposeth it, be made fitte by the Lorde for the execution thereof. They who thinke the essence of a magistrate, any more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in the gifts of courage, vnderstanding, wisdome, fearing God, dealing trulie,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod 18.21. deut. 1.13.</note> hating couetousnes, (the onely properties mentioned by Iethro, whence
<pb n="49" facs="27"/>this life of a magistrate is falsely gathered) then the being of a minister is contained in his<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.7.</note> faithfulnes, verie inconsiderately gaine-say the Apostle Peter in the place before quoted, because hereby they make the magistracie not to bee an humaine ordinaunce, but an ecclesiasticall constitution, prescribed in the word. The obiection therefore that a minister shold be no more denied to be a minister, bicause he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth gifts, then a magistrate denied to bee a magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, for the same defect prooueth not woorth the answering. Because the Lorde hath tied a mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herytance, no otherwaies vnto him, then hee hath the magistracie vnto that person or persons who haue aucthoritie to make a magistrate. So that the very magistracie, may bee deriued from him by the outwarde calling, as well as the substantiall interest of this inheritance, by the best conuaiaunce in law. No such thing beeing tied vnto the Church, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a minister; Because none can say they are in the possession of a ministerie, who haue not the same from the Lord. And what ministerie haue our readers from him? Any outward thing in the pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of man: (of which nature all men knowe the magistracie to be:) may bee conuaied really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, (ought not alwaies I graunt) vnto him vppon whomsoeuer man the possessour thereof will confer the same, and there it ought to be inuiolablie inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, as long as man whose right it is to bestow it, or take it away, wil haue it so. Hath a man lesse interest in his money, because, either for want of witte, hee knoweth not how to vse, or by his leudnes dooth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse it? Candanles a foole, is no lesse a magistrate, (a far worse I deny not) among the Lydians,<note place="margin">Herod. lib. 1. Plato de reip. dial. 2.</note> then E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesilaus among the Lacedemonians, a wise and a politike gouernor. The same is to be said of Ioab &amp;
<pb n="50" facs="28"/>Benaiah, of Licinius, a persecutour and Constantine a christan emperor. Tib. Ghracchus abuseth his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy, the senate and people sin, because they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him not, but as long as they tollerat him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the magistracie is his owne, and therefore not lawfull for any priuate man by disobedience to rob him thereof. And why so? Because the swoorde in his hand, is still the Lords sword, the sedition &amp; ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie in him is his owne. To come to the ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the Church maketh that wretch a minister, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom it will be said, I<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 7.22.23.</note> know thee not, thou wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of iniquitie. But did the Lorde by enduing him with graces meete for the ministerie, say vnto him go prophesie in my name? hee did. Then there is a ministerie committed vnto him, which is, neither his, nor the churches, but the Lordes, the same dare not I denie (vntill the Lorde take it awaye) for the foulnes of his handes. Another commeth with the same calling of the church, &amp; he sayth b I am a plain heardman,<note place="margin">a Zachary. 13.5.</note> neither prophet, nor the sonne of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. (Now Lord if it be thy will, bee mercifull vnto them, conuert them, and disburden thy church of them) but I haue my letters of orders from the Lord bishop, and am in possession of the liuing; I knowe no ministerie he hath. And therefore I denie him to be any more a minister for his outward calling sake, there Herdonius a traiterous and slauish seruant is a magistrate, though by treacherie, he with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of other rogish vagabonds like him selfe, hath now gotten possession of the Capitol. That the spech may not seeme straunge vnto any, let men way but the prerogatiue which the Lord reserueth vnto him selfe, in making ministers in hys Church: with the priuilege, which hir Maiestie hath in ordaining ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates within hir dominions. The whole assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="51" facs="28"/>of Parliament for some causes mouing them, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a Lord high Constable of England, (as France hath) hir Maiestie sheweth hir publik disliking ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And that shee will hauen) such officer within hir Realme, is he a magistrate? hee is none neither wil I acknowledge him for any, as long as it shalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst hir wil &amp; pleasure to haue any such within hir dominions. For what magistrate is he in this land, which she saith to be none as long as the royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue is in hir hand. In like maner, what minister is he in the Church of God, whome the Lord deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be any. The case is too to manifest.</p>
   <p>The distinctiō that readers are ministers of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (that is sent of the Lorde in iudgement to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the sinnes in this age) but not ministers of the mercie and grace of God, is as if they were sayd to be ministers of an ordinance neuer ordayned: now farre be it we shoulde make a ministery of an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance neuer reuealed, of an ordinaunce that is but temporary. And in very deed I cannot but thinke it a very strange matter, that these men who make a conscience of that which they teach, being also wise and godly learned, are not ashamed to be reported the forgers and setters abroach of such shifting and siely stuffe. The other obiection concerning the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery vnder Moses, is as faultie For to square the ministerie of the new couenant, according vnto the Leuitical priesthood, is to require the Consulship of Rome, to be framed after the Maioraltie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, besides manye other foule inconsequentes it hath in it. I haue alreadie shewed the weaknes her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and if it deserued a further aunsweare, I woulde vouchsafe it the same.</p>
   <p>The reasons expressed in the booke, are now to be set downe. Such of them as are noted with this
<pb n="52" facs="29"/>marke,<note place="margin">The thinges which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to seeke, I imbrace, their seperation I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test.</note> * are some of the reasons, whereby I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily induced, vtterly to condemne that course of those (I hope fearing God) who haue made a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from those ministers in this lande (&amp; their congregations) who truely preache the worde. And although there bee in our godly assemblies manye corruptions, and more wants tollerated, whiche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Christian heart must needs abhorre: yet I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test that I would (as to my comfort I doe) ioyne my selfe in the publike hearing of the worde, receiuing of the sacraments, praying, fasting, giuing of almes, and other holy exercises, which these congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as the assemblies of Gods people, amongst whō publike saluation is to be had, and with these mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, as the messengers of Iesus Christ, whose com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission from him, to make known vnto me the way of saluation, I dare not deny for my soule because there is some want in the seale, I mean the outward calling. My reasons are these; Where I am obscure, the booke may giue light. The conclusion for breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties sake I haue omitted in the most. The Prosyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme or second proof of any doutfull action where it is omitted, is afterwarde concluded in the syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme, which serueth for a proofe of all my reasons, where any of them might be thought to be weake.</p>
   <p>Euery one that hath the * life of a minister good or bad (or that is a minister in deede) is ordained of God for the gathering<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12.3. 1. Cor. 4.11.28. Ephes. 4.12.</note> together of the saintes. For ther is no other minister spoken of in the word. No bare reader is ordained of God for this end. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no bare reader is a minister in deede, or hath the life of a minister good or bad. The faithfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in the Church of England haue and do shewe by the good euidence of their teachinge, whereby soules are gathered vnto the church, and fed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="53" facs="29"/>that they were ordained of God for this ende. Therefore the seperation from them and their as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, is an vngodly, wicked, and scismatical rent from the visible body of the churche. An vngodly, wicked, and scismaticall rent, I call it vpon good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation &amp; aduice. Because that seperation from the companye where publike saluation is had and professed, which is made in such sort, as if the sayde company had not the means of saluation sounding in it, or worshipped God after a false maner is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and scismaticall. Such is the rent of these men. For as they themselues do anouch, they are sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from vs, because in all our meetings the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are so great, that we serue the true God after a false maner, hold not the foundation, and so haue no meanes to be saued among vs. For the men thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, I hope the Lorde will recall them, and I am perswaded the most of them haue fallen into this snare of meare and simple ignorance. And woe, woe woe (vnlesse they repent) will be vnto them, that in smiting and keeping backe the carefull and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse sheapheardes, haue beene the cause of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable dispersion &amp; straying of the poore sheep. For the course, whiche they take in seekinge good things it is to be auoyded, as a course very likely to shake them from eternall life that continue in it. I know what I say. For where is there now any more meanes left for them to be saued without their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce (we hauing the onely ordinarie meanes of saluation among vs, as before is prooued) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they seperate themselues from vs, as from those who serue the true God after a false maner, and plainly shew that they would haue no saluation ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that whereof wee are by the mercies of God pertakers, through the ministery of the worde
<pb n="54" facs="30"/>in our assemblies. They cannot deny (&amp; I desire thē to grant no more then the reasons folowing, &amp; the former proue in this point) but that saluation is to be had by the ministery of our preachers. And they also know that there is but one ordinary way to be saued, which being accounted but in one assembly to be the way of seruing God after a false manner, the passage of saluation is shut vp euery where, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are thus seduced, for any thing that I know to be reuealed. Shall I because the churche-gouernement is not as yet established<note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> in Creta, or is iniuriously kept out, and some great corruptions tollerated in steade thereof, therefore affirme that those congregations of the Cretians, where the word of god is taught by men of fit gifts; are assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies where the true god is worshipped after a false manner, and yet notwithstanding thinke I may be saued by the worde preached at Philippi (continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing still in the same error.) Whereas they that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the worde at Creta, are men endued with as rare gifts from the Lorde, for the worke of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery, as vpright in life, and haue called as many to saluation, as they had done who are at Philippi. I doubt hereof. Naye, if I seperate my selfe from the assemblies in Creta, to go to Philippi, it shall not be because I deny them to be meetings of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, among whome he ruleth by the scepter of the worde, or because I account them prophane syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogs, but because I see them too slacke in growing to that perfection, whereunto they desire to bee brought, so that my departing shall not be a separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a going forwarde. And while I addresse my selfe to goe forwarde, I will be sure not to cut of my selfe, from the publike meetinges where the worde preached is inioyned. A strong maner of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="55" facs="30"/>for men to cutte them-selues off, from the true Churche, to the ende they may haue a perfect out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gouernment. The practize of these silly men might seeme to be more tollerable, if they had ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themselues with any Churche vnder heauen. Nay, I would see what church dareth receiue them as long as they holde these congregations for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous synagogs, where that ordinance of God is, by which men are brought out of the kingdome of darknes vnto the kingdome of Christ. Euery one of the syllogismes noted with this marke, * inferre the former conclusion against their practize. I wishe their conuersion from my heart, and will be readie to performe any christian duetie (as a brother) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that the Lord hath enabled me.</p>
   <p>Euery minister<note n="(2)" place="margin">2</note> indeed * of that ordinaunce<note n="a" place="margin">Ephes. 4.13.</note> which is to continue in the church, for the worke of the ministerie to the worlds end. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. Noe bare reader is a minister of this ordinance. For this ordinance is the woord preached. Ergo no bare reader is a minister indeed.<note n="(3)" place="margin">3</note> Euery minister is able * to make the elect to be members of<note n="b" place="margin">Ephes. 4.13.</note> Christ. No bare reader is such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument. Ergo;<note n="(4)" place="margin">4</note> Euerie minister * is a meanes by the worde of the grace of God to giue the elect an inheritaunce among them that are<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> sanctified. None of our readers is such a meanes, ergo:<note n="(5)" place="margin">5</note> Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie minister indeede, is able to feed the * elect with the food of knowledge and<note n="d" place="margin">Iere. 3.15.</note> vnderstanding. None of our bare readers are able to do this: ergo:<note n="(6)" place="margin">6</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie * minister at the least, in regard of gifts, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the Lords owne<note n="e" place="margin">Ierem. 3.15.</note> heart, that is, his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance reuciled concerning his * choice. None of our readers is such: ergo:<note n="(7)" place="margin">7</note> Euery minister is * an instrument to make knowen by the word preached,
<pb n="56" facs="31"/>the purpose<note n="a" place="margin">Colos. 1.20.23 28.</note> of God concerning mans reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō. No reder is such: ergo:<note n="(8)" place="margin">8</note> Euery minister is able to lay open * the mysteries of saluation. No reader is &amp;c:<note place="margin">Looke this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the book.</note> ergo:<note n="(9)" place="margin">9</note> Euery minister is an * instrument of our new<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.21.</note> birth. No bare reader is &amp;c: ergo:<note n="(10)" place="margin">10</note> Euerie minister is able by the preaching of the Gospell. to manifest those hidden secreats, whiche the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets them-selues could not artaine vnto,<note place="margin">1, Pet, 1.10.12.</note> without great search and enquirie. No bare reader can doo this by preaching: ergo:<note n="(11)" place="margin">11</note> Euery minister is * a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by his publike ministery, to bring the elect vnto the knowledge of the truth and so to saluation.<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4.</note> No bare reader can doe this: ergo:<note n="(12)" place="margin">12</note> Whosoeuer are fit in regard of their sufficiencie to bee their miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters alone, that would haue no God,<note n="d" place="margin">2. Chron. 15.3.</note> are no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters indeede. All bare readers, not beeing able to lay open the will of the true God, are onely fit to bee their ministers that would haue no God: ergo: they are no ministers indeede.<note n="(13)" place="margin">13</note> They are no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, whosoeuer are able to performe the whole worke of their ministerie without studie, and giuing heed vnto learning, as the<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.14.14.</note> apostle commandeth. But all our readers (if they can read) can performe the whole work of their calling, as long as they liue, without any further studye: ergo: they are no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters indeed<note n="14" place="margin">14</note>. Euery minister * is able to expound that which<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 8.13.14.</note> cannot be vnderstoode without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretour, viz, that, which is to be learned out of the word concerning the Lorde, &amp; mans saluation. Our bare readers cannot do this: ergo:<note n="15" place="margin">15</note>. Euerie minister * is a minister of that waye, whereby the Lord bestoweth vpon men the spirite of wisedome, and reuelation through his knowledge.<note n="g" place="margin">Eze. 2.17:</note> Our bare readers are not such: ergo:<note n="16" place="margin">16</note>. Euery * minister is able to make the word of God powerfull, either vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="57" facs="31"/>to death or vnto life, in<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 4 12.2. 2. chro. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> some of the hearers. Our readers are not able to doe this: ergo: 17 Euerye minister is * able to deuide the word of God aright<note place="margin">12</note> vnto the seuerall vse of the hearers.<note n="b" place="margin">2. Tim 1.10. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>os. 1.5.7.</note> Our readers are not able to do this: ergo:<note place="margin">18</note> 18 Euery minister is able to tech those that can read,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim▪ 5.22. &amp; 3.10.</note> as wel as himself. No bare reader can do this: ergo:<note place="margin">19</note> 19 Euery mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster can doe some thing in regarde of teaching his flocke, which euery christian, who can read well &amp; distinctly, is not able to performe. Our readers can not do this: ergo:<note place="margin">20</note> 20 whosoeuer by naturall gifts alone, are able to performe, whatsoeuer belongeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their<note n="d" place="margin">Rom 7.7. &amp; 12.3. ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 3.8. 1. coa. 3.10. &amp; 4.7. heb. 5.4. ephes. 4.7.</note> calling they are no ministers, bicause there is some thing (to speak the least) in the ministry of euery minister whiche cannot postiblie bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by natural gifts alone. Our readers are able by the onely gifts of nature, to perfourme whatsoeuer belong vnto their calling, ergo: our readers are no ministers indeed.<note place="margin">21</note> 21 Euery minister * hath gifts to labour in Gods husbandrie, and Gods building:<note place="margin">22</note> 1. Cor. 3.8. 1. Thes. 5.2. our readers haue not: ergo: 22 Euerye * minister hath necessarily annexed, vnto his calling, workes of that admiration, that it maye bee truly sayd of them, who is fit for these things. 2. Cor. 2.16. our readers are not: ergo:<note place="margin">23</note> 23. Euerye minister is able to make the Lord so knowen to the elect, that they dare call vpon him, in saith and full perswasion to be hard. Rom. 10.14. &amp; 8.15. our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders cannot do this: ergo: 24. Euerie minister is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cōpare spirituall things with spirituall things,<note place="margin">24</note> and to speake the worde<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 2 13. 1. thes 4.11.</note> of GOD, as the word of God: our readers are not able to doe this ergo:<note place="margin">25</note> 25 Whosoeuer preserueth * not knowledge in his lips, that is, wanteth the thing, the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>whereof, in a priuate man, not beeing censurable by the church,
<pb n="58" facs="32"/>viz. not being a sin in it selfe, giueth the Lord &amp; the church iust cause, both to keep them from the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie, and to expell them out of the ministery, in whome this want is found, though they bee euerye way els qualified for the ministery, according vnto the<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ir. 1.6.7. 1. cor. 4.2.1. thes. 2.2.11</note> proprieties required in the word, hee is no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister. Our readers haue this wante in them: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their lips doe not preserue knowledge: ergo, they are no ministers indeed. Thus my reason is in the booke page 8. drawen out of Mala. 2.7. is to bee concluded. For although a man want all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties of a minister, yet being fit to teach, he hath some allowaunce from the Lorde to bee a minister, whereas the want heere of kepeth back the Lordes whole consent, from the admission of him into the ministerie, in whom it is.</p>
   <p>The reason whereof is, that all other proprieties in a minister, sauing this, are such, as according to the ordinance of God, ought to be in euery christian (as to be modest, harberous, no striker, &amp;c.) as well as in the minister, though not in the same measute, this by the Lords institution, is to be in the minister one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of necessitie: howbeit other christians also may be and are capable thereof.<note place="margin">26</note> 26 Whosoeuer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goeth that ministery,<note place="margin">Looke the book page 8.</note> and no other, whereof a Turk, Painime, or Iewe, who will not learne true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may be capable, he in deede is no minister. Our readers vndergoe no other ministerie;<note place="margin">27</note> &amp;c. ergo. 27 They whose ministery make the whole religion of christians, not to haue in it, so much as one mystery, (the secrecie whereof euen in regard of knowledge, might disable one, that neuer heard of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a publike minister thereof) are no ministers in deede. The ministerye of all bare readers is such▪ ergo,<note place="margin">28</note> 28 They are no ministers, who for their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery
<pb n="59" facs="32"/>alone, call for the wrath of God vpon the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern ours and the land, where they are tollerated: our readers though otherwise the holiest men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen call, &amp;c, ergo. 29 All ministers * maye truely say of themselues,<note place="margin">19 2. Cor. 5.20.</note> now then are we ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadours from Christe, as though God did beseeche you through vs, we pray you in Christs steade, that you be reconciled vnto God: Our readers cannot truely say, &amp;c: ergo. 30 Euery one that is a minister in deed, hath more in him, then parents,<note place="margin">30 Look the book page 9.</note> both vnder the law, and vnder the Gospell, were and are bound to haue in thē, who though they neither coulde nor can read, were and are bounde to reach their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: our readers haue not thus much:<note place="margin">31 Looke page 10.</note> ergo. 31 E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery minister * is a minister of the wholsom doctrine spoken of by the Apostle, 2, Tim. 4, 3: our readers are not: ergo. 32 Euery minister, * in what age soeuer he liueth,<note place="margin">32 Colos. 13.29.</note> is able to bring the electe (who are borne citizens of darknes, vnto the kingdome of Christe: our readers cannot do this: ergo.<note place="margin">33</note> 33 Euerye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster is able by the word preached, to cut of the buds that spring, out of the roote of corruptions, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the regenerate: Our readers are not: ergo, 34 Euery minister * is able to make the food of life, to be milke vnto the weak,<note place="margin">34 b 1. Cor. 3.2. heb 5.14</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and strong meat to thē that are capable thereof: our readers are not: ergo. 35 Euery minister * is able to make cleare vnto the elect, what the fellowship is, of the misterie,<note place="margin">35</note> whiche b from the beginning of the world hath bene hid in God: our readers are not:<note place="margin">c Ephe 3.9.</note> ergo.<note place="margin">36 Looke page 11.</note> 36 They who are ministers * of those visions alone, that cannot turne the people from iniquitie, nor discouer sinner, are no ministers in deed: our readers are such: ergo.<note place="margin">37</note> 37 The * people liuinge vnder them that are ministers in deed, may hope for eternall life by their ministerie,
<pb n="60" facs="33"/>if they faithfully execute the same: But the people liuing vnder our readers, though they faithfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute their ministerie, cannot hope: ergo. 38 Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie * minister is a minister of the waye,<note place="margin">38</note> whereby the Lord ordained, he should be publikely serued of his people, and they trained vp in his feare: our readers are not: ergo. 39 They are no ministers * whose flockes the Lord may pursue,<note place="margin">39</note> with his eternal curse, for contenting them-selues with their ministerie, though they faithfully discharge, whatsoeuer by their outwarde calling is enioyned them: But the flocks of our readers are such as, &amp;c: ergo. 40 They * are no ministers,<note place="margin">40</note> whose flocks by their ministerye, cannot sanctifie the Sabboth: our readers are such: ergo.<note place="margin">41</note> 41 They * are no ministers in deed, that haue not gifts to obey Paules charge: Our readers haue not:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1.2.</note> ergo.<note place="margin">42</note> 42 They are no ministers in deede, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer may truely say of themselues, truely wee are no ministers in deed, b though we haue an outwarde calling:<note n="a" place="margin">Zach. 3.5.</note> our readers may truely say thus: ergo. 43 They who are in the estate of damnation for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in the ministery,<note place="margin">43.</note> though they be guiltie of no other notorious sinne, are no ministers: Suche are our readers: ergo. 44 They are no ministers, whose congregations hauing no other ministry,<note place="margin">44</note> since they haue bene Idolatrous synagogs, can neuer by their ministery be said to haue the outward<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 28.18.19. ephEs. 1.13. col. 2.11.17. Looke page 24.25.</note> markes of a true Church: But the congregations of our readers are such: ergo. 45 They that are * ministers in deed, do not sinne because they do administer the sacraments: But our readers (as all the godly confesse) sin in presuming to deal with any action belonging vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a minister,<note place="margin">45</note> and therfore the sacraments: ergo. All these reasons, besides the other syllogistically sette down, where I deale with the prophanation of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="61" facs="33"/>by our readers, are expressed in the booke. Now that euery one of these seuerally, &amp; all iointly are of themselues alone (none of thē depending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the proofe, that is gotten by the other) seuerall, and ioynt demonstrations, concluding our readers to be no ministers, I thus prooue.</p>
   <p>All these reasons whereof euery one seuerally &amp; all ioyntly, do conclude them to be no ministers in deede, who are not preaching ministers, they also conclude our readers to be no ministers. But all the former reasons (or the most of them) conclude thē to be no ministers in deed, which are not preachers, (by preachers; I mean not euery one that can speak for an houre in the pulpit, but such in deed, as shew b by the enidence of their reaching,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.14. ephes. 4.12. gal. 3.1.2. cor. 10.4. 1. thes. 1.5.</note> that they are ordained of God, for the gathering togither of the Saints) therefore also they conclude our readers to be no ministers indeed: Vnto the former I ad these.<note place="margin">46</note> 46 The calling * of euerye one thot is a minister in deed, is a sanctified calling in it selfe, to him that is thereunto called, and hath giftes to discharge the same. But the very calling, (I do not say popedomes, archbishopriks, pride, couetousnes, epicurism, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, &amp; wretched ignorance, Lording ouer others, opposing themselues to the Lord Iesus and his mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) of our readers, is an vngodly, and vnsanctified vocation, to bee a calling of the ministery, because there is no suche ministerie as they vndergoe, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the worde: ergo, they are no ministers in deed.<note place="margin">47</note> 47 Their * calling is no calling of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, and so they no ministers: for the remouing of whose ministerie, it is<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 9.38.</note> lawfull * for vs to pray: But it is lawfull to pray for the remoouing of this dumb ministery out of the Church: ergo.<note place="margin">48</note> 48 They * are no ministers, who may betake themselues without
<pb n="62" facs="34"/>sinne, to another calling, when the Churche wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ministers, especially if they may exercise their ministerie in peace, Our readers may: ergo. 49 E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery * one that is a minister,<note place="margin">44</note> hath that calling vpon him, whereunto the Lorde according vnto his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance b committeth the charge of soules: our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders haue no such calling: ergo. 50 Euery minister * hauing a flocke committed vnto him may be,<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Doctor or the Pastor thereof:<note place="margin">50</note> Our readers can be neither: ergo.<note place="margin">51</note> 51 The birth of that which, was neuer conceiued, is no birthe in deede. But our readers are birthes that were neuer conceiued, that is, ministers by their outward ordination, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they neuer had any conception, that is, inwarde calling:<note place="margin">52</note> ergo. 52 They * are no ministers, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whose triall, there bee no rules set downe<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 22. &amp; 3.10.</note> in the word: Such are our readers: ergo. 53 They are no ministers, the essentiall worke of whose supposed ministerie, may bee performed according vnto the ordinance of God, by those, who both haue a func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diuers from the calling of these readers, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, without offence vnto Gods children, such a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie, as ignorant readers take vpon them. This proposition is most true, because there is but one fort of ministers, namely, the ordinance of God, and not of the Church mentioned in the word: But our readers are such, as the essentiall work of their sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed calling, being the works of a minister in deed, may according to the ordinance of God, be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by those, who both haue a function diuers from (yea, contrarie to) these readers function, as good is to euill, vz. by preachers, whose calling being a san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified calling, must needes be in nature, not onely diuers from, but contrarie to, the caling of readers, which is not warranted by the worde, a calling war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted
<pb n="63" facs="34"/>and a calling not warranted being contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and detest without offence vnto Gods children, such a ministerie, as dumb readers take vpon them. Therefore our bare readers though they haue the name and supplie the place of ministers, are not ministers in deed: And not being in deed ministers, it is not left vnto me as a thing indifferent by chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian libertie, whether I will communicate with thē or no: Because that of necessity, I am bound to com for the sacraments, vnto the ordinaunce of<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 21.25. &amp; 11.11. 1. cor. 12.4.11.</note> God, that is, vnto a minister: and not vnto the ordinance of the church, neither haue I any liberty to attempt the contrarie. And as before hath bene prooued, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery minister is the ordinaunce of<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 12.5.28 ephes. 4.7.11.</note> God, &amp; not the ordinance of the Church, ordained when our saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christe led captiuitie<note n="c" place="margin">Ephes. 4.8. math. 28.19.</note> captiue, and not since. Nowe our readers being but the ordinance of the Church, ordained since that time, and the Church hauing no libertie to ordaine sacramentes: I haue also no libertie, no not in the time of necessitie, to come vnto the ordinance of the Church for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes: because there I can haue no more, for any thing I know, then the Church whence the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance is, hath power to giue. And I pray you what sacrament is that, which the bare ordinance of the Church can deliuer?</p>
   <p>These be some of the reasons, (and I take no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the nomber of them) wherevpon, as on the infallible trueth of Gods sacred word, I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude the most within wales, supplying the places of ministers, to be no ministers in deed, and to haue nothing in them, that giueth life vnto a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, good or bad. And therevpon I dare as boldly affirme the course to bee a wicked and sismatticall course, which they take, that seperate them selues
<pb n="64" facs="35"/>from the publike assemblies, where the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched is truly taught in this land, as from those who serue the true God, after a false maner. In the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of whiche reasons, I protest with a good conscience, that I haue so laboured, both at the first edition of the booke, (some reasons then moouing me to deale more timorouslie in the action) &amp; since that time especialle, as I haue not suffered my selfe to be deceiued by any sophisme, or fallation. And I prorest before the Lord, that vpon these grounds, I both assuredly know their course, (of whome I haue spoken, to be dangerous and detestable, and am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so as surely perswaded, that menne not ordained of God for the gathering of the saints, are no ministers whatsoeuer calling they haue in the Church, as I beleeue the blessed apostle Paule to haue beene an apostle sent from God. And bicause I am one daye to bee reckonad with, before the iudgement seat of Iesus Christe, of my sinceare dealing in both those points, and liue now in the church of God, the least member whereof; Woe be vnto me if I offende, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause also I liue vnder hir highnes a Christian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, whose sacred ancthoritie I subiect my selfe vnto, &amp; reuerence as the royall ordinance of gods owne maiestie, and whose positiue lawes and procc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, as far as I may with a good conscience tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate their imperfections, I dare not gain-saye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause likewise, what I haue written, shalbe recorded and called in question in the church of God, (when I am gone the way of all flesh) vnto whome I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide to commend my name, as a brocher of newe doctrines: therefore I haue beene carefull to sette down nothing, but that which will abide the triall of all whosoeuer, and abide firme against all. If any of my godly, teuerēd, &amp; lerned brethren of the church
<pb n="65" facs="35"/>of Englande, will doe me the fauour (which thing I earnestly request at their hands) in short syllogisms to communicate with mee in writing, their reasons for the ministerie of these ignoraunt men. I shall haue cause to praise the Lord, and thanke them for their loue towards me in this point also, and the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier satisfie whatsoeuer may be sayd on the behalf of this vnlearned (I woulde vnknowen) ministerie. I greatlye reuerence many godlye and learned, that are contrary minded vnto me in this cause; I know my yeares to bee subiect vnto that bolde temerity, hoat, and heady rashnes, which blessed Timothy in<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.22.</note> consideration of his age, was bidden by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to auoide: notwithstanding, in regarde of the cause (in humilitie before the Lord, his elect angels and children bee it spoken) I may iustly (for beit I should) contemne and despise, almost not vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to answer, whatsoeuer man or angell, can bring against it. And I dare arest and attaint, of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son against the maiestie of the highest all those, both men and aungels, who either defend the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with them lawfull; communicate with them, or tollerate them as ministers vnder their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>