<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>P., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94700_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07982</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19766.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94700</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>P., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A direction to death : teaching man the way to die well, that being dead, he may liue euer. Made in the forme of a dialogue, for the ease and benefite of him that shall reade it. The speakers therein are, Quirinus and Regulus</title>
                 <author>Perneby, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 65, 65-78, 77, 81-493, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian reader, I know not thy conceite: it may be good, it may bee bad, it may bee indifferent, if thou answerest ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the titles J haue giuen thee, it cannot be bad. Jf courtesie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not compell thee, yet Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may counsell thee to thinke and iudge the best; here is nothing done to the preiudice of any: if it please God to blesse, there may bee some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the benefite of many.
<pb facs="7"/>
Though some others haue written of the same matter that J haue written of, yet that lets not but J may doe the like: as diuerse Musi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may play vpon one instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, so diuerse men may write of one thing. J hope J haue iniured no man in writing. Jf I haue imitated any (as J denie not but J haue) J thinke in so doing, J haue rather honoured them than hurt them. For as J take it, it is an honour to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitated. VVhatsoeuer it is that J haue done, I referre it to thy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian courtesie, or thy courteous Christianitie to iudge. Iudge I pray thee the best: my purpose was not to offend thee, bee not thou offended with me. VVhat is giuen thee with the right hand to doe good with,
<pb facs="7"/>
take not thou with the left to doe hurt by: thou canst neuer heare too often of that thou maiest here reade of. Man is neuer so mindles of any thing, as of his owne death: for that cause God hath bidden thee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy end; some haue had those that haue put them in minde of their end, and I haue collected this as thou seest to direct thee to thy end. As thou dislikest not the marke that sheweth thee thy way, though it goes not with thee in the way, so dislike not of me for directing thee to death, though J go not with thee to death. <hi>Statutum est omnibus semel mori:</hi> It is appointed to all men to die once: and sure I am that therefore once J must die. <hi>Certius nil morte:</hi> Nothing more sure than
<pb facs="8"/>
death. VVhether thou or I shall soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest tread the track to death, is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to either vnknowne. <hi>Nescit homo finem suum:</hi> Man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not his end. And as that ancient writer saith: <hi>Mortis hora incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius nihil:</hi> Than the houre of death nothing more vncertaine. Jf thou goest before me, <hi>ego te sequar,</hi> J will, nay shall follow thee. Jf J goe before thee, assuredly thou canst not deny, but that thou must follow me. That we may goe both well when we goe, God giue vs grace to prepare thereto, and for ere wee goe: though it bee the last to vs in action, yet it ought to be the first with vs in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. First, because it is certaine it will come. Secondly, because it is vncertaine when it will come.
<pb facs="8"/>
Thirdly, because it is the greatest worke wee haue to doe when it doth come. Fourthly, because there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing but iudgement when it is come and gone. Js it euer amisse thinkest thou to be put in mind here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? If thou so thinkest, thou thinkest not right: the better shalt thou die, whensoeuer thou doest die, if oft thou beest made to remember thou must die. Seldome doth he die well, that thinks not oft to die once: and euer dies he ill, that neuer thinkes to die at all. Jf not therefore for curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, which thou wilt deigne many men, yet for Christianitie (which thou shouldest not denie any man) take it in gree, that thus J haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished thee. This if thou doest, J shall thinke my selfe beholding: if
<pb facs="9"/>
not, J must and will bee contented with that which is assigned. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer thou handlest me, God blesse thee whilest thou readest, that thou maist be blessed whē thou hast read, and when thou remembrest, that so thou maist be too when thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest. And thus for this once J bid thee farewell in Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord. <hi>W.P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>