<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HO∣NORABLE AND MOST VIRTVOVS LADY, the Lady Elizabeth Carey, wife to the thrise-noble, Sir George Carey, Knight Marshall, &amp;c. all prosperitie and happines.</title>
           <author>Playfere, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94747_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00565</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20015</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94747</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HO∣NORABLE AND MOST VIRTVOVS LADY, the Lady Elizabeth Carey, wife to the thrise-noble, Sir George Carey, Knight Marshall, &amp;c. all prosperitie and happines.</title>
                 <author>Playfere, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The meane in mourninge : A sermon preached at Saint Maryes Spittle in London on Tuesday in Easter weeke. 1595. By Thomas Playfere Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Playfere, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wise (Wythes), Andrew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND MOST VIRTVOVS LADY, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Carey,</hi> wife to the thrise-noble, Sir <hi>George Carey,</hi> Knight Marshall, &amp;c. all prosperitie and happines.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, it is reported that <hi>Demonax</hi> hauing his head broken with a stone, and being aduised to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to the Proconsull of that iniurie, answered that hee had more neede goe to a surgeon to heale his head, then to a Magistrate to redresse his wrong. I must also confesse, I had rather haue had my head broken, then my sermon so mangled. For this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hath been twise printed already without my procurement or priuitie any manner of way. Yea to my very great griefe and trouble. Neuertheles I haue
<pb facs="3"/>thought good to complaine of no man. For in whom the fault resteth I cannot learne certainely. This I am sure, not any whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in my selfe. <hi>Clinius</hi> a Historiographer, hauing written the story of <hi>Virginius,</hi> and meeting with him vpon a time saide, If you find any thing amisse in your story, I pray you pardon it. To whom <hi>Virginius</hi> answered, What <hi>Clinius,</hi> doest thou not know I haue done as I did, that such fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes as thou art, might write as you would? And so, it was my part, to take such paynes as conueniently I could, is furnishing and prouiding this sermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the appoynted time. But afterward what others, eyther by reporting or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting would make of it, that was not my fault, that was not in me either to helpe or hinder. Therefore I haue not gone vnto any Magistrate to complaine, but though it be one of the greatest iniuries that euer was offered mee, yet because I knowe not what secret purpose the Lord had in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this affliction vpon me, I doe most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pardon it. Yea, euen as <hi>Moyses,</hi> when the first tables were broken, was content to make new: in like manner, finding in the first editions so many bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-ended
<pb facs="3"/>sentences, I haue as it were gone to a surgeon, or rather in deede I haue played the surgeon my selfe, and by setting out the sermon a new, haue salued the matter as well as I could. <hi>Diogenes</hi> seeing the city of <hi>Myndus</hi> very little and poore, but the gate thereof very large and stately, sayd, You of <hi>Myndus,</hi> shut your gate, and keepe in your citie, that it runne not away. After the same sorte, the gate (as I may say) and the first entrance into this Sermon, was before very lofty and stately, the Sermon it selfe very simple and poore. Such a stirre they kept, in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it very vainely and most fondly, <hi>A most excellent Sermon,</hi> as if they would haue cast the house out of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or the citie out of the gate. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue made the gate lesser, and the citie greater. The gate lesser, by entitling it, <hi>The meane in Mourning,</hi> which is the very drift in deede, and the right scope of the whole Sermon. And the citie greater, by adding diuers notes, in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places of the Sermon, as I haue since thought best. So that if any which heard it preached be disposed to reade it, he shall not, I hope, altogether lose his labour. For
<pb facs="4"/>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>though hee haue all heere which he heard then, yet hee heard not all then, which he hath heere. But how it will please God to affect others I know not. This I wot well, that many a time and oft I haue beene much mooued my selfe with the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of some poyntes in this Sermon. And now of late, next to God and to his holy word, I could take comfort in nothing so much, as in reading that which I haue written in the seuenth part, the first secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. Occasioned thereto, by the certaine report of the death of my most deare father, who was well knowne, for his place and calling, to be as good a man, and as sincere a christian, as any hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this age. But for conclusion, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly desire your Ladiship, that as I haue dedicated the <hi>Pathway to Perfection</hi> to my very Honorable good patron, Sir <hi>George Carey:</hi> so it would please your Ladiship, to let this Sermon passe vnder the countenance and credit of your name. For if your Ladiship will deigne to reade it ouer, then I doubt not but diuers other Ladies &amp; Gentlewomen, which haue vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and noble mindes, will vouchsafe also to learne thereby, how they ought
<pb facs="6"/>with the daughters of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> not to weepe for Christ, but to weepe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. Especially, hauing such a singular ensample before their eyes as your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship is, whom God hath endued with al or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments &amp; gifts, both of nature &amp; grace.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Saint Iohns Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge
<date>the first day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary. <hi>1595.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Ladyships euer to be commaunded, Thomas Playfere.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>