<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honorable Sir Rebert Sydnie, Lord gouernour of Flushing, T. P. wisheth all increase of Honour, with the continuance of his house in that florishing estate wherein it is now established.</title>
           <author>Powell, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94769_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B07996</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20166.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94769</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honorable Sir Rebert Sydnie, Lord gouernour of Flushing, T. P. wisheth all increase of Honour, with the continuance of his house in that florishing estate wherein it is now established.</title>
                 <author>Powell, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Loues leprosie : The preface to the title. The leprosie yf phisicke bin approued, Achilles cure, because Achilles loued: the leprosie (saith Gordon) a disease, which on the child as yet vnborne doth sease, infectious and contagious, I could proue it is incurable, and so is loue. Loues leprosie according to her kinde, made him a leaper in a louers minde</title>
                 <author>Powell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honorable Sir Rebert Sydnie, Lord gouernour of Flushing, T. P. wisheth all increase of <hi>Honour, with the continuance of his</hi> house in that florishing estate wherein it is now established.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Knovv not (right Honorable) hovv to excuse this insinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine, in committing this vnballast Barke to the maine of your protection, considering that euerie little Riuer hath vvater enough to beare it from the ground: yet if the Ozean rage not (as in disdayne to support so vveake a vessell) I may accomplish the period of my desires, and by this voiage learne to correct my Compasse; if othervvise, this Barke conteyning all my fortunes, suffers vntimely ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvracke, and I banquerout of my infant hopes:
<q>
         <l>At tua supplicibus domus est assueta iuuandis,</l>
         <l>In quorum numero me praecor esse velis.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>There is a Sea interuenting the Hauen <hi>Aulis</hi> of
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Beotia</hi> and <hi>Eubaea,</hi> called <hi>Euripus;</hi> vvhich flovves vvith such violence, that it preuayles against the vvindes in maynteining full sayles displayed <hi>exad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerso:</hi> The same Sea (right Honorable) a true <hi>Idaea,</hi> resembles the Loue vvherevvith you imbrace the Muses sonnes in rescuing from the <hi>Phocian Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> the <hi>Pyerian</hi> queristers, vvhom headstronglust seekes to dishonour; I present to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppe the lucklesse loues of <hi>Achilles:</hi> vvhich if they may but gaine a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vievv in your iudiciall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, you shall buy my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at a high rate, and I thinke my selfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith bountifully revvarded.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordshippes officious in all dueties of humilitie,</hi> Tho. Povvell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>