<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           <author>Philodikaios, Irenicvs</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94721_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00559</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19881.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94721</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 <author>Philodikaios, Irenicvs</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise declaring, and confirming against all obiections the just title and right of the moste excellent and worthie prince, Iames the sixt : King of Scotland, to the succession of the croun of England. Wherevnto is added A discovrse shewing how necessarie it is for the realme of England, that he be in due time acknowledged and admitted to the succession of the kingdome</title>
                 <author>Philodikaios, Irenicus, pseudonym</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Hooper, Humphrey.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>SEING the great diuersitie of opinions, which is found in men of all Estates throughout this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, concerning the Royall succession, and fore-se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manifest danger of ciuill and forraine warres which thence are lyke to ensue, to the notable hurte and domage, if not to the vtter ruine of this noble Kingdome; except the subjects thereof bee in due time rightlie informed to whom by right the croun falleth, next after her Maiestie: I thought it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, being a member of one bodie with them trulie to informe so manie of them, as I might, concerning this matter, by publishing this treatise; wherein the right of the next lawfull successour is declared, and confirmed against all obiections. And for that I know it to be the opinion of sundry men, that in this present controuersie it is not onlie to be considered, to whom by right the croune appertaineth; but also whether his admission may be auailable or hurtfull to the common wealth: I thought good to adde to the saide declaration, &amp; defence of his right, a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course shewing howe necessarie and expedient it is for the common wealth, that hee be in due time ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and admitted to the succession of this Kingdome. Both which parts I haue brieflie hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, thinking it ynough to proue and confirme them with a competent number of weighty and forceable arguments, the rather for that the former part hath beene more at length declared and confirmed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in treatises alreadie published: and the other
<pb facs="3"/>
point is of it self so cleare and manifest, as fewer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons than I alledge may be sufficient for the certain proofe and euidencie therof. I hope, that you (my deare countrie-men) for whose instruction and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe I haue published this little pamphlet, will thankfully accept this my good meaning and honest endeuour, making your profite therof by embtacing and furthering so iuste and honorable a cause, as is heere recommended vnto you, and procuring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (together with your owne safetie and advantage) the peace, honour, &amp; prosperitie of this your natiue countrie. With which happie fore-sight beseeching God to indue you, I hartilie bid you fare-well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IRENICVS PHILODIKAIOS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>