<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my esteemed good Friend Mr. GYLBERT RO∣BARTES, all well wishes of true loue and contiuall happinesse.</title>
           <author>Roberts, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S948_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10814</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21087.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S948</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my esteemed good Friend Mr. GYLBERT RO∣BARTES, all well wishes of true loue and contiuall happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true relation of a most worthy and notable fight, performed the nineteenth day of Iune now last past : by two small shippes of the citie of London: the Vineyard of a hundred and twentie tunnes; and the Vnicorne of a hundred and fourtie tunnes, against sixe great gallies of Tunes, hauing in them a thousand and eight hundred men, of the ile of Way-yorcke in the Straights: our shippes hauing in all, mariners, merchants, and passengers, fifty sixe men. Written by H.R</title>
                 <author>H. R. (Henry Roberts)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>White, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Langley, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my esteemed good Friend M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> GYLBERT RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BARTES, all well wishes of true loue and contiuall happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our remote liuing from this famous Citie, old acquantance, and many lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing friends, cannot choose but increase a longing desire to heare such Newes as may beguile some time with contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating on them; but the vncertaintie of report for home-bred occasions are such, as makes me silent; yet to giue you some cause of admiration, and a good liking of men worthy, and most skilfull in their profession, I haue made bold to commende vnto you, the hardy and most dangerous Aduenture of two worthy Shippes of <hi>London,</hi> and their Companies in their last Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age for the <hi>Straights,</hi> made this passed Sommer, against Six great Gallies of the <hi>Turkes:</hi> wherein they shewed true vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and gallant resolution, gayning fame to them-selues, been a terrour to the enemie, and giuen a most worthy example for all of their coates: A pattorne worth recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for others to follow, a comfort to Owners, and Marchantes, that commit their Shippes and goods to such mens gouernment, and a ioy to all those that heare their deserued comendations; to the further view wherof I leaue you, &amp; pray God neuer to giue worse successe then they haue had, nor worseminds, then they haue shewed to be in them, but euer encrease, for our Countries honour the number of such, and keepe you and all others your good friends, for euer-more vnder his holy protection.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London</hi>
         <date>this 2. of Februarie 1616.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your louing friend euer yours,
Hen. Robarts</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>