<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY CHRISTIAN FRIENDS IN NOR∣wich, and theerabouts, Grace and salvation from the God and giver thereof.</title>
           <author>Robinson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S94919_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00623</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21115a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S94919</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY CHRISTIAN FRIENDS IN NOR∣wich, and theerabouts, Grace and salvation from the God and giver thereof.</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The peoples plea for the exercise of prophesie : Against Mr. Iohn Yates his monopolie. By Iohn Robinson</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Brewster, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Leiden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 77, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY CHRISTIAN <hi>FRIENDS IN NOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, and theerabouts, Grace and salvation from the God and giver thereof.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat loving and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remembrance, in which I alwaies haue you (my Christian friends) provoketh me as continually to commend unto God your welfare, so to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce greatly when I understand thereof, and specially that your soules doe prosper. And as the prosperity of the soule is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally furthered by the zealous preaching of the Gospell, so hath it been matter of unfained reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing unto me, to heare how God hath of late stirred up amongst
<pb facs="3"/>you, divers instruments, whose zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous indevours hee hath used that way, and covering in mercy what is evill (of ignorance &amp; infirmity on their parts (I hope) in their ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, &amp; ministrations, doth blesse what is of himselfe, to the good of his chosen. But as it falleth out in nature, that the pure waters draw of the tainture of the soyl through which they run; so with you it seemes, the pure truths of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell haue suffered by some, too great mixture with sundry Popish errours about the Church and ministery, in and by which they are propounded: and this more especially by M. <hi>Yates,</hi> a man of good gifts in himselfe, and note amongst you: pleading the cause of the Whoore of Babylon, the Church of Rome, as Christs wife, and of Antichrists cleargie, as of Christs ministery. And as this clergies exaltation is not a little
<pb facs="3"/>furthered by usurpatiō on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples liberty, which it swalloweth up, and thereby swelleth aboue proportion, so in all his pleading for the one, hee doth necessarily implead the other; and as in other things, so specially in the exercise of Prophesie, or teaching in the church by an ordinary gift; in which every one that is able brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his shot in due time and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for a ioynt feast of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly repast, the word of God.</p>
   <p>The Arguments in his writing (sent unto me by <hi>W. E.</hi> with his consent, and that before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate) I haue set down word for word, and answered: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with confirmed what I haue else where published in iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of this exercise against his exceptions and answers: which,
<note place="margin">In the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
      </note> being scattered here and there in his large discourse, and divers of them divers times repeated, I haue
<pb facs="4"/>collected, contracted, and set in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly oppsition to their contrary Arguments: and that without any the least wrong (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) unto him or his cause; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left out nothing in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which might seeme to bring advantage to his purpose.</p>
   <p>Now if any shall aske me, why I haue not rather answered M. <hi>Hall</hi> his large and learned volume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, and the generall cause which I professe, my reasons are, First, because it is a large volume so full farced by him, as it seemes, that he might prevent further answer. Secondly, his treatise is as much (and more immediately) against the Reformists, and their cause in the maine, as against us and ours. Thirdly, the truth requireth not that persons, but things be answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and thing in it know I none not answerd in my <hi>Defence</hi> against M. <hi>Bernard.</hi> Lastly, I doe put as
<pb facs="4"/>great difference between him and M. <hi>Yates,</hi> as between a word-wise Oratour, both labouring more, and being better able to feed his Reader with the leaues of words, &amp; flowers of Rhetorick, then with the fruits of knowledge, as also striving rather to oppresse the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of his adversary with false and proud reproches, then to convince his <hi>tenet</hi> by sound Arguments: and between a man sincerely zealous for the truth, and by his simple &amp; solid dealing by the Scriptures, as M. <hi>Yates</hi> doth, giving testimony of his unfained loue thereof. Which truth, my prayer to God is, that he, with my selfe, and all other so see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it, may find, and therein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in all things.</p>
   <p>And for you (my Christian friends) towards whom for your persons, I am minded even as when I lived with you, be you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished by me (which I also en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat
<pb facs="5"/>at the hands of the Lord on your behalfe) that you carefully beware, lest in any thing you fall from your stedfastnesse; but, on the contrary, grow in grace, and in the knowledge and obedience of the Lord Iesus in his whole revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will. And let me the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly exhort you hereunto, by how much the contrary evill is the more both dangerous &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. A man may fall forward, and in so doing, endanger his hands and face: but in falling backward, the danger is farre greater, as wee see in old <hi>Eli,</hi> of whom we read, that he <hi>fell backward, and his necke brake, and he died,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18. And how common a thing it is for men amongst you, and the whole land thorough, in their declining age, to decline in grace, wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth: there being few <hi>old Disciples</hi> to be found, vvho in their age do hold the same temper
<pb facs="5"/>of zeale and goodnesse which they had upon them in their yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger times: this being one maine reason thereof, That the meanes amongst you are farre more for conversion then preservation: and for birth, then nourishment: Whereas <hi>they</hi> (by the Lords graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dispensation in the orderly state of things) <hi>who are planted in the house of the Lord, in the Courts of our God, shall flourish, yea shall sprout in old age, and are fat and greene, to shew that the Lord is iust, and with him is none unrighteousnesse. Psalm.</hi> 92. Of this grace he vvho is the Authour and finisher of our faith, make both you and us partakers alwayes <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Robinson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>