<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Honou∣rable Sir Francis Walsin∣gham knight, principal Secretarie to her excellent Maiestie, and one of her highnesse priuie Counsell: Robert Some wisheth increase of Gods giftes by Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Some, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95257_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08102</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22910</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95257</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Honou∣rable Sir Francis Walsin∣gham knight, principal Secretarie to her excellent Maiestie, and one of her highnesse priuie Counsell: Robert Some wisheth increase of Gods giftes by Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Some, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie treatise of the church : Written by Robert Some. You shall finde in the ende of this booke, a treatise against oppression</title>
                 <author>Some, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Sir Francis Walsin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gham</hi> knight, principal Secretarie to her excellent Maiestie, and one of her <hi>highnesse priuie Counsell: Robert</hi> Some wisheth increase of Gods giftes by Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleased your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to fauour me both at, and since my wayting on my Lord and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, the Earle of Leycester in the Courte, I doe not forget your goodnes to me, and I thanke God very heartily, for your Honourable both care of, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Gods Churche and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is very cleere, that many are as friendlye to Gods trueth and Church, as the East winde is to the fruites of the earth: I neede not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb facs="3"/> particulers, for there are so greate store, and (as it were) swarmes of such, that if almighty GOD did not bridle them, as hee did Sanballat, the Arrabians, and the Ammonites in Nehemias time, and rayse vp excellent personages for the rearing vp of his Churche nowe, as hee did Ezra, Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Zorobabel, and Iehoshua, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the captiuitie of Babylon, Gods Church shoulde goe to wracke, and Religion shoulde bee handeled like a ward. But Gods Church is aliue, (thankes bee to GOD) howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wicked men doe make it eyther a faire marke to shoote at, or a dead carcase to feede vppon, and will outliue and outcountenance all eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies whatsoeuer. Almightie God to that ende hath blessed this noble Land in our time with an excellente Prince of our owne nation, (as he
<pb facs="3"/> did the Iewes with Zorobabel af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the captiuitie) and with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye notable personages vnder her Highnesse (as hee did the Israelites with Eliachim vnder Ezechias the king of Iuda.) Amongest whiche excellent personages, because your Honours place is greate in respect of the trust whiche is committed to you, and that GOD hath moued you to fauour mee, I doe present vnto you these my Treatises of the Churche, and against Oppression, as a sure argument of my duetifull mynde. My meaning is not to set downe the seuerall poyntes of this Booke, it were a needelesse labour, and you haue it in your handes to reade at your good pleasure and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
   <p>Thus with my heartie pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Almightye GOD for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of his good giftes in your
<pb facs="4"/> Honour, I take my leaue in most humble manner.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Queenes col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Cambridge <date>the first of Nouember. 1582.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honours <hi>to commaund</hi> Robert Some.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>