<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace from IESVS CHRIST the Prince of Peace.</title>
           <author>Smith, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95246_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08096</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22847.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95246</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace from IESVS CHRIST the Prince of Peace.</title>
                 <author>Smith, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great assize, or, Day of ivbilee : Deliuered in foure sermons vpon the 20. chapter of the Reuel. ver. 12. 13. 14. 15. Whereunto are annexed two sermons upon the 1. chapter of the Canticles, verse 6. 7 [sic] The second impression, corrected and amended by the authour Samuel Smith, minister of the word of God at Prittlewell in Essex</title>
                 <author>Smith, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 332, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace from IESVS CHRIST the <hi>Prince of Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, I present heere vnto thy view, the third pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique fruite of my Ministerie, wherein I haue endeuoured, that those especially of mine owne Hearers, might a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time take notice of my Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises, that in publike I deliuered vnto them. <hi>The night commeth
<pb facs="10"/> when no man can worke:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it stands vs all in hand, both Minister and People, to esteeme of <hi>Time</hi> as the most precious thing in the world; and the rather, because we know not how soone we shall be called to an account of our <hi>Works.</hi> Many haue had many times many good purposes of hart to cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, that haue beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by Death, for want of time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repentance. It shall then be our wisedome, <hi>To agree with our Aduersarie while wee are in the way with him;</hi> for if wee be but once arrested by Death, we shall be sure <hi>to pay the vtmost farthing.</hi> Vse this as a help vnto thee, to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee in the performance of that dutie which concerns thee so near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That thou must one day giue an accompt of thy Workes.</hi> If thou reape any benefit by it, giue the praise vnto God, <hi>from whom
<pb facs="10"/> euery good &amp; perfect gift pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth;</hi> and help me in thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which I shall take as a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of all my Labours, and be encoraged to spend some houres more in the like dueties for thy good. In the meane time I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the common Sauiour, SAMVEL SMITH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>