<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the deuout Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95235_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08095</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22811</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95235</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the deuout Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of the most honourable and vertuous lady the La. Magdalen Viscountesse Montague : Written in Latin, and published soone after her death, by Richard Smith, Doctour of Diuinity, and her confessour. And now translated into English, by C. F</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF THE AVTHOR to the deuout Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOSE auncient Fathers (deuout Reader) who by their writings, eyther gaue ornament to the Christian Religion, or defended it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst Heretikes, did also accustome to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to writing the liues of such pious women of their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as eyther by affinity, or familiarity were conioyned vnto them. Wherof, whosoeuer hath byn but indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">The cause of this Worke.</note> conuersant in the workes of <hi>S. Hierome, S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine, S. Gregory,</hi> or others, cannot be ignorant. For these most holy men vnderstood, that therby they did sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy theyr owne deuotion, gaue honest intermission to <note place="margin">We iudg vertues by the mind not by the sexe.</note> their grauer studies, praysed God in his Saintes, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by these examples induced others to piety. I imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their proceedings, though in a far meaner degree, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting for the present, my writing against our moderne Heretikes, (which also by enioyned employments, I was <note place="margin">Hier. de obit. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellae.</note> inforced to interrupt) haue vndertaken to write the lyfe of the right Vertuous Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> with whome I familiarly conuersed many yeares, and was her Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sour. <note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing.</note> In writing wherof, as I haue endeauoured to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd barbarous language, so haue I purposely abstayned
<pb facs="4"/> from the pleasing veyne of eloquence, &amp; the flourishes of Rhetorike. For as the one vseth to offend the eares of the Reader, and sometymes to auert him from reading the matter written: so the other by ouermuch delighting ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him lesse attentiue to the matter it selfe, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes makes him doubtfull of the truth therof. The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a chast Matrone ought to be as free from paynting as from vncleannes. Let those be adorned with wordes whose lyfe is not adorned with deeds. Our <hi>Magdalen</hi> doth so shine with Vertues, that she needeth not the splē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of a pleasing discourse. Yea rather, as she euer abstai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from painting, &amp; neuer made vse of a looking-glasse: so is it requisite that all vnnecessary flourish of speech be shunned in the description of her lyfe. My principall ayme shalbe at the truth, that I write nothing, but what <note place="margin">The fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this writing.</note> my selfe haue seene, or haue receyued from the mouth of this Lady her selfe, or of other witnesses worthy of credit: so that with <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writing the lyfe of <hi>S. Paula, I may call IESVS to witnes, and his Saints, &amp; the very Angell who was Guardian, and companion of this admirable Woman, that I speake nothing for fauour, nothing in flattering manner; but what I am to say, I speake as a testimony, and lesse then her merits.</hi> And that which may be a great satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to indifferent Readers, what I heere commit to writing, I vttered before a great audience at the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Lady <hi>Magdalen,</hi> her familiar acquaintance there present; and diuulging it within the space of 19. monthes after her death, if I lye, I may be disproued by the mouth, eyes, &amp; testimony of all that knew her; and especially of Heretikes, who sith they could not endure true glory to be attributed vnto her liuing, would lesse
<pb facs="4"/> permit false honour to be fayned on her, dead. Therfore their silence in this matter may be an assured testimony <note place="margin">That the liue so some pious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be writen.</note> vnto posterity of the truth of my discourse. But as I feare not calumniators of the truth, so do I desire to satisfy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who perhaps thinke that the liues only of such persons ought to be recorded, whose worthy Sanctity me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riteth that they be enrolled in the Catalogue of Saints. From the iudgment of these I cannot but dissent, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that not only the liues of <hi>S. Paula,</hi> and <hi>S. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cella,</hi> but also of <hi>Blesilla, Fabiola,</hi> and the like are wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">For exā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> by that most graue Father. <hi>S. Hierome;</hi> and the life of <hi>S. Monica</hi> by her Sonne <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> whiles he feareth that she was yet detayned in the paines of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. And with good reason; for as Gods power doth not only shine in the composition of the sunne and moone, but appeareth also in the fabrick of the lesser starres: so his heauenly grace doth not only giue a lustre in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of famous Saints, but shineth euen in the worth of euery pious person. Besides the sunne and moone, to haue added also starres vnto the heauēs, was not the least increase of their ornament; and so to record the liues of some pious people, wilbe some addition to the glory of God <note place="margin">For the honour of God.</note> and of his Church. And as men for the most part do ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther admire then clime the highest mountaynes, who yet by the lownes of little hilles are inuited to ascend: so, more doe commend, then imitate the vertues of famous Saints, who yet with no great difficulty ayme at the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of lesse vertuous persons. And vnto these I propose a woman, not famous for rudenesse of habit, or rigour of diet, or seuerity of discipline, or abnegation of the <note place="margin">For edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour.</note> world; but one that was humble, chast, meeke, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and pious, neither resplendent by miracles, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding
<pb facs="5"/> with vertues: so that they who despaire to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the admirable sanctity of <hi>S. Mary Magdalen,</hi> may see themselues capable to attaine the piety of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Viscountesse <hi>Montague.</hi> Neither yet doe I enrole her in the number of Saints, or the Blessed: Mine intention is only for the glory of God, &amp; edification of my neyghbour, sincerely to commend her lyfe to writing; whether she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued the opinion of sanctity, let others iudge. Thus much (deuout Reader) I desired to premonish thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou takest in hand, the reading of the lyfe of our <hi>Magdalen.</hi> Make thou the benefit thereof, and fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>