<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95203_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12198</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22508.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95203</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules conflict with it selfe, and victory over it self by faith : A treatise of the inward disquietments of distressed spirits, with comfortable remedies to establish them. By R. Sibbs D.D. Master of Katherine Hall in Cambridge, and Preacher of Grayes Inne London</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 572, 22 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be two sorts of people alwaies in the visible Church. One that Satan keepes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with false peace, whose life is nothing but a diversion to pre sent contentments, and a running away from God and their owne hearts, which they know can speake no good unto them; these speake peace to themselves, but God speakes none. Such have nothing to doe with this</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>the way for these men to enjoy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, is to be soundly troubled. True peace arises from knowing the worst first, &amp; then our freedome from it. It is a miserable peace that riseth from ignorance of evill. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> troubled the waters, <hi>and then cured</hi>
      <note place="margin">John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>:</note>
      <hi>those that stept in. It is Christs manner, to trouble our soules first, and then to come with healing in his wings.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But there is another sort of people, who</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>being drawen out of</hi> Satans <hi>kingdome, and within the Covenant of grace, whom</hi> Satan <hi>labours to unsettle and disquiet: being the</hi> God of the world, <hi>he is vexed to see men in the world, walke</hi> above <hi>the world. Since he cannot hinder their estate, he will trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their peace, and dampe their spirits, and cut a sunder the sinewes of all their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. These should take themselves to taske as</hi> David <hi>doth here, and labour to maintain their portion, and the glory of a Christian profession. For whatsoever is in God or comes from God, is for their comfort.</hi> Him selfe <hi>is the God of comfort; his</hi> Spirit <hi>most knowne by that office. Our blessed Saviour was so carefull that his</hi> Disciples <hi>should not be too much deiected, that he forgat his own bitter passion to comfort them, whom yet he knew would all forsake him:</hi> Let not your hearts be troubled <hi>saith he. And his owne soule was troubled to death, that we should not be troubled:</hi> whatsoever is written is written for this end; <hi>every article of</hi> faith <hi>hath a speciall influence in comforting a beleeving soule. They are not onely food, but cordials: Yea he put himselfe to his</hi> Oath, <hi>that we might not onely have</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>but strong</hi> Consolation. <hi>The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments seale unto us all the comforts wee have by the death of Christ; the exercise of Religion, as</hi> Prayer, Hearing, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. <hi>is that</hi> our joy may be full: <hi>the</hi> Communion of Saints <hi>is chiefly ordained to</hi> comfort the feeble minded, <hi>and to</hi> strengthen the weake. <hi>Gods government of his Church tends to this. Why doth hee sweeten our pilgrimage, and let us see so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny comfortable dayes in the world, but that we should serve him with cheerefull and good hearts? As for crosses, he doth but cast us downe, to raise us up, and empty us that hee may fill us, and melt us, that we may bee</hi> vessels of glory, <hi>loving us as well in the furnace, as when we are out, and standing by us all the while.</hi> We are troubled, but not distressed; perplexed, but not in <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> despaire; persecuted, but not forsaken. <hi>If wee consider from what</hi> fatherly love <hi>afflictions come, how they are not only moderated, but sweetned and sanctified in the issue to us, how can it but minister mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of comfort in the greatest seeming discō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts? How then can we let the reines of our affections loose to sorow without being inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>to God and his providence? as if wee would teach him how to govern his Church?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>What unthankfulnesse is it to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our consolation, and to looke only upon matter of grievance: to thinke so much upon two or three crosses as to forget a hundred blessings? To suck poyson out of that, from which we should suck honey? What folly is it to straighten and darken our owne spirits? And indispose our selves for doing or taking good? A limbe out of ioynt can doe nothing without deformity and paine; deiection takes off the wheeles of the soule.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of all other, Satan hath most advantage of discontented persons, as most agreeable to his disposition, being the most discontented creature under heaven; He hammers all his darke plots in their braines. The discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the</hi> Israelires in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, <hi>provoked God to</hi> sweare, <hi>that</hi> they <note place="margin">Ps. 95. ult.</note> should never enter into his rest. <hi>There is</hi> another spirit in my servant Caleb <hi>saith God; the spirit of Gods people is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageing spirit. Wisdome teaches them if they feele any grievances to conceale them from others that are weaker, least they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>disheartned. God threatens it as a</hi> curse <hi>to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deu 28. 65</note>
      <hi>give a</hi> trembling heart <hi>and</hi> sorrow of minde; <hi>whereas on the contrary</hi> joy <hi>is as oyle to the soule, it makes duties come off cheerefully and sweetly from our selves, gratiously to others, and acceptably to God. A</hi> Prince <hi>cannot indure it in his subiects, nor a Father in his children to be lowring at their presence. Such usually have stollen wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to delight themselves in.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>How many are there that upon the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace that followes Religion, are frighted from it? But what are discouragements, to the incouragements Religion brings with it? which are such as the very Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves admire at. Religion indeede brings crosses with it, but then it brings comforts</hi> above <hi>those crosses. What a dishonour is it to Religion to conceive that God will not maintaine and honour his followers? as if his service were not the best service; what a shame is it for an heire of heaven to be cast downe for every pety losse and crosse: To bee afraid of a man whose breath is in his nos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trils,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tua praesen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Domine Laurentio ipsam crati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culam dulcē fecit.</note>
      <hi>in not standing to a good cause, when we are sure God will stand by us, assisting and comforting us, whose presence is able to</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>make the greatest torments sweete.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>My discourse tends not to take men off from all griefe and mourning;</hi> Light for the righteous is sowen in sorrow: <hi>Our state of absence from the Lord, and living here in a vail of teares, our daily infirmities, and our sympathy with others, requires it; and where most grace is there is most sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness, as in Christ. But we must distinguish between griefe and that fullennesse and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of spirit, which is with a repining and taking off from duty; when</hi> Joshua <hi>was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch cast down at Israels turning their backs before their enemies, God reproves him,</hi> Get thee up Joshua, why liest thou <note place="margin">Judg. 7. 10.</note> upon thy face?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Some would have men after the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of grosse sinne to be presently comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and</hi> beleeve <hi>without humbling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves at all; indeed when we ore once in Christ, we ought not to question our state in him, and if we doe, it comes not from the spirit: But yet a guilty conscience will be clamorous and full of obiections, &amp; God will not speake peace unto it till it be humbled. God will let his best children know what it is to be too bold with sinne, as we see in</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>who felt no peace till they had renued their repentance: The way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce</hi> with joy unspeakable and glorious, <hi>is to stirre up fighs</hi> that cannot be uttered. <hi>And it is so farre, that the knowledge of our state in grace should not humble us, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ingenuity cōsidering Gods love to us, out of the nature of the thing it self workes sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and shame in us, to offend his Maiesty.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>One maine stop that hinders Christians from reioycing, is, that they give themselves too much liberty to question their grounds of comfort and interest in the promises. This is wonderfull cōfortable say they, but what is it to me? the promise belōgs not to</hi> me. <hi>This ariseth from want of giving all</hi> diligence <note place="margin">2 Pet. 10.</note> to make their calling sure <hi>to themselves. In watchfulnesse and diligence we sooner meet with comfort thē in idle complaining. Our care therefore should be to get sound</hi> evidence <hi>of a good estate, and then like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to keepe our</hi> evidence cleare; <hi>wherein we are not to hearken to our own feares and doubts, or the suggestion of our enemy, who studies to falsifie our</hi> evidence: <hi>but to the</hi> Word, <hi>and our owne consciences inlightned by the spirit: and then it is pride and pettish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>to stand out against comfort to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Christians should studie to corrobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate their title: We are never more in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, before we come thither, then when wee can read our evidences: It makes us converse much with God, it sweetens all conditions, and makes us willing to doe and suffer any thing. It makes us have comfortable and honourable thoughts of our selves, as too good for the service of any base lust, and brings confidence in God both in life and death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But what if our condition be so darke, that we cannot reade our evidence at all?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Here looke up to Gods infinite mercy in Christ, as we did at the first when we found no goodnesse in our selves, and that is the way to recover whatsoever we thinke wee have lost. By honouring Gods mercy in Christ, we come to have the Spirit of Christ; therefore when the waters of sanctification are troubled and muddy, let us runne to the witnesse of</hi> blood. <hi>God seemes to walke sometimes contrary to himselfe; he seemes to discourage, when secretly he doth incourage, as the</hi> woman of Canaan; <hi>but faith can finde out these wayes of God, and untie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>se</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>knots, by looking to the free promise and mercifull nature of God. Let our sottish and rebellious flesh murmure as much as it will,</hi> who art thou? and what is thy worth? <hi>Yet a Christian</hi> knowes whom hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves. Faith <hi>hath learned to set God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Againe, we must goe on to</hi> adde grace to grace. <hi>A growing and fruitfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, is alwayes a comfortable Christian; the oyle of</hi> grace <hi>brings forth the oyle of</hi> gladnesse. <hi>Christ is first a King of</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse, <hi>and then a King of</hi> peace; <hi>the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 2.</note>
      <hi>righteousnesse that hee workes by his Spirit brings a peace of</hi> sanctification, <hi>whereby though we are not freed from sinne, yet we are enabled to combate with it, &amp; to get the victory over it. Some degree of comfort fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes every good action, as heate accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies fire, and as beames and influences issue from the</hi> Sunne; <hi>which is so true, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Heathens <hi>upon the discharge of a good conscience, have found comfort and peace answerable; this is a reward before our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Praemium ante praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Another thing that hinders the comfort of Christians is, that they forget what a</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>gratious and mercifull covenant they live under, wherein, the perfection that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired is to be found in Christ. Perfection in us is sincerity: What is the end of</hi> faith <hi>but to bring us to Christ? Now imperfect faith, if sincere, knits to Christ, in whom our perfection lies.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Gods designe in the covenant of grace, is to exalt the riches of his mercy, above all sinne and unworthinesse of man; and wee yeeld him more glory of his mercy by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, then it would be to his Iustice to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy us. If we were perfect in our selves, we should not honour him so much, as when we labour to bee found in Christ, having his righteousnesse upon us.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>There is no one portion of Scripture oftner used to fetch up drooping spirits then this,</hi> Why art thou cast downe oh my soule? <hi>it is figurative, and full of Rhetorique, and all little enough to perswade the perplexed soule, quietly to</hi> trust in God; <hi>which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this retiring into our selves and check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our hearts, wil never be brought to passe.</hi> Chrysostome <hi>brings in a man loaden with</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>it in Gen.</note>
      <hi>troubles, comming into the</hi> Church, <hi>where when he heard this passage read, he presently</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>recovered himselfe, and becomes another man. As</hi> David <hi>therefore did acquaint himselfe with this forme of dealing with his soule, so let us, demanding a reason of our selves</hi> Why wee are cast downe; <hi>which will at least checke and put a stoppe to the distresse, and make us fit to consider more so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid grounds of true comfort.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of necessity the soule must bee somthing calmed and staid before it can be comforted. Whilest the humours of the body rage in a great distemper, there is no giving of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke: So when the soule gives way to passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is unfit to entertaine any counsell, therefore it must be stilled by degrees, that it may heare reason; and sometimes it is fitter to be moved with ordinary reason, (as being more familiar unto it) then with higher reasons fetcht from our supernaturall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Christ, as from the condition of mans nature subject to changes, from the uncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse of yeelding to passion for that, which it is not in our power to mend, &amp;c. these and such like reasons have some use to stay the fit for a while, but they leave the coar untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which is</hi> sinne, <hi>the trouble of all troubles. Yet when such considerations are made spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>by</hi> faith <hi>on higher grounds, they have some operation upon the soule, as the influence of the</hi> Moone <hi>having the stronger influence of the</hi> Sun <hi>mingled with it, becomes more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall upon these inferiour bodies. A candle light being ready at hand, is sometimes as use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as the Sun it selfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But our maine care should be to have</hi> Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall <hi>grounds of comfort, neere to us, as</hi> Reconciliation with God, <hi>whereby all things else are reconciled unto us,</hi> Adoption and Communion with Christ, &amp;c. <hi>which is never sweeter then under the Crosse.</hi> Philip Lansgrave <hi>of</hi> Hesse, <hi>being a long time pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner under</hi> Charles the fifth, <hi>was demanded what upheld him all that time, Who answered that</hi> hee felt the divine comforts of the Martyrs: <hi>there be</hi> divine comforts <hi>which</hi>
      <note place="margin">Respondit, divinas consolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum se sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisse.</note>
      <hi>are felt under the</hi> Crosse, <hi>and not at other times,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Besides personall troubles, there are many much dejected with the present state of the Church, seeing the blood of so many Saints to be shed, and the enemies oft to prevaile; but God hath stratagems, as</hi> Joshua, <hi>at</hi> Ay; <hi>he seemes sometimes to retire that he may come upon his enemies with the greater advantage;</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>the end of all these troubles will no doubt be the ruine of the Antichristian faction; and we shall see the Church in her more perfect beauty; when the enmies shall be in that place which is fittest for them, the</hi> lowest, <hi>that is, the</hi> footstoole of Christ; <hi>the Church as it is highest in the favour of God, so it shall be highest in it selfe.</hi> The mountaine of the Lord shall bee exalted above all moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. <hi>In the worst condition, the Church hath two faces: One towards heaven and Christ, which is alwaies constant and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Another toward the world, which is in appearance contemptible and changeable. But God will in the end give her beauty for ashes, and glory double to her shame: and she shall in the end prevaile; in the meane time, the power of the enemies is in Gods hand:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Robur ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stium apud Deum.</note>
      <hi>The Church of God conquers when it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered: even as our Head Christ did, who overcame by patience as well as by power. Christs victory was upon the Crosse. The Spirit of a Christian conquers, when his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is conquered.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The way is, in stead of discouragement, to search al the promises made to the Church in these latter times, and to turne them into</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>prayers, and presse God earnestly for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them. Then we shall soone find God both</hi> cursing <hi>his enemies, and</hi> blessing <hi>his people out of</hi> Zion, <hi>by the faithfull pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that ascend up from thence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In all the</hi> promises <hi>we should have spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall recourse to God in them. In all storms there is Sea roome enough in the infinite goodness of God, for faith to be carried with full saile.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And it must be remembred that in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where God is mentioned, we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand God in the promised</hi> Messiah, <hi>ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified out so many waies unto us. And to put the more vigor into such places in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, we in this latter age of the Church must thinke of God shining upon</hi> us <hi>in the face of Christ, and</hi> our <hi>Father in him. If they had so much confidence in so little light, it is a shame for us not to be confident in good things when so strong a light shines round about us; when we professe we beleeve</hi> a crowne of righteousnesse is laid up for all those that love his appearing. <hi>Presenting these things to the soul by</hi> faith, <hi>setteth the soule in such a pitch of resolution, that no discouragements are able to seise</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>upon it.</hi> We faint not <hi>saith</hi> S. Paul, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth he not faint? because</hi> these light and short afflictions procure an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding weight of glory.</p>
   <p>Luther <hi>when he saw</hi> Melancthon <hi>a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; learned man too much dejected for the state of the Church in those times, fals a chiding of him, as</hi> David <hi>doth here his own soule,</hi> I strongly hate those miserable <note place="margin">Ego miserri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas curas, quibus te consumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribis, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementer odi. Quod sic regnat in corde tuo, non est mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sae, sed ma gnitudo in credulitatis nostrae. Si causa salsa est, revoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Si ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, cur faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus illum tantis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacem; I u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> contra teipsum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stem.</note> cares, <hi>saith he,</hi> whereby thou writest thou art even spent. It is not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the cause, but the greatnesse of the incredulity. If the cause be false let us revoke it. If true, why doe wee make God in his rich promises a lyar? Strive against thy selfe, the greatest e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie; why doe we feare the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red world, that have the conquerour himselfe on our side.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now to speake something concerning the publishing of this Treatise. I began to preach on the Text about twelue yeares since in the</hi> City, <hi>and afterwards finished the same at Grayes-Inne. After which, some having gotten imperfect notes, endeavoured to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish them without my privity. Therefore to doe my selfe right, I thought fit to reduce</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>them to this forme: There is a pious and studious gentleman of Grayes-Inne, that hath of late published observations upon the whole</hi> psalme; <hi>and another upon this very</hi> verse <hi>very well; and many others by Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises of</hi> faith <hi>and such like, have furthered the spirituall peace of Christians much. It were to be wished that we would all joyne to doe that which the Apostle gloried in,</hi> to be helpers of the joy of Gods people. <hi>By</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. ult.</note>
      <hi>reason of my absence, while the worke was in printing, some sentences were mistaken. Some will be ready to deprave the labours of other men; but so good may be done, let such ill disposed persons be what they are, and what they will be unlesse God turne their hearts: and so I commend thee and this poore Treatise to Gods blessing.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>GRAYES INNE, July. 1. 1635.</p>
   <p>R. SIBBES.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>