<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS Apologie to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Timothy</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S953_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10976</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21245</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS Apologie to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Timothy</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The righteous mans euidences for heauen. Or A treatise shewing how euery one, while hee liues heere, may certainely know what shall become of him after his departure out of this life. The sixt edition, corrected and inlarged. By Tymothy Rogers, preacher of Gods word in Essex</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Timothy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 297, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS Apologie to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Arre was it frō my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the first, Christiā Reader, thus to haue exposed my selfe to the common view of men, but rather to haue hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="3"/>
this my weake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception for euer, neuer to haue come to the birth: but when it would abide no longer, to bee imprisoned in the womb, but violently brake forth, I thought to deale wisely with it, though not (as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi>) cruelly to murther it, yet at least (as <hi>Moses</hi> his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) charitably to hide it, for my own priuat vse: or at the best to haue put it to Nurse in an obscure Country-village, where my selfe am Pastor, to see the good vsage of it; for which end I be-trusted a
<pb facs="3"/>
friend or two, for the printing of some few, copies, onely for my selfe: but through friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship I was deceiued: for whereas I expected a small number, like the children of <hi>Israel,</hi> that went against <hi>Benhadad,</hi> like two little flocks of Kids: My bookes were sent forth in multitudes, like the <hi>Aramites</hi> that fill'd the country. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.27. Onely this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, they came not forth against the host of <hi>Israel,</hi> the people of God, (as did the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi>) but rather to serue
<pb facs="4"/>
on their side. Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driuen to a straight, (though that which is done, can not bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done) yet I thought it my part to doe what I could, namely, to mend, and inlarge that which is done; that seeing it must bee common, it may not be altogether vn-vsefull: Confessing ingenuously, I had rather it should not haue bin common; especially considering, that there are better bred and nobler borne Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises of very worthy men, concerning this subiect; but thus it must
<pb facs="4"/>
bee now: if therefore it may but serue as an hand-maid to theirs, so thou mayest reape some profit hereby, I haue both my desire, and full contentment. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the bond of Faith and Loue, <hi>Timothy Rogers.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>