<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle of the Com∣missarie Generall. THE EPISTLE OF THE Reuerend Father, Frater PETER GONZALIS, Commissarie Gene∣rall of the whole order of our holy Father S. FRANCIS, in his fami∣lie, on this side the Alpes, vnto all the Prouincialls in Generall, but especially of Spaine.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95388_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B08135</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23212</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95388</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle of the Com∣missarie Generall. THE EPISTLE OF THE Reuerend Father, Frater PETER GONZALIS, Commissarie Gene∣rall of the whole order of our holy Father S. FRANCIS, in his fami∣lie, on this side the Alpes, vnto all the Prouincialls in Generall, but especially of Spaine.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of penance : vvith an explication of the rule, and maner of liuing, of the brethren and sisters, of the third order of S. Frauncis; commonly called, of the order of penance, ordayned for those which desire to liue holilie [sic] and doe penance in their owne houses. By F. W.S. Strict. Obser. Wherevnto is added, the epistle and annotations vpon this rule, of the reuerend father, Fa. Peter Gonzales, Commissarie General. With a catalogue made by him, of the names of the chiefe persons of this order, aswell canonized saincts, as beatified, with the other honorable and worthy persons, who for their vertuous deeds, and holinesse of life, are cronacled to their perpetuall memory here in earth, and no doubt to thier euerlasting glorie in heauen</title>
                 <author>Stanney, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 97, 100-148, 189-198, 180-181, 202-498, 66 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>The Epistle of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missarie Generall. <hi>THE EPISTLE OF THE</hi> Reuerend Father, Frater <hi>PETER GONZALIS,</hi> Commissarie Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the whole order of our holy Father S. <hi>FRANCIS,</hi> in his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, on this side the Alpes, vnto all the Prouincialls in Generall, but especially of Spaine.</head>
   <opener>
      <signed>FRater PETER GONZALES, of Mendoza, Commissarie generall, of the order of our holy Father S. FRANCIS, in this Familie of Cismontana,</signed>
      <salute>to all the Reuerend Father Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Ministers of the same, health and peace in our Lord</salute>
   </opener>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <p>Forasmuch as in the last ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Chapter, helde at <hi>Tolledo, Anno Dom.</hi> 1606. It was ordained, that the third order, which our Seraphical Father, S. FRANCIS did institut, aswel for married, as single persons, should be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. And that it should be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to be instituted and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued in the Prouinces of the Crowne of <hi>Castile,</hi> to the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that which is kept al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie in <hi>Arogone.</hi> And finally, that there should bee no lesse knowledge of his holy Rule in any parte of <hi>Spaine,</hi> then there is in many other partes of the worlde. And that the deuout Christians, might not loose so many spiritual fruits, as may be gained by the obseruance of this Rule, and the graces of so many Popes graunted vnto it,
<pb facs="14"/> VVherefore that this ordinance of the generall Chapter, may be fulfilled and put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with all diligence; VVe send vnto all you (most Reuerend Fathers) a copie of the said Rule, with some notes and aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which vve haue thought necessarie, for the better keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and obseruing of the saide Rule, beseeching all your Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and for the more encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of your merits. VVee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, by the vertue of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obedience, that vvith all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, you cause the said Rule to bee published in the tovvnes of your Prouinces, and especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvhere there is any conuent, and that you giue order vnto the venerable Father Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they be very carefull to establish and conserue this so holy a Rule. And also to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="14"/> Preachers, and Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, to perswade all deuout per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons vnto it, both in publike and secreete. And in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that it be published in the tovvnes vvhere there is no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasterie of Fryers or Nunnes. And that they vse all the best meanes they can, that so great a good be not lost, commanding it to the Religious Fathers, vvho shall go thither to preach, heare confessions; And in all the Conuents, let there be a booke vvherein may be vvritten the names of all such as shall enter into this Religion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>t their profession be set dovvne vnder the hands of him vvho made it, &amp; the superiors who did assist it: vvhich booke ought to remaine in the custodie of that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous person vvithin euery Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, must be be named by the
<pb facs="15"/> Reuerend Father Prouinciall, for the Confessors of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of this order, that he may assist vvith them in the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings vvhich the rule requireth. VVe declare moreouer, that if any of them haue deuotion and desire to make his confession to some other, let him not be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. <hi>Dated in our Conuent of</hi> Madrid, <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>of August.</hi> 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Fr. PETER GONZALES of <hi>Mendoza,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missarie generall.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>