<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95612_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00812</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24416</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dialogue philosophicall : VVherein natures secret closet is opened, and the cause of all motion in nature shewed, out of matter and forme, tending to mount mans minde from nature to supernaturall and celestiall promotion: and how all things exist in the number of three. Together with the wittie inuention of an artificiall perpetuall motion, presented to the Kings most excellent Maiestie. All which are discoursed betweene two speakers, Philadelph, and Theophrast, brought together by Thomas Tymme, Professour of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Knight, Clement.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Almighty Creatour of the Heauens and the Earth, (Christian Reader) hath set before our eyes two most principall Bookes: the one of Nature, the other of his written Word. By these we know that, God was before all times, infinitely one, comprehending all things that now be, in himselfe: and being the beginning of Time, created those things in number, measure, and waight, adorning his worke most wonderfully with these three Instruments, as with the first Formes. And formed thus this vniuersall frame after the similitude of Vnitie, in circular compasse, in pure and meere simplicitie.</p>
   <p>The wisedome of Natures booke, men commonly call <hi>Naturall Philosophie,</hi> which serueth to allure to the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of that great and incomprehensible God, that wee might glorifie him in the greatnesse of his worke. For the ruled Motions of the Orbes: the wonderfull workmanship of so many starrie Tents: the connexion, agreement, force, vertue, and beauty of the Elements: the scituation, firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and spreading of the Earth amidst the waters: and so many sundry natures and creatures in the world, are so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie interpreters to teach vs, that God is the efficient cause of them, and that he is manifested in them, and by them, as their finall cause to whom also they tend. Yea, the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Motions which belong to all creatures, euen to Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, casting their rootes downewards, and their sprouts vpwards, doe therein set forth the power and wisedome of the omnipotent Creator. But the Mirrour wherein we may
<pb facs="4"/>yet better behold God, is Man, a little World, in whom shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and is imprinted a Diuine Essence, the like whereof is not to be found in any visible creature besides. How ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie is it then, for men to consider the workes of God in his creatures? And how much more necessarie is it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde their owne person and nature, wherein there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most as many meruailous workes of God, as there are in the whole frame besides? For what will it profit a man to measure the Vniuersall: to compasse the whole Elementarie Region: to know the things in them, and their nature: and in the meane time to be ignorant of himselfe? For albeit, a generall knowledge of all the creatures of this visible world, will greatly helpe to leade man to the knowledge of God the Creator, yet he shall neuer be able to know him well, if with all he know not himselfe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plato</hi> searching by the meanes of Motion, what was the substance, nature, and immortalitie of mans Soule, attained to the vnderstanding of the Diuine Essence. <hi>Aristotle</hi> also taking the same way, acknowledgeth that he knew God vnder the name of the first Mouer, who is perpetuall and immoueable. But the wisedome Supernaturall, called <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> reuealed in the written word of God, being farre more excellent then all naturall <hi>Philosophie,</hi> sublimeth our spirits, through the light of the diuine Spirit, to mount (as it were) by <hi>Iacobs ladder,</hi> with Phoenix wings, from the things of Nature to Celestiall and Diuine things, whereby we haue a light and bright vnderstanding.</p>
   <p>If man had not sinned, the booke of <hi>Nature</hi> would haue sufficed to haue kept him alwaies in the knowledge &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of God his Creator. For then he should himselfe haue carried that Booke whole &amp; perfect, imprinted in his heart and minde, neither should his Soule haue needed any other Teacher to know it selfe; but it selfe should haue clearely beheld and contemplated it selfe so long as she preferred and preserued her first light, wherein God had created her. But now that she is in the body as it were some excellent
<pb facs="4"/>picture of <hi>Apelles,</hi> fallen into a sinke of mire, couered and compassed about with thicke mistes and obscure darknesse, it is very needefull that we should haue another new light brought to vs from Heauen, not naturall, as the first, but su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall. For this cause God hath giuen vs his sacred Booke, by meanes whereof, as also by his holy spirit, hee communicateth to vs as much heauenly light as is needfull for the knowledge of our selues, and of his high Maiestie.</p>
   <p>Now (Christian Reader) because all things liue, moue, and haue their being in God, a fire most pure &amp; simple, and a light inacceslible, (from whom that subtill fire which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrateth into euery thing, and is the cause of all motion, proceedeth, and hath originall,) I haue compiled this <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> discoursing naturall Philosophie, that thereby thou mayest not onely pry into Nature, but also throughly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the cause and beginning thereof to be in God. And for that rare things moue much, I haue thought it pertinent to this Treatise, to set before thee a most strange and wittie inuention of another <hi>Archimedes,</hi> which concerneth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall perpetuall motion, immitating Nature by a liuely pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of the Instrument it selfe, as it was presented to the Kings most royall hands, by <hi>Cornelius Drebble</hi> of Alchmar in Holland, and entertained according to the worthinesse of of such, a gift my paines herein bestowed and intended for thy profit and pleasure, if it seeme but as Iron, yet let it serue for the Forge and Anuile of good conceit, if the discourse seeme rough, shaddow it I pray thee with the curtaine of smooth excuse: but if it be found of thee as Bullion, fit for the Mint, and currant for the stampe, then grace it with the golden approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Touch</hi> and <hi>Teste.</hi> So shall I rest thine during life,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Tymme.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>