<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults escaped.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95630_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00820</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24508.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95630</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults escaped.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe replie : of Thomas Udall, gent. to a short memorandum, or shew of answere against his booke intituled: A briefe view of the weake grounds of poperie: by B.C. student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Udall, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 47, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <p>Good Reader, let me request thy fauourable censure touching the faults committed by the Printer, which escaped by reason of my absence at the time of the printing, and partly by the difficulty of the hand in the Coppie: all which I pray thee first take notice of, as they are set downe here following and then read in their due places, as they are heere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and corrected.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Faults escaped.</head>
      <p>IN the Preface pag. <hi>3.</hi> line last, for fellowes read followers. p. <hi>5.</hi> l. <hi>13.</hi> there for Questions, r. quotations. l. <hi>17.</hi> for them r. then. l. <hi>18.</hi> for them. r. thee.</p>
      <p>Pag. <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> for I haue yet made you r. you haue yet made, p. <hi>6</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> for may be borrowed. r. may be he borrowed, p. <hi>8.</hi> l. <hi>14.</hi> for But is it a iust difference. r. But it is a nice difference, li. <hi>23.</hi> for blasphemie maintained is, r. Bohemians maintained, p. <hi>14.</hi> l. <hi>19.</hi> for whence r. whom, p. <hi>16.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> for receiueth r. recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. p. <hi>18.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> after the word Pope adde these wordes, who are very many, p. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>27.</hi> for I do r. I owe. p. <hi>31.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> for conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence r. consequentes p. <hi>34.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> for receiued r. reiected.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>In the Margent</head>
      <p>Pag. <hi>8.</hi> l. <hi>18.</hi> Doct. Downam against Antich. l. <hi>5.</hi> Sect. <hi>10.</hi> omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. p. <hi>11.</hi> for Heric. Magist. r. Heric. doctor Magist. p. <hi>14.</hi> for Salu. sempit. r. sacr. script. for de sar. de sacram. p. <hi>21.</hi> Greg. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>291.</hi> placed in the margent to no purpose. p. <hi>27.</hi> this quotation Prefac. synod Trul. ad Iustin. should be placed <hi>2.</hi> lines higher. Many of which the carefull reader I hope will easily obserue and pardon.</p>
   </div>
   <pb facs="30"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>