<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOrable George, Marquesse of Buckingham, Viscount Villiers, Barron of Whaddon, Master of his Maie∣sties Horse, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, and one of his most honourable Priuie COVNCELL.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95654_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14307</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24624</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOrable George, Marquesse of Buckingham, Viscount Villiers, Barron of Whaddon, Master of his Maie∣sties Horse, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, and one of his most honourable Priuie COVNCELL.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cantus. The first set: beeing songs of divers ayres and natures : of fîue and sixe parts: apt for vyols and voyces. Newly composed by Thomas Vautor, batcheler of musicke</title>
                 <author>Vautor, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>cantus, 4, xxii, that is xxiii), 1 page, altus, 4, xxii, that is xxiii), 1 page, tenor, 4, xxii, that is xxiii), 1 page, bassus, 4, xxii, that is xxiii), 1 page, quintus, 4, xxii, that is xxiii), 1 page, sextus, 4, xvii-xxii, that is xxiii), 1 page, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<seg rend="sup">rable</seg>
      <hi>George,</hi> Marquesse of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Viscount <hi>Villiers,</hi> Barron of <hi>Whaddon,</hi> Master of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Horse, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, Gentleman of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, and one of his most honourable Priuie COVNCELL.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O infinite is Loue in operation, and so forcible are the faculties of the Soule, as beside mute respects of dutie and seruice, they will neuer rest without reall remonstrance of actuall fruites, which I (my right noble Lord) hauing beene an indiuiduall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant of your no lesse noble Mothers house and name, and a religious obseruant of your owne heroique and hopefull vertues, from your Cradle, do humbly present as a tribute of my deuotion, to your fauourable entertainment and protection, these few Songs, whereof some were composed in your tender yeares, and in your most worthy Fathers house, (from whom, and your most honourable Mother, for many yeares I receiued part of my meanes and liuelyhoode) which hath the rather emboldened mee, with many other more neere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, to intreat your Honour to let them passe vnder your gracious fauour, as the most noble and truest fauourite of this our too much vnrespected quality. This is but a small testimony to paralell the proportion of my minde in this kinde, or any other seruice which my faculty and fortune are any way able to affoord: But knowing your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble disposition to accept the meanest seruice proce<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ing from so loyall and faithfull a heart, I make no doubt of your Lordships acceptation On which hope relying, with all humility crauing pardon for my bold presumption, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> present them, and will euer pray to God for your health, honour, and happinesse, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, great Marquesse</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> be the Seruant <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> your commands, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> VAVTOR.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>