<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian
Reader.</title>
           <author>S., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S957_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11228</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21491.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S957</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian
Reader.</title>
                 <author>S., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The picture of a vvanton : her leawdnesse discouered</title>
                 <author>F. S.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Alomon</hi> in his <hi>Prouers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 5.</note> doth in
many Chapters so wisely and pithily
describe the impudencie and leawde
behauiour of an <hi>Harlot,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 6.</note> that if men
would aduisedly read them,<note place="margin">Prou. 7.</note> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
obey the diuine Counsell in
them contained, they would refraine
comming neere her doores, least they
might be insnared with her allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
But there are some that frequent <hi>Harlots</hi> houses to
beare their Friend company (as they affirme,) not knowing, or
at least not considering the corruption of their Nature, nor their
owne weakenesse to resist temptation, nor the danger to walke in
the counsell of the vngodly, and to stand in the way of sinners.
Some beeing setled on the Lees of their Sinnes, make it almost
their dayly practise to conuerse with them; not regarding how
griuously they offende Almightie GOD, transgressing his
holy Ordinances; nor weighing how they Defile their bodyes,
which are the Temples of the holy Ghost: nor considering into
what penurie and want they may be brought to: nor fearing the
Iudgements and Punishments which God hath threatned to
vnchast lyuers:<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 4.</note> For, <hi>Fornicators and Adulterors, God
will iudge.</hi> Almightie GOD, who is holy▪ yea, holinesse it
selfe, rightious in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes, hating
all vncleannesse; though he had abundance of Spirit, yet hee
made but one Man for one Woman; and one Woman for one
<pb facs="3"/>
Man, ioyning them togeather in holy Matrimonie for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation
of Children, to gather vnto himselfe a Church out of
man-kind; as also to auoyde Fornication: Therefore GOD
sayth,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note>
      <hi>Thou shalt not commit Adulterie. Know ye not,</hi>
(saith S. Paul,) <hi>that your Bodies are the members of
Christ?</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16. 15.</note>
      <hi>Shall I then take the members of Christ, and
make them the members of an Harlot? God forbidde:</hi>
Yea saith;<note place="margin">19</note> or, <hi>Know ye not that your Body is the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of the holy Ghost, which is in you, whom ye haue
of God? and ye are not your owne: ye are bought with
a price.</hi> Consider then how such as couple them-selues <hi>with
Harlots,</hi> defile the members of <hi>Christ,</hi> and pollute the Temple
of the holy Ghost, and cut them-selues off from the fellowship
of <hi>Christ,</hi> and driue away the holy Spirit from them: <hi>For
what fellowship hath Rightiousnesse with Vnrighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse?</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 14.</note>
      <hi>What communion hath Light with Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse?
What concord hath Christ with Beliall? Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
cannot enter into a wicked heart,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Wisdom. 1. 4.</note>
      <hi>nor dwell in a
body subiect to sinne.</hi> And who doth not know to what
penurie, yea to extreame beggarie many haue been brought by
following of <hi>Harlots.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 26.</note>
      <hi>For because of the whorish Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
a man is brought to a morsell of Bread.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Alea, Vina, Venus, tribus his sum factus egenus.</note> The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of the <hi>Prodigall Child</hi> doth plainely declare it. And lastly,
God hath, &amp; will iudge Fornicators Corporally Spiritually, and
Eternally: Corporally, in this life with many foule and noysome
Diseases, as Batches, the French Pox, wherewith many are
consumed and eate to the bones. Spiritually, in their Ʋnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing;
For,<note place="margin">Hose. 4.</note>
      <hi>Fornication and Wine, take away a mans
heart.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 2. 18.</note> Eternally, both in body and soule in Hell fire; For, <hi>her
House tendes to death,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 7. 27.</note>
      <hi>and her Paths to the Graue.</hi>
Therefore,<note place="margin">Scortorum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis scribatur Ianua mortis.</note> saith S. Paul, <hi>Bee not deceiued, neither For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators,
nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Wantons,
nor Buggerers, nor Theeues, nor Couetous, nor Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards,
nor Raylers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 9. 10.</note>
      <hi>nor Extortioners, shall inherite the
Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> And S. <hi>Iohn</hi> saith, <hi>But the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="3"/>
and vnbeleeuing,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reuel. 21. 8.</note>
      <hi>and the abhominable, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,
and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
and all Lyers, shall haue their part in the Lake
which burneth with Fire and Brimstone: which is the
second death.</hi> And let not the secret <hi>Fornicator</hi> and close
<hi>Adulterer,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 24. 15.</note> whose <hi>Eye waiteth for the twilight, and saith,
no eye shall see mee, and disguiseth his Face,</hi> thinke that
he shall goe vnseene:<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 13.</note> For, <hi>all things are naked and bare
to Gods eyes, with whom he hath to doe. Darkenesse
and Light are all one to him.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psalm. 139.</note>
      <hi>He knoweth the thoughts
of all men:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 21. 27.</note>
      <hi>And will set in order all that they haue
done;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psalm. 50.</note>
      <hi>for he is the searcher of the Heart and Reines.</hi>
Therefore sayth Salomon,<note place="margin">Prou. 5. 20.</note>
      <hi>Why shouldest thou delight,
my Sonne, in a strange Woman, or imbrace the bosome
of a stranger?</hi>
      <note place="margin">21.</note>
      <hi>For the wayes of man are before the
eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his paths. His
owne iniquities shall take the wicked himselfe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">22.</note>
      <hi>and hee
shall be holden with the cordes of his owne sinne. He
shall die for fault of instruction,</hi>
      <note place="margin">23.</note>
      <hi>and shall goe astray
through his great folly.</hi> These thinges while I considered
with my selfe, I remembred a Dialogue betweene two, written
in Latine by that reuerend learned man <hi>Erasmus,</hi> to disswade
young Women from this euill kind of life, by shewing the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
filthinesse thereof. I haue inlarged it both with addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of more persons, and larger matter; endeuouring to warne
both young Men, and young Women; yea, and all of what age
or condition soeuer, to take heed of this foule vice, and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
sinne, which will exclude them out of Heauen, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
not. I know that the multitude of Bookes in this age, are
many: but good Bookes, which tende either to the instruction
of Vertue, or to the destruction of Vice, are to be regarded, and
diligently read: But filthy and vnchast Pamphlets, (whereof
the World is too full) are fitter to be burned as corrupters of
Youth: And who soeuer doth so misspende his time, and abuse
his Witte, and peruert the good guiftes and graces of God, shall
<pb facs="4"/>
receiue condigne punishment, and his owne Bookes shall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
as witnesses against him. I now intreat thee (courtious
Reader) to peruse this little Treatise: and if thou thinke it
needfull for these times, fitte to promote Gods glorie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
to men; as I hope, and am perswaded it is, giue God the
glorie, and pray for mee his vnworthy seruant.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
F. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>