<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vnto the moste excellent prynces que Catharine / the moste gratious wyfe  to the moste noble and myghty prince kynge Henry the .viij. her humble bedman and oratour Richarde Hyrd prayeng good pro∣sperite and welfare.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1529</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S95706_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00841</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24856.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S95706</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vnto the moste excellent prynces que Catharine / the moste gratious wyfe  to the moste noble and myghty prince kynge Henry the .viij. her humble bedman and oratour Richarde Hyrd prayeng good pro∣sperite and welfare.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very frutefull and pleasant boke called the instructio [n] of a Christen woma [n] : made fyrst in Laten, and dedicated vnto the quenes good grace, by the right famous clerke mayster Lewes Viues, and turned out of Laten in to Enlgysshe by Rycharde Hyrd. whiche boke who so redeth diligently shall haue knowlege of many thynges, wherin he shal take great pleasure, and specially women shal take great co [m] modyte and frute towarde the [n] creace of vertue [and] good maners</title>
                 <author>Vives, Juan Luis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1529</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>322 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Vnto the moste excellent prynces que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> Catharine / the moste gratious wyfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to the moste noble and myghty prince kynge Henry the .viij. her humble bedman and oratour Richarde Hyrd prayeng good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperite and welfare.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it nat moste excellent princesse / that the consideration of your great goodnesse and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignite dyd as moche encorage and bolde me / as the respecte and regarde of myn owne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce retardeth me and holdeth backe / I neuer durst presume to dedicate and present vnto the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iestie of your noble grace this my rude and symple translation / so moche the more vncumly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete to be offered in your hygh presence / in howe moche theloquence of thautour stayneth and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the rude speche of the translatour. For had I mooste gracious princesse that gyfte of erudition and vtterance / that I were able in our englysshe tonge / to gyue this boke as moche perspicuite / light / lyfe / fauour / grace / and quickenes / as mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Lewes Viues hath gyuen hit in Laten / than durste I boldely put hit forthe to your grace / nat without good hope of thanke / consyderynge the
<pb facs="4"/>matter to be suche / as neyther a more profitable nor more necessarye can lyghtly comme in hande. For what is more frutefull than the good educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ordre of women / the one halfe of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynd / and that halfe also / whose good behauour or euyll tatchis gyueth or bereueth the other halfe / almoste all the holle pleasure and cōmodite of this present lyfe / byside the furtherance or hynderance forther growyng there vpon / concernyng the lyfe to come? And surely for the plantynge and nurys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shynge of good vertuous in euerye kynde of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men / virgins / wyues / and wydowes / I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue there was neuer any treatis made / either fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nisshed with more goodly counsayles / or sette out with more effectuall reasons / or garnysshed with more substanciall authoritees or stored more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuously of conuenient examples / nor all these thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to gether more goodly treated and handeled / than maister Viues hath done in his boke: Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che boke whan I redde / I wisshed in my mynde that eyther in euery countre women were lerned in the latin tonge / or the boke out of latin transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in to euery tonge: and moche I marueiled / as I often do / of the vnreasonable ouer sight of men / whiche neuer ceace to complayne of womens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. And yet hauyng the education and order of them in theyr owne handes / nat only do litell di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to teache them and bryng them vp better / but also purposely with drawe them fro lernynge / by whiche they myghte haue occasyons to waxe
<pb facs="4"/>better by them selfe. But sith this faute is so farre gone and ouer largely spredde / to be shortly reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died / I thought at the least wyse for my parte hit wolde do well to translate this boke into our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glisshe tonge / for the commodite and profite of our owne countre. Whiche whan I had secretely done by my selfe / I shewed hit vnto my syngular good mayster and brynger vppe Syr Thomas More / to whose iugemēt and correction I vse to submyt what so euer I do or go about / that I set any store by: who nat onely for the matter it selfe was very gladde therof / but also for that (as he than shewed me) he perceyued that hit shulde be to your noble maiestie for the gracious zele that ye beare to the vertuous education of the womankynde of this realme / wherof our lorde hath ordeyned you to be quene / so great and speciall pleasure / that he had entended / his manyfolde busynes nat withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng / to haue taken the tymes to haue translated this boke hym selfe / in whiche he was (as he said) very glad that he was nowe preuented / nor for es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewyng of his labour / whiche he wolde haue bē very glad to bestowe there in / but for bicause that the frute therof may nowe soner come forthe than he coulde haue founde the tyme. Howe be it as I answered hym / It were better to bryng forth da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in an hundred yeres (for so longe hit is or that tre brynge forthe his frute) than crabbis in .iiij. yere. And thoughe he rekenned hym selfe easedde of the translatynge I besoughte hym to take the
<pb facs="5"/>labour to rede hit ouer / and correcte hit. Whiche he ryght gladlye dyd. Wherbye I haue bene the more encoraged to put forth vnto your most noble grace this translation: to whose maieste sith the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall worke was dedicate / I was of very duety me thought bounden to dedicate the translation. Wherfore if there be / as I well wote there is / any good in the matter / thanke be to mayster Viues the maker: if any thyng be well in this translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / thanke be to the labour of my good mayster. For nothynge in this worke clayme I for myne owne / but the shewe of my good zele to do good to other / and seruyse to your noble grace: whom with the sacredde maiestie of the mooste excellent prince your derest spouse / &amp; your noble issue / with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crese of more / our lorde lōge preserue in to the weale of your selfe / your realme / and all Christendome besyde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>