<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>H., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S987_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12470</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22795.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S987</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>H., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true relation of such occurrences and accidents of noate as hath hapned in Virginia since the first planting of that collony, which is now resident in the south part thereof, till the last returne from thence. Written by Captaine Smith Coronell of the said collony, to a worshipfull friend of his in England</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Tapp (Tap), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Welby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>COurteous, Kind, &amp; indifferent Readers, whose wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnesse
to reade &amp; heare this following discourse,
doth explaine to the world your hearty affection,
to the prosecuting and furtherance of so worthy an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
so it is, that like to an vnskilfull actor, who hauing
by misconstruction of his right Cue, ouer-slipt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
in beginning of a contrary part, and fearing the
hatefull hisse of the captious multitude, with a modest
blush retires himselfe in priuate; as doubting the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension
of his whole audience in publicke, and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
vpon further deliberation, thinking it better to
know their censures at the first, and vpon submission to
reape pardon, then by seeking to smother it, to incurre
the danger of a secret scandall: Imboldening himselfe
vpon the curteous kindnesse of the best, and not greatly
respecting the worst, comes fourth againe, makes an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollogie
for himselfe, shewes the cause of his error,
craues pardon for his rashnes, and in fine, receiues a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
applauditie of the whole assemblie: so I gentle
Readers, happening vpon this relation by chance (as I
take it, at the second or third hand) induced thereunto
by diuers well willers of the action, and none wishing
better towards it then my selfe, so farre foorth as my
poore abilitie can or may stretch too, I thought good to
publish it: but the Author being absent from the presse,
it cannot be doubted but that some faults haue escaped
in the printing, especially in the names of Countries,
<pb facs="5"/>
Townes, and People, which are somewhat strange vnto
vs: but most of all, and which is the chiefe error, (for
want of knowledge of the Writer) some of the bookes
were printed vnder the name of <hi>Thomas Watson,</hi> by
whose occasion I know not, vnlesse it were the ouer rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
or mistaking of the workemen, but since hauing
learned that the saide discourse was written by Captaine
<hi>Smith,</hi> who is one of the Counsell there in <hi>Virginia:</hi> I
thought good to make the like Apollogie, by shewing
the true Author so farre as my selfe could learne, not
doubting, but that the wise noting it as an error of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
will passe it ouer with patience, and if worthy an
applauditie, to reserue it to the Author, whose paines in
my iudgement deserueth commendations; somewhat
more was by him written, which being as I thought (fit
to be priuate) I would not aduenture to make it publicke
what more may be expected concerning the scituation of
the Country, the nature, of the clime, number of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
there resident, the manner of their gouernment, and
liuing, the commodities to be produced, &amp; the end &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
it maycome too, I can say nothing more then is here
written, only what I haue learned and gathered from the
generall consent of all (that I haue conuersed withall) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well
marriners as others, which haue had imploymēt that
way; is that the Country is ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cellēt &amp; pleasant, the clime
temperate and healthfull, the ground fertill and good,
the commodities to be expected (if well followed) many,
for our people, the worst being already past, these former
hauing indured the heate of the day, whereby those that
sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l succeede, may at ease labour for their profit, in the
most sweete, coole, and temperate shade: the action most
honorable, and the end to the high glory of God, to the
erecting of true religion among Infidells, to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
of superstition and idolatrie, to the winning of
<pb facs="5"/>
many thousands of wandring sheepe, vnto Christs fold,
who now, and till now, haue strayed in the vnknowne
paths of Paganisme, Idolatrie, and susperstition: yea, I
say the Action being well followed, as by the graue Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators,
and worthy aduenturors, it hath beene worthily
begunne: will tend to the euerlasting renowne of our
Nation, and to the exceeding good and benefit of our
Weale publicke in generall: whose Counsells, labours,
godly and industrious endeuours, I beseech the mightie
<hi>Iehouah</hi> to blesse, prosper, and further, with his heauenly
ayde, and holy assistance.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell.
I. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>